<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<document xmlns:codify="http://code.dccouncil.us/schemas/codify" id="Pub. L. 90-226">
  <num>90-226</num>
  <meta>
    <effective>1967-12-27</effective>
    <cites>
      <law session="90" lawId="226"/>
    </cites>
  </meta>
  <container>
    <prefix>Title</prefix>
    <num>III</num>
    <section from-code="true">
      <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" before="§5-115.02" path="|5|1|VIII"/>
      <num codify:value="5-115.01">301</num>
      <heading>Limitation on period of questioning; advisement of rights; release uncharged; admissibility of confessions.</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>Any person arrested in the District of Columbia may be questioned with respect to any matter for a period not to exceed 3 hours immediately following his arrest. Such person shall be advised of and accorded his rights under applicable law respecting any such interrogation. In the case of any such arrested person who is released without being charged with a crime, his detention shall not be recorded as an arrest in any official record.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>Any statement, admission, or confession made by an arrested person within 3 hours immediately following his arrest shall not be excluded from evidence in the courts of the District of Columbia solely because of delay in presentment.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annoGroup>
          <heading>History</heading>
          <annotation doc="Pub. L. 90-226">Dec. 27, 1967, 81 Stat. 735, Pub. L. 90-226, title III, § 301</annotation>
        </annoGroup>
        <annoGroup>
          <heading>Section References</heading>
          <annotation>This section is referenced in § <cite path="§5-302">5-302</cite>.</annotation>
        </annoGroup>
        <annoGroup>
          <heading>Prior Codifications</heading>
          <annotation>1981 Ed., § 4-140.</annotation>
          <annotation>1973 Ed., § 4-140a.</annotation>
        </annoGroup>
      </annotations>
    </section>
  </container>
  <container>
    <prefix>Title</prefix>
    <num>VI</num>
    <section from-code="true">
      <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" path="|5|1|IX"/>
      <num codify:value="5-117.05">608</num>
      <heading>False or fictitious reports to Metropolitan Police.</heading>
      <text>Except as provided in § <cite path="§22-1319">22-1319</cite>, whoever shall make or cause to be made to the Metropolitan Police force of the District of Columbia, or to any officer or member thereof, a false or fictitious report of the commission of any criminal offense within the District of Columbia, or a false or fictitious report of any other matter or occurrence of which such Metropolitan Police force is required to receive reports, or in connection with which such Metropolitan Police force is required to conduct an investigation, knowing such report to be false or fictitious; or who shall communicate or cause to be communicated to such Metropolitan Police force, or any officer or member thereof, any false information concerning the commission of any criminal offense within the District of Columbia or concerning any other matter or occurrence of which such Metropolitan Police force is required to receive reports, or in connection with which such Metropolitan Police force is required to conduct an investigation, knowing such information to be false, shall be punished by a fine of not exceeding $300 or by imprisonment not exceeding 30 days.</text>
      <annotations>
        <annoGroup>
          <heading>History</heading>
          <annotation doc="Pub. L. 90-226">Dec. 27, 1967, 81 Stat. 739, Pub. L. 90-226, title VI, § 608</annotation>
          <annotation doc="D.C. Law 14-194">Oct. 17, 2002, D.C. Law 14-194, § 152, 49 DCR 5306</annotation>
        </annoGroup>
        <annoGroup>
          <heading>Prior Codifications</heading>
          <annotation>1981 Ed., § 4-151.</annotation>
          <annotation>1973 Ed., § 4-150a.</annotation>
        </annoGroup>
        <annoGroup>
          <heading>Effect of Amendments</heading>
          <annotation><cite doc="D.C. Law 14-194">D.C. Law 14-194</cite> substituted “Except as provided in § <cite path="§22-1319">22-1319</cite>, whoever” for “Whoever”.</annotation>
        </annoGroup>
      </annotations>
    </section>
  </container>
  <container>
    <prefix>Title</prefix>
    <num>IX</num>
    <section from-code="true">
      <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" path="|22|13"/>
      <num codify:value="22-1322">901</num>
      <heading>Rioting or inciting to riot.</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>A riot in the District of Columbia is a public disturbance involving an assemblage of 5 or more persons which by tumultuous and violent conduct or the threat thereof creates grave danger of damage or injury to property or persons.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>Whoever willfully engages in a riot in the District of Columbia shall be punished by imprisonment for not more than 180 days or a fine of not more than the amount set forth in § <cite path="§22-3571.01">22-3571.01</cite>, or both.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(c)</num>
        <text>Whoever willfully incites or urges other persons to engage in a riot shall be punished by imprisonment for not more than 180 days or a fine of not more than the amount set forth in § <cite path="§22-3571.01">22-3571.01</cite>, or both.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(d)</num>
        <text>If in the course and as a result of a riot a person suffers serious bodily harm or there is property damage in excess of $5,000, every person who willfully incited or urged others to engage in the riot shall be punished by imprisonment for not more than 10 years or a fine of not more than the amount set forth in § <cite path="§22-3571.01">22-3571.01</cite>, or both.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annoGroup>
          <heading>History</heading>
          <annotation doc="Pub. L. 90-226">Dec. 27, 1967, 81 Stat. 742, Pub. L. 90-226, title IX, § 901</annotation>
          <annotation doc="D.C. Law 10-151">Aug. 20, 1994, D.C. Law 10-151, § 111, 41 DCR 2608</annotation>
          <annotation doc="D.C. Law 19-317">June 11, 2013, D.C. Law 19-317, § 216, 60 DCR 2064</annotation>
        </annoGroup>
        <annoGroup>
          <heading>Cross References</heading>
          <annotation>Burning of cross or other religious symbol, see § <cite path="§22-3312.02">22-3312.02</cite>.</annotation>
          <annotation>Defacement of public or private building or property, see § <cite path="§22-3312.01">22-3312.01</cite>.</annotation>
          <annotation>Wearing of masks for particular purposes, see § <cite path="§22-3312.03">22-3312.03</cite>.</annotation>
        </annoGroup>
        <annoGroup>
          <heading>Prior Codifications</heading>
          <annotation>1981 Ed., § 22-1122.</annotation>
          <annotation>1973 Ed., § 22-1122.</annotation>
        </annoGroup>
        <annoGroup>
          <heading>Effect of Amendments</heading>
          <annotation>The 2013 amendment by <cite doc="D.C. Law 19-317">D.C. Law 19-317</cite> substituted “not more than the amount set forth in § <cite path="§22-3571.01">22-3571.01</cite>” for “not more than $1,000” in (b) and (c), and for “not more than $10,000” in (d).</annotation>
        </annoGroup>
        <annoGroup>
          <heading>Temporary Addition of Section</heading>
          <annotation>Temporary addition of sections: D.C. Law 11-75 added 2 new sections to read as follows: “§ 101. Definitions. For the purposes of this title, the term: (1) ”Act“ shall not include speech. (2) ”Health professional“ means a person licensed to practice a health occupation in the District pursuant to § 2-3301.1 1981 Ed.. (3) ”Medical facility“ means a facility, agency, or organizational entity, as defined in § 32-1301 1981 Ed., licensed or otherwise authorized to provide health care services in the District. (4) ”Person“ means: (A) The chief medical officer of a medical facility or the chief medical officer’s designee; (B) The chief executive officer of a medical facility or the chief executive officer’s designee; (C) An agent of a medical facility; or. (D) A law enforcement officer in the performance of the enforcement officer’s official duty.” “§ 102. Interference with entering and leaving a medical facility or home. (a) A person shall not act alone or in concert with others with the intent to prevent another person from entering or leaving a medical facility. A person shall not detain a person or obstruct, impede, or hinder a person’s free passage. (b) A person shall not act alone or in concert with others with the intent to prevent a medical provider or a member of the medical provider’s family from entering or leaving the medical provider’s home. (c) Subsections (a) and (b) of this section shall not be construed to prohibit any lawful picketing or assembly. (d) Any person who violates either subsection (a) or (b) of this section, upon conviction, shall be fined not more than $1,000, imprisoned for not more than 6 months, or both.”</annotation>
          <annotation>Section 301(b) of <cite doc="D.C. Law 11-75">D.C. Law 11-75</cite> provided that the act shall expire after 225 days of its having taken effect.</annotation>
        </annoGroup>
        <annoGroup>
          <heading>Emergency Legislation</heading>
          <annotation>For temporary amendment of section, see § 111 of the Omnibus Criminal Justice Reform Emergency Amendment Act of 1994 (D.C. Act 10-255, June 22, 1994,  41 DCR 4286).</annotation>
          <annotation>Interference with medical facilities and health professionals: For temporary prohibition of a person interfering with the free access to or egress from a medical facility or the home of a health professional in the District of Columbia, see §§ 101 and 102 of the Interference with Medical Facilities and Health Professionals and Reestablishment of Health Services Planning and Certificate of Need Program Emergency Act of 1995 (D.C. Act 11-117, July 25, 1995,  42 DCR 4044) and §§ 2 and 3 of the Interference with Medical Facilities and Health Professionals Congressional Review Emergency Act of 1995 (D.C. Act 11-152, November 9, 1995,  42 DCR 6565).</annotation>
          <annotation>For temporary (90 days) amendment of this section, see § 216 of the Criminal Fine Proportionality Emergency Act of 2013 (D.C. Act 20-45, April 1, 2013,  60 DCR 5400, 20 DCSTAT 1300).</annotation>
        </annoGroup>
        <annoGroup>
          <heading>Editor's Notes</heading>
          <annotation>Applicability of <cite doc="D.C. Law 19-317">D.C. Law 19-317</cite>: Section 401 of <cite doc="D.C. Law 19-317">D.C. Law 19-317</cite> provided that the act shall apply only to offenses committed on or after June 11, 2013.</annotation>
        </annoGroup>
      </annotations>
    </section>
  </container>
</document>
