<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<document xmlns:codify="http://code.dccouncil.us/schemas/codify" id="D.C. Law 20-275">
  <num type="law">20-275</num>
  <heading type="short">Criminalization of Non-Consensual Pornography Act of 2014</heading>
  <meta>
    <effective>2015-05-07</effective>
    <cites>
      <law lawId="275" period="20" url="http://lims.dccouncil.us/Download/32304/B20-0903-SignedAct.pdf"/>
      <register page="16" vol="62"/>
    </cites>
    <history url="http://lims.dccouncil.us/Legislation/B20-0903">
      <narrative>Law 20-275, the “Criminalization of Non-Consensual Pornography Act of 2014,” was introduced in Council and assigned Bill No. 20-903. The Bill was adopted on first and second readings on November 18, 2014, and December 2, 2014, respectively. Signed by the Mayor on December 19, 2014, it was assigned Act No. 20-534 and transmitted to Congress for its review. D.C. Law 20-275 became effective May 7, 2015.</narrative>
    </history>
  </meta>
  <section from-code="true">
    <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" path="|22|30A"/>
    <num codify:value="22-3051">2</num>
    <heading>Definitions.</heading>
    <text>For the purposes of this chapter, the term:</text>
    <para>
      <num>(1)</num>
      <text>“Disclose” means to transfer or exhibit to 5 or fewer persons.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(2)</num>
      <text>“Harm” means any injury, whether physical or nonphysical, including psychological, financial, or reputational injury.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(3)</num>
      <text>“Internet” means an electronically available platform by which sexual images can be disseminated to a wide audience, including social media, websites, and smartphone applications; provided, that the term “Internet” does not include a text message.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(4)</num>
      <text>“Private area” means the genitals, anus, or pubic area of a person, or the nipple of a developed female breast, including the breast of a transgender female.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(5)</num>
      <text>“Publish” means to transfer or exhibit to 6 or more persons, or to make available for viewing by uploading to the Internet.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(6)</num>
      <text>“Sexual conduct” shall have the same meaning as provided in § <cite path="§22-3101">22-3101</cite>(5).</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(7)</num>
      <text>“Sexual image” means a photograph, video, or other visual recording of an unclothed private area or of sexual conduct.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>History</heading>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 20-275">May 7, 2015, D.C. Law 20-275, § 2, 62 DCR 16</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section from-code="true">
    <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" path="|22|30A"/>
    <num codify:value="22-3052">3</num>
    <heading>Unlawful disclosure.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>(a)</num>
      <text>It shall be unlawful in the District of Columbia for a person to knowingly disclose one or more sexual images of another identified or identifiable person when:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The person depicted did not consent to the disclosure of the sexual image;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>There was an agreement or understanding between the person depicted and the person disclosing that the sexual image would not be disclosed; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The person disclosed the sexual image with the intent to harm the person depicted or to receive financial gain.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(b)</num>
      <text>A person who violates this section shall be guilty of a misdemeanor and, upon conviction, shall be fined not more than the amount set forth in § <cite path="§22-3571.01">22-3571.01</cite>, imprisoned for not more than 180 days, or both.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>History</heading>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 20-275">May 7, 2015, D.C. Law 20-275, § 3, 62 DCR 16</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section from-code="true">
    <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" path="|22|30A"/>
    <num codify:value="22-3053">4</num>
    <heading>First-degree unlawful publication.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>(a)</num>
      <text>It shall be unlawful in the District of Columbia for a person to knowingly publish one or more sexual images of another identified or identifiable person when:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The person depicted did not consent to the disclosure or publication of the sexual image;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>There was an agreement or understanding between the person depicted and the person publishing that the sexual image would not be disclosed or published; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The person published the sexual image with the intent to harm the person depicted or to receive financial gain.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(b)</num>
      <text>A person who violates this section shall be guilty of a felony and, upon conviction, shall be fined not more than the amount set forth in § <cite path="§22-3571.01">22-3571.01</cite>, imprisoned for not more than 3 years, or both.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>History</heading>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 20-275">May 7, 2015, D.C. Law 20-275, § 4, 62 DCR 16</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section from-code="true">
    <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" path="|22|30A"/>
    <num codify:value="22-3054">5</num>
    <heading>Second degree unlawful publication.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>(a)</num>
      <text>It shall be unlawful in the District of Columbia for a person to knowingly publish one or more sexual images of another identified or identifiable person obtained from a third party or other source when:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The person depicted did not consent to the disclosure or publication of the sexual image; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The person published the sexual image with conscious disregard that the sexual image was obtained as a result of a previous disclosure or publication of the sexual image made with an intent to harm the person depicted or to receive financial gain.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(b)</num>
      <text>A person who violates this section shall be guilty of a misdemeanor and, upon conviction, shall be fined not more than the amount set forth in § <cite path="§22-3571.01">22-3571.01</cite>, imprisoned for not more than 180 days, or both.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>History</heading>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 20-275">May 7, 2015, D.C. Law 20-275, § 5, 62 DCR 16</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section from-code="true">
    <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" path="|22|30A"/>
    <num codify:value="22-3055">6</num>
    <heading>Exclusions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>(a)</num>
      <text>This chapter shall not apply to:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Constitutionally protected activity; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A person disclosing or publishing a sexual image that resulted from the voluntary exposure of the person depicted in a public or commercial setting.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(b)</num>
      <text>Nothing in this chapter shall be construed to impose liability on an interactive computer service, as defined in section 230(e)(2) of the Communications Act of 1934, approved February 8, 1996 (110 Stat. 139; 47 U.S.C. § 230(f)(2)), for content provided by another person.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>History</heading>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 20-275">May 7, 2015, D.C. Law 20-275, § 6, 62 DCR 16</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section from-code="true">
    <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" path="|22|30A"/>
    <num codify:value="22-3056">7</num>
    <heading>Affirmative defenses.</heading>
    <text>It shall be an affirmative defense to a violation of § <cite path="§22-3052">22-3052</cite>, § <cite path="§22-3053">22-3053</cite>, or § <cite path="§22-3054">22-3054</cite> if the disclosure or publication of a sexual image is made in the public interest, including the reporting of unlawful conduct, the lawful and common practices of law enforcement, or legal proceedings.</text>
    <annotations>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>History</heading>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 20-275">May 7, 2015, D.C. Law 20-275, § 7, 62 DCR 16</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section from-code="true">
    <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" path="|22|30A"/>
    <num codify:value="22-3057">8</num>
    <heading>Jurisdiction.</heading>
    <text>A violation of § <cite path="§22-3052">22-3052</cite>, § <cite path="§22-3053">22-3053</cite>, or § <cite path="§22-3054">22-3054</cite> shall be deemed to be committed in the District of Columbia if any part of the violation takes place in the District of Columbia, including when either the person depicted or the person who disclosed or published the sexual image was a resident of, or located in, the District of Columbia at the time that the sexual image was made, disclosed, or published.</text>
    <annotations>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>History</heading>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 20-275">May 7, 2015, D.C. Law 20-275, § 8, 62 DCR 16</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
    </annotations>
  </section>
</document>
