<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<document xmlns:codify="http://code.dccouncil.us/schemas/codify" id="Pub. L. 60-1-ch2510">
  <heading/>
  <meta>
    <effective>1907-03-02</effective>
    <cites>
      <law congress="60" session="1" chapter="2510"/>
    </cites>
  </meta>
  <section from-code="true">
    <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" path="|48|6|II"/>
    <reason>Repealed</reason>
    <num codify:value="48-631">1</num>
    <heading>Conflicts of interest of government officers or employees.</heading>
    <text>Repealed.</text>
    <annotations>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>History</heading>
        <annotation>Mar. 2, 1907, 34 Stat. 1145, ch. 2510, § 1</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 14-116">May 2, 2002, D.C. Law 14-116,§ 8(c), 49 DCR 1945</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Prior Codifications</heading>
        <annotation>1981 Ed., § 33-311.</annotation>
        <annotation>1973 Ed., § 33-320.</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Temporary Amendment of Section</heading>
        <annotation>For temporary (225 day) repeal of section, see § 8(c) of Food Regulation Temporary Amendment Act of 2001 (<cite doc="D.C. Law 14-55">D.C. Law 14-55</cite>, December 6, 2001, law notification  49 DCR 356).</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Emergency Legislation</heading>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 day) repeal of section, see § 8(c) of Food Regulation Emergency Amendment Act of 2001 (D.C. Act 14-128, August 3, 2001,  48 DCR 7939).</annotation>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 day) repeal of section, see § 8(c) of Food Regulation Legislative Review Emergency Amendment Act of 2001 (D.C. Act 14-147, October 23, 2001,  48 DCR 10183).</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Editor's Notes</heading>
        <annotation>Health Department abolished: The Health Department of the District of Columbia, including the office of the head thereof, was abolished and the functions thereof transferred to the Board of Commissioners of the District of Columbia by Reorganization Plan No. 5 of 1952. Reorganization Order No. 57 of the Board of Commissioners, dated June 30, 1953, and Reorganization Order No. 52, dated June 30, 1953, combined and redesignated Organization Order No. 141, dated February 11, 1964, established, under the direction and control of a Commissioner, a Department of Public Health headed by a Director, for the purpose of planning, implementing, and directing public health and hospital care programs, and for performing certain other allied medical and paramedical functions. The Anatomical Board was established under the direction and control of the Director of Public Health consisting of members as prescribed in the D.C. Code. Prior to redesignation, the Order abolished the previously existing Health Department, Gallinger Hospital, Glenn Dale Sanatorium, and the Anatomical Board, and transferred their functions and positions to the new Department. The organization of the new Department was set out in the Order. The executive functions of the Board of Commissioners were transferred to the Commissioner of the District of Columbia by § 401 of Reorganization Plan No. 3 of 1967. Functions stated in Organization Order No. 141 were transferred to the Director of the Department of Human Resources by Commissioner’s Order No. 69-96, dated March 7, 1969, as amended by Commissioner’s Order No. 70-83, dated March 6, 1970. The Department of Human Resources was replaced by Reorganization Plan No. 2 of 1979, dated February 21, 1980, which Plan established the Department of Human Services.</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section from-code="true">
    <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" path="|34|16"/>
    <num codify:value="34-1607">1</num>
    <heading>Annual reports to Congress.</heading>
    <text>Any association or corporation engaged in the manufacture and sale of gas for illuminating and fuel purposes in the District of Columbia, through its president or other duly authorized officer, shall make a sworn statement to Congress annually, on or before the 1st day of February in each year. Said report shall contain a detailed statement of the condition of the business of said association or corporation for the year ending December 31st next preceding, and such statement shall set forth the actual cost and also present value of the property of such association or corporation used in the conduct of its business, the amount of paid-up capital stock, the amount and character of the indebtedness of such association or corporation, the amount and cost of materials used in making gas, the amount of gas manufactured, the amount of gas sold, the average price per 1,000 cubic feet received for gas sold, the revenue from the sale of all by-products, the revenues from all other sources, the extensions and improvements made in the plant and works, the actual cost of the same, the amount expended for labor, the amount set aside for depreciation, the amount set apart for insurance and renewals, the amount paid out of earnings for betterments, the amount paid for betterments from other sources, the amount set aside and paid in interest and dividends, the surplus after paying the operating expenses and fixed charges, the statement of the operating expenses to be itemized and classified as is done by other public utility corporations, in the District of Columbia, the names of the stockholders and the amount of the stock held in such association or corporation by each of them on December 31st next preceding the date of such report.</text>
    <annotations>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>History</heading>
        <annotation>Mar. 2, 1907, 34 Stat. 1133, ch. 2510, § 1</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Cross References</heading>
        <annotation>Utility service, valuation and accounts, reports to Commission, notice to People’s Counsel, disclosure, see § <cite path="§34-1118">34-1118</cite>.</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Prior Codifications</heading>
        <annotation>1981 Ed., § 43-1106.</annotation>
        <annotation>1973 Ed., § 43-1206.</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
    </annotations>
  </section>
</document>
