<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<document xmlns:codify="http://code.dccouncil.us/schemas/codify" id="D.C. Law 16-169">
  <num type="law">16-169</num>
  <heading type="short">Drug Offense Driving Privileges Revocation and Disqualification Amendment Act of 2006</heading>
  <meta>
    <effective>2006-09-29</effective>
    <cites>
      <law lawId="169" period="16" url="./docs/16-169.pdf"/>
      <register page="6223" vol="53"/>
    </cites>
    <history url="http://lims.dccouncil.us/Legislation/B16-0665">
      <narrative>Law 16-169, the “Drug Offense Driving Privileges Revocation and Disqualification Amendment Act of 2006”, was introduced in Council and assigned Bill No. 16-665 which was referred to the Committee of the Whole. The Bill was adopted on first and second readings on June 20, 2006, and July 11, 2006, respectively. Signed by the Mayor on July 18, 2006, it was assigned Act No. 16-438 and transmitted to both Houses of Congress for its review. D.C. Law 16-169 became effective on September 29, 2006.</narrative>
    </history>
  </meta>
  <section from-code="true">
    <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" path="|2|6|IV"/>
    <num codify:value="2-631">2</num>
    <heading>Definitions.</heading>
    <text>For purposes of this subchapter, the term:</text>
    <para>
      <num>(1)</num>
      <text>“Disability” means, with respect to an individual:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(A)</num>
        <text>A physical or mental impairment that substantially limits one or more of the major life activities of that individual;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(B)</num>
        <text>A record of such an impairment; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(C)</num>
        <text>Being regarded as having such an impairment.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(2)</num>
      <text>“Internet publication” means any information posted to an official web site of a public body, except for archival documents.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(3)</num>
      <text>“Policies” means official instructions and guiding principles issued by a public body for the implementation of its programs.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(4)</num>
      <text>“Public body” shall have the same meaning as set forth in § <cite path="§2-502">2-502</cite>(18A).</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(5)</num>
      <text>“Publications” means any written material issued by a public body, either for internal or external use, and does not include internet publications, policies, rules, regulations, and signage.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(6)</num>
      <text>“Regulation” shall have the same meaning as set forth in § <cite path="§2-502">2-502</cite>(17).</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(7)</num>
      <text>“Rule” shall have the same meaning as set forth in § <cite path="§2-502">2-502</cite>(6).</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(8)</num>
      <text>“Signage” means any poster on paper larger than 8 1/2 inches by 11 inches issued by a public body and any signs regardless of size made of any material other than paper and posted or issued by a public body.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>History</heading>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 16-169">Sept. 29, 2006, D.C. Law 16-169, § 2, 53 DCR 6223</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section from-code="true">
    <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" path="|2|6|IV"/>
    <num codify:value="2-632">3</num>
    <heading>Respectful language.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>(a)</num>
      <text>On or after September 29, 2006, all new and revised sections of the District of Columbia Official Code, all new, revised, or republished District regulations, rules, policies, or publications and all internet publications shall, when referring to persons with disabilities:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Avoid any use of following terms, except as required by any law or regulation: “afflicted,” “cripple,” “crippled,” “defective,” “feebleminded,” “handicapped,” “handicap,” “idiot,” “lunatic,” “imbecile,” “insane,” “invalid,” “maimed,” “moron,” “suffering,” “wheelchair user,” or “wheelchair bound”;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Use “person,” “people,” “individual,” “individuals,” “adult,” “adults,” “child,” “children,” or “youth” in sentence construction so that the language refers to individuals:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(A)</num>
          <text>With disabilities or with conditions that result in disability;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(B)</num>
          <text>Who have disabilities or who have conditions that result in disability; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(C)</num>
          <text>Who use or who need assistive technology.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(a-1)</num>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Beginning on Sept. 26, 2012, all new and revised sections of the District of Columbia Code, all new, revised, or republished District regulations, rules, policies, or publications, and all internet publications shall avoid the use of the terms “mental retardation,” “mentally retarded,” and “retarded,” except as required by any law or regulation, and further:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(A)</num>
          <text>Where the term “mental retardation” is used, the term “intellectual disability” or “intellectual disabilities” shall be substituted;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(B)</num>
          <text>Where the term “intermediate care facility for persons with mental retardation” is used, the term “intermediate care facility for persons with intellectual or developmental disabilities” shall be substituted;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(C)</num>
          <text>Where the term “qualified mental retardation professional” is used, the term “qualified developmental disability professional” shall be substituted; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(D)</num>
          <text>Where the term “is at least moderately mentally retarded” is used, the term “has at least a moderate intellectual disability” shall be substituted.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(a-2)</num>
      <text>Beginning 6 months after Sept. 26, 2012, all policies and signage shall comply with subsection (a-1) of this section.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(a-3)</num>
      <text>Upon the earlier of reprinting or after one year following Sept. 26, 2012, all publications shall comply with subsection (a-1) of this section.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(b)</num>
      <text>On or after 6 months following September 29, 2006, all policies and signage shall comply with subsection (a) of this section.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(c)</num>
      <text>Upon the earlier of reprinting or September 30, 2007, all publications shall comply with subsection (a) of this section.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(d)</num>
      <text>No statute, regulation, or rule shall be invalid because it does not comply with this section.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>History</heading>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 16-169">Sept. 29, 2006, D.C. Law 16-169, § 3, 53 DCR 6223</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 19-169">Sept. 26, 2012, D.C. Law 19-169, § 6(a), 59 DCR 5567</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Section References</heading>
        <annotation>This section is referenced in § <cite path="§2-552">2-552</cite>, § <cite path="§2-553">2-553</cite>, and § <cite path="§2-612">2-612</cite>.</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Effect of Amendments</heading>
        <annotation>The 2012 amendment by <cite doc="D.C. Law 19-169">D.C. Law 19-169</cite> added (a-1), (a-2), and (a-3).</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Editor's Notes</heading>
        <annotation>Section 35 of <cite doc="D.C. Law 19-169">D.C. Law 19-169</cite> provided that no provision of the act shall impair any right or obligation existing under law.</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section from-code="true">
    <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" path="|2|6|IV"/>
    <reason>Repealed</reason>
    <num codify:value="2-633">4</num>
    <heading>Report.</heading>
    <text>Repealed.</text>
    <annotations>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>History</heading>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 16-169">Sept. 29, 2006, D.C. Law 16-169, § 4, 53 DCR 6223</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 19-169">Sept. 26, 2012, D.C. Law 19-169, § 6(b), 59 DCR 5567</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Editor's Notes</heading>
        <annotation>Section 35 of <cite doc="D.C. Law 19-169">D.C. Law 19-169</cite> provided that no provision of the act shall impair any right or obligation existing under law.</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
    </annotations>
  </section>
</document>
