<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<document xmlns:codify="http://code.dccouncil.us/schemas/codify" id="Pub. L. 69-1-ch443">
  <heading/>
  <meta>
    <effective>1925-03-03</effective>
    <cites>
      <law congress="69" session="1" chapter="443"/>
    </cites>
  </meta>
  <section from-code="true">
    <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" path="|50|14|I"/>
    <num codify:value="50-1401.01">7</num>
    <heading>Fee; examination; age requirements; lost permits; provisions for armed forces personnel; contents; operation without permit prohibited; restrictions for minors.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>(a)</num>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The Mayor is authorized to issue a new or renewed motor vehicle operator’s permit, valid for a period not to exceed 8 years plus any time period prior to the expiration date of a previous license not to exceed 2 months, to any individual 17 years of age or older, subject to the following conditions and any other conditions the Mayor may prescribe to protect the public:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(A)</num>
          <text>The applicant shall pay an application fee of $30, which may be increased by the Mayor to compensate the District for processing and evaluating the application and issuing the permit. Alternatively, the Mayor is authorized to prorate existing fees to correspond to the duration of the license issued.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(A-i)</num>
          <text>Effective October 1, 2015, an applicant for an operator’s permit shall pay an application fee of $47, which the Mayor may increase or decrease to compensate the District for processing and evaluating the application and issuing the permit. The Mayor may prorate the fee to correspond to the duration of the license issued.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(B)</num>
          <text>The applicant shall demonstrate that he or she is mentally, morally, and physically qualified to operate a motor vehicle in a manner not to jeopardize the safety of individuals or property. The Mayor shall determine whether an applicant is qualified through:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>An examination of the applicant’s knowledge of the traffic regulations and regulations for safely sharing roadways with pedestrians and bicyclists in the District;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>A practical demonstration, or evidence acceptable to the Mayor of the applicant’s ability to operate a motor vehicle within any portion of the District, except that upon renewal of an operator’s permit or upon the application of an individual who meets the criteria set forth in subparagraph (C) of this paragraph, the examination and demonstration may be waived in the discretion of the Mayor; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Any other criteria as the Mayor may establish.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(C)</num>
          <text>An applicant under the age of 21, shall meet the following additional qualifications in addition to the qualifications in subparagraph (B) of this paragraph:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>The applicant shall be the holder of a valid provisional permit issued at least 6 months prior to the application in accordance with paragraph (2A) of this subsection;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>The applicant shall not have admitted to, been liable for, or convicted of an offense for which points may be assessed during the 12 consecutive month period immediately preceding the application; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>The applicant shall have received 10 hours of nighttime driving experience, as certified by the holder of a valid motor vehicle operator’s permit from any jurisdiction, who is 21 years of age or older and has accompanied the applicant while the applicant was operating the motor vehicle.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(D)</num>
          <text>No permittee under the age of 18 shall:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Operate a motor vehicle occupied by more than 2 passengers under the age of 21, except that this restriction shall not apply to a passenger who is a sibling of the permittee;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Operate a motor vehicle in which the permittee or any passenger fails to wear a seat belt; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Operate a motor vehicle between 11:00 p.m. on any Sunday, Monday, Tuesday, Wednesday or Thursday until 6:00 a.m. on the following day during any month except July or August, and from 12:01 a.m. until 6:00 a.m. during July and August and on any Saturday or Sunday the rest of the year, unless driving to or from employment, a school-sponsored activity, religious or an athletic event or related training session in which the permittee is a participant, sponsored by the District of Columbia, a civic organization, or another similar entity that takes responsibility for the minor, or unless accompanied by the holder of a valid motor vehicle operator’s permit who is 21 years of age or older and who is occupying a seat beside the permittee; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iv)</num>
            <text>Operate a motor vehicle other than a passenger vehicle or motorized bicycle used solely for the purposes of pleasure and not for compensation.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The Mayor is authorized to issue a new or renewed learner’s permit valid for 1-year to any individual 16 years of age or older subject to the following conditions and any other conditions the Mayor may prescribe to protect the public:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(A)</num>
          <text>The applicant shall pay an application fee of $15, which may be increased by the Mayor for the costs of processing and evaluating the application and issuing the permit.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(B)</num>
          <text>The applicant shall have successfully passed all parts of the examination other than the driving demonstration test; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(C)</num>
          <text>No holder of a learner’s permit shall:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Operate a motor vehicle except for a passenger vehicle used solely for pleasure;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Operate a motor vehicle for compensation;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Operate a motor vehicle unless while under the instruction of and accompanied by the holder of a valid motor vehicle operator’s permit who is 21 years of age or older, occupying a seat beside the permittee, and wearing a seat belt; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iv)</num>
            <text>Operate a motor vehicle except during the hours of 6 a.m. and 9 p.m.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2A)</num>
        <text>The Mayor is authorized to issue a new or renewed provisional motor vehicle operator’s permit, valid for a period not to exceed 1-year, to any individual 16 and 1/2 years of age or older subject to the following conditions and any other conditions the Mayor may prescribe to protect the public:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(A)</num>
          <text>The applicant shall pay an application fee of $15, which may be increased by the Mayor for the costs of processing and evaluating the application and issuing the permit;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(B)</num>
          <text>The applicant shall satisfy the qualification requirements set forth in subsection (a)(1)(B) of this section and:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Shall be the holder of a valid learner’s permit issued at least 6 months prior to the application for a provisional permit;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Shall not have admitted to, been found liable for, or been convicted of an offense for which points may be assessed in the last 6 months; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Shall have received 40 hours of driving experience as certified by the holder of a valid motor vehicle operator’s permit from any jurisdiction, who is 21 years of age or older and who has accompanied the applicant while the applicant was operating the motor vehicle.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(C)</num>
          <text>No holder of a provisional permit shall:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Operate a motor vehicle occupied by any passengers other than one holder of a valid motor vehicle operator’s permit who is 21 years of age or older, occupying the seat beside the permittee, and wearing a seat belt, and any other passenger who is a sibling or parent of the permittee; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Operate a motor vehicle between 11:00 p.m. on any Sunday, Monday, Tuesday, Wednesday or Thursday until 6:00 a.m. on the following day during any month except July or August, and from 12:01 a.m. until 6:00 a.m. during July and August and on any Saturday or Sunday the rest of the year, unless driving to or from employment, a school-sponsored activity, religious or an athletic event or related training session in which the permittee is a participant, sponsored by the District of Columbia, a civic organization, or another similar entity that takes responsibility for the minor, or unless accompanied by the holder of a valid motor vehicle operator’s permit who is 21 years of age or older, wearing a seat belt, and occupying a seat beside the permittee.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2B)</num>
        <text>Notwithstanding the provision of subsection (a)(1)(C), (a)(2)(B), and (a)(2A) of this section, a person under the age of 21 who holds a valid motor vehicle permit from another jurisdiction shall be eligible for a comparable District of Columbia driver’s permit, provided that the permittee’s operation of a motor vehicle shall be subject to the applicable restrictions set forth in subsection (a)(1)(D), (a)(2)(C), or (a)(2A)(C) of this section.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2C)</num>
        <text>Penalties:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(A)</num>
          <text>Any violation of the permit restrictions set forth [in] subsection (a)(1)(D), (a)(2)(C), or (a)(2A)(C) of this section, in addition to any other penalties that may be imposed by law, shall result in the suspension of the permits issued pursuant to subsection (a)(1)(C), (a)(2), or (a)(2A) and the addition of a period of time equal to the period of permit suspension to the requirements set forth in (a)(1)(C)(i) and (a)(2A)(B)(i) as follows:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>The first offense shall result in a suspension of 30 days;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>The second offense shall result in suspension of 60 days; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>The third and subsequent offenses shall result in a suspension of 90 days.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(B)</num>
          <text>The Mayor shall notify, in writing, the parent or legal guardian of a permittee who is under 18 years of age and who violates subsection (a)(1)(D), (a)(2)(C), or (a)(2A)(C);</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2D)</num>
        <text>Operator’s permits subject to the provisions of this subchapter, including a learner’s permit, provisional permit and operator’s permit, shall be visually distinguishable pursuant to rules promulgated by the Department of Motor Vehicles.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Any pupil 15 years of age or over enrolled in a high school or junior high school driver education and training course approved by the Mayor or his designated agent may, without obtaining either an operator’s or a learner’s permit, operate a dual control motor vehicle between the hours of 6 a.m. and 11 p.m., where the pupil is under instruction and accompanied by a licensed motor vehicle driving instructor; provided, that such instructor shall at all times while he is engaged in such instruction have on his person a certificate from the principal or other person in charge of such school, stating that such instructor is officially designated to instruct pupils enrolled in such course, and whenever demand is made by a police officer such instructor shall display to him such certificate.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3A)</num>
        <text>Notwithstanding the passenger restrictions set forth in subsection (a)(1)(D), (a)(C)(iii), and (a)(2A)(C)(iii) of this subsection, a permittee who is enrolled in a driver education course may operate a motor vehicle containing a greater number of passengers while the permittee is under the instruction of and accompanied by a licensed motor vehicle driving instructor provided that the other passengers are also receiving driving instruction.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>In the event an operator’s permit, learner’s permit, or a provisional permit issued under the authority of this section is lost or destroyed, or requires replacement for any reason, other than through error or other act of the Mayor, not caused by the person to whom such permit was issued, such person may obtain a duplicate or replacement operator’s permit upon payment of a fee of $20, or such person may obtain a duplicate or replacement learner’s permit, or replacement provisional permit upon payment of a fee of $20.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Enlisted men of the Army, Navy, Air Force, Marine Corps, and Coast Guard shall be issued, without charge, a permit to operate government-owned vehicles, while engaged in official business, upon the presentation of a certificate from their commanding officers to the effect that they are assigned to operate a government vehicle and are qualified to drive, and upon proving to the satisfaction of the Director of the Department of Transportation that they are familiar with the traffic regulations of the District of Columbia.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5A)</num>
        <para>
          <num>(A)</num>
          <text>Except as provided in subparagraph (C) of this paragraph, any eligible United States citizen or resident who is at least 18 years of age but no more than 26 years of age shall be registered with the Selective Service System, in compliance with the requirements of 50 U.S.C. App. § 453, when applying for an operator’s permit or identification card pursuant to the laws of the District.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(B)</num>
          <text>The Director of the Department of Motor Vehicles (“Department”) shall forward, in an electronic format, the personal information required of the applicant identified in subparagraph (A) of this paragraph to the Selective Service System for registration. The Department shall notify the applicant on the application for an operator’s permit or an identification card that submitting the application serves as consent to register with the Selective Service System, in compliance with federal law.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(C)</num>
          <text>The Director of the Department of Motor Vehicles shall make available a form, separate from the application, which shall indicate that the applicant has chosen not to use the operator’s permit or identification card application as a means of registering with the Selective Service System (“waiver form”). The waiver form shall state the effects of failure to register and the programs that condition eligibility upon registration with the Selective Service System. Applicants shall be informed that the waiver form is available upon request. The waiver form shall also state the civil and criminal penalties for failure to register for Selective Service. Failure to submit the waiver form is form shall be deemed affirmative proof that the applicant authorizes the Director of the Department to forward to the Selective Service System the information necessary to complete registration on behalf of the applicant. The waiver form, after completion, shall be added to the applicants file.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(D)</num>
          <text>This form shall comply with the requirements of subchapter II of Chapter 31 of Title 2 [§ <cite path="§2-1931">2-1931</cite> et seq.] including being printed in each required language under § <cite path="§2-1933">2-1933</cite>.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(E)</num>
          <text>An applicant’s submission of the waiver form specified in subparagraph (C) of this paragraph shall not be treated as grounds for denial of an application for an operator’s permit or an identification card.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(F)</num>
          <text>The Director of the Department shall not forward to the Selective Service System the personal information of an individual who completes and submits the waiver form described in subparagraph (C) of this paragraph.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Notwithstanding the provisions of this subsection, the Mayor or his designated agent may, upon compliance with such regulations as the Mayor may prescribe, extend for a period not in excess of 6 years the validity of the operator’s permit of any person who is a resident of the District and who is on active duty outside the District in the armed forces or the Merchant Marine of the United States and who was at the time of leaving the District the holder of a valid operator’s permit.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(a-1)</num>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The Mayor and the Board of Elections and Ethics shall jointly develop an application form and a change of name and address form by January 1, 1989, which shall allow an applicant wishing to register to vote to do so by the use of a single form containing the necessary information for voter registration and the information required for the issuance, renewal, or correction of the applicant’s driver’s permit or identification card.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Commencing not later than May 1, 1989, the Mayor shall provide each qualified elector who applies for the issuance, renewal, or correction of any type of driver’s permit or for an identification card an opportunity to complete an application to register to vote by use of a single form containing the necessary required information for the issuance, renewal, or correction of the driver’s permit or identification card.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The Mayor shall forward all new applications to the Board of Elections and Ethics within 10 days of receipt.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Applications received from the Mayor shall be considered received by the Board of Elections and Ethics as of the date the application was made.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(b)</num>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Each operator’s permit shall state the name and address, and bear the signature of the permittee, together with any additional information that the Mayor may by regulation prescribe. Pursuant to section 205(c)(2)(C)(vi) of the Social Security Act, approved August 14, 1935 (49 Stat. 624, 42 U.S.C. § 405(c)(2)(C)(vi)), the Mayor shall use a randomly generated number as the identification number on any new or renewed license.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The Mayor shall require an applicant for an operator’s permit to provide a social security number, if such a number was issued to the applicant, or, if required by the Mayor, proof that the applicant is not eligible for a social security number, for the purposes of administering and enforcing the laws of the District of Columbia. Notwithstanding any other provision of law, the social security number or other tax identification number shall not be a matter of public record. The social security number shall be kept on file with the issuing agency and the applicant shall be so advised. This paragraph shall not apply to an applicant eligible for a limited purpose driver’s license or permit pursuant to § <cite path="§50-1401.05">50-1401.05</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>An applicant for an operator’s permit who served on active duty in the Armed Forces of the United States and was discharged under conditions other than dishonorable may submit to the Department of Motor Vehicles, along with any other documentation required by this chapter, a DD Form 214, a WD AGO form, or a DD256 form certifying the applicant’s veteran status. Upon receipt of this documentation, the Department of Motor Vehicles shall display the word “veteran” in capital letters on the applicant’s operator’s permit.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(c)</num>
      <text>Any individual to whom a license or permit to operate a motor vehicle has been issued shall have the license or permit in his or her immediate possession at all times while operating a motor vehicle in the District of Columbia and shall exhibit the license or permit to any police officer upon demand. Any person who fails to comply with the requirements of this subsection shall, upon conviction, be fined not less than $10 nor more than $50.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(d)</num>
      <text>No individual shall operate a motor vehicle in the District, except as provided in § <cite path="§50-1401.02">50-1401.02</cite>, without first having obtained an operator’s permit, learner’s permit, provisional permit, or a motorcycle endorsement if operating a motorcycle, issued under the provisions of this subchapter and Title 18 of the District of Columbia Municipal Regulations. Except as provided in subsection (d-1) of this section, any individual violating any provision of this subsection shall be fined not more than the amount set forth in § <cite path="§22-3571.01">22-3571.01</cite> or shall be imprisoned not more than 90 days.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(d-1)</num>
      <text>Any individual who operates a motor vehicle with a District of Columbia permit expired for not more than 90 days shall be subject to a civil fine of not more than $100 pursuant to §§ <cite path="§50-2301.04">50-2301.04</cite>(b) and <cite path="§50-2301.05">50-2301.05</cite>, and shall not be subject to the criminal penalties contained in subsection (d) of this section.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(e)</num>
      <text>Nothing in this subchapter shall relieve any individual from compliance with § <cite path="§47-2829">47-2829</cite>(e).</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(f)</num>
      <text>For purposes of this section and §§ <cite path="§50-1401.02">50-1401.02</cite> and <cite path="§50-1403.01">50-1403.01</cite>, the term “motor vehicle” means a vehicle propelled by an internal-combustion engine, electricity, or steam. The term “motor vehicle” shall not include a traction engine, road roller, vehicle propelled only upon rails or tracks, personal assistive mobility device, as defined by § <cite path="§50-2201.02">50-2201.02</cite>(12), a battery-operated wheelchair when operated by a person with a disability, or a motorized bicycle.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(g)</num>
      <text>[Expired].</text>
    </para>
    <annotations>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>History</heading>
        <annotation>Mar. 3, 1925, 43 Stat. 1121, ch. 443, § 7</annotation>
        <annotation>July 3, 1926, 44 Stat. 812, ch. 739, § 2</annotation>
        <annotation>Feb. 18, 1929, 45 Stat. 1226, ch. 258</annotation>
        <annotation>Feb. 27, 1931, 46 Stat. 1424, ch. 317, § 2</annotation>
        <annotation>June 20, 1939, 53 Stat. 850, ch. 231</annotation>
        <annotation>Nov. 25, 1942, 56 Stat. 1023, ch. 642, § 2</annotation>
        <annotation>Dec. 15, 1944, 58 Stat. 806, ch. 589, § 1</annotation>
        <annotation>Apr. 20, 1948, 62 Stat. 173, ch. 215, §§ 1, 2</annotation>
        <annotation>Aug. 16, 1954, 68 Stat. 732, ch. 741, §§ 1, 2, 3, 4, 5</annotation>
        <annotation>July 24, 1956, 70 Stat. 633, ch. 695, § 2</annotation>
        <annotation doc="Pub. L. 87-737">Oct. 3, 1962, 76 Stat. 710, Pub. L. 87-737, § 1</annotation>
        <annotation doc="Pub. L. 88-287">Mar. 18, 1964, 78 Stat. 167, Pub. L. 88-287, § 1</annotation>
        <annotation doc="Pub. L. 91-106">Oct. 31, 1969, 83 Stat. 174, Pub. L. 91-106, title IV, § 405</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 1-110">Apr. 7, 1977, D.C. Law 1-110, § 4, 23 DCR 8740</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 1-133">Apr. 26, 1977, D.C. Law 1-133, title II, § 201(b), 23 DCR 9697</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 2-104">Sept. 12, 1978, D.C. Law 2-104, § 601, 25 DCR 1275</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 4-36">Oct. 8, 1981, D.C. Law 4-36, § 2, 28 DCR 3383</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 4-97">Apr. 3, 1982, D.C. Law 4-97, § 6, 29 DCR 765</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 4-145">Sept. 14, 1982, D.C. Law 4-145, § 7, 29 DCR 3138</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 5-176">Mar. 15, 1985, D.C. Law 5-176, § 12(b), 32 DCR 748</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 6-38">Sept. 27, 1985, D.C. Law 6-38, § 3, 32 DCR 4307</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 6-194">Feb. 28, 1987, D.C. Law 6-194, § 3, 34 DCR 479</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 7-155">Sept. 29, 1988, D.C. Law 7-155, § 2, 35 DCR 5718</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 9-30">Aug. 17, 1991, D.C. Law 9-30, § 4(b), 38 DCR 4215</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 11-48">Sept. 20, 1995, D.C. Law 11-48, § 5, 42 DCR 3627</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 11-124">May 24, 1996, D.C. Law 11-124, § 2, 43 DCR 1546</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 13-73">Apr. 5, 2000, D.C. Law 13-73, § 2, 46 DCR 10417</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 13-74">Apr. 5, 2000, D.C. Law 13-74, § 2, 46 DCR 10423</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 13-91">Apr. 12, 2000, D.C. Law 13-91, § 150, 47 DCR 520</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 13-289">Apr. 27, 2001, D.C. Law 13-289, § 401(b), 48 DCR 2057</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 14-235">Mar. 25, 2003, D.C. Law 14-235, § 10(d), 49 DCR 9788</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 15-289">Apr. 5, 2005, D.C. Law 15-289, § 2(b), 52 DCR 1446</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 15-307">Apr. 8, 2005, D.C. Law 15-307, § 205(a), 52 DCR 1700</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 16-224">Mar. 6, 2007, D.C. Law 16-224, § 101(c), 53 DCR 10225</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 16-279">Mar. 14, 2007, D.C. Law 16-279, §§ 202(c), 401(b), 54 DCR 903</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 17-219">Aug. 16, 2008, D.C. Law 17-219, § 6011, 55 DCR 7598</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 19-21">Sept. 14, 2011, D.C. Law 19-21, § 6002, 58 DCR 6226</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 19-189">Oct. 23, 2012, D.C. Law 19-189, § 2, 59 DCR 10156</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 19-290">Apr. 27, 2013, D.C. Law 19-290, § 5(b), 60 DCR 2343</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 19-317">June 11, 2013, D.C. Law 19-317, § 268(a), 60 DCR 2064</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 20-49">Dec. 13, 2013, D.C. Law 20-49, § 2(a), 60 DCR 15148</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 20-52">D.C. Law 20-52, § 2(a), 60 DCR 15157</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 20-62">Jan. 17, 2014, D.C. Law 20-62, § 2(a), 60 DCR 16026</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Cross References</heading>
        <annotation>Driver education programs in public schools, see § <cite path="§38-912">38-912</cite>.</annotation>
        <annotation>Registration of motor vehicles, fee schedules, see § <cite path="§50-1501.03">50-1501.03</cite>.</annotation>
        <annotation>Regulation of traffic, power to promulgate regulations, see § <cite path="§50-2201.03">50-2201.03</cite>.</annotation>
        <annotation>Traffic adjudication, violations prosecuted as criminal offenses, see § <cite path="§50-2302.02">50-2302.02</cite>.</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Section References</heading>
        <annotation>This section is referenced in § <cite path="§16-801">16-801</cite>, § <cite path="§50-1401.02">50-1401.02</cite>, § <cite path="§50-1401.05">50-1401.05</cite>, § <cite path="§50-1403.02">50-1403.02</cite>, § <cite path="§50-2201.03">50-2201.03</cite>, and § <cite path="§50-2302.02">50-2302.02</cite>.</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Prior Codifications</heading>
        <annotation>1981 Ed., § 40-301.</annotation>
        <annotation>1973 Ed., § 40-301.</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Effect of Amendments</heading>
        <annotation><cite doc="D.C. Law 13-73">D.C. Law 13-73</cite> rewrote subsecs. (a)(1) and (a)(2), inserted new pars. (2A) to (2D) and (3A) in subsec. (a) and rewrote pars. (3) and (4) of subsec. (a).</annotation>
        <annotation>Section 5 of <cite doc="D.C. Law 13-73">D.C. Law 13-73</cite>, as amended by section 14 of <cite doc="D.C. Law 13-313">D.C. Law 13-313</cite> provided: “This act shall apply on September 1, 2000.”</annotation>
        <annotation><cite doc="D.C. Law 13-74">D.C. Law 13-74</cite> rewrote subsec. (b) in order to prohibit the Mayor from requiring that the social security number be used as identification number for driver’s licenses.</annotation>
        <annotation><cite doc="D.C. Law 13-91">D.C. Law 13-91</cite> added subsec. (a)(2)(C)(iv).</annotation>
        <annotation><cite doc="D.C. Law 13-289">D.C. Law 13-289</cite>, in subsec. (a), added par. (5A).</annotation>
        <annotation><cite doc="D.C. Law 14-235">D.C. Law 14-235</cite> rewrote subsec. (f) which had read as follows: “(f) For purposes of this section and §§ <cite path="§50-1403.01">50-1403.01</cite> and <cite path="§50-1401.02">50-1401.02</cite> the term ‘motor vehicle’ means all vehicles propelled by internal combustion engines, electricity, or steam. The term ‘motor vehicle’ shall not include traction engines, road rollers, vehicles propelled only upon rails or tracks, and battery-operated wheelchairs when operated by a handicapped person at speeds not exceeding 10 miles per hour.”</annotation>
        <annotation><cite doc="D.C. Law 15-289">D.C. Law 15-289</cite>, in subsec. (a)(1)(B)(ii), substituted “Mayor; and” for “Mayor. No practical demonstration shall be required for a motorized bicycle permit; and”.</annotation>
        <annotation><cite doc="D.C. Law 15-307">D.C. Law 15-307</cite>, in subsec. (a)(2A)(B)(ii), inserted “in the last 6 months” following “assessed”.</annotation>
        <annotation><cite doc="D.C. Law 16-224">D.C. Law 16-224</cite>, in subsec. (f), substituted “personal mobility devices, as defined by § <cite path="§50-2201.02">50-2201.02</cite>(12), or a battery-operated wheelchair when operated by a person with a disability” for “electric personal assistive mobility devices, as defined by § <cite path="§50-2201.02">50-2201.02</cite>(12), and battery-operated wheelchairs when operated by a handicapped person at speeds not exceeding 10 miles per hour”.</annotation>
        <annotation><cite doc="D.C. Law 16-279">D.C. Law 16-279</cite>, in subsec. (a)(1)(A), added a sentence to the end of the paragraph relating to the proration of fees; in subsec. (a)(2), substituted “issue a new or renewed” for “issue a”; in subsec. (a)(4), increased the duplicate operators permit fee from $5 to $7 and increased the duplicate learner’s or replacement provisional permit fee from $3 to $7; in subsec. (b)(1), substituted “Pursuant to section 205(c)(2)(vi) of the Social Security Act, approved August 14, 1935 (49 Stat. 624,  42 U.S.C. 405(c)(2)(C)(vi)), the Mayor shall use a randomly generated number as the identification number on any new or renewed license” for “The Mayor shall use a randomly generated number as the identification number of the license and shall not print the social security number of the permittee on the license, unless the permittee requests that their social security number be used as the identification number of the license”; and, in subsec. (b)(2), substituted “provide a social security number, if such a number was issued to the applicant, or, if required by the Mayor, proof that the applicant is not eligible for a social security number” for “provide a social security number”; and in subsec. (d), substituted “provisional permit, or a motorcycle endorsement if operating a motorcycle, issued under the provisions of this subchapter and Title 18 of the District of Columbia Municipal Regulations” for “or a provisional permit issued under the provisions of this subchapter”.</annotation>
        <annotation><cite doc="D.C. Law 17-219">D.C. Law 17-219</cite> rewrote the lead-in language of subsec. (a)(1), which had read as follows: “(a)(1) The Mayor is authorized to issue a new or renewed motor vehicle operator’s permit, valid for a period not to exceed 5 years, to any individual 17 years of age or older subject to the following conditions and any other conditions the Mayor may prescribe to protect the public:”.</annotation>
        <annotation><cite doc="D.C. Law 19-21">D.C. Law 19-21</cite>, in subsec. (a)(4), substituted “$20” for “$7” in two places.</annotation>
        <annotation>The 2012 amendment by <cite doc="D.C. Law 19-189">D.C. Law 19-189</cite> rewrote (a)(5A).</annotation>
        <annotation>The 2013 amendment by <cite doc="D.C. Law 19-290">D.C. Law 19-290</cite> rewrote (f).</annotation>
        <annotation>The 2013 amendment by <cite doc="D.C. Law 19-317">D.C. Law 19-317</cite> substituted “not more than the amount set forth in § <cite path="§22-3571.01">22-3571.01</cite>” for “not more than $300” in (d).</annotation>
        <annotation>The 2013 amendment by <cite doc="D.C. Law 20-49">D.C. Law 20-49</cite> substituted “traffic regulations and regulations for safely sharing roadways with pedestrians and bicyclists in the District” for “traffic regulations of the District” in (a)(1)(B)(i).</annotation>
        <annotation>The 2013 amendment by <cite doc="D.C. Law 20-52">D.C. Law 20-52</cite> added (b)(3).</annotation>
        <annotation>The 2014 amendment by <cite doc="D.C. Law 20-62">D.C. Law 20-62</cite> added (a)(1)(A-i); and added the last sentence in (b)(2).</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Temporary Amendment of Section</heading>
        <annotation>For temporary (225 day) amendment of section, see § 109 of Omnibus Budget Support Temporary Act of 1991 (<cite doc="D.C. Law 9-19">D.C. Law 9-19</cite>, June 21, 1991, law notification  38 DCR 5786).</annotation>
        <annotation>For temporary (225 day) amendment of section, see § 12 of Child Support and Welfare Reform Compliance Temporary Amendment Act of 1998 (<cite doc="D.C. Law 12-210">D.C. Law 12-210</cite>, April 13, 1999, law notification  46 DCR 3832).</annotation>
        <annotation>For temporary (225 day) amendment of section, see § 112 of Child Support and Welfare Reform Compliance Temporary Amendment Act of 1999 (<cite doc="D.C. Law 13-57">D.C. Law 13-57</cite>, March 7, 2000, law notification  47 DCR 1979).</annotation>
        <annotation>For temporary (225 day) amendment of section, see § 112 of Child Support and Welfare Reform Compliance Temporary Amendment Act of 2000 (<cite doc="D.C. Law 13-207">D.C. Law 13-207</cite>, March 31, 2001, law notification  48 DCR 3238).</annotation>
        <annotation>For temporary (225 day) amendment of section, see § 2 of Safe Teenage Driving and Merit Personnel Technical Amendment Temporary Amendment Act of 2000 (<cite doc="D.C. Law 13-210">D.C. Law 13-210</cite>, March 31, 2001, law notification  48 DCR 3241).</annotation>
        <annotation>For temporary (225 day) amendment of section, see § 3 of Motor Vehicle Registration and Operator’s Permit Issuance Enhancement Temporary Amendment Act of 2002 (<cite doc="D.C. Law 14-221">D.C. Law 14-221</cite>, March 25, 2003, law notification  50 DCR 2734).</annotation>
        <annotation>For temporary (225 day) amendment of section, see § 10(b) of Motor Vehicle Definition Electric Personal Assistive Mobility Device Exemption Temporary Amendment Act of 2006 (<cite doc="D.C. Law 16-85">D.C. Law 16-85</cite>, April 4, 2006, law notification  53 DCR 3344).</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Emergency Legislation</heading>
        <annotation>For temporary amendment of section, see § 14 of the Child Support and Welfare Reform Compliance Second Emergency Amendment Act of 1998 (D.C. Act 12-439, August 12, 1998,  45 DCR 6110), § 13 of the Child Support and Welfare Reform Compliance Legislative Review Emergency Amendment Act of 1998 (D.C. Act 12-503, October 27, 1998,  45 DCR 8495), and § 13 of the Child Support and Welfare Reform Compliance Second Congressional Review Emergency Amendment Act of 1998 (D.C. Act 12-600, January 20, 1999,  46 DCR 1239.</annotation>
        <annotation>For temporary (90-day) amendment of section, see § 112 of the Child Support and Welfare Reform Compliance Emergency Amendment Act of 1999 (D.C. Act 13-126, August 4, 1999,  46 DCR 6606).</annotation>
        <annotation>For temporary (90-day) amendment of section, see § 112 of the Child Support and Welfare Reform Compliance Legislative Review Emergency Amendment Act of 1999 (D.C. Act 13-177, November 2, 1999,  46 DCR 9678).</annotation>
        <annotation>For temporary (90-day) amendment of section, see § 112 of the Child Support and Welfare Reform Compliance Congressional Review Emergency Amendment Act of 1999 (D.C. Act 13-241, January 11, 2000,  47 DCR 581).</annotation>
        <annotation>For temporary (90-day) amendment of section, see § 2 of the Safe Teenage Driving and Merit Personnel Technical Amendment Emergency Amendment Act of 2000 (D.C. Act 13-430, August 14, 2000,  47 DCR 7459).</annotation>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 day) amendment of section, see § 112 of the Child Support and Welfare Reform Compliance Emergency Amendment Act of 2000 (D.C. Act 13-446, November 7, 2000,  47 DCR 9213).</annotation>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 day) amendment of section, see § 2 of the Safe Teenage Driving and Merit Personnel Technical Amendment Legislative Review Emergency Amendment Act of 2000 (D.C. Act 13-489, December 18, 2000,  48 DCR 43).</annotation>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 day) amendment of section, see § 2 of Safe Teenage Driving and Merit Personnel Technical Amendment Congressional Review Emergency Amendment Act of 2001 (D.C. Act 14-30, April 2, 2001,  48 DCR 3336).</annotation>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 day) amendment of section and establishment of adjudication process, see §§ 3 and 4 of Motor Vehicle Registration and Operator’s Permit issuance Enhancement Congressional Review Emergency Act of 2002 (D.C. Act 14-540, December 2, 2002,  49 DCR 11657).</annotation>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 day) amendment of section and establishment of adjudication process, see §§ 3 and 4 of Motor Vehicle Registration and Operator’s Permit Issuance Enhancement Second Congressional Review Emergency Amendment Act of 2002 (D.C. Act  14-601, January 7, 2003,  50 DCR 681).</annotation>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 day) amendment of section, see §§ 3 and 4 of Motor Vehicle Registration and Operator’s Permit Issuance Enhancement Emergency Amendment Act of 2002 (D.C. Act 14-413, July 16, 2002,  49 DCR 7378).</annotation>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 day) amendment of section, see § 201 of Prohibition on the Reckless Operation of Recreational Motor Vehicles Emergency Act of 2004 (D.C. Act 15-462, June 23, 2004,  51 DCR 6750).</annotation>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 day) amendment of section, see § 10(d) of Motor Vehicle Definition Electric Personal Assistive Mobility Device Exemption Emergency Amendment Act of 2005 (D.C. Act 16-237, December 22, 2005,  53 DCR 249).</annotation>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 day) amendment of section, see § 10(d) of Motor Vehicle Definition Electric Personal Assistive Mobility Device Exemption Congressional Review Emergency Amendment Act of 2006 (D.C. Act 16-323, March 23, 2006,  53 DCR 2567).</annotation>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 day) amendment of section, see § 101(c) of Personal Mobility Device Emergency Amendment Act of 2006 (D.C. Act 16-528, December 4, 2006,  53 DCR 9826).</annotation>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 day) amendment of section, see § 6002 of Fiscal Year 2012 Budget Support Emergency Act of 2011 (D.C. Act 19-93, June 29, 2011,  58 DCR 5599).</annotation>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 days) amendment of this section, see § 268(a) of the Criminal Fine Proportionality Emergency Act of 2013 (D.C. Act 20-45, April 1, 2013,  60 DCR 5400, 20 DCSTAT 1300).</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Short Title</heading>
        <text>Short title: Section 6010 of <cite doc="D.C. Law 17-219">D.C. Law 17-219</cite> provided that subtitle D of title VI of the act may be cited as the “Department of Motor Vehicles Driver License, Special Identification Card, and Vehicle Inspection Amendment Act of 2008”.</text>
        <text>Short title: Section 6001 of <cite doc="D.C. Law 19-21">D.C. Law 19-21</cite> provided that subtitle A of title VI of the act may be cited as “Department of Motor Vehicles Fee Modification Amendment Act of 2011”.</text>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Expiration of Law</heading>
        <text>Expiration of Law 14-235</text>
        <text>Section 14 of <cite doc="D.C. Law 14-235">D.C. Law 14-235</cite> provided that the act shall expire on October 1, 2005.</text>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Delegation of Authority</heading>
        <annotation>Delegation of authority pursuant to <cite doc="D.C. Law 6-194">D.C. Law 6-194</cite>, “District of Columbia Anatomical Gift Amendment Act of 1986.”, see Mayor’s Order 88-49, February 25, 1988.</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Editor's Notes</heading>
        <text>Department of Vehicles and Traffic abolished: See Historical and Statutory Notes following § <cite path="§50-2201.03">50-2201.03</cite>.</text>
        <text>Definitions applicable: For definitions applicable in this chapter, see § <cite path="§50-2201.02">50-2201.02</cite>.</text>
        <text><cite doc="D.C. Law 11-48">D.C. Law 11-48</cite> held unconstitutional: The Juvenile Curfew Act of 1995, which added subsection (g) of this section, held unconstitutional.</text>
        <text>Section 6005 of <cite doc="D.C. Law 19-21">D.C. Law 19-21</cite> provided: “Sec. 6005. This subtitle shall apply as of July 1, 2011.”</text>
        <text>Section 3 of <cite doc="D.C. Law 19-189">D.C. Law 19-189</cite> provided that the act shall apply as of January 1, 2013.</text>
        <text>Applicability of <cite doc="D.C. Law 19-317">D.C. Law 19-317</cite>: Section 401 of <cite doc="D.C. Law 19-317">D.C. Law 19-317</cite> provided that the act shall apply only to offenses committed on or after June 11, 2013.</text>
        <text>Applicability of <cite doc="D.C. Law 20-52">D.C. Law 20-52</cite>: Section 3 of <cite doc="D.C. Law 20-52">D.C. Law 20-52</cite> provided that the act shall apply as of October 1, 2013.</text>
        <text>Applicability of <cite doc="D.C. Law 20-62">D.C. Law 20-62</cite>: Section 3 of <cite doc="D.C. Law 20-62">D.C. Law 20-62</cite> provided that the act shall apply as of May 1, 2014.</text>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Change in Government</heading>
        <annotation>This section originated at a time when local government powers were delegated to a Board of Commissioners of the District of Columbia (see Acts Relating to the Establishment of the District of Columbia and its Various Forms of Governmental Organization in Volume 1). Section 401 of Reorganization Plan No. 3 of 1967 (see Reorganization Plans in Volume 1) transferred all of the functions of the Board of Commissioners under this section to a single Commissioner. The District of Columbia Self-Government and Governmental Reorganization Act, 87 Stat. 818, § 711 ( D.C. Code, § <cite path="§1-207.11">1-207.11</cite>), abolished the District of Columbia Council and the Office of Commissioner of the District of Columbia. These branches of government were replaced by the Council of the District of Columbia and the Office of Mayor of the District of Columbia, respectively. Accordingly, and also pursuant to § 714(a) of such Act ( D.C. Code, § <cite path="§1-207.14">1-207.14</cite>(a)), appropriate changes in terminology were made in this section.</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section from-code="true">
    <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" path="|50|14|I"/>
    <num codify:value="50-1401.01a">7a</num>
    <heading>Notification of operator’s permit expiration.</heading>
    <text>The Mayor shall notify an owner of the expiration date of the owner’s operator’s permit. The required notice shall be mailed to the named owner at the address of record at least 30 days prior to the date of expiration.</text>
    <annotations>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>History</heading>
        <annotation>Mar. 3, 1925, ch. 443, § 7a</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 15-307">as added Apr. 8, 2005, D.C. Law 15-307, § 702, 52 DCR 1700</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section from-code="true">
    <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" path="|50|14|I"/>
    <num codify:value="50-1401.01b">7b</num>
    <heading>Prohibition on release and use of certain personal information from motor vehicle records and accident reports.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>(a)</num>
      <text>For the purposes of this section, the term:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>“Accident report” means any record prepared as a result of a vehicular accident, also known as the Metropolitan Police Department Form PD-10.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(1A)</num>
        <text>“Information relating to legal presence” means any information that may reveal whether a person is legally present in the United States, including whether a person’s driver’s license or identification card was issued under § <cite path="§50-1401.05">50-1401.05</cite>, and the documentation provided by an applicant to prove identity, date of birth, and residence in connection with an application for a driver’s license or identification card.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>“Motor vehicle record” means any record that pertains to a motor vehicle operator’s application, permit, motor vehicle title, motor vehicle registration, or identification card issued by the Department of Motor Vehicles.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <para>
          <num>(A)</num>
          <text>“Personal information” shall include an individual’s photograph or image, social security number, driver identification number or identification card number, name, address, telephone number, medical or disability information, and emergency contact information.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(B)</num>
          <text>The term “personal information” shall not include information relating to vehicular crashes, driving violations, or driver status.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(b)</num>
      <text>Except as provided in subsections (c), (d) and (e) of this section, the Department of Motor Vehicles (“Department”), the Metropolitan Police Department, and any officer, employee, or contractor affiliated with either department, or any other person or entity shall not knowingly disclose or otherwise make available personal information about an individual obtained by the Department or the Metropolitan Police Department in connection with a motor vehicle record or an accident report.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(c)</num>
      <text>Personal information contained in motor vehicle records or accident reports prohibited from disclosure by subsection (b) of this section may be released to a person upon the showing of sufficient written proof for the following uses:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>To carry out the purposes of Titles I and IV of the Anti Car Theft Act of 1992, approved October 25, 1992 (106 Stat. 3384; 49 U.S.C. § 30501 et seq. 49 U.S.C. § 33101 et seq.); the Automobile Information Disclosure Act, approved July 7, 1958 (72 Stat. 325; 15 U.S.C. § 1231 et seq.), the Clean Air Act, approved December 17, 1963 (77 Stat. 392; 42 U.S.C. § 7401 et seq.), and chapters 301, 305, and 321-331 of Title 49 of the United States Code (49 U.S.C. § 30101 et seq., 49 U.S.C. § 30501 et seq., 49 U.S.C. § 32101 et seq. through 49 U.S.C. § 33101 et seq.), in connection with matters of:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(A)</num>
          <text>Motor vehicles or driver safety and theft;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(B)</num>
          <text>Motor vehicle emissions;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(C)</num>
          <text>Motor vehicle product alterations, recalls, or advisories;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(D)</num>
          <text>Performance monitoring of motor vehicles and dealers by motor vehicle manufacturers; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(E)</num>
          <text>Removal of non-owner records from the original owner records of motor vehicle manufacturers;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>By any government agency, including any court or law enforcement agency, in carrying out its core functions, or any private person or entity acting on behalf of a federal, state, or local agency in carrying out its core functions;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>In the normal course of business by a legitimate business or its agents, employees, or contractors, but only to verify the accuracy of personal information submitted by the individual to the business or its agents, employees, or contractors;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>For use in connection with an actual or contemplated civil, criminal, administrative, or arbitral proceeding in a court or agency, or before a self-regulatory body for any of the following, except that the use shall not include the solicitation of clients, prohibited by § <cite path="§22-3225.14">22-3225.14</cite>:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(A)</num>
          <text>For use by a person involved in the accident and listed on the accident report;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(B)</num>
          <text>Service of process by a certified process server, special process server, or other person authorized to serve process in the District;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(C)</num>
          <text>For an accident report, an investigation in anticipation of litigation by an attorney representing a person or entity involved in the motor vehicle accident and licensed to practice law in the District or any other United States jurisdiction, or the agent of the attorney;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(D)</num>
          <text>For a motor vehicle record, an investigation in anticipation of litigation by an attorney licensed to practice law in the District or any other United States jurisdiction, or the agent of the attorney;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(E)</num>
          <text>Execution or enforcement of judgments and orders; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(F)</num>
          <text>Compliance with a court order;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>In research activities and for use in producing statistical reports; so long as the personal information is not published, re-disclosed, or used to contact individuals;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>For use by any insurer or insurance support organization, or by a self-insured entity, or its agents, employees, or contractors, in connection with claims of investigation activities, anti-fraud activities, rating, or underwriting;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>In providing notice to the owners of towed or impounded vehicles;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>For use by a licensed private investigative agency or licensed security service for a purpose permitted under this subsection; provided, that the use shall not include the solicitation of clients, prohibited by § <cite path="§22-3225.14">22-3225.14</cite>. Personal information obtained based on an exempt driver’s record may not be provided to a client who cannot demonstrate a need based on a permitted use under this subsection;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>By an employer or its agent or insurer to obtain or verify information relating to a holder of a commercial driver’s license required under 49 U.S.C. § 31301 et seq.;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(10)</num>
        <text>For bulk distribution for surveys, marketing, or solicitations when the department has obtained the express consent of the person to whom such personal information pertains;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(11)</num>
        <text>By an organ or tissue donor organization; provided, that the person to whom such information applies has consented in a writing submitted to the Department to be an organ or tissue donor;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(12)</num>
        <text>For any use if the requesting person demonstrates that he or she has obtained the written consent of the person who is the subject of the motor vehicle record or accident report. The consent shall remain in effect until it is revoked by the person who is the subject of the motor vehicle record or accident report; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(13)</num>
        <text>For use in connection with the operation of private toll transportation facilities.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(d)</num>
      <text>Notwithstanding subsection (c) of this section, without the express consent of the person to whom such information applies, the following information contained in motor vehicle records or accident reports may be released only as specified in this subsection:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Social security numbers may be released only as provided in subsections (c)(2) or (c)(9) of this section;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>An individual’s photograph or image may be released only as provided in subsection (c)(2) of this section;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Medical disability information may be released only as provided in subsections (c)(2) or (c)(9) of this section;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Emergency contact information may be released only to law enforcement agencies for the purposes of contacting individuals listed in the event of an emergency; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Information relating to legal presence shall not be disclosed to any person, and shall not be disclosed to any federal, state, or local governmental entity except as necessary to comply with a legally issued warrant or subpoena.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(1)</num>
      <text>Personal information prohibited from disclosure by subsection (b) of this section may be disclosed by the Department to a firm, corporation, or similar business entity whose primary business interest is to resell or re-disclose the personal information to persons who are authorized to receive such information. Before the Department’s disclosure of personal information, such firm, corporation, or similar business entity must first enter into a contract with the Department regarding the care, custody, and control of the personal information to ensure compliance with the Driver’s Privacy Protection Act of 1994, approved September 13, 1994 (108 Stat. 2099; 18 U.S.C. § 2721 et seq.), and applicable District laws.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(2)</num>
      <text>An authorized recipient of personal information contained in a motor vehicle record, except a recipient under subsection (c)(10) of this section, may contract with the Department to resell or re-disclose the information for any use permitted under this section. Authorized recipients of personal information under subsection (c)(10) of this section may resell or re-disclose personal information only in accordance with subsection (c)(10) of this section.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(3)</num>
      <text>An authorized recipient who resells or re-discloses personal information shall maintain, for a period of 5 years, records identifying each person or entity that receives the personal information and the permitted purpose for which it will be used. The records shall be made available for inspection upon request by the Department.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(4)</num>
      <text>The Department and the Metropolitan Police Department may require documentation to support a request for personal information, and either department shall have the sole discretion to determine whether the documentation provided is sufficient to support the request.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(f)</num>
      <text>The Department and the Metropolitan Police Department may adopt rules to carry out the purposes of this section. Rules adopted by either department may provide for the payment of applicable fees. In addition, the rules may require an individual requesting the disclosure of personal information pursuant to this subsection to provide proof of identity and, to the extent required, provide assurance that the use will be only as authorized or that the consent of the person who is the subject of the personal information has been obtained. These conditions may include the making and filing of a written application in a form and containing information and certification requirements required by either department.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(g)</num>
      <text>Failure to comply with the restrictions set forth in this section may subject the violator to penalties and civil action as set forth in the Driver’s Privacy Protection Act of 1994, approved September 13, 1994 (108 Stat. 2099; 18 U.S.C. §§ 2721, 2723, 2724).</text>
    </para>
    <annotations>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>History</heading>
        <annotation>Mar. 3, 1925, 43 Stat. 1121, ch. 443, § 7b</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 19-207">as added Mar. 5, 2013, D.C. Law 19-207, § 3, 59 DCR 12507</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 19-320">June 19, 2013, D.C. Law 19-320, § 512, 60 DCR 3390</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 20-62">Jan. 17, 2014, D.C. Law 20-62, § 2(b), 60 DCR 16026</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Effect of Amendments</heading>
        <annotation>The 2013 amendment by <cite doc="D.C. Law 19-207">D.C. Law 19-207</cite> added this section.</annotation>
        <annotation>The 2013 amendment by <cite doc="D.C. Law 19-320">D.C. Law 19-320</cite> substituted “name, address” for “name address” in (a)(3)(A); in (b), substituted “obtained by the Department” for “obtained by the Department of Motor Vehicles” and substituted “motor vehicle” for “motor-vehicle”; rewrote (c)(4)(A), which read; “A person listed on the accident report”; added the second occurrence of “or accident report” in (c)(12); substituted “prohibited from disclosure by subsection (b) of this section” for “made confidential and prohibited from disclosure” near the beginning of (e)(1); in the second sentence of (e)(2), deleted “However only” from the beginning and substituted “only in accordance with” for “pursuant to”; and deleted “of Motor Vehicles” following “the Department” in (e)(2), (e)(4), and (f).</annotation>
        <annotation>The 2014 amendment by <cite doc="D.C. Law 20-62">D.C. Law 20-62</cite> added (a)(1A); and added (d)(5) and made related changes.</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Emergency Legislation</heading>
        <annotation>For temporary amendment of section, see § 512 of the Omnibus Criminal Code Amendments Emergency Amendment Act of 2012 (D.C. Act 19-599, January 14, 2013,  60 DCR 1017).</annotation>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 days) amendment of this section, see § 512 of the Omnibus Criminal Code Amendment Congressional Review Emergency Act of 2013 (D.C. Act 20-44, April 1, 2013,  60 DCR 5381, 20 DCSTAT 1281).</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Editor's Notes</heading>
        <annotation>Applicability of <cite doc="D.C. Law 20-62">D.C. Law 20-62</cite>: Section 3 of <cite doc="D.C. Law 20-62">D.C. Law 20-62</cite> provided that the act shall apply as of May 1, 2014.</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section from-code="true">
    <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" path="|50|14|I"/>
    <num codify:value="50-1401.02">8</num>
    <heading>Exemptions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>(a)</num>
      <text>The owner or operator of any motor vehicle who is not a legal resident of the District of Columbia, and who has complied with the laws of any state, territory, or possession of the United States, or of a foreign country or political subdivision thereof, shall, subject to the provisions of this section, be exempt for a continuous 30 day period immediately following the entrance of such owner or operator into the District of Columbia from compliance with § <cite path="§50-1401.01">50-1401.01</cite> and § <cite path="§50-1501.02">50-1501.02</cite>. The 30-day exemption period shall not apply to commercial motor vehicles required to obtain a permit, as provided by § <cite path="§50-1507.03">50-1507.03</cite> or charter busses identified in § <cite path="§50-1501.02">50-1501.02</cite>(j).</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(b)</num>
      <text>Upon expiration of the 30 day exemption period, the owner or operator of any motor vehicle shall be required either:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>To comply with the provisions of §§ <cite path="§50-1401.01">50-1401.01</cite> and <cite path="§50-1501.02">50-1501.02</cite> and all applicable provisions of the District of Columbia Municipal Regulations requiring the registration of motor vehicles, the display of identification tags, and the licensing of owners or operators of motor vehicles in the District of Columbia; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>To purchase, from the Mayor or his designated agent, a reciprocity sticker which shall be valid 180 days from the date of its issuance if the owner or operator has complied with the motor vehicle registration and licensing laws of the state, territory, or possession of the United States, or of a foreign country or political subdivision thereof, of which the owner or operator is a legal resident and the owner or operator is not a legal resident of the District of Columbia. Upon expiration of the reciprocity sticker, the owner or operator who continues to reside in the District of Columbia shall be required to comply with §§ <cite path="§50-1401.01">50-1401.01</cite> and <cite path="§50-1501.02">50-1501.02</cite> and all applicable provisions of the District of Columbia Municipal Regulations requiring the registration of motor vehicles, the display of identification tags, and the licensing of owners or operators of motor vehicles in the District of Columbia.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(c)</num>
      <text>The following persons shall, if they have complied with the motor vehicle registration and licensing laws of the state, territory, or possession of the United States of which they are a legal resident, be exempt during their respective term of office or employment from compliance with §§ <cite path="§50-1401.01">50-1401.01</cite> and <cite path="§50-1501.02">50-1501.02</cite>, and all applicable provisions of the District of Columbia Municipal Regulations requiring the registration of motor vehicles, the display of identification tags, and the licensing of owners or operators of motor vehicles in the District of Columbia:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Senators, Representatives, and Delegates of the United States Congress;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Personal employees of Senators, Representatives, and Delegates of the United States Congress who are legal residents of the state, territory, or possession from which said Senators, Representatives, and Delegates have been elected or appointed. Personal employees include only those individuals who work directly and specifically for a Senator, Representative, or Delegate of the United States Congress and does not include those staff members considered committee or patronage staff;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The President and Vice-President of the United States;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Officers of the executive branch of the United States government who are not domiciled within the District of Columbia, whose appointment to the office held by them was by the President of the United States, subject to confirmation by the Senate, and whose tenure of office is at the pleasure of the President;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Any nonresident service member in accordance with section 511 of the Soldiers’ and Sailors’ Civil Relief Act of 1940, approved December 19, 2003 (117 Stat. 2835;  50 U.S.C. § 571);</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Any foreign mission, its members, or dependents of its members, but only if they have been issued a title and registration by the United States Department of State; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>Any minor under 21 years of age or spouse of any person identified in paragraphs (1) through (6); provided, that the person identified in paragraphs (1) through (6) signs an affidavit stating the minor or spouse resides at the same address in the District as the affiant.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(d)</num>
      <text>Those persons listed under subsection (c) of this section shall be required to obtain and display a valid reciprocity sticker. The Mayor shall issue, upon application and a fee of $50, a reciprocity sticker for those persons listed under subsection (c) of this section, valid for 1 year, and renewable for the respective term of office or employment.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(e)</num>
      <text>Persons enrolled as full-time students engaged in higher education (as defined by the respective institutions of higher education in the District of Columbia) in an institution of higher education licensed to operate in the District of Columbia, and who are not residents of the District of Columbia, shall, if they have complied with the motor vehicle registration and licensing laws of the state, territory, or possession of the United States of which they are a legal resident, be exempt during their respective tenure as full-time students engaged in higher education from compliance with §§ <cite path="§50-1401.01">50-1401.01</cite> and <cite path="§50-1501.02">50-1501.02</cite>, and all applicable provisions of the District of Columbia Municipal Regulations requiring the registration of motor vehicles, the display of identification tags, and the licensing of owners or operators of motor vehicles in the District of Columbia; provided, that the full-time student shall be required to obtain and display a valid reciprocity sticker.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A full-time student shall be required to submit proof, as required by the Mayor, that the student is a full-time student and is in compliance with this subsection.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The Mayor shall issue, upon application and for a $338 fee, a reciprocity sticker to full-time students who comply with this section. Such sticker shall be valid for 1 year. A full-time student while enrolled in an institution of higher education in the District of Columbia and while in compliance with this subsection shall be able to obtain successive reciprocity stickers, each valid for 1 year and each for a fee of $338.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>A full-time student who is a resident of the District of Columbia, who is registered to vote in the District of Columbia, who is employed for more than 20 hours a week, whose address for the purpose of paying tuition for higher education is in the District of Columbia, whose parent or parents domicile in the District of Columbia or whose parents are divorced or separated and the custodial parent domiciles in the District of Columbia, whose student loan is from a bank or savings and loan in the District of Columbia, or who fulfills any criteria promulgated by the Mayor of the District of Columbia shall be required to comply with § <cite path="§50-1401.01">50-1401.01</cite> and § <cite path="§50-1501.02">50-1501.02</cite>, and all applicable provisions of the District of Columbia Municipal Regulations requiring the registration of motor vehicles, the display of identification tags, and the licensing of owners or operators of motor vehicles in the District of Columbia.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Notwithstanding any other law, full-time students who reside within the boundaries of Advisory Neighborhood Commissions 2A and 2E shall not be issued or use a reciprocity parking sticker for out of state vehicles. As of January 1, 2003, this provision shall also apply to full-time students who reside within the boundaries of ANC 3D06 and 3D09.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(e-1)</num>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>An owner or operator of a motor vehicle shall be exempt from compliance with § <cite path="§50-1401.01">50-1401.01</cite>, § <cite path="§50-1501.02">50-1501.02</cite>, and sections 414.1, 422.1, and 422.7 of Title 18 of the District of Columbia Municipal Regulations (18 DCMR § 414.1, 422.1, 422.7); provided, that the owner or operator:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(A)</num>
          <text>Is a legal resident of a state, territory, possession of the United States, foreign country, or political subdivision other than the District of Columbia;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(B)</num>
          <text>Owns residential property in the District of Columbia;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(C)</num>
          <text>Lives at the residential property described in subparagraph (B) of this paragraph on a part-time basis;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(D)</num>
          <text>Has a motor vehicle registered and licensed in a state, territory, possession of the United States, foreign country, or political subdivision other than the District of Columbia; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(E)</num>
          <text>Has complied with the motor vehicle registration and licensing laws of a state, territory, or possession of the United States, or of a foreign country or political subdivision thereof, of which the owner or operator is a legal resident.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>An individual who meets the qualifications set forth in paragraph (1) of this subsection shall be required to submit proof, as required by the Mayor, that the individual owns residential property in the District and is a part-time resident.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>An individual who meets the qualifications set forth in paragraphs (1) and (2) of this subsection may obtain and display a valid reciprocity sticker. The Mayor shall issue, upon application and for a $338 fee, a reciprocity sticker to the motor vehicle owner or operator who complies with this subsection, which shall be valid for one year. A motor vehicle owner or operator while in compliance with this subsection shall be able to obtain successive reciprocity stickers, each valid for one year, and each for a fee of $338.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(e-2)</num>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A motor vehicle owner that is a partnership, corporation, association, trust, limited liability company, or government entity and has legally complied with the motor vehicle registration and licensing laws of a state, territory, or possession of the United States, shall be exempt from compliance with § <cite path="§50-1501.02">50-1501.02</cite>, and sections 414.1, 422.1, 422.7, and 422.10 of Title 18 of the District of Columbia Municipal Regulations (18 DCMR § 414.1, 422.1, 422.7, 422.10); provided, that:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(A)</num>
          <text>The vehicle is housed in the District of Columbia;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(B)</num>
          <text>The vehicle is provided to an employee of the owner or lessee for the employee’s use;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(C)</num>
          <text>The employee is domiciled in the District of Columbia;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(D)</num>
          <text>The employee is licensed by the District of Columbia to operate a motor vehicle; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(E)</num>
          <text>The business or government entity purchases a reciprocity sticker for the vehicle provided to its employee.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The Mayor shall issue, upon application and for a $338 fee, a reciprocity sticker to the motor vehicle owner or operator who complies with this subsection, which shall be valid for one year. While in compliance with this subsection, the motor vehicle owner or operator shall be able to obtain successive reciprocity stickers, each valid for one year, and each for a fee of $338. There shall be no fee for vehicles owned by the District or the United States government.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(f)</num>
      <text>Repealed.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(g)</num>
      <text>The Mayor or his designated agent is authorized to enter into reciprocal agreements or arrangements with the duly authorized representatives of a state, territory, or possession of the United States or a foreign country or political subdivision thereof, to vary the conditions under which the validity of motor vehicle registration and identification tags of any category of vehicles such as dealer tags, tags for persons with disabilities, and rental vehicle tags of such state, territory, or possession of the United States or foreign country or political subdivision thereof, shall be recognized in the District of Columbia.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(h)</num>
      <text>The Mayor of the District of Columbia shall promulgate such rules and regulations as are necessary to implement and enforce this section. Such rules and regulations shall include, but not be limited to, a determination of how many times during the 30-day exemption period an agent or employee of the Mayor of the District of Columbia must observe a motor vehicle for purposes of the enforcement of this section and a method of enforcing the provisions of this section applicable to commercial vehicles.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(i)</num>
      <text>Any operator of a motor vehicle who is not a legal resident of the District of Columbia and who does not have in his immediate possession an operator’s permit issued by a state, territory, or possession of the United States, or foreign country or political subdivision thereof, having motor vehicle reciprocity relations with the District, shall not operate a motor vehicle in the District unless: (1) the laws of the state, territory, or possession of the United States, or foreign country or political subdivision thereof, under which the motor vehicle is registered do not require the issuance of a motor vehicle operator’s permit; or (2) has submitted to examination within 72 hours after entering the District and obtained an operator’s permit in accordance with the provisions of § <cite path="§50-1401.01">50-1401.01</cite>. Any individual who violates any provision of this subsection shall, upon conviction thereof, be fined not less than $5 and not more than the amount set forth in § <cite path="§22-3571.01">22-3571.01</cite> or imprisoned not less than 30 days, or both.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>History</heading>
        <annotation>Mar. 3, 1925, 43 Stat. 1123, ch. 443, § 8</annotation>
        <annotation>Feb. 27, 1931, 46 Stat. 1424, ch. 317, § 2</annotation>
        <annotation>Aug. 16, 1954, 68 Stat. 733, ch. 741, § 6</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 2-69">Apr. 6, 1978, D.C. Law 2-69, § 5, 24 DCR 6800</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 4-80">Mar. 16, 1982, D.C. Law 4-80, § 2, 29 DCR 149</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 4-122">July 1, 1982, D.C. Law 4-122, § 2, 29 DCR 2080</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 4-145">Sept. 14, 1982, D.C. Law 4-145, § 7, 29 DCR 3138</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 5-24">Aug. 2, 1983, D.C. Law 5-24, § 9, 30 DCR 3341</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 11-198">Apr. 9, 1997, D.C. Law 11-198, § 506, 43 DCR 4569</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 12-14">Sept. 5, 1997, D.C. Law 12-14, § 8, 44 DCR 3620</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 14-167">June 28, 2002, D.C. Law 14-167, § 3, 49 DCR 4475</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 14-307">June 5, 2003, D.C. Law 14-307, § 1706(b), 49 DCR 11664</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 16-279">Mar. 14, 2007, D.C. Law 16-279, §§ 202(d), 401(c), 54 DCR 903</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 19-21">Sept. 14, 2011, D.C. Law 19-21, § 6062, 58 DCR 6226</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 19-169">Sept. 26, 2012, D.C. Law 19-169, § 34, 59 DCR 5567</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 19-244">Mar. 19, 2013, D.C. Law 19-244, § 2, 59 DCR 14942</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 19-317">June 11, 2013, D.C. Law 19-317, § 268(b), 60 DCR 2064</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Cross References</heading>
        <annotation>Registration of motor vehicles, exemptions, see §§ <cite path="§50-1501.02">50-1501.02</cite> and <cite path="§50-1501.04">50-1501.04</cite>.</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Section References</heading>
        <annotation>This section is referenced in § <cite path="§50-1401.01">50-1401.01</cite>, § <cite path="§50-1403.01">50-1403.01</cite>, § <cite path="§50-1403.02">50-1403.02</cite>, § <cite path="§50-1501.02">50-1501.02</cite>, § <cite path="§50-1501.04">50-1501.04</cite>, and § <cite path="§50-2201.03">50-2201.03</cite>.</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Prior Codifications</heading>
        <annotation>1981 Ed., § 40-303.</annotation>
        <annotation>1973 Ed., § 40-303.</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Effect of Amendments</heading>
        <annotation><cite doc="D.C. Law 14-167">D.C. Law 14-167</cite> rewrote subsec. (e)(4) which had read:</annotation>
        <annotation>“(4) Notwithstanding any other law, this subsection shall not apply to full-time students who reside within the boundaries of Advisory Neighborhood Commissions 2A and 2E.”</annotation>
        <annotation><cite doc="D.C. Law 14-307">D.C. Law 14-307</cite>, in subsec. (e)(2), substituted “$338” for “$250” in two different places.</annotation>
        <annotation><cite doc="D.C. Law 16-279">D.C. Law 16-279</cite> rewrote subsec. (a); in subsec. (c), added pars. (5), (6), and (7); and in subsec. (d), substituted “a fee of $10, which may be increased by the Mayor to cover administrative costs” for “without a fee”. Prior to amendment, subsec. (a) read as follows: “(a) The owner or operator of any motor vehicle who is not a legal resident of the District of Columbia, and who has complied with the laws of any state, territory, or possession of the United States, or of a foreign country or political subdivision thereof, shall, subject to the provisions of this section, be exempt for a continuous 30 day period immediately following the entrance of such owner or operator into the District of Columbia from compliance with § <cite path="§50-1401.01">50-1401.01</cite> and § <cite path="§50-1501.02">50-1501.02</cite>.”</annotation>
        <annotation><cite doc="D.C. Law 19-21">D.C. Law 19-21</cite>, in subsec. (d), substituted “a fee of $50,” for “a fee of $10, which may be increased by the Mayor to cover administrative costs,”.</annotation>
        <annotation>The 2012 amendment by <cite doc="D.C. Law 19-169">D.C. Law 19-169</cite> substituted “tags for persons with disabilities” for “handicapped tags” in (g).</annotation>
        <annotation>The 2013 amendment by <cite doc="D.C. Law 19-244">D.C. Law 19-244</cite> added (e-1) and (e-2).</annotation>
        <annotation>The 2013 amendment by <cite doc="D.C. Law 19-317">D.C. Law 19-317</cite> substituted “and not more than the amount set forth in § <cite path="§22-3571.01">22-3571.01</cite>” for “nor more than $50” in (i).</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Temporary Amendment of Section</heading>
        <annotation>For temporary (225 day) amendment of section, see § 8 of International Registration Plan Agreement Temporary Act of 1996 (<cite doc="D.C. Law 11-189">D.C. Law 11-189</cite>, April 9, 1997, law notification  43 DCR 2384).</annotation>
        <annotation>For temporary (225 day) amendment of section, see § 506 of Fiscal Year 1997 Budget Support Temporary Amendment Act of 1996 (<cite doc="D.C. Law 11-226">D.C. Law 11-226</cite>, April 9, 1997, law notification  44 DCR 2584).</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Emergency Legislation</heading>
        <annotation>For temporary amendment of section, see § 8 of the International Registration Plan Agreement Emergency Act of 1996 (D.C. Act 11-291, July 9, 1996,  43 DCR 4152), § 8 of the International Registration Plan Agreement Congressional Review Emergency Act of 1996 (D.C. Act 11-401, October 9, 1996,  43 DCR 5702), § 8 of the International Registration Plan Agreement Second Congressional Review Emergency Act of 1996 (D.C. Act 11-465, December 30, 1996,  44 DCR 161) and, § 8 of the International Registration Plan Agreement Congressional Review Emergency Act of 1997 (D.C. Act 12-17, March 3, 1997,  44 DCR 1756).</annotation>
        <annotation>For temporary inapplicability of subsection (e) of this section to full-time students who reside within the boundaries of Advisory Neighborhood Commissions 2A and 2E, see § 506 of the Fiscal Year 1997 Budget Support Emergency Act of 1996 (D.C. Act 11-302, July 25, 1996,  43 DCR 4181), § 506 of the Fiscal Year 1997 Budget Support Emergency Amendment Act of 1996 (D.C. Act 11-429, October 29, 1996,  43 DCR 6151), and § 506 of the Fiscal Year 1997 Budget Support Congressional Adjournment Emergency Amendment Act of 1997 (D.C. Act 12-2, February 19, 1997,  44 DCR 1590).</annotation>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 day) amendment of section, see § 1706(b) of Fiscal Year 2003 Budget Support Amendment Emergency Act of 2002 (D.C. Act 14-544, December 4, 2002,  49 DCR 11700).</annotation>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 day) amendment of section, see § 1706(b) of the Fiscal Year 2003 Budget Support Amendment Congressional Review Emergency Act of 2003 (D.C. Act 15-27, February 24, 2003,  50 DCR 2151).</annotation>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 day) amendment of section, see § 1706(b) of Fiscal Year 2003 Budget Support Amendment Second Congressional Review Emergency Act of 2003 (D.C. Act 15-103, June 20, 2003,  50 DCR 5499).</annotation>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 days) amendment of this section, see § 268(b) of the Criminal Fine Proportionality Emergency Act of 2013 (D.C. Act 20-45, April 1, 2013,  60 DCR 5400, 20 DCSTAT 1300).</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Short Title</heading>
        <annotation>Short title: Section 6061 of <cite doc="D.C. Law 19-21">D.C. Law 19-21</cite> provided that subtitle G of title VI of the act may be cited as “Reciprocity Registration Amendment Act of 2011”.</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Editor's Notes</heading>
        <text>Section 1001 of <cite doc="D.C. Law 11-198">D.C. Law 11-198</cite> provided that titles I, II, III, V, and VI and sections 405 and 406 of the act shall apply after September 30, 1996.</text>
        <text>Definitions applicable: For definitions applicable in this chapter, see § <cite path="§50-2201.02">50-2201.02</cite>.</text>
        <text>Section 35 of <cite doc="D.C. Law 19-169">D.C. Law 19-169</cite> provided that no provision of the act shall impair any right or obligation existing under law.</text>
        <text><cite doc="D.C. Law 19-182">D.C. Law 19-182</cite>, effective October 22, 2012, amended this section subject to the inclusion of its fiscal effect in an approved budget and financial plan, as certified by the Chief Financial Officer to the Budget Director of the Council in a certification published by the Council in the District of Columbia Register. As of April 1, 2013, this certification has not occurred; therefore the amendment has not been implemented.</text>
        <text>Applicability of <cite doc="D.C. Law 19-317">D.C. Law 19-317</cite>: Section 401 of <cite doc="D.C. Law 19-317">D.C. Law 19-317</cite> provided that the act shall apply only to offenses committed on or after June 11, 2013.</text>
      </annoGroup>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section from-code="true">
    <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" path="|50|14|I"/>
    <num codify:value="50-1401.03">8a</num>
    <heading>Federally-accepted driver’s license — Identification card option.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>(a)</num>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The Mayor may offer a resident the option of applying for a driver’s license or a special identification card that will be accepted by the federal government for any official purpose, subject to the applicable federal requirements.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>An applicant for an identification card who served on active duty in the Armed Forces of the United States and was discharged under conditions other than dishonorable may submit to the Department of Motor Vehicles, along with any other documentation required by this chapter, a DD Form 214, a WD AGO form, or a DD256 form certifying the applicant’s veteran status. Upon receipt of this documentation, the Department of Motor Vehicles shall display the word “veteran” in capital letters on the applicant’s identification card.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(b)</num>
      <text>The Mayor is authorized to take actions as specified in the Emergency Supplemental Appropriations Act for Defense, the Global War on Terror, and Tsunami Relief, 2005, approved May 11, 2005 (Pub. L. No. 109-13; 119 Stat. 231) [see note under 49 U.S.C. § 30301], and the regulations authorized pursuant to that act so that a driver’s license or special identification card issued to a person choosing an option described in subsection (a) of this section shall be accepted by the federal government for any official purpose.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>History</heading>
        <annotation>Mar. 3, 1925, ch. 443, § 8a</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 16-279">as added Mar. 14, 2007, D.C. Law 16-279, § 202(e), 54 DCR 903</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 20-52">Dec. 13, 2013, D.C. Law 20-52, § 2(b), 60 DCR 15157</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Effect of Amendments</heading>
        <annotation>The 2013 amendment by <cite doc="D.C. Law 20-52">D.C. Law 20-52</cite> added (a)(2).</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Editor's Notes</heading>
        <annotation>Applicability of <cite doc="D.C. Law 20-52">D.C. Law 20-52</cite>: Section 3 of <cite doc="D.C. Law 20-52">D.C. Law 20-52</cite> provided that the act shall apply as of October 1, 2013.</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section from-code="true">
    <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" path="|50|14|I"/>
    <num codify:value="50-1401.04">8b</num>
    <heading>Mayor’s authority to seize suspect documents.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>(a)</num>
      <text>The Mayor may immediately seize and retain any document presented by a person in connection with a Department of Motor Vehicles service, if the document is reasonably believed to be fraudulent, counterfeit, stolen, or intentionally altered.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(b)</num>
      <text>Any document seized under subsection (a) of this section shall be returned to the person presenting the document only if the Mayor later determines that the document is not fraudulent, counterfeit, stolen, or intentionally altered on the person’s own initiative or after the hearing provided for in subsection (c) of this section.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(c)</num>
      <text>Any person presenting a document that was retained pursuant to subsection (a) of this section may request a hearing within 10 days of the retention on the validity of that retention.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(d)</num>
      <text>Any person whose document was retained and not subsequently returned pursuant to this section shall not be entitled to apply for a driver’s license, special identification card, or vehicle registration for a period of one year from the date of seizure.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(e)</num>
      <text>For the purposes of this section, “document” means any printed material, including a letter, notice, bill, receipt, driver’s permit, registration card, title, insurance card, passport, picture identification, birth certificate, currency, credit card, check, or copy of the same.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>History</heading>
        <annotation>Mar. 3, 1925, ch. 443, § 8b</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 16-279">as added Mar. 14, 2007, D.C. Law 16-279, § 202(e), 54 DCR 903</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section from-code="true">
    <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" path="|50|14|I"/>
    <num codify:value="50-1401.05">8c</num>
    <heading>Limited purpose driver’s license, permit, or identification card.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>(a)</num>
      <text>The Mayor, consistent with subsections (b) and (c) of this section, shall issue a limited purpose driver’s license, permit, or identification card to an applicant who:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Has resided in the District for longer than 6 months;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <para>
          <num>(A)</num>
          <text>Has not been assigned a social security number;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(B)</num>
          <text>Has been assigned a social security number but cannot establish legal presence in the United States at the time of application; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(C)</num>
          <text>Is ineligible to obtain a social security number; and</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Meets the requirements of this section.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(b)</num>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>To obtain a limited purpose driver’s license or permit in accordance with subsection (a) of this section, an applicant shall:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(A)</num>
          <text>Provide, under penalty of perjury, proof of identity, date of birth, and residency to the Department of Motor Vehicles (“Department”) as defined by the Department by rule; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(B)</num>
          <text>Satisfy the applicable requirements of § <cite path="§50-1401.01">50-1401.01</cite> and sections 100 through 111 of Title 18 of the District of Columbia Municipal Regulations (18 DCMR §§ 1<cite path="§00-111">00-111</cite>); provided, that the Mayor shall not require an applicant for a limited purpose driver’s license or permit under this section to provide a social security number or any document to prove the absence of a social security number.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>An applicant shall include a certified translation of a document provided that is not in English.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(c)</num>
      <text>To obtain a limited purpose identification card in accordance with subsection (a) of this section, an applicant shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Meet the requirements of subsection (b)(1)(A) of this section; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Meet the applicable requirements of section 112 of Title 18 of the District of Columbia Municipal Regulations (18 DCMR § 112); provided, that the Mayor shall not require an applicant for a limited purpose identification card under this section to provide a social security number or any document to prove the absence of a social security number.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(d)</num>
      <text>A limited purpose driver’s license or identification card issued under subsection (a) of this section shall be valid for 8 years. A limited purpose learner’s or provisional permit shall be valid for the time period as set forth in §§ <cite path="§50-1401.01">50-1401.01</cite>(a)(2) and <cite path="§50-1401.01">50-1401.01</cite>(a)(2A).</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(e)</num>
      <text>An individual who is issued a limited purpose driver’s license or permit under this section shall have the equivalent authorization to operate a motor vehicle as provided in § <cite path="§50-1401.01">50-1401.01</cite> and shall be subject to all statutory and regulatory provisions pertaining to driver licensing and operation of a motor vehicle.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(f)</num>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A limited purpose driver’s license, permit, or identification card issued under subsection (a) of this section shall state the following on the face of the card and in its machine-readable zone in a font size no larger than the smallest font size otherwise appearing on the card: “Not valid for official federal purposes.”</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The Mayor may incorporate different features but only if doing so would result in a card that appears more similar to a license issued under § <cite path="§50-1401.01">50-1401.01</cite>, or if required by the Department of Homeland Security; provided, that the Mayor does so to the minimum extent necessary to comply.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(g)</num>
      <text>A limited purpose driver’s license, permit, or identification card issued under subsection (a) of this section shall not be used to consider an individual’s citizenship or immigration status, or as a basis for a criminal investigation, arrest, or detention.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(h)</num>
      <text>The Mayor, pursuant to subchapter I of Chapter 5 of Title 2 [§ <cite path="§2-501">2-501</cite> et seq.], may issue rules to implement the provisions of this section. The proposed rules shall be submitted to the Council for a 45-day period of review, excluding Saturdays, Sundays, legal holidays, and days of Council recess. If the Council does not approve or disapprove the proposed rules, in whole or in part, by resolution within this 45-day period, the proposed rules shall be deemed approved.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>History</heading>
        <annotation>Mar. 3, 1925, ch. 443, § 8c</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 20-62">as added Jan. 17, 2014, D.C. Law 20-62, § 2(c), 60 DCR 16026</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 20-145">Dec. 17, 2014, D.C. Law 20-145, § 2, 61 DCR 8061</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Section References</heading>
        <annotation>This section is referenced in § <cite path="§50-1401.01">50-1401.01</cite> and § <cite path="§50-1401.01b">50-1401.01b</cite>.</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Effect of Amendments</heading>
        <annotation>The 2014 amendment by <cite doc="D.C. Law 20-62">D.C. Law 20-62</cite> added this section.</annotation>
        <annotation>The 2014 amendment by <cite doc="D.C. Law 20-145">D.C. Law 20-145</cite>, in (a)(2), added the subdivision (a)(2)(A) and (a)(2)(C) designations; and added (a)(2)(B).</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Temporary Legislation</heading>
        <annotation>For temporary (225 days) amendment of this section, see § 2 of the Driver's Safety Clarification Temporary Amendment Act of 2014 (<cite doc="D.C. Law 20-111">D.C. Law 20-111</cite>, June 21, 2014,  61 DCR 4326).</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Emergency Legislation</heading>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 days) amendment of this section, see § 2 of the Driver’s Safety Clarification Emergency Amendment Act of 2014 (D.C. Act 20-293, March 12, 2014,   61 DCR 2435).</annotation>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 days) amendment of this section, see §§ 2 and 3 of the Driver’s Safety Clarification Congressional Review Emergency Amendment Act of 2014 (D.C. Act 20-350, June 17, 2014,   61 DCR 6326).</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Editor's Notes</heading>
        <annotation>Applicability of <cite doc="D.C. Law 20-62">D.C. Law 20-62</cite>: Section 3 of <cite doc="D.C. Law 20-62">D.C. Law 20-62</cite> provided that the act shall apply as of May 1, 2014.</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section from-code="true">
    <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" path="|50|14|II"/>
    <num codify:value="50-1403.01">13</num>
    <heading>Revocation or suspension; new permit after revocation; nonresidents; penalty for operation with revoked or suspended license.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>(a)</num>
      <text>Except where for any violation of this subchapter revocation of the operator’s permit is mandatory or where suspension or revocation is mandatory for accumulated point totals pursuant to Chapter 3 of Title 18 of the District of Columbia Municipal Regulations, the Mayor or his designated agent may revoke or suspend an operator’s permit for any cause which he or his agent may deem sufficient; provided, that in each case where a permit is revoked or suspended the reasons therefor shall be set out in the order of revocation or suspension; provided further, that such order shall take effect 10 (15, if the person is a nonresident) days after its issuance unless the holder of the permit shall have filed within such period, written application with the Mayor of the District of Columbia for a review of his order or the order of his agent, and, if upon such review, the Mayor shall sustain such order, the same shall become effective immediately; provided further, that application to said Mayor for a review shall not operate as a stay of such order of the Mayor or his agent when the order has been issued revoking or suspending a permit on account of mental or physical incapacity, for driving while the person is intoxicated as defined by § <cite path="§50-2206.01">50-2206.01</cite>(9), or while under the influence of intoxicating liquor or any drug or any combination thereof, or while the ability to operate a vehicle is impaired by the consumption of intoxicating liquor; for manslaughter when an automobile is involved, or for operating a motor vehicle equipped with a smoke screen.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(b)</num>
      <text>In case the operator’s permit of any individual is revoked no new permit shall be issued to such individual for at least 6 months after the revocation except in the discretion of the Mayor or his designated agent.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(c)</num>
      <text>The Mayor of the District of Columbia, or his designated agent, may suspend or revoke the right of any nonresident person as defined in § <cite path="§50-1401.02">50-1401.02</cite>, to operate a motor vehicle in the District of Columbia, for any cause he or his agent may deem sufficient, and the proper authority at the place of issuance of the permit, or other authority to operate a motor vehicle shall be notified of such suspension and the reason therefor, immediately; provided, that such order of suspension or revocation shall take effect 10 days after its issuance, and the same be subject to review and appeal in the manner and under the same conditions as are provided for such matters in subsection (a) of this section.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(d)</num>
      <text>Notwithstanding any other provision of this section, the provisions of the District of Columbia Administrative Procedure Act (§ <cite path="§2-501">2-501</cite> et seq.) and particularly those of § <cite path="§2-509">2-509</cite>, shall apply to each proceeding, decision, or other administrative action specified in this subchapter.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(e)</num>
      <text>Any individual found guilty of operating a motor vehicle in the District during the period for which the individual’s license is revoked or suspended, or for which his right to operate is suspended or revoked, shall, for each such offense, be fined not more than the amount set forth in § <cite path="§22-3571.01">22-3571.01</cite> or imprisoned for not more than 1 year, or both.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>History</heading>
        <annotation>Mar. 3, 1925, 43 Stat. 1125, ch. 443, § 13</annotation>
        <annotation>July 3, 1926, 44 Stat. 814, ch. 739, § 3</annotation>
        <annotation>Feb. 27, 1931, 46 Stat. 1424, 1428, ch. 317, §§ 2, 4</annotation>
        <annotation>June 7, 1934, 48 Stat. 926, ch. 426</annotation>
        <annotation>May 15, 1936, 49 Stat. 1273, ch. 393</annotation>
        <annotation>Aug. 31, 1954, 68 Stat. 1048, ch. 1173, § 1</annotation>
        <annotation doc="Pub. L. 88-60">July 8, 1963, 77 Stat. 78, Pub. L. 88-60, § 6</annotation>
        <annotation doc="Pub. L. 88-241">Dec. 23, 1963, 77 Stat. 617, Pub. L. 88-241, § 8</annotation>
        <annotation doc="Pub. L. 91-358">July 29, 1970, 84 Stat. 583, Pub. L. 91-358, title I, § 163(g)(1)</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 1-133">Apr. 26, 1977, D.C. Law 1-133, title I, §§ 102-104, 23 DCR 9697</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 4-145">Sept. 14, 1982, D.C. Law 4-145, §§ 6, 7, 29 DCR 3138</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 4-174">Mar. 9, 1983, D.C. Law 4-174, § 12, 29 DCR 5753</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 12-212">Apr. 13, 1999, D.C. Law 12-212, § 2(b), 46 DCR 5</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 13-289">Apr. 27, 2001, D.C. Law 13-289, § 301, 48 DCR 2057</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 16-195">Mar. 2, 2007, D.C. Law 16-195, § 9, 53 DCR 8675</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 16-279">Mar. 14, 2007, D.C. Law 16-279, § 202(f), 54 DCR 903</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 19-266">Apr. 27, 2013, D.C. Law 19-266, § 307, 59 DCR 12957</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 19-317">June 11, 2013, D.C. Law 19-317, § 268(c), 60 DCR 2064</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Cross References</heading>
        <annotation>Criminal procedure, warrantless arrests, see § <cite path="§23-581">23-581</cite>.</annotation>
        <annotation>Motor vehicle exhaust emissions inspections, uninspected or unfit vehicles, applicability of this section, see § <cite path="§50-1105">50-1105</cite>.</annotation>
        <annotation>Regulation of traffic, certificates of title for motor vehicles, procedures for when title is refused, see § <cite path="§50-2201.03">50-2201.03</cite>.</annotation>
        <annotation>Regulation of traffic, conviction reports, see § <cite path="§50-2201.27">50-2201.27</cite>.</annotation>
        <annotation>Traffic adjudication, violations prosecuted as criminal offenses, see § <cite path="§50-2302.02">50-2302.02</cite>.</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Section References</heading>
        <annotation>This section is referenced in § <cite path="§23-581">23-581</cite>, § <cite path="§50-1105">50-1105</cite>, § <cite path="§50-1401.01">50-1401.01</cite>, § <cite path="§50-1403.02">50-1403.02</cite>, § <cite path="§50-2201.03">50-2201.03</cite>, § <cite path="§50-2201.05a">50-2201.05a</cite>, § <cite path="§50-2201.05b">50-2201.05b</cite>, § <cite path="§50-2201.27">50-2201.27</cite>, and § <cite path="§50-2302.02">50-2302.02</cite>.</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Prior Codifications</heading>
        <annotation>1981 Ed., § 40-302.</annotation>
        <annotation>1973 Ed., § 40-302.</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Effect of Amendments</heading>
        <annotation><cite doc="D.C. Law 12-212">D.C. Law 12-212</cite>, § 2(b), in subsec. (a) substituted “blood contains .08% or more, by weight, of alcohol, or while .38 micrograms or more of alcohol are contained in 1 milliliter of the individual’s breath, consisting substantially of alveolar air, or while the individual’s urine contains .10% or more,” for “blood or breath contains .10 percent or more by weight, of alcohol, or the individual’s urine contains .13 percent or more,”.</annotation>
        <annotation><cite doc="D.C. Law 13-289">D.C. Law 13-289</cite>, in subsec. (a), inserted “or where suspension or revocation is mandatory for accumulated point totals pursuant to Chapter 3 of Title 18 of the District of Columbia Municipal Regulations” following “permit is mandatory”.</annotation>
        <annotation><cite doc="D.C. Law 16-195">D.C. Law 16-195</cite>, in subsec. (a), substituted “person’s alcohol concentration is 0.08 grams or more either per 100 milliliters of blood or per 210 liters of breath or is 0.10 grams or more per 100 milliliters of urine” for “individual’s blood contains .08% or more, by weight, of alcohol, or while .38 micrograms or more of alcohol are contained in 1 milliliter of the individual’s breath, consisting substantially of alveolar air, or while the individual’s urine contains .10% or more, by weight, of alcohol person’s alcohol concentration is 0.08 grams or more either per 100 milliliters of blood or per 210 liters of breath or is 0.10 grams or more per 100 milliliters of urine”.</annotation>
        <annotation><cite doc="D.C. Law 16-279">D.C. Law 16-279</cite>, in subsec. (a), substituted “shall take effect 10 (15, if the person is a nonresident) days out” for “shall take effect 5 days out”.</annotation>
        <annotation>The 2013 amendment by <cite doc="D.C. Law 19-266">D.C. Law 19-266</cite> substituted “person is intoxicated as defined by § <cite path="§50-2206.01">50-2206.01</cite>(9)” for “person’s alcohol concentration is 0.08 grams or more either per 100 milliliters of blood or per 210 liters of breath or is 0.10 grams or more per 100 milliliters of urine” in (a).</annotation>
        <annotation>The 2013 amendment by <cite doc="D.C. Law 19-317">D.C. Law 19-317</cite> substituted “not more than the amount set forth in § <cite path="§22-3571.01">22-3571.01</cite>” for “not to exceed $5,000” in (e).</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Temporary Amendment of Section</heading>
        <annotation>For temporary (225 day) amendment of section, see § 8(b) of Driving Under the Influence Repeat Offenders Temporary Amendment Act of 2000 (<cite doc="D.C. Law 13-198">D.C. Law 13-198</cite>, October 21, 2000, law notification  47 DCR 8988).</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Emergency Legislation</heading>
        <annotation>For temporary (90-day) repeal of expiration date of section, see § 4 of the Driving Under the Influence Repeat Offenders Emergency Amendment Act of 2000 (D.C. Act 13-382, July 24, 2000,  47 DCR 6697).</annotation>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 day) amendment of section, see § 4 of the Driving Under the Influence Repeat Offenders Congressional Review Emergency Amendment Act of 2000 (D.C. Act 13-437, October 20, 2000,  47 DCR 8737).</annotation>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 day) amendment of section, see § 4(e)(2) of Anti-Drunk Driving Clarification Emergency Amendment Act of 2006 (D.C. Act 16-469, July 31, 2006,  53 DCR 6764).</annotation>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 day) amendment of section, see § 9 of Anti-Drunk Driving Clarification Second Congressional Review Emergency Amendment Act of 2006 (D.C. Act 16-518, October 27, 2006,  53 DCR 9104).</annotation>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 day) amendment of section, see § 8(b) of Anti-Drunk Driving Clarification Congressional Review Emergency Amendment Act of 2007 (D.C. Act 17-6, January 16, 2007,  54 DCR 1452).</annotation>
        <annotation>For temporary amendment of (a), see § 307 of the Comprehensive Impaired Driving and Alcohol Testing Program Congressional Review Emergency Amendment Act of 2012 (D.C. Act 19-508, October 26, 2012, 59 DCR 12774).</annotation>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 days) amendment of this section, see § 307 of the Comprehensive Impaired Driving and Alcohol Testing Program Congressional Review Emergency Act of 2013 (D.C. Act 20-3, January 29, 2013,  60 DCR 2762, 20 DCSTAT 410).</annotation>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 days) amendment of this section, see § 268(c) of the Criminal Fine Proportionality Emergency Act of 2013 (D.C. Act 20-45, April 1, 2013,  60 DCR 5400, 20 DCSTAT 1300).</annotation>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 days) amendment of this section, see § 307 of the Comprehensive Impaired Driving and Alcohol Testing Program Second Congressional Review Emergency Act of 2013 (D.C. Act 20-51, April 17, 2013,  60 DCR 6344, 20 DCSTAT 1360).</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Expiration of Law</heading>
        <text>Expiration of Law 12-212</text>
        <text>Section 8(b) of <cite doc="D.C. Law 12-212">D.C. Law 12-212</cite>, which provided that the act shall expire on September 30, 2000, was repealed by section 4 of <cite doc="D.C. Law 13-238">D.C. Law 13-238</cite>.</text>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Editor's Notes</heading>
        <text>Section 5 of  46 Stat. 1429, ch. 317, effective Feb. 27, 1931, provided that all convictions under the Act shall be reported by the clerk of the court to the commissioners [Mayor] or their [his] designated agent.</text>
        <text>Section 8(b) of <cite doc="D.C. Law 12-212">D.C. Law 12-212</cite> provided: “(b) This act shall expire on September 30, 2000.”</text>
        <text>Section 8(b) of <cite doc="D.C. Law 12-212">D.C. Law 12-212</cite>, providing for the expiration of the act on September 30, 2000, was repealed by section 4 of <cite doc="D.C. Law 13-238">D.C. Law 13-238</cite>.</text>
        <text>Definitions applicable: For definitions applicable in this chapter, see § <cite path="§50-2201.02">50-2201.02</cite>.</text>
        <text>Applicability of <cite doc="D.C. Law 19-317">D.C. Law 19-317</cite>: Section 401 of <cite doc="D.C. Law 19-317">D.C. Law 19-317</cite> provided that the act shall apply only to offenses committed on or after June 11, 2013.</text>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Change in Government</heading>
        <annotation>This section originated at a time when local government powers were delegated to a Board of Commissioners of the District of Columbia (see Acts Relating to the Establishment of the District of Columbia and its Various Forms of Governmental Organization in Volume 1). Section 401 of Reorganization Plan No. 3 of 1967 (see Reorganization Plans in Volume 1) transferred all of the functions of the Board of Commissioners under this section to a single Commissioner. The District of Columbia Self-Government and Governmental Reorganization Act, 87 Stat. 818, § 711 ( D.C. Code, § <cite path="§1-207.11">1-207.11</cite>), abolished the District of Columbia Council and the Office of Commissioner of the District of Columbia. These branches of government were replaced by the Council of the District of Columbia and the Office of Mayor of the District of Columbia, respectively. Accordingly, and also pursuant to § 714(a) of such Act ( D.C. Code, § <cite path="§1-207.14">1-207.14</cite>(a)), appropriate changes in terminology were made in this section.</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section from-code="true">
    <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" path="|50|14|II"/>
    <num codify:value="50-1403.02">13a</num>
    <heading>Revocation and disqualification of motor vehicle operator’s permit.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>(a)</num>
      <text>The Mayor shall revoke the motor vehicle operator’s permit of a District resident or the privilege to operate a motor vehicle in the District of a nonresident, convicted as a result of the commission of a drug offense or adjudicated a juvenile delinquent as a result of the commission of a drug offense. Where the person is imprisoned as a result of the drug offense, the revocation shall occur following the person’s release from imprisonment. If a person does not have an operator’s permit, or the permit is or has been revoked or suspended at the time of the conviction of a drug offense, the issuance or reinstatement of an operator’s permit will be delayed for a period of at least 6 months and not more than 2 years. If a person is convicted for the commission of a drug offense or adjudicated a delinquent for the commission of a drug offense before the person is 16 years of age, the period of disqualification shall not begin to run until the person is 16 years of age. Notification of the conviction or adjudication shall be sent electronically by the court to the Mayor within one business day of the conviction or adjudication and shall include the person’s name, address, date of birth, conviction date, driver’s license number, if any, social security number, if any, the offense, and any other information required by the Mayor to take the action required by this section. The revocation shall be for not less than six months and not more than 2 years. For the purposes of this section, notwithstanding any other District law, a violation of § <cite path="§48-1201">48-1201</cite> shall not constitute a drug offense.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(a-1)</num>
      <text>The Mayor may delay issuance of an operator’s permit by disqualifying anyone not already in possession of a valid operator’s permit when such individual is convicted of or adjudicated delinquent as a result of:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The commission of a stolen vehicle offense;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Operating a motor vehicle without a permit (§ <cite path="§50-1401.01">50-1401.01</cite>(d) — residents; § <cite path="§50-1401.02">50-1401.02</cite>(i) — non-residents);</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Operating a motor vehicle after revocation or suspension of an operator’s permit (§ <cite path="§50-1403.01">50-1403.01</cite>); or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Any felony in the commission of which a motor vehicle is involved.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(a-2)</num>
      <text>In all cases where a person is convicted or adjudicated delinquent of any of the offenses set forth in subsection (a-1) of this section, the disqualification period shall commence on the later of:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The date of conviction or adjudication if the person is imprisoned or legal custody of the person has been transferred to a public agency for care of delinquent children as a result of the conviction or adjudication;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The person’s 16th birthday if the conviction or adjudication occurs before the person is 16 years of age; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The date that a person over 16 years of age becomes eligible to have driving privileges restored if such privileges have previously been revoked or suspended.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(a-3)</num>
      <text>The disqualification period referenced in subsection (a-2) of this section shall, for any offense set forth in subsection (a-1) of this section, be:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Six months for a first time violation of any offense set forth in subsection (a-1) of this section;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>One year for a second violation; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Two years for each subsequent violation.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(a-4)</num>
      <text>A copy of the conviction or adjudication shall be forwarded by the court to the Mayor, along with the offender’s social security number or operator’s permit number, together with a copy of the operator’s permit.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(b)</num>
      <text>For the purposes of this section, the term:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>“Drug offense” means:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(A)</num>
          <text>The possession, distribution, manufacture, cultivation, sale, transfer, or the attempt or conspiracy to possess, distribute, manufacture, cultivate, sell, or transfer any substance the possession of which is prohibited under the Comprehensive Drug Abuse Prevention and Control Act of 1970, approved October 27, 1970 (84 Stat. 1236; 21 U.S.C. § 801 et seq.), Unit A of Chapter 9 of Title 48 [§ <cite path="§48-901.01">48-901.01</cite> et seq.], or the law of any state, territory, or possession of the United States; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(B)</num>
          <text>The operation of a motor vehicle under the influence of such a substance.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>“Stolen vehicle offense” means:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(A)</num>
          <text>A theft of a motor vehicle in violation of § <cite path="§22-3211">22-3211</cite>;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(B)</num>
          <text>The unauthorized use of a motor vehicle in violation of § <cite path="§22-3215">22-3215</cite>; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(C)</num>
          <text>Trafficking in or receiving a stolen motor vehicle in violation of § <cite path="§22-3231">22-3231</cite> or § <cite path="§22-3232">22-3232</cite>.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>History</heading>
        <annotation>Mar. 3, 1925, ch. 443, § 13a</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 7-222">as added Mar. 16, 1989, D.C. Law 7-222, § 2, 36 DCR 570</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 9-253">Mar. 25, 1993, D.C. Law 9-253, § 2, 40 DCR 790</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 16-167">Sept. 29, 2006, D.C. Law 16-167, § 2, 53 DCR 6194</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 16-279">Mar. 14, 2007, D.C. Law 16-279, § 405, 54 DCR 903</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 16-306">Apr. 24, 2007, D.C. Law 16-306, § 228(b), 53 DCR 8610</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 20-126">July 17, 2014, D.C. Law 20-126, §  410, 61 DCR 3482</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Section References</heading>
        <annotation>This section is referenced in § <cite path="§16-2318">16-2318</cite> and § <cite path="§16-2331">16-2331</cite>.</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Prior Codifications</heading>
        <annotation>1981 Ed., § 40-302.1.</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Effect of Amendments</heading>
        <annotation><cite doc="D.C. Law 16-167">D.C. Law 16-167</cite>, in subsec. (a), substituted “Notification of the conviction or adjudication shall be sent electronically by the court to the Mayor within one business day of the conviction or adjudication and shall include the person’s name, address, date of birth, conviction date, driver’s license number, if any, social security number, if any, the offense, and any other information required by the Mayor to take the action required by this section.” for “A copy of the conviction or adjudication shall be forwarded by the court to the Mayor.”</annotation>
        <annotation><cite doc="D.C. Law 16-279">D.C. Law 16-279</cite>, in subsec. (a), deleted “in the absence of compelling circumstances warranting an exception” following “shall revoke” following “Mayor shall revoke”.</annotation>
        <annotation><cite doc="D.C. Law 16-306">D.C. Law 16-306</cite> added subsecs. (a-1), (a-2), (a-3), and (a-4); and rewrote subsec. (b).</annotation>
        <annotation>The 2014 amendment by <cite doc="D.C. Law 20-126">D.C. Law 20-126</cite> added the last sentence in (a).</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Temporary Legislation</heading>
        <annotation>For temporary (225 day) amendment of section, see § 2 of Drug Offense Driving Privileges Revocation and Disqualification Temporary Amendment Act of 2006 (<cite doc="D.C. Law 16-99">D.C. Law 16-99</cite>, May 12, 2006, law notification  53 DCR 4232).</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Emergency Legislation</heading>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 day) amendment of section, see § 2 of Drug Offence Driving Privileges Revocation and Disqualification Emergency Amendment Act of 2006 (D.C. Act 16-256, January 26, 2006,  53 DCR 770).</annotation>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 day) amendment of section, see § 2 of Drug Offence Driving Privileges Revocation and Disqualification Congressional Review Emergency Amendment Act of 2006 (D.C. Act 16-360, April 26, 2006,  53 DCR 3617).</annotation>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 day) amendment of section, see § 228(b) of Omnibus Public Safety Emergency Amendment Act of 2006 (D.C. Act 16-445, July 19, 2006,  53 DCR 6443).</annotation>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 day) amendment of section, see § 228(b) of Omnibus Public Safety Congressional Review Emergency Amendment Act of 2006 (D.C. Act 16-490, October 18, 2006,  53 DCR 8686).</annotation>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 day) amendment of section, see § 228(b) of Omnibus Public Safety Congressional Review Emergency Amendment Act of 2007 (D.C. Act 17-10, January 16, 2007,  54 DCR 1479).</annotation>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 day) amendment of section, see § 228(b) of Omnibus Public Safety Second Congressional Review Emergency Amendment Act of 2007 (D.C. Act 17-25, April 19, 2007,  54 DCR 4036).</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Editor's Notes</heading>
        <annotation>Section 501 of <cite doc="D.C. Law 20-126">D.C. Law 20-126</cite> provided that the Mayor, pursuant to subchapter I of Chapter 5 of Title 2 [§ <cite path="§2-501">2-501</cite> et seq.], may issue rules to implement the provisions of the act.</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section from-code="true">
    <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" path="|50|14|II"/>
    <num codify:value="50-1403.03">13b</num>
    <heading>Suspension of minor’s motor vehicle operator’s permit for alcohol violation.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>(a)</num>
      <text>The Mayor shall suspend the motor vehicle operator’s permit of a person under 21 years of age convicted of violating, or adjudicated in violation of § <cite path="§25-130">25-130</cite>. The suspension shall be for the duration required by § <cite path="§25-130">25-130</cite>. A copy of the conviction or adjudication shall be forwarded to the Mayor by the court or the administrative body authorized to adjudicate violations under Chapter 1 of Title 25.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(b)</num>
      <text>Any person found guilty of operating a motor vehicle in the District during the period for which the person’s license or privilege is suspended, shall, for each offense, be fined not more than the amount set forth in § <cite path="§22-3571.01">22-3571.01</cite>, imprisoned for not more than 180 days, or both.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>History</heading>
        <annotation>Mar. 3, 1925, ch. 443, § 13b</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 10-122">as added May 24, 1994, D.C. Law 10-122, § 4, 41 DCR 1658</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 19-317">June 11, 2013, D.C. Law 19-317, § 268(d), 60 DCR 2064</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Prior Codifications</heading>
        <annotation>1981 Ed., § 40-302.2.</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Effect of Amendments</heading>
        <annotation>The 2013 amendment by <cite doc="D.C. Law 19-317">D.C. Law 19-317</cite> substituted “not more than the amount set forth in § <cite path="§22-3571.01">22-3571.01</cite>” for “not more than $1,000” in (b).</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Emergency Legislation</heading>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 days) amendment of this section, see § 268(d) of the Criminal Fine Proportionality Emergency Act of 2013 (D.C. Act 20-45, April 1, 2013,  60 DCR 5400, 20 DCSTAT 1300).</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>References in Text</heading>
        <annotation>Section 25-130 and Chapter 1 of Title 25, referred to in this section, are part and all, respectively, of Title 25, D.C. Official Code, which title was amended and enacted by <cite doc="D.C. Law 13-298">D.C. Law 13-298</cite>, effective May 3, 2001. For disposition of the subject matter of former Title 25, see the Disposition Table preceding § <cite path="§25-101">25-101</cite>.</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Editor's Notes</heading>
        <annotation>Applicability of <cite doc="D.C. Law 19-317">D.C. Law 19-317</cite>: Section 401 of <cite doc="D.C. Law 19-317">D.C. Law 19-317</cite> provided that the act shall apply only to offenses committed on or after June 11, 2013.</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section from-code="true">
    <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" path="|50|22|I|A"/>
    <num codify:value="50-2201.01">1</num>
    <heading>Short title.</heading>
    <text>This part may be cited as the “District of Columbia Traffic Act, 1925.”</text>
    <annotations>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>History</heading>
        <annotation>Mar. 3, 1925, 43 Stat. 1119, ch. 443, § 1</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Section References</heading>
        <annotation>This section is referenced in § <cite path="§23-581">23-581</cite> and § <cite path="§50-1501.05">50-1501.05</cite>.</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Prior Codifications</heading>
        <annotation>1981 Ed., § 40-701.</annotation>
        <annotation>1973 Ed., § 40-601.</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Emergency Legislation</heading>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 day) addition, see §§ 101 to 104 of Prohibition on the Reckless Operation of Recreational Motor Vehicles Emergency Act of 2004 (D.C. Act 15-462, June 23, 2004,  51 DCR 6750).</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Mayor's Orders</heading>
        <annotation>Establishment—Task Force on Transportation, see Mayor’s Order 2001-147, October 3, 2001 ( 48 DCR 9522).</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section from-code="true">
    <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" path="|50|22|I|A"/>
    <num codify:value="50-2201.02">2</num>
    <heading>Definitions.</heading>
    <text>For the purposes of this chapter, the term:</text>
    <para>
      <num>(1)</num>
      <text>“Alcohol” means a liquid, gas, or solid, containing ethanol from whatever source or by whatever processes produced, whether or not intended for human consumption.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(2)</num>
      <text>“All-terrain vehicle” or “ATV” means any motor vehicle with not less than 3 low-pressure tires, but not more than 6 low-pressure tires, designed primarily for off-road use and which has a seat or saddle designed to be straddled by the operator. The terms “all-terrain vehicle” and “ATV” shall not include golf carts, riding lawnmowers, or tractors.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(3)</num>
      <text>“Collision” means an impact between the operator’s vehicle, or anything attached to or transported by the vehicle, and anything else, regardless of whether it is a person, a wild or domestic animal, real property, or personal property.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(4)</num>
      <text>“Commercial vehicle” means a vehicle used to transport passengers or property:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(A)</num>
        <text>If the vehicle has a gross vehicle weight rating of greater than 26,000 pounds or a lesser rating as determined by federal regulation but not less than a gross vehicle weight rating of 10,001 pounds;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(B)</num>
        <text>If the vehicle is designed to transport more than 15 passengers, including the driver;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(C)</num>
        <text>If the vehicle is a locomotive or a streetcar;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(D)</num>
        <text>If the vehicle is used to transport a material found to be hazardous by the Mayor in accordance with Chapter 14 of Title 8 [§ <cite path="§8-1401">8-1401</cite> et seq.], or by the Secretary of Transportation in accordance with the Hazardous Materials Transportation Act, approved January 3, 1975 (88 Stat. 2156; 49 U.S.C. § 1801 et seq.); or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(E)</num>
        <text>If the vehicle is a vehicle for hire.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(5)</num>
      <text>“Court” means the Superior Court of the District of Columbia, except when used in the definition of “prior offense” when it shall also include courts of other jurisdictions.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(6)</num>
      <text>“Dirt bike” means any motorcycle designed primarily for off-road use.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(7)</num>
      <text>“Highway” means any street, road, or public thoroughfare, or the entire width between the boundary lines of every publicly or privately maintained way, when any part thereof is open to the use of the public for purposes of vehicular or pedestrian travel.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(8)</num>
      <text>“Identifying information” means the name, complete address, and telephone number of the operator of the vehicle; if the owner of the vehicle is different from the operator of the vehicle, the name, complete address, and telephone number of the owner of the vehicle operated; the tag number of the vehicle operated or, if no tag number, the vehicle identification number; and insurance information for the vehicle operated.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(9)</num>
      <text>“Law enforcement officer” means a sworn member of the Metropolitan Police Department or a sworn member of any other police force operating in the District of Columbia.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(10)</num>
      <text>“Mayor” means the Mayor of the District of Columbia or his or her designee.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(11)</num>
      <text>“Motor vehicle” means all vehicles propelled by internal-combustion engines, electricity, or steam. The term “motor vehicle” shall not include traction engines, road rollers, vehicles propelled only upon rails or tracks, personal mobility devices, as defined in paragraph (13) of this section, or a battery-operated wheelchair when operated by a person with a disability.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(12)</num>
      <text>“Park” means to leave any motor vehicle standing on a highway, whether or not attended.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(13)</num>
      <text>“Personal mobility device” or “PMD” means a motorized propulsion device designed to transport one person or a self-balancing, two non-tandem wheeled device, designed to transport only one person with an electric propulsion system, but does not include a battery-operated wheelchair.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(14)</num>
      <text>“Prior offense” means any guilty plea or verdict, including a finding of guilty in the case of a juvenile, for an offense under District law or a disposition in another jurisdiction for a substantially similar offense which occurred before the current offense regardless of when the arrest occurred. The term “prior offense” does not include an offense where the later of any term of incarceration, supervised release, parole, or probation ceased or expired more than 15 years prior to the arrest on the current offense.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(15)</num>
      <text>“This chapter” includes all lawful regulations issued thereunder by the Council of the District of Columbia and all lawful rules issued thereunder by the Mayor of the District of Columbia or his designated agent.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(16)</num>
      <text>“Traffic” includes not only motor vehicles but also all vehicles, pedestrians, and animals, of every description.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(17)</num>
      <text>“Vehicle” includes any appliance moved over a highway on wheels or traction tread, including street cars, draft animals, and beasts of burden.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(18)</num>
      <text>“Vehicle conveyance fee” shall have the same meaning as provided in § <cite path="§50-2301.02">50-2301.02</cite>(9).</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(19)</num>
      <text>“Vehicle for hire” means:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(A)</num>
        <text>Any motor vehicle operated in the District by a private concern or individual as an ambulance, funeral car, sightseeing vehicle, or for which the rate is fixed solely by the hour;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(B)</num>
        <text>Any motor vehicle operated in the District by a private concern used for services including transportation paid for by a hotel, venue, or other third party;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(C)</num>
        <text>Any motor vehicle used to provide transportation within the District between fixed termini or on a schedule, including vehicles operated by the Washington Metropolitan Area Transit Authority or other public authorities, not including rental cars; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(D)</num>
        <text>Any other vehicle that provides transportation for a fee not operated on a schedule or between fixed termini and operating in the District, including taxicabs, limousines, party buses, and pedicabs.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(20)</num>
      <text>“Work zone” means the area of a highway or roadway that is affected by construction, maintenance, or utility work activities, including the area delineated by and within all traffic control devices erected or installed to guide vehicular, pedestrian, and bicycle traffic.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>History</heading>
        <annotation>Mar. 3, 1925, 43 Stat. 1119, ch. 443, § 2</annotation>
        <annotation>July 3, 1926, 44 Stat. 812, ch. 739, § 1</annotation>
        <annotation>Feb. 27, 1931, 46 Stat. 1424, ch. 317, § 1</annotation>
        <annotation>Apr. 1, 1942, 56 Stat. 190, ch. 207, § 1</annotation>
        <annotation doc="Pub. L. 91-358">July 29, 1970, 84 Stat. 570, Pub. L. 91-358, title I, § 155(a)</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 1-133">Apr. 26, 1977, D.C. Law 1-133, title II, § 201(a), 23 DCR 9697</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 5-42">Nov. 15, 1983, D.C. Law 5-42, § 2(a), 30 DCR 4999</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 5-176">Mar. 15, 1985, D.C. Law 5-176, § 12(a), 32 DCR 748</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 9-96">May 5, 1992, D.C. Law 9-96, § 4(a), 38 DCR 7274</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 13-289">Apr. 27, 2001, D.C. Law 13-289, § 401(a), 48 DCR 2057</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 14-235">Mar. 25, 2003, D.C. Law 14-235, § 10(a), 49 DCR 9788</annotation>
        <annotation>Mar. 13, 2004, D.C. Law 15-105, §§ 90(c), 94 - 97, 51 DCR 881</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 15-289">Apr. 5, 2005, D.C. Law 15-289, § 2(a), 52 DCR 1446</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 16-224">Mar. 6, 2007, D.C. Law 16-224, § 101(a), 53 DCR 10225</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 17-67">Jan. 23, 2008, D.C. Law 17-67, § 2(a), 54 DCR 11646</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 17-303">Mar. 20, 2009, D.C. Law 17-303,§ 3(a), 55 DCR 12803</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 19-171">Sept. 26, 2012, D.C. Law 19-171, § 140, 59 DCR 6190</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 19-266">Apr. 27, 2013, D.C. Law 19-266, § 102(a), 59 DCR 12957</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Section References</heading>
        <annotation>This section is referenced in § <cite path="§5-114.01">5-114.01</cite>, § <cite path="§31-2402">31-2402</cite>, § <cite path="§50-601">50-601</cite>, § <cite path="§50-1108">50-1108</cite>, § <cite path="§50-1201">50-1201</cite>, § <cite path="§50-1301.02">50-1301.02</cite>, § <cite path="§50-1331.01">50-1331.01</cite>, § <cite path="§50-1401.01">50-1401.01</cite>, § <cite path="§50-1501.01">50-1501.01</cite>, § <cite path="§50-1505.01">50-1505.01</cite>, § <cite path="§50-1901">50-1901</cite>, § <cite path="§50-2301.02">50-2301.02</cite>, and § <cite path="§50-2602">50-2602</cite>.</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Prior Codifications</heading>
        <annotation>1981 Ed., § 40-702.</annotation>
        <annotation>1973 Ed., § 40-602.</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Effect of Amendments</heading>
        <annotation><cite doc="D.C. Law 13-289">D.C. Law 13-289</cite> added the definition for the term mini-van.</annotation>
        <annotation><cite doc="D.C. Law 14-235">D.C. Law 14-235</cite> rewrote par. (1) and added par. (12). Par. (1) had read as follows: “(1) The term ‘motor vehicle’ means all vehicles propelled by internal-combustion engines, electricity, or steam. The term ‘motor vehicle’ shall not include traction engines, road rollers, vehicles propelled only upon rails or tracks, and battery-operated wheelchairs when operated by a handicapped person at speeds not exceeding 10 miles per hour.”</annotation>
        <annotation><cite doc="D.C. Law 15-105">D.C. Law 15-105</cite> validated previously made technical corrections; repealed par. (3); and in par. (10), substituted “The term ‘traffic’ shall” for “Traffic shall”. Prior to amendment, par. (3) had read as follows: “(3) The term ‘District’ means the District of Columbia.”</annotation>
        <annotation><cite doc="D.C. Law 15-289">D.C. Law 15-289</cite> added pars. (13) and (14).</annotation>
        <annotation><cite doc="D.C. Law 16-224">D.C. Law 16-224</cite> revived the provisions of <cite doc="D.C. Law 14-235">D.C. Law 14-235</cite> that expired on October 1, 2005, and rewrote pars. (1) and (12).</annotation>
        <annotation><cite doc="D.C. Law 16-305">D.C. Law 16-305</cite>, in par. (1), purported to substitute “person with a disability” for “handicapped person”.</annotation>
        <annotation><cite doc="D.C. Law 17-67">D.C. Law 17-67</cite> added par. (15).</annotation>
        <annotation><cite doc="D.C. Law 17-303">D.C. Law 17-303</cite> added par. (16).</annotation>
        <annotation>The 2012 amendment by <cite doc="D.C. Law 19-171">D.C. Law 19-171</cite> substituted “The term ‘vehicle conveyance fee’ shall” for “ ‘Vehicle conveyance fee’ shall” in (16).</annotation>
        <annotation>The 2013 amendment by <cite doc="D.C. Law 19-266">D.C. Law 19-266</cite> rewrote this section.</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Temporary Amendment of Section</heading>
        <annotation>For temporary (225 day) amendment of section, see § 10(a) of Motor Vehicle Definition Electric Personal Assistive Mobility Device Exemption Temporary Amendment Act of 2006 (<cite doc="D.C. Law 16-85">D.C. Law 16-85</cite>, April 4, 2006, law notification  53 DCR 3344).</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Emergency Legislation</heading>
        <annotation>For temporary (90-day) amendment of section, see § 2(a) of the Motor Coach Vehicles Tax Exemption Emergency Amendment Act of 1999 (D.C. Act 13-182, November 22, 1999,  47 DCR 1).</annotation>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 day) amendment of section, see § 10(a) of Motor Vehicle Definition Electric Personal Assistive Mobility Device Exemption Emergency Amendment Act of 2005 (D.C. Act 16-237, December 22, 2005,  53 DCR 249).</annotation>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 day) amendment of section, see § 10(a) of Motor Vehicle Definition Electric Personal Assistive Mobility Device Exemption Congressional Review Emergency Amendment Act of 2006 (D.C. Act 16-323, March 23, 2006,  53 DCR 2567).</annotation>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 day) amendment of section, see § 101(a) of Personal Mobility Device Emergency Amendment Act of 2006 (D.C. Act 16-528, December 4, 2006,  53 DCR 9826).</annotation>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 day) amendment of section, see § 2(a) of Doubled Fines in Construction and Work Zones Emergency Amendment Act of 2007 (D.C. Act 17-149, October 18, 2007,  54 DCR 10894).</annotation>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 day) amendment of section, see § 2(a) of Doubled Fines in Construction and Work Zones Congressional Review Emergency Amendment Act of 2008 (D.C. Act 17-252, January 23, 2008,  55 DCR 1264).</annotation>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 day) amendment of section, see § 102(a) of Comprehensive Impaired Driving and Alcohol Testing Program Emergency Amendment Act of 2012 (D.C. Act 19-429, July 30, 2012,  59 DCR 9387).</annotation>
        <annotation>For temporary amendment of section, see § 102(a) of the Comprehensive Impaired Driving and Alcohol Testing Program Congressional Review Emergency Amendment Act of 2012 (D.C. Act 19-508, October 26, 2012, 59 DCR 12774).</annotation>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 days) amendment of this section, see § 102(a) of the Comprehensive Impaired Driving and Alcohol Testing Program Congressional Review Emergency Act of 2013 (D.C. Act 20-3, January 29, 2013,  60 DCR 2762, 20 DCSTAT 410).</annotation>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 days) amendment of this section, see § 102(a) of the Comprehensive Impaired Driving and Alcohol Testing Program Second Congressional Review Emergency Act of 2013 (D.C. Act 20-51, April 17, 2013,  60 DCR 6344, 20 DCSTAT 1360).</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Expiration of Law</heading>
        <text>Expiration of Law 14-235</text>
        <text>Section 14 of <cite doc="D.C. Law 14-235">D.C. Law 14-235</cite> provided that the act shall expire on October 1, 2005.</text>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Change in Government</heading>
        <annotation>This section originated at a time when local government powers were delegated to a Board of Commissioners of the District of Columbia (see Acts Relating to the Establishment of the District of Columbia and its Various Forms of Governmental Organization in Volume 1). Section 402 (292, 293, 295 to 299) of Reorganization Plan No. 3 of 1967 (see Reorganization Plans in Volume 1) transferred all of the functions of the Board of Commissioners under this section to the District of Columbia Council, subject to the right of the Commissioner as provided in § 406 of the Plan. The District of Columbia Self-Government and Governmental Reorganization Act, 87 Stat. 818, § 711 ( D.C. Code, § <cite path="§1-207.11">1-207.11</cite>), abolished the District of Columbia Council and the Office of Commissioner of the District of Columbia. These branches of government were replaced by the Council of the District of Columbia and the Office of Mayor of the District of Columbia, respectively. Accordingly, and also pursuant to § 714(a) of such Act ( D.C. Code, § <cite path="§1-207.14">1-207.14</cite>(a)), appropriate changes in terminology were made in this section.</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section from-code="true">
    <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" path="|50|22|I|A"/>
    <num codify:value="50-2201.03">6</num>
    <heading>Mayor to make rules; Department of Transportation; Director; Congressional and Council parking; title fees; common carriers; penalties; prosecutions; publication of regulations; excise tax; impoundment for outstanding violations.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>(a)</num>
      <text>The Mayor is authorized and empowered to make, modify, repeal, and enforce rules relating to and concerning the following:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The control of traffic and the movement of traffic;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <para>
          <num>(A)</num>
          <text>The length, weight, height, and width of vehicles; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(B)</num>
          <text>The brakes, horns, lights, mufflers, and other equipment of vehicles and the inspection of same;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <para>
          <num>(A)</num>
          <text>The registration and reregistration of vehicles;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(B)</num>
          <text>The titling and retitling of motor vehicles and trailers, and the transfer of titles to motor vehicles and trailers; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(C)</num>
          <text>The revocation, suspension, restoration, and reinstatement of the registration for motor vehicles and trailers and of certificates of title to motor vehicles and trailers;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The issuance, suspension, revocation, restoration, and reinstatement of operator’s permits and operating privileges; provided, that the fee for restoration or reinstatement shall be $98;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>The establishment and location of hack stands; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>The speed, routing, and parking of vehicles; provided, that the Mayor shall establish and locate parking areas in the vicinity of government establishments for use only by members of Congress and governmental officials when on official business.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(b)</num>
      <text>There is established in the government of the District of Columbia a Department of Transportation, which under the direction of the Mayor, shall have charge of the issuance and revocation of operators’ permits, the registration and titling of motor vehicles, the making of traffic studies and plans, the establishment and designation of arterial and other public highways, providing for the equipment of any street, road, or highway with control lights or other devices, or both, for the regulation of traffic, the installation and maintenance of traffic signs, signals, and markers, and of such other matters as may be determined by the Mayor. The Mayor shall appoint a Director of Vehicles and Traffic, who shall be in charge of said Department, and such other personnel as he or she may deem necessary to perform the duties thereof and as may be appropriated for by Congress. The Director of Vehicles and Traffic shall be responsible directly to the Mayor for the faithful performance of his or her duties and shall be subject to removal by the Mayor for cause.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(c)</num>
      <text>Members of Congress or the Council may park their vehicles in any available curb space in the District of Columbia, when:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The vehicle is used by the member of Congress or the Council on official business;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The vehicle is displaying a Congressional or Council registration tag or parking placard issued for the current session or by the District; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The vehicle is not parked in violation of a loading zone, rush hour, firehouse, or fire plug limitation.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(d)</num>
      <text>The Mayor shall cause to be levied, collected, and paid a $26 fee for each titling, duplicate titling, and retitling, and he or she shall not, after the 1st day of January, 1932, register or renew the registration of any motor vehicle or trailer unless and until the owner thereof shall make application in the form prescribed by the Mayor and be granted an official certificate of title for such vehicle. No registration or titling fee shall be charged for vehicles owned by the District government. The owner of a motor vehicle or trailer registered in the District of Columbia shall not, after the 1st day of January, 1932, operate or permit or cause to be operated any such vehicle upon any public highway in the District without first obtaining a certificate of title therefor, nor shall any individual knowingly permit any certificate of title to be obtained in his or her name for any vehicle not in fact owned by him or her, and any individual violating any provision of this subsection or any regulations promulgated thereunder shall be fined not more than the amount set forth in § <cite path="§22-3571.01">22-3571.01</cite> or imprisoned not more than one year, or both. If the properly designated agent of the Mayor shall determine that an applicant for a certificate of title is not entitled thereto, such certificate of title may be refused, and in that event unless such determination is reversed upon written application to the Mayor by the individual affected, such individual shall be entitled to proceed further as provided under § <cite path="§50-1403.01">50-1403.01</cite>(a); provided, that reasonable time for hearing be given the applicant in the first instance.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(e)</num>
      <text>As to all common carriers by vehicle which enter, operate in, or leave the District of Columbia, the power to route small vehicles within the District of Columbia, to regulate their equipment other than that specifically named elsewhere in this part, to regulate their schedules and their loading and unloading, to locate their stops and all platforms and loading zones, and to require the appropriate marking thereof is vested in the Public Service Commission of the District of Columbia.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(f)</num>
      <text>Except as otherwise provided in this part or in the District of Columbia Traffic Adjudication Act of 1978 (§ <cite path="§50-2301.01">50-2301.01</cite> et seq.), any person violating any provision of this part or any rule promulgated hereunder shall, upon conviction thereof, be fined not more than the amount set forth in § <cite path="§22-3571.01">22-3571.01</cite> or imprisoned for not more than 90 days, or both. Prosecution for violations shall be in the Superior Court of the District of Columbia upon information or indictment filed by the Corporation Counsel of the District of Columbia or any of his or her assistants.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(g)</num>
      <text>All regulations promulgated under the authority of this part shall be published in accordance with the requirements of subchapter I of Chapter 5 of Title 2 [§ <cite path="§2-501">2-501</cite> et seq.].</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(h)</num>
      <text>Repealed.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(i)</num>
      <text>Repealed.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(j)</num>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>In addition to the fees and charges levied under other provisions of this part, there is levied and imposed an excise tax on the issuance of every original certificate of title for a motor vehicle or trailer in the District of Columbia and every subsequent certificate of title issued in the District of Columbia in the case of a sale, resale, or gift, except in the case of a bona fide gift of a vehicle already titled in the District given between spouses, parent and child, or domestic partners, as that term is defined in § <cite path="§32-701">32-701</cite>(3), or other transfer at the following percentage of the fair market value of the motor vehicle or trailer at the time the certificate of title is issued:</text>
        <text>Weight Class  Registration Fee</text>
        <text>Class I (3,499 pounds or less)  6%</text>
        <text>Class II (3,500 — 4,999 pounds)  7%</text>
        <text>Class III (5,000 pounds or greater)  8%.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>For the purpose of this section, the Mayor or his or her duly authorized representative shall determine the fair market value of a motor vehicle or trailer. As used in this section, the term “original certificate of title” shall mean the first certificate of title issued by the District of Columbia for any particular motor vehicle or trailer. No certificate of title so issued shall be delivered or furnished to the person entitled thereto until the tax has been paid in full. The Assessor of the District of Columbia may require every applicant for a certificate to title to supply such information as he or she deems necessary as to the time of purchase, the purchase price, and other information relative to the determination of the fair market value of any motor vehicle or trailer for which a certificate of title is required and issued.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The issuance of certificates of title for the following motor vehicles and trailers shall be exempt from the tax imposed by this subsection:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(A)</num>
          <text>Motor vehicles and trailers owned by the United States or the District of Columbia;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(B)</num>
          <text>Repealed;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(C)</num>
          <text>Repealed;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(D)</num>
          <text>Motor vehicles and trailers owned by a utility or public service company for use in furnishing a commodity or service; provided, that the receipts from furnishing such commodity or service are subject to a gross receipts or mileage tax in force in the District of Columbia at the time of a certificate of title for any such vehicle or trailer is issued.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(E)</num>
          <text>New motor vehicles acquired from dealers as replacements for defective vehicles purchased new not more than 60 days prior to the date of such replacement, except that if the fair market value of any replacement vehicle is greater than that of the vehicle which it replaces, then the tax imposed by this section shall be paid on such difference in value. If the fair market value of any replacement vehicle is less than that of the vehicle which it replaces, then the Mayor or his or her designated agent is authorized to refund to the owner of the replacement vehicle an amount equal to the difference between the excise tax paid on the defective vehicle and the excise tax paid on the replacement vehicle.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(F)</num>
          <text>Rental or leased motor vehicles or trailers; provided, that the rental or leasing of such vehicles is subject to the gross receipts tax described in § <cite path="§47-2002">47-2002</cite>(3)(C).</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(G)</num>
          <text>Taxis or taxicabs as defined in § <cite path="§50-303">50-303</cite>(8).</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(H)</num>
          <text>Motor vehicles and trailers registered or titled in another state or United States jurisdiction by a nonresident before the nonresident established or maintained residency in the District.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(I)</num>
          <text>Commercial vehicles having the characteristics specified [in] § <cite path="§47-2352">47-2352</cite>(c) that are owned or leased by a company with an established place of business (as defined in § <cite path="§47-2302">47-2302</cite>(13)) located within the District of Columbia, if such vehicles are used to furnish a commodity or service; provided, that, the receipts from furnishing such commodity or service are subject to a gross receipts or mileage tax in force in the District of Columbia at the time a certificate of title is issued for the vehicle.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(J)</num>
          <text>Motor vehicles, excluding motorcycles and motor-driven cycles, with an estimated average miles per gallon (“MPG”) for city driving at or above 40 MPG, as determined in accordance with 40 CFR § 600.001-08, and published in the Fuel Economy Guide by the United States Environmental Protection Agency and the United States Department of Energy or other alternative fueled vehicles as determined by the Department of Motor Vehicles through rulemaking.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(K)</num>
          <text>Motor vehicles following the death of one co-owner; provided, that the title is issued to a surviving owner.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(L)</num>
          <text>Motor vehicles whose ownership is determined by a decree of divorce or separation or pursuant to a written instrument incident to such divorce or separation; or, in the case of former domestic partners, ownership is either determined by a court order or one co-owner transfers his or her interest to the other co-owner provided that the applicant also submits the termination statement provided for in § <cite path="§32-702">32-702</cite>(d)(1); and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(M)</num>
          <text>Motor vehicles re-titled by an insurance company in connection with an insurance claim or pursuant to Chapter 13A of this title.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(N)</num>
          <text>Any vehicle for which the certificate of title issued is a scrap title issued pursuant to § <cite path="§50-2705">50-2705</cite>.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(O)</num>
          <text>Repealed.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(P)</num>
          <text>Vehicles for which a District of Columbia title is being issued to the lienholder because of repossession or was re-issued to the owner after repossession.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(Q)</num>
          <text>Vehicles designated as non-repairable or salvage pursuant to Chapter 13A of this title [§ <cite path="§50-1331.01">50-1331.01</cite> et seq.].</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(k)</num>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Any unattended motor vehicle found parked at any time upon any public highway of the District of Columbia against which there are 2 or more unpaid notices of infraction or vehicle conveyance fees that the owner was deemed to have admitted or that were sustained after a hearing, pursuant to § <cite path="§50-2303.05">50-2303.05</cite>, § <cite path="§50-2303.06">50-2303.06</cite>, or § <cite path="§50-2209.02">50-2209.02</cite>, or against which there have been issued 2 or more warrants may, by or under the direction of a law enforcement officer or member of the Metropolitan Police force or the United States Park Police force or an employee of the District of Columbia Department of Transportation, either by towing or otherwise, be removed or conveyed to and impounded in any place designated by the Mayor or immobilized in such manner as to prevent its operation; except, that no such vehicle shall be immobilized by any means other than by the use of a device or other mechanism which will cause no damage to such vehicle unless it is moved while such device or mechanism is in place.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The notice, reclamation, and disposition procedures set forth in §§ <cite path="§50-2421.06">50-2421.06</cite> through <cite path="§50-2421.10">50-2421.10</cite>, shall apply to any vehicle impounded pursuant to this section. In any case involving immobilization of a vehicle pursuant to this subsection, such member or law enforcement officer or employee shall cause to be placed on such vehicle, in a conspicuous manner, notice sufficient to warn any individual to the effect that such vehicle has been immobilized and that any attempt to move such vehicle might result in damage to such vehicle.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Repealed.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The owner of an immobilized vehicle shall be subject to a booting fee of $75 for such immobilization.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Before the removal of an immobilization mechanism on a motor vehicle or the release of a motor vehicle from impoundment, the owner shall pay all outstanding fees, charges, civil fines, or penalties incurred pursuant to this section and §§ <cite path="§50-1401.01">50-1401.01</cite>, <cite path="§50-1401.02">50-1401.02</cite>,  <cite path="§31-2413">31-2413</cite>(b)(2)(A), <cite path="§50-1101">50-1101</cite>, <cite path="§50-1106">50-1106</cite>, <cite path="§50-1501.02">50-1501.02</cite>, <cite path="§50-1501.03">50-1501.03</cite>, <cite path="§50-2301.05">50-2301.05</cite>, <cite path="§50-2303.04a">50-2303.04a</cite>, and <cite path="§50-2421.09">50-2421.09</cite>(a), against the owner or any motor vehicle in which the owner has an ownership interest or had an ownership interest when a notice of infraction was issued.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(l)</num>
      <text>The Director of the Department of Motor Vehicles may establish a fee discount of up to 10% on any service obtained through the telephone, Internet, mail, or other method that does not involve an in-person visit to the Department. This subsection shall not apply to the payment of the motor vehicle title tax.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>History</heading>
        <annotation>Mar. 3, 1925, 43 Stat. 1121, ch. 443, § 6</annotation>
        <annotation>July 3, 1926, 44 Stat. 814, ch. 739, § 4</annotation>
        <annotation>Feb. 27, 1931, 46 Stat. 1424, ch. 317, §§ 3, 4</annotation>
        <annotation>Dec. 19, 1932, 47 Stat. 750, ch. 5</annotation>
        <annotation>Apr. 1, 1942, 56 Stat. 190, ch. 207, § 1</annotation>
        <annotation>July 2, 1945, 59 Stat. 313, ch. 222</annotation>
        <annotation>May 27, 1949, 63 Stat. 128, title III, ch. 146, § 301</annotation>
        <annotation>Oct. 28, 1949, 63 Stat. 972, title XI, ch. 782, § 1106(a)</annotation>
        <annotation>July 24, 1956, 70 Stat. 633, ch. 695, § 1</annotation>
        <annotation doc="Pub. L. 85-273">Sept. 2, 1957, 71 Stat. 598, Pub. L. 85-273, § 3</annotation>
        <annotation doc="Pub. L. 87-745">Oct. 3, 1962, 76 Stat. 742, Pub. L. 87-745, § 1</annotation>
        <annotation doc="Pub. L. 88-60">July 8, 1963, 77 Stat. 77, Pub. L. 88-60, § 1</annotation>
        <annotation doc="Pub. L. 88-503">Aug. 30, 1964, 78 Stat. 634, Pub. L. 88-503, § 21</annotation>
        <annotation doc="Pub. L. 89-610">Sept. 30, 1966, 80 Stat. 856, Pub. L. 89-610, title II, § 201</annotation>
        <annotation>1967 Reorg. Plan No. 3, 81 Stat. 980, § 503(c)</annotation>
        <annotation doc="Pub. L. 90-172">Dec. 4, 1967, 81 Stat. 532, Pub. L. 90-172, § 1</annotation>
        <annotation doc="Pub. L. 91-106">Oct. 31, 1969, 83 Stat. 172, 174, Pub. L. 91-106, §§ 201, 404</annotation>
        <annotation doc="Pub. L. 91-145">Dec. 12, 1969, 83 Stat. 343, Pub. L. 91-145, § 101</annotation>
        <annotation doc="Pub. L. 91-358">July 29, 1970, 84 Stat. 570, 583, Pub. L. 91-358, title I, §§ 155(a), 163(g)(2)</annotation>
        <annotation doc="Pub. L. 92-196">Dec. 15, 1971, 85 Stat. 657, Pub. L. 92-196, title VII, § 705</annotation>
        <annotation doc="Pub. L. 92-518">Oct. 21, 1972, 86 Stat. 1015, Pub. L. 92-518, title III, § 301(a)</annotation>
        <annotation doc="Pub. L. 93-145">Nov. 1, 1973, 87 Stat. 531, Pub. L. 93-145, § 101</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 1-23">Oct. 21, 1975, D.C. Law 1-23, title I, § 102, 22 DCR 2094</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 1-42">Jan. 22, 1976, D.C. Law 1-42, § 7(b), 22 DCR 6317</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 1-70">June 15, 1976, D.C. Law 1-70, title II, § 201, 23 DCR 536</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 1-124">Apr. 19, 1977, D.C. Law 1-124, title I, § 102, 23 DCR 8749</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 1-133">Apr. 26, 1977, D.C. Law 1-133, title IV, § 402, 23 DCR 9697</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 2-104">Sept. 12, 1978, D.C. Law 2-104, §§ 501, 601, 25 DCR 1275</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 2-139">Mar. 3, 1979, D.C. Law 2-139, § 3205(l), 25 DCR 5740</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 2-157">Mar. 6, 1979, D.C. Law 2-157, § 5, 25 DCR 6995</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 4-97">Apr. 3, 1982, D.C. Law 4-97, § 5, 29 DCR 765</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 4-145">Sept. 14, 1982, D.C. Law 4-145, § 7, 29 DCR 3138</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 5-14">June 22, 1983, D.C. Law 5-14, §§ 803, 804, 30 DCR 2632</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 5-42">Nov. 15, 1983, D.C. Law 5-42, § 2(b), 30 DCR 4999</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 8-103">May 1, 1990, D.C. Law 8-103, § 2, 37 DCR 1615</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 8-170">Sept. 26, 1990, D.C. Law 8-170, § 2, 37 DCR 4839</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 9-30">Aug. 17, 1991, D.C. Law 9-30, § 4(a), 38 DCR 4215</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 9-96">May 5, 1992, D.C. Law 9-96, § 4(b), 38 DCR 7274</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 12-175">Mar. 26, 1999, D.C. Law 12-175, § 802, 45 DCR 7193</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 13-80">April 5, 2000, D.C. Law 13-80, § 2, 46 DCR 10463</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 14-213">Oct. 19, 2002, D.C. Law 14-213, § 34, 49 DCR 8140</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 14-307">June 5, 2003, D.C. Law 14-307, § 1706(a), 49 DCR 11664</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 15-35">Oct. 28, 2003, D.C. Law 15-35, § 13(b), 50 DCR 6579</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 15-239">Mar. 16, 2005, D.C. Law 15-239, § 2(a), 51 DCR 9600</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 15-307">Apr. 8, 2005, D.C. Law 15-307, § 402, 52 DCR 1700</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 16-33">Oct. 20, 2005, D.C. Law 16-33, § 6002, 52 DCR 7503</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 16-129">June 16, 2006, D.C. Law 16-129, § 2, 53 DCR 4716</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 16-139">June 22, 2006, D.C. Law 16-139, § 10, 53 DCR 3682</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 16-191">Mar. 2, 2007, D.C. Law 16-191, § 89, 53 DCR 6794</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 16-279">Mar. 14, 2007, D.C. Law 16-279, §§ 202(a), 401(a), 54 DCR 903</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 17-219">Aug. 16, 2008, D.C. Law 17-219, § 6006, 55 DCR 7598</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 17-231">Sept. 12, 2008, D.C. Law 17-231, § 42, 55 DCR 6758</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 17-303">Mar. 20, 2009, D.C. Law 17-303, § 3(b), 55 DCR 12803</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 19-272">Apr. 23, 2013, D.C. Law 19-272, § 2, 60 DCR 1729</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 19-266">Apr. 27, 2013, D.C. Law 19-266, § 102(b), 59 DCR 12957</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 19-290">Apr. 27, 2013, D.C. Law 19-290, § 5(a), 60 DCR 2343</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 19-317">June 11, 2013, D.C. Law 19-317, § 271(a), 60 DCR 2064</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 20-61">Dec. 24, 2013, D.C. Law 20-61, §§ 6012, 6133, 60 DCR 12472</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Cross References</heading>
        <annotation>Alcoholic beverage control, operation of trains, streetcars, and other vehicles by intoxicated persons, see § <cite path="§25-1009">25-1009</cite>.</annotation>
        <annotation>General license law, vehicles hauling goods from public space, hack stands, see § <cite path="§47-2831">47-2831</cite>.</annotation>
        <annotation>Motor vehicle exhaust emissions inspections, see § <cite path="§50-1101">50-1101</cite> et seq.</annotation>
        <annotation>National Capital Region Transportation, revenues allocated to the Metrorail/Metrobus Account, see § <cite path="§9-1111.15">9-1111.15</cite>.</annotation>
        <annotation>Parks and playgrounds, regulation of vehicles and traffic, see § <cite path="§10-105">10-105</cite>.</annotation>
        <annotation>Public roads and bridges, jurisdiction and control, see § <cite path="§9-101.02">9-101.02</cite>.</annotation>
        <annotation>Public roads, designation of “business streets” for parking and sidewalk purposes, see § <cite path="§9-1201.05">9-1201.05</cite>.</annotation>
        <annotation>Public Service Commission, promulgated rules and regulations, prosecution for violations, see § <cite path="§34-731">34-731</cite>.</annotation>
        <annotation>Public Service Commission, suspension of powers by the Compact for Mass Transportation, see § <cite path="§9-1103.04">9-1103.04</cite>.</annotation>
        <annotation>Public utilities, regulation and enforcement, powers and duties of the Mayor, see § <cite path="§34-809">34-809</cite>.</annotation>
        <annotation>Registration of motor vehicles, issuance and expiration of registration documents, see § <cite path="§50-1501.02">50-1501.02</cite>.</annotation>
        <annotation>Regulations necessary for the protection of lives, limbs, health, comfort, and quiet, see § <cite path="§1-303.03">1-303.03</cite>.</annotation>
        <annotation>Senior citizen motor vehicle accident prevention course certification, see § <cite path="§50-2001">50-2001</cite> et seq.</annotation>
        <annotation>Taxi stands, see § <cite path="§1-301.71">1-301.71</cite>.</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Section References</heading>
        <annotation>This section is referenced in § <cite path="§1-636.02">1-636.02</cite>, § <cite path="§9-1103.04">9-1103.04</cite>, § <cite path="§9-1111.15">9-1111.15</cite>, § <cite path="§34-731">34-731</cite>, § <cite path="§47-2831">47-2831</cite>, § <cite path="§50-2201.22">50-2201.22</cite>, § <cite path="§50-2201.25">50-2201.25</cite>, § <cite path="§50-2201.27">50-2201.27</cite>, § <cite path="§50-2421.02">50-2421.02</cite>, and § <cite path="§50-2421.09">50-2421.09</cite>.</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Prior Codifications</heading>
        <annotation>1981 Ed., § 40-703.</annotation>
        <annotation>1973 Ed., § 40-603.</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Effect of Amendments</heading>
        <annotation><cite doc="D.C. Law 13-80">D.C. Law 13-80</cite> added par. (j)(3)(III).</annotation>
        <annotation>Section 3 of D.C. Law 13-80 provided: “The Council adopts the fiscal impact statement in the committee report, as revised and amended by the attached memorandum dated October 25, 1999, as the fiscal impact statement required by section 602(c)(3) of the Home Rule Act, approved December 24, 1973 (87 Stat. 813;  D.C. Code § 1-233(c)(3)) [§ 1-206.02(c)(3), 2001 Ed.].”</annotation>
        <annotation>Section 4 of <cite doc="D.C. Law 13-80">D.C. Law 13-80</cite> provided: “This act shall apply as of January 1, 2000.”</annotation>
        <annotation><cite doc="D.C. Law 14-213">D.C. Law 14-213</cite>, in the section heading, substituted “Congressional and Council parking” for “Congressional parking”; in subsecs. (c) and (c)(1), substituted “Congress or the Council” for “Congress”; and in subsec. (c)(2), substituted “Congressional or Council” for “Congressional”.</annotation>
        <annotation><cite doc="D.C. Law 14-307">D.C. Law 14-307</cite>, in subsec. (a)(4), substituted “$98” for “$75”; and in subsec. (d), substituted “$26 fee for each titling, duplicate titling, and retitling,” for “$20 fee for each titling and retitling,”.</annotation>
        <annotation><cite doc="D.C. Law 15-35">D.C. Law 15-35</cite>, in subsec. (k), substituted “The notice, reclamation, and disposition procedures set forth in §§ <cite path="§50-2421.06">50-2421.06</cite> through <cite path="§50-2421.10">50-2421.10</cite>, shall apply to any vehicle impounded pursuant to this section.” for “It shall be the duty of the officer or member of the police force or employee of the District of Columbia Department of Transportation, removing or immobilizing such motor vehicle, or under whose direction such vehicle is removed or immobilized, to inform as soon as practicable the owner of an impounded or immobilized vehicle of the nature and circumstances of the prior unsettled traffic violation notices, notices of infractions or warrants, for which or an account of which such vehicle was impounded or immobilized.” in the first sentence of par. (2), repealed par. (3), and deleted the second and third sentences in par. (4).</annotation>
        <annotation><cite doc="D.C. Law 15-239">D.C. Law 15-239</cite>, in subsec. (f), substituted “otherwise provided in this part” for “provided”, and substituted “upon information or indictment” for “upon information”.</annotation>
        <annotation><cite doc="D.C. Law 15-307">D.C. Law 15-307</cite>, in subsec. (j), rewrote par. (1) and added subpars. (J), (K), (L), and (M) in par. (3).</annotation>
        <annotation><cite doc="D.C. Law 16-33">D.C. Law 16-33</cite>, in subsec. (k)(4), substituted “$75” for “$50”.</annotation>
        <annotation><cite doc="D.C. Law 16-129">D.C. Law 16-129</cite> rewrote subpar. (j)(3)(J), which had read as follows: “(J) A clean-fuel vehicle or electric vehicle determined by the United States Internal Revenue Service to be eligible for a federal tax deduction or credit pursuant to  26 U.S.C. §§ 30 and  179A for the tax year during which it is being titled.”</annotation>
        <annotation><cite doc="D.C. Law 16-139">D.C. Law 16-139</cite> added subpar. (j)(3)(N).</annotation>
        <annotation><cite doc="D.C. Law 16-191">D.C. Law 16-191</cite>, in subsec. (j), validated a previously made technical correction.</annotation>
        <annotation><cite doc="D.C. Law 16-279">D.C. Law 16-279</cite>, in subsec. (d), substituted “No registration or titling fee shall be charged for vehicles owned by the District government” for “No registration or other fee shall be charged to vehicles owned by the federal or District government or any duly accredited representative of a foreign government”; in subsec. (j)(3), substituted “Rental vehicles and utility trailers being registered as part of a rental fleet pursuant to subchapter III of Chapter 15 of this title” for “Rental vehicles and utility trailers, as defined in § <cite path="§50-1505.01">50-1505.01</cite>” in subpar. (F), and added subpars. (O), (P), and (Q); and added subsec. (l); and rewrote subsecs. (j)(1) and (k)(1), which formerly read:</annotation>
        <annotation>“(j)(1) In addition to the fees and charges levied under other provisions of this part, there is hereby levied and imposed an excise tax on the issuance of every original certificate of title for a motor vehicle or trailer in the District of Columbia and, in the case of a sale, resale, gift or other transfer thereof, on the issuance of every subsequent certificate of title, except in the case of a bona fide gift between spouses, parent and child, or domestic partners, as that term is defined in § <cite path="§32-701">32-701</cite>(3), at the following percentage of the fair market value of the motor vehicle or trailer at the time the certificate of title is issued:”</annotation>
        <annotation>“(k)(1) Any unattended motor vehicle found parked at any time upon any public highway of the District of Columbia against which there are 2 or more outstanding or otherwise unsettled traffic violation notices or notices of infraction or against which there have been issued 2 or more warrants may, by or under the direction of an officer or member of the Metropolitan Police force or the United States Park Police force or an employee of the District of Columbia Department of Transportation, either by towing or otherwise, be removed or conveyed to and impounded in any place designated by the Mayor or immobilized in such manner as to prevent its operation; except, that no such vehicle shall be immobilized by any means other than by the use of a device or other mechanism which will cause no damage to such vehicle unless it is moved while such device or mechanism is in place.”</annotation>
        <annotation><cite doc="D.C. Law 17-219">D.C. Law 17-219</cite>, in subsec. (j)(3), rewrote subpars. (F) and (J) and repealed subpar. (O.</annotation>
        <annotation><cite doc="D.C. Law 17-231">D.C. Law 17-231</cite>, in subsec. (j)(3)(L), substituted “§ <cite path="§32-702">32-702</cite>(d)(1)” for “§ <cite path="§32-702">32-702</cite>”.</annotation>
        <annotation><cite doc="D.C. Law 17-303">D.C. Law 17-303</cite>, in subsec. (k)(1), substituted “notices of infraction or vehicle conveyance fees” for “notices of infraction”.</annotation>
        <annotation>The 2013 amendment by <cite doc="D.C. Law 19-266">D.C. Law 19-266</cite> substituted “$2,500” for “$1,000” in (d); substituted “$500” for “$300” in (f); substituted “a law enforcement officer” for “an officer” in (k)(1); substituted “law enforcement officer” for “officer” in (k)(2); made gender-neutral changes throughout the section; and made stylistic changes.</annotation>
        <annotation>The 2013 amendment by <cite doc="D.C. Law 19-272">D.C. Law 19-272</cite> rewrote (j)(1) and (j)(3)(H).</annotation>
        <annotation>The 2013 amendment by <cite doc="D.C. Law 19-290">D.C. Law 19-290</cite> substituted “motor-driven cycles” for “motorized bicycles” in (j)(3)(J).</annotation>
        <annotation>The 2013 amendment by <cite doc="D.C. Law 19-317">D.C. Law 19-317</cite> substituted “not more than the amount set forth in § <cite path="§22-3571.01">22-3571.01</cite>” for “not more than $1,000 [$2,500]” in (d), and for “not more than $300 [$500]” in (f).</annotation>
        <annotation>The 2013 amendment by <cite doc="D.C. Law 20-61">D.C. Law 20-61</cite> substituted “registration tag or parking placard issued for the current session or by the District”’ for “registration tag issued by the jurisdiction represented by the member” in (c)(2); and added (k)(5).</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Temporary Amendment of Section</heading>
        <annotation>For temporary (225 day) amendment of section, see § 2 of Certificate of Title Excise Tax Exemption Temporary Amendment Act of 2004 (<cite doc="D.C. Law 15-312">D.C. Law 15-312</cite>, April 8, 2005, law notification  52 DCR 4701).</annotation>
        <annotation>For temporary (225 day) amendment of section, see § 2 of Low-Emissions Motor Vehicle Tax Exemption Temporary Amendment Act of 2006 (<cite doc="D.C. Law 16-88">D.C. Law 16-88</cite>, April 4, 2006, law notification  53 DCR 3347).</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Emergency Legislation</heading>
        <annotation>For temporary amendment of section, see § 502 of the Fiscal Year 1999 Budget Support Emergency Act of 1998 (D.C. Act 12-401, July 13, 1998,  45 DCR 4794), § 502 of the Fiscal Year 1999 Budget Support Congressional Review Emergency Act of 1998 (D.C. Act 12-564, January 12, 1999,  46 DCR 669), and § 502 of the Fiscal Year 1999 Budget Support Congressional Review Emergency Act of 1999 (D.C. Act 13-41, March 31, 1999,  46 DCR 3446).</annotation>
        <annotation>For temporary (90-day) amendment of section, see § 502 of the Fiscal Year 1999 Budget Support Congressional Review Emergency Act of 1999 (D.C. Act 13-41, March 31, 1999,  46 DCR 3446).</annotation>
        <annotation>For temporary (90-day) amendment of section, see § 2(b) of the Motor Coach Vehicles Tax Exemption Emergency Amendment Act of 1999 (D.C. Act 13-182, November 22, 1999,  47 DCR 1).</annotation>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 day) amendment of section, see § 1706(a) of Fiscal Year 2003 Budget Support Amendment Emergency Act of 2002 (D.C. Act 14-544, December 4, 2002,  49 DCR 11700).</annotation>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 day) amendment of section, see § 1706(a) of the Fiscal Year 2003 Budget Support Amendment Congressional Review Emergency Act of 2003 (D.C. Act 15-27, February 24, 2003,  50 DCR 2151).</annotation>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 day) amendment of section, see § 1706(a) of Fiscal Year 2003 Budget Support Amendment Second Congressional Review Emergency Act of 2003 (D.C. Act 15-103, June 20, 2003,  50 DCR 5499).</annotation>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 day) amendment of section, see § 13(b) of the Removal and Disposition of Abandoned, Dangerous and Other Unlawfully Parked Vehicles Reform Emergency Act of 2002 (D.C. Act 15-104, June 20, 2003,  50 DCR 5534).</annotation>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 day) amendment of section, see § 13(b) of Removal and Disposition of Abandoned and Other Unlawfully Parked Vehicles Reform Congressional Review Emergency Act of 2003 (D.C. Act 15-171, October 6, 2003,  50 DCR 9163).</annotation>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 day) amendment of section, see § 2 of Certificate of Title Excise Tax Exemption Emergency Amendment Act of 2004 (D.C. Act 15-615, November 30, 2004,  51 DCR 11441).</annotation>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 day) amendment of section, see § 2 of Certificate of Title Excise Tax Exemption Congressional Review Emergency Amendment Act of 2005 (D.C. Act 16-20, February 17, 2005,  52 DCR 2967).</annotation>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 day) amendment of section, see § 6002 of Fiscal Year 2006 Budget Support Emergency Act of 2005 (D.C. Act 16-168, July 26, 2005,  52 DCR 7667).</annotation>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 day) amendment of section, see § 2 of Low-Emissions Motor Vehicle Tax Exemption Emergency Amendment Act of 2005 (D.C. Act 16-239, December 22, 2005,  53 DCR 258).</annotation>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 day) amendment of section, see § 2 of Low-Emissions Motor Vehicle Tax Exemption Congressional Review Emergency Amendment Act of 2006 (D.C. Act 16-324, March 23, 2006,  53 DCR 2574).</annotation>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 day) amendment of section, see § 102(b) of Comprehensive Impaired Driving and Alcohol Testing Program Emergency Amendment Act of 2012 (D.C. Act 19-429, July 30, 2012,  59 DCR 9387).</annotation>
        <annotation>For temporary amendment of (b), (d), (f), (j) and (k), see § 102(b) of the Comprehensive Impaired Driving and Alcohol Testing Program Congressional Review Emergency Amendment Act of 2012 (D.C. Act 19-508, October 26, 2012, 59 DCR 12774).</annotation>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 days) amendment of this section, see § 102(b) of the Comprehensive Impaired Driving and Alcohol Testing Program Congressional Review Emergency Act of 2013 (D.C. Act 20-3, January 29, 2013,  60 DCR 2762, 20 DCSTAT 410).</annotation>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 days) amendment of this section, see § 271(a) of the Criminal Fine Proportionality Emergency Act of 2013 (D.C. Act 20-45, April 1, 2013,  60 DCR 5400, 20 DCSTAT 1300).</annotation>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 days) amendment of this section, see § 102(b) of the Comprehensive Impaired Driving and Alcohol Testing Program Second Congressional Review Emergency Act of 2013 (D.C. Act 20-51, April 17, 2013,  60 DCR 6344, 20 DCSTAT 1360).</annotation>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 days) amendment of this section, see §§ 6012 and 6133 of the Fiscal Year 2014 Budget Support Emergency Act of 2013 (D.C. Act 20-130, July 30, 2013,  60 DCR 11384, 20 DCSTAT 1827).</annotation>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 days) amendment of this section, see §§ 6012 and 6133 of the Fiscal Year 2014 Budget Support Congressional Review Emergency Act of 2013 (D.C. Act 20-204, October 17, 2013,  60 DCR 15341, 20 DCSTAT 2311).</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Short Title</heading>
        <text>Short title of subtitle A of title VI of Law 16-33: Section 6001 of <cite doc="D.C. Law 16-33">D.C. Law 16-33</cite> provided that subtitle A of title VI of the act may be cited as the Traffic Amendment Act of 2005.</text>
        <text>Short title: Section 6005 of <cite doc="D.C. Law 17-219">D.C. Law 17-219</cite> provided that subtitle B of title VI of the act may be cited as the “Department of Motor Vehicles Incentive Exemption for Leased Vehicles and Low Emission Vehicles Amendment Act of 2008”.</text>
        <text>Section 6011 of <cite doc="D.C. Law 20-61">D.C. Law 20-61</cite> provided that Subtitle B of Title VI of the act may be cited as the “DMV Immobilization Amendment Act of 2013”.</text>
        <text>Section 6131 of <cite doc="D.C. Law 20-61">D.C. Law 20-61</cite> provided that Subtitle N of Title VI of the act may be cited as the “Representation Tags Amendment Act of 2013”.</text>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Delegation of Authority</heading>
        <annotation>Delegation of authority under Law 5-14, see Mayor’s Order 83-190, July 25, 1983.</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Editor's Notes</heading>
        <text>Section 5 of  46 Stat. 1429, ch. 317, effective Feb. 27, 1931, provided that all convictions under the Act shall be reported by the clerk of the court to the commissioners [Mayor] or their [his] designated agent.</text>
        <text>Application of Law 15-35: Section 15 of <cite doc="D.C. Law 15-35">D.C. Law 15-35</cite> provided: “This act shall apply to all vehicles impounded after its effective date. This act shall also apply to all vehicles impounded prior to its effective date provided that notice is sent to the owners and lien holders in accordance with the provisions of subsections 7(b) or (c), as is applicable.”</text>
        <text>Department of Vehicles and Traffic abolished: The Department of Vehicles and Traffic, including the Director, was abolished and the functions thereof transferred to the Board of Commissioners of the District of Columbia by Reorganization Plan No. 5 of 1952. Reorganization Order No. 54 of the Board of Commissioners, dated June 30, 1953, as amended, September 1, 1953, established a Department of Vehicles and Traffic, headed by a Director; a Board of Revocation and Review of Hackers’ Identification Cards; a Motor Vehicle Parking Agency; and a Commissioners’ Traffic Advisory Board; prescribed the functions thereof; and abolished the previously existing Department of Vehicles and Traffic, the Registrar of Titles and Tags, the Board of Revocation and Review of Hackers’ Identification Cards, the Driver Improvement Section, and the Motor Vehicle Parking Agency. Reorganization Order No. 54 was repealed and replaced by Organization Order Nos. 105, 106, 107, and 108, dated May 17, 1955. Organization Order No. 105 continued the Department of Vehicles and Traffic and prescribed the functions thereof. Organization Order No. 106 continued the Motor Vehicle Parking Agency and prescribed the composition and functions thereof. The Department of Vehicles and Traffic was redesignated as the Department of Motor Vehicles by Commissioners’ Order No. 58-919, dated June 10, 1958. The Department of Highways was replaced by Reorganization Order No. 58-1116, dated July 15, 1958, which order established the Department of Highways and Traffic. The executive functions of the Board of Commissioners were transferred to the Commissioner of the District of Columbia by § 401 of Reorganization Plan No. 3 of 1967. Organization Order No. 107, relating to the Hackers’ Board was redesignated as Organization Order No. 13, dated August 15, 1968, and amended. Organization Order No. 108, as amended, replaced the Commissioners’ Traffic Advisory Board with a Citizens’ Traffic Board, and prescribed the composition and functions thereof. Reorganization Plan No. 2 of 1975 combined the Department of Motor Vehicles and the Department of Highways and Traffic to form the Department of Transportation.</text>
        <text>The functions of the Department of Transportation were transferred to the Department of Public Works by Reorganization Plan No. 4 of 1983, effective March 1, 1984.</text>
        <text>Office of Assessor abolished: The Office of the Assessor was abolished and the functions thereof transferred to the Board of Commissioners of the District of Columbia by Reorganization Plan No. 5 of 1952. All functions of the Office of the Assessor including the functions of all officers, employees and subordinate agencies were transferred to the Department of General Administration by Reorganization Order No. 3 of the Board of Commissioners, dated August 28, 1952. Reorganization Order No. 20, dated November 10, 1952, abolished the Office of the Assessor and transferred the functions to the Finance Office in the Department of General Administration. The same order provided that an Office of the Assessor would be created in the Finance Office. Reorganization Order No. 20 was superseded and replaced by Organization Order No. 121, dated December 12, 1957, provided that the Finance Office (consisting of the Office of the Finance Officers, Property Tax Division, Revenue Division, Treasury Division, Accounting Division, and Data Processing Division) shall continue under the direction and control of the Director of General Administration, and prescribed the functions thereof. The executive functions of the Board of Commissioners were transferred to the Commissioner of the District of Columbia by § 401 of Reorganization Plan No. 3 of 1967. Organization Order No. 121 was revoked by Organization Order No. 3, dated December 13, 1967, Part IVC of which prescribed the functions of the Finance Office within a newly established Department of General Administration. Functions of the Finance Office was stated in Part IVC of Organization Order No. 3 were transferred to the Director of the Department of Finance and Revenue by Commissioner’s Order No. 69-96, dated March 7, 1969. Functions pertaining to centralized accounting as set forth in Commissioner’s Order No. 69-96 were transferred to the Director of the Office of Budget and Financial Management by Organization Order No. 30, dated April 5, 1972. The Office of Budget and Financial Management was replaced by Organization Order No. 50, dated December 31, 1974, which Order established the Office of Budget and Management Systems. The Office of Budget and Management Systems was replaced by Mayor’s Order 79-5, dated January 2, 1979, which Order established the Office of Budget and Resource Development.</text>
        <text>Mayor authorized to issue rules: Section 1102 of <cite doc="D.C. Law 5-14">D.C. Law 5-14</cite> provided that the Mayor shall issue rules necessary to carry out the provisions of the act.</text>
        <text>Effect of repeal provisions: Section 14 of <cite doc="D.C. Law 15-35">D.C. Law 15-35</cite> provided: “Any repeal of a law or regulation by this act shall not invalidate any enforcement action, adjudication, or any other action made or taken pursuant to such law or regulation.”</text>
        <text>Applicability of <cite doc="D.C. Law 19-317">D.C. Law 19-317</cite>: Section 401 of <cite doc="D.C. Law 19-317">D.C. Law 19-317</cite> provided that the act shall apply only to offenses committed on or after June 11, 2013.</text>
        <text>Applicability of <cite doc="D.C. Law 20-61">D.C. Law 20-61</cite>: Section 11001 of <cite doc="D.C. Law 20-61">D.C. Law 20-61</cite> provided that, except as otherwise provided, the act shall apply as of October 1, 2013.</text>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Change in Government</heading>
        <annotation>This section originated at a time when local government powers were delegated to a Board of Commissioners of the District of Columbia (see Acts Relating to the Establishment of the District of Columbia and its Various Forms of Governmental Organization in Volume 1). Section 402 (295 to 299) of Reorganization Plan No. 3 of 1967 (see Reorganization Plans in Volume 1) transferred all of the functions of the Board of Commissioners under this section to the District of Columbia Council, subject to the right of the Commissioner as provided in § 406 of the Plan. The District of Columbia Self-Government and Governmental Reorganization Act, 87 Stat. 818, § 711 ( D.C. Code, § <cite path="§1-207.11">1-207.11</cite>), abolished the District of Columbia Council and the Office of Commissioner of the District of Columbia. These branches of government were replaced by the Council of the District of Columbia and the Office of Mayor of the District of Columbia, respectively. Accordingly, and also pursuant to § 714(a) of such Act ( D.C. Code, § <cite path="§1-207.14">1-207.14</cite>(a)), appropriate changes in terminology were made in this section.</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section from-code="true">
    <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" path="|50|22|I|A"/>
    <num codify:value="50-2201.03a">6a</num>
    <heading>Regulations for personal mobility devices.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>(a)</num>
      <text>The Mayor shall promulgate regulations governing the PMD, including:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Exempting the personal mobility device from the regulations governing motor vehicles;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Establishing a registration process, such as, for example, requiring that each PMD bear a serial number, valid registration tag, or valid registration plate;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Establishing a fine schedule for violations of the PMD regulations; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Providing an adjudication process for violations of PMD law and regulations.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(b)</num>
      <text>Regulations promulgated pursuant to this section shall be submitted to the Council for a 45-day period of review, excluding Saturdays, Sundays, holidays, and days of Council recess. If the proposed rules are not approved within the 45-day period of review, the rules shall be deemed disapproved.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>History</heading>
        <annotation>Mar. 3, 1925, ch. 443, § 6a</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 14-235">as added Mar. 25, 2003, D.C. Law 14-235, § 10(b), 49 DCR 9788</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 16-224">Mar. 6, 2007, D.C. Law 16-224, § 101(b), 53 DCR 10225</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Effect of Amendments</heading>
        <annotation><cite doc="D.C. Law 16-224">D.C. Law 16-224</cite> revived the provisions of <cite doc="D.C. Law 14-235">D.C. Law 14-235</cite> that expired on October 1, 2005.</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Temporary Addition of Section</heading>
        <annotation>For temporary (225 day) addition, see § 10(b) of Motor Vehicle Definition Electric Personal Assistive Mobility Device Exemption Temporary Amendment Act of 2006 (<cite doc="D.C. Law 16-85">D.C. Law 16-85</cite>, April 4, 2006, law notification  53 DCR 3344).</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Emergency Legislation</heading>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 day) addition, see § 10(b) of Motor Vehicle Definition Electric Personal Assistive Mobility Device Exemption Emergency Amendment Act of 2005 (D.C. Act 16-237, December 22, 2005,  53 DCR 249).</annotation>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 day) addition, see § 10(b) of Motor Vehicle Definition Electric Personal Assistive Mobility Device Exemption Congressional Review Emergency Amendment Act of 2006 (D.C. Act 16-323, March 23, 2006,  53 DCR 2567).</annotation>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 day) addition, see § 101(b) of Personal Mobility Device Emergency Amendment Act of 2006 (D.C. Act 16-528, December 4, 2006,  53 DCR 9826).</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Editor's Notes</heading>
        <annotation>Expiration of previous addition: Section 14 of <cite doc="D.C. Law 14-235">D.C. Law 14-235</cite> ( 49 DCR 9788), which previously added this section, expired on October 1, 2005.</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section from-code="true">
    <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" path="|50|22|I|A"/>
    <num codify:value="50-2201.04">9</num>
    <heading>Speeding and reckless driving.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>(a)</num>
      <text>No vehicle shall be operated at a greater rate of speed than permitted by the regulations adopted under the authority of this part.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(b)</num>
      <text>A person shall be guilty of reckless driving if the person drives a vehicle upon a highway carelessly and heedlessly in willful or wanton disregard for the rights or safety of others, or without due caution and circumspection and at a speed or in a manner so as to endanger or be likely to endanger a person or property.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(b-1)</num>
      <text>A person shall be guilty of aggravated reckless driving if the person violates subsection (b) of this section and the person does one or more of the following:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Operates the vehicle at a rate or speed at or greater than 30 miles per hour over the stated speed limit;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Causes bodily harm or permanent disability or disfigurement to another; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Causes property damage in excess of $1,000.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(c)</num>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A person violating subsection (b) of this section shall, upon conviction for the first offense, be fined no more than the amount set forth in § <cite path="§22-3571.01">22-3571.01</cite>, or incarcerated for no more than 90 days, or both.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A person violating subsection (b) of this section when the person has been convicted of a prior offense under subsection (b) of this section within a 2-year period and is being sentenced on the current offense shall be fined no more than the amount set forth in § <cite path="§22-3571.01">22-3571.01</cite>, or incarcerated for no more than 180 days.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>A person violating subsection (b) of this section when the person has 2 or more prior convictions for offenses under subsection (b) of this section within a 2-year period and is being sentenced on the current offense shall be fined no more than the amount set forth in § <cite path="§22-3571.01">22-3571.01</cite>, or incarcerated for no more than one year.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(c-1)</num>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A person violating subsection (b-1) of this section shall, upon conviction for the first offense, be fined no more than the amount set forth in § <cite path="§22-3571.01">22-3571.01</cite>, or incarcerated for no more than 180 days, or both.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A person violating subsection (b-1) of this section when the person has one or more prior convictions for offenses under subsection (b-1) within a 2-year period and is being sentenced on the current offense shall be fined no more than the amount set forth in § <cite path="§22-3571.01">22-3571.01</cite>, or incarcerated for no more than one year.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(d)</num>
      <text>Any individual violating any provision of this section, except where the offense constitutes aggravated reckless driving, shall be subject to a civil fine under the District of Columbia Traffic Adjudication Act (§ <cite path="§50-2301.01">50-2301.01</cite> et seq.).</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(e)</num>
      <text>A presumption shall exist that a reckless, careless, hazardous, or aggressive driving conviction that occurred in a foreign jurisdiction constitutes reckless driving as provided in subsection (b) of this section, unless the District can show evidence that the person met the requirements for aggravated reckless driving in subsection (b-1) of this section.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(f)</num>
      <text>The fines set forth in this section shall not be limited by § <cite path="§22-3571.01">22-3571.01</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>History</heading>
        <annotation>Mar. 3, 1925, 43 Stat. 1123, ch. 443, § 9</annotation>
        <annotation>July 3, 1926, 44 Stat. 814, ch. 739, § 5</annotation>
        <annotation>Feb. 27, 1931, 46 Stat. 1427, ch. 317, § 4</annotation>
        <annotation>June 24, 1936, 49 Stat. 1901, ch. 749</annotation>
        <annotation>Nov. 25, 1942, 56 Stat. 1023, ch. 642, § 1</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 2-104">Sept. 12, 1978, D.C. Law 2-104, § 601, 25 DCR 1275</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 4-145">Sept. 14, 1982, D.C. Law 4-145, § 7, 29 DCR 3138</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 15-289">Apr. 5, 2005, D.C. Law 15-289, § 2(c), 52 DCR 1446</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 19-266">Apr. 27, 2013, D.C. Law 19-266, § 102(c), 59 DCR 12957</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 19-316">June 8, 2013, D.C. Law 19-316, § 2, 60 DCR 1713</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 19-317">June 11, 2013, D.C. Law 19-317, § 113(e), 60 DCR 2064</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Cross References</heading>
        <annotation>Alcoholic beverage control, operation of trains, streetcars, and other vehicles by intoxicated persons, see § <cite path="§25-1009">25-1009</cite>.</annotation>
        <annotation>Compensation of victims of violent crime, “crime of violence,” “crime,” and “victim” defined, see § <cite path="§4-501">4-501</cite>.</annotation>
        <annotation>Criminal procedure, warrantless arrests, see § <cite path="§23-581">23-581</cite>.</annotation>
        <annotation>Traffic adjudication, violations prosecuted as criminal offenses, see § <cite path="§50-2302.02">50-2302.02</cite>.</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Section References</heading>
        <annotation>This section is referenced in § <cite path="§4-501">4-501</cite>, § <cite path="§23-581">23-581</cite>, § <cite path="§50-329.05">50-329.05</cite>, § <cite path="§50-2201.05b">50-2201.05b</cite>, § <cite path="§50-2201.27">50-2201.27</cite>, and § <cite path="§50-2302.02">50-2302.02</cite>.</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Prior Codifications</heading>
        <annotation>1981 Ed., § 40-712.</annotation>
        <annotation>1973 Ed., § 40-605.</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Effect of Amendments</heading>
        <annotation><cite doc="D.C. Law 15-289">D.C. Law 15-289</cite> rewrote subsec. (c) which had read:</annotation>
        <annotation>“(c) Any individual violating any provision of this section where the offense constitutes reckless driving shall upon conviction for the 1st offense be fined not more than $250 or imprisoned not more than 3 months, or both; and upon conviction for the 2nd or any subsequent offense committed within 2 years from the date of any such previous offense such individual shall be fined not more than $1,000 or imprisoned not more than 1 year, or both.”</annotation>
        <annotation>The 2013 amendment by <cite doc="D.C. Law 19-266">D.C. Law 19-266</cite> substituted “$2,500” for “$1,000” in (c).</annotation>
        <annotation>The 2013 amendment by <cite doc="D.C. Law 19-316">D.C. Law 19-316</cite> rewrote (b) and (c); added (b-1) and (c-1); substituted “aggravated reckless driving” for “reckless driving” in (d); and added (e).</annotation>
        <annotation>The 2013 amendment by <cite doc="D.C. Law 19-317">D.C. Law 19-317</cite> added the subsection designated herein as (f).</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Emergency Legislation</heading>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 day) amendment of section, see § 102(c) of Comprehensive Impaired Driving and Alcohol Testing Program Emergency Amendment Act of 2012 (D.C. Act 19-429, July 30, 2012,  59 DCR 9387).</annotation>
        <annotation>For temporary amendment of (c), see § 102(c) of the Comprehensive Impaired Driving and Alcohol Testing Program Congressional Review Emergency Amendment Act of 2012 (D.C. Act 19-508, October 26, 2012, 59 DCR 12774).</annotation>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 days) amendment of this section, see § 102(c) of the Comprehensive Impaired Driving and Alcohol Testing Program Congressional Review Emergency Act of 2013 (D.C. Act 20-3, January 29, 2013,  60 DCR 2762, 20 DCSTAT 410).</annotation>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 days) amendment of this section, see § 113(e) of the Criminal Fine Proportionality Emergency Act of 2013 (D.C. Act 20-45, April 1, 2013,  60 DCR 5400, 20 DCSTAT 1300).</annotation>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 days) amendment of this section, see § 102(c) of the Comprehensive Impaired Driving and Alcohol Testing Program Second Congressional Review Emergency Act of 2013 (D.C. Act 20-51, April 17, 2013,  60 DCR 6344, 20 DCSTAT 1360).</annotation>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 days) amendment of this section, see § 2 of the Reckless Driving Emergency Act of 2013 (D.C. Act 20-75, May 23, 2013,  60 DCR 7597, 20 DCSTAT 1428).</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Editor's Notes</heading>
        <text>Section 5 of  46 Stat. 1429, ch. 317, effective Feb. 27, 1931, provided that all convictions under the Act shall be reported by the clerk of the court to the commissioners [Mayor] or their [his] designated agent.</text>
        <text>Definitions applicable: For definitions applicable in this section, see § <cite path="§50-2201.02">50-2201.02</cite>.</text>
        <text>Section 8 of <cite doc="D.C. Law 19-316">D.C. Law 19-316</cite> provided that the act shall apply as of June 1, 2013.</text>
        <text>Applicability of <cite doc="D.C. Law 19-317">D.C. Law 19-317</cite>: Section 401 of <cite doc="D.C. Law 19-317">D.C. Law 19-317</cite> provided that the act shall apply only to offenses committed on or after June 11, 2013.</text>
      </annoGroup>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section from-code="true">
    <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" path="|50|22|I|A"/>
    <num codify:value="50-2201.04a">9a</num>
    <heading>Operation of personal mobility devices.</heading>
    <text>A personal mobility device shall not be operated:</text>
    <para>
      <num>(1)</num>
      <text>In the District if it has not been validly registered, unless it is validly registered in another jurisdiction, when required by applicable law of that jurisdiction, and bears readily visible evidence of being registered.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(2)</num>
      <text>By a person under 16 years of age;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(3)</num>
      <text>Above the maximum speed limit of 10 miles per hour;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(4)</num>
      <text>Upon a sidewalk within the Central Business District, as defined by section 9901 of Title 18 of the District of Columbia Municipal Regulations (18 DCMR 9901);</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(5)</num>
      <text>By a person carrying any package, bundle, or other article that hinders the person from keeping both hands on the handlebars; or</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(6)</num>
      <text>On any roadway or sidewalk while the person is wearing a headset, headphone, or earphone, unless the device is used to improve the hearing of a person with a hearing impairment or covers or is inserted in one ear only.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>History</heading>
        <annotation>Mar. 3, 1925, ch. 443, § 9a</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 14-235">as added Mar. 25, 2003, D.C. Law 14-235, § 10(c), 49 DCR 9788</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 16-224">Mar. 6, 2007, D.C. Law 16-224, § 101(d), 53 DCR 10225</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Effect of Amendments</heading>
        <annotation><cite doc="D.C. Law 16-224">D.C. Law 16-224</cite> revived the provisions of <cite doc="D.C. Law 14-235">D.C. Law 14-235</cite> that expired on October 1, 2005.</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Temporary Amendment of Section</heading>
        <annotation>Section 2 of <cite doc="D.C. Law 18-89">D.C. Law 18-89</cite>, in par. (4), substituted “9901), unless operated by a person with a disability;” for “9901);”.</annotation>
        <annotation>Section 4(b) of <cite doc="D.C. Law 18-89">D.C. Law 18-89</cite> provided that the act shall expire after 225 days of its having taken effect.</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Temporary Addition of Section</heading>
        <annotation>For temporary (225 day) addition, see § 2 of Motor Vehicle Definition Electric Personal Assistive Mobility Device Exemption Temporary Amendment Act of 2006 (<cite doc="D.C. Law 16-85">D.C. Law 16-85</cite>, April 4, 2006, law notification  53 DCR 3344).</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Emergency Legislation</heading>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 day) addition, see § 10(c) of Motor Vehicle Definition Electric Personal Assistive Mobility Device Exemption Emergency Amendment Act of 2005 (D.C. Act 16-237, December 22, 2005,  53 DCR 249).</annotation>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 day) addition, see § 10(c) of Motor Vehicle Definition Electric Personal Assistive Mobility Device Exemption Congressional Review Emergency Amendment Act of 2006 (D.C. Act 16-323, March 23, 2006,  53 DCR 2567).</annotation>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 day) addition, see § 101(d) of Personal Mobility Device Emergency Amendment Act of 2006 (D.C. Act 16-528, December 4, 2006,  53 DCR 9826).</annotation>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 day) amendment of section, see § 2 of Personal Mobility Device for Persons with Disabilities Emergency Amendment Act of 2009 (D.C. Act 18-195, October 8, 2009,  56 DCR 8126).</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Editor's Notes</heading>
        <annotation>Expiration of previous addition: Section 14 of <cite doc="D.C. Law 14-235">D.C. Law 14-235</cite> ( 49 DCR 9788), which previously added this section, expired on October 1, 2005.</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section from-code="true">
    <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" path="|50|22|I|A"/>
    <num codify:value="50-2201.04b">9b</num>
    <heading>Operation of all-terrain vehicles and dirt bikes.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>(a)</num>
      <text>No person shall operate at any time an all-terrain vehicle or dirt bike on public property including any public space in the District.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(b)</num>
      <text>All-terrain vehicles or dirt bikes shall not be registered with the Department of Motor Vehicles.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(c)</num>
      <text>Any individual violating any provision of this section shall upon conviction be fined not more than the amount set forth in § <cite path="§22-3571.01">22-3571.01</cite> or imprisoned not more than 30 days, or both. All such prosecutions shall be in the Superior Court of the District of Columbia upon information filed by the Attorney General of the District of Columbia or any of his assistants in the name of the District of Columbia.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>History</heading>
        <annotation>Mar. 3, 1925, ch. 443, § 9b</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 15-289">as added Apr. 5, 2005, D.C. Law 15-289, § 2(d), 52 DCR 1446</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 19-266">Apr. 27, 2013, D.C. Law 19-266, § 102(d), 59 DCR 12957</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 19-317">June 11, 2013, D.C. Law 19-317, § 271(b), 60 DCR 2064</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Effect of Amendments</heading>
        <annotation>The 2013 amendment by <cite doc="D.C. Law 19-266">D.C. Law 19-266</cite> substituted “$250” for “$1,000” in (c).</annotation>
        <annotation>The 2013 amendment by <cite doc="D.C. Law 19-317">D.C. Law 19-317</cite> substituted “not more than the amount set forth in § <cite path="§22-3571.01">22-3571.01</cite>” for “not more than $1000 [$250]” in (c).</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Emergency Legislation</heading>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 day) amendment of section, see § 102(d) of Comprehensive Impaired Driving and Alcohol Testing Program Emergency Amendment Act of 2012 (D.C. Act 19-429, July 30, 2012,  59 DCR 9387).</annotation>
        <annotation>For temporary amendment of (c), see § 102(d) of the Comprehensive Impaired Driving and Alcohol Testing Program Congressional Review Emergency Amendment Act of 2012 (D.C. Act 19-508, October 26, 2012, 59 DCR 12774).</annotation>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 days) amendment of this section, see § 102(d) of the Comprehensive Impaired Driving and Alcohol Testing Program Congressional Review Emergency Act of 2013 (D.C. Act 20-3, January 29, 2013,  60 DCR 2762, 20 DCSTAT 410).</annotation>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 days) amendment of this section, see § 271(b) of the Criminal Fine Proportionality Emergency Act of 2013 (D.C. Act 20-45, April 1, 2013,  60 DCR 5400, 20 DCSTAT 1300).</annotation>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 days) amendment of this section, see § 102(d) of the Comprehensive Impaired Driving and Alcohol Testing Program Second Congressional Review Emergency Act of 2013 (D.C. Act 20-51, April 17, 2013,  60 DCR 6344, 20 DCSTAT 1360).</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Editor's Notes</heading>
        <annotation>Applicability of <cite doc="D.C. Law 19-317">D.C. Law 19-317</cite>: Section 401 of <cite doc="D.C. Law 19-317">D.C. Law 19-317</cite> provided that the act shall apply only to offenses committed on or after June 11, 2013.</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section from-code="true">
    <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" path="|50|22|I|A"/>
    <num codify:value="50-2201.04c">9c</num>
    <heading>Motor vehicle moving infractions in work zones; signage required.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>(a)</num>
      <text>For any motor vehicle moving infraction, as defined in Chapter 26 of Title 18 of the District of Columbia Municipal Regulations, committed by the driver within a work zone, during any time when traffic is regulated or restricted through or around the zone, when work is actually being performed in the zone by workers acting in their official capacity, the civil fine shall be double the amount otherwise prescribed and, in a criminal infraction case, the fine shall be one category higher than the penalty prescribed by law.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(b)</num>
      <text>Signs or notices shall be affixed at the point of ingress of constriction or work zones alerting drivers of doubled fines and increased penalties for moving infractions within the zone.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>History</heading>
        <annotation>Mar. 3, 1925, 43 Stat. 1119, ch. 443, § 9c</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 17-67">as added Jan. 23, 2008, D.C. Law 17-67, § 2(b), 54 DCR 11646</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Emergency Legislation</heading>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 day) addition, see § 2(b) of Doubled Fines in Construction and Work Zones Emergency Amendment Act of 2007 (D.C. Act 17-149, October 18, 2007,  54 DCR 10894).</annotation>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 day) addition, see § 2(b) of Doubled Fines in Construction and Work Zones Congressional Review Emergency Amendment Act of 2008 (D.C. Act 17-252, January 23, 2008,  55 DCR 1264).</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section from-code="true">
    <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" path="|50|22|I|A"/>
    <num codify:value="50-2201.04d">9d</num>
    <heading>Bicyclists’ use of leading pedestrian intervals.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>(a)</num>
      <text>A bicyclist may cross at an intersection while following the pedestrian traffic control signal for the bicyclist’s direction of travel unless otherwise directed by traffic signs or traffic control devices.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(b)</num>
      <text>A bicyclist may cross an intersection where a leading pedestrian interval is used.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>History</heading>
        <annotation>Mar. 3, 1925, ch. 443, § 9d</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 20-49">as added Dec. 13, 2013, D.C. Law 20-49, § 2(b), 60 DCR 15148</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Effect of Amendments</heading>
        <annotation>The 2013 amendment by <cite doc="D.C. Law 20-49">D.C. Law 20-49</cite> added this section.</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section from-code="true">
    <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" path="|50|22|I|A"/>
    <reason>Repealed</reason>
    <num codify:value="50-2201.05">10</num>
    <heading>Fleeing from scene of accident; driving under the influence of liquor or drugs.</heading>
    <text>Repealed.</text>
    <annotations>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>History</heading>
        <annotation>Mar. 3, 1925, 43 Stat. 1124, ch. 443, § 10</annotation>
        <annotation>Feb. 27, 1931, 46 Stat. 1427, ch. 317, § 4</annotation>
        <annotation>Dec. 15, 1944, 58 Stat. 805, ch. 588</annotation>
        <annotation>Aug. 16, 1954, 68 Stat. 732, ch. 741, §§ 7, 8</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 4-29">Aug. 5, 1981, D.C. Law 4-29, § 604(b)(1), 28 DCR 3081</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 4-145">Sept. 14, 1982, D.C. Law 4-145, §§ 5, 7, 29 DCR 3138</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 4-174">Mar. 9, 1983, D.C. Law 4-174, §§ 10, 11, 29 DCR 5753</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 9-96">May 5, 1992, D.C. Law 9-96, § 4(c), 38 DCR 7274</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 10-68">Feb. 5, 1994, D.C. Law 10-68, § 32, 40 DCR 6311</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 10-122">May 24, 1994, D.C. Law 10-122, § 3, 41 DCR 1658</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 12-212">Apr. 13, 1999, D.C. Law 12-212, § 2(a), 46 DCR 5</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 13-238">Apr. 3, 2001, D.C. Law 13-238, § 2(a), 48 DCR 602</annotation>
        <annotation doc="Pub. L. 109-356">Oct. 16, 2006, 120 Stat. 2042, Pub. L. 109-356, § 307</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 16-195">Mar. 2, 2007, D.C. Law 16-195, § 8, 53 DCR 8675</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 16-306">Apr. 24, 2007, D.C. Law 16-306, § 228(a), 53 DCR 8610</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 17-353">Mar. 25, 2009, D.C. Law 17-353, § 141, 56 DCR 1117</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 18-88">Dec. 10, 2009, D.C. Law 18-88, § 228, 56 DCR 7413</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 19-21">Sept. 14, 2011, D.C. Law 19-21, § 9002, 58 DCR 6226</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 19-266">Apr. 27, 2013, D.C. Law 19-266, § 102(e), 59 DCR 12957</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Cross References</heading>
        <annotation>Alcoholic beverage control, operation of trains, streetcars, and other vehicles by intoxicated persons, see § <cite path="§25-1009">25-1009</cite>.</annotation>
        <annotation>Compensation of victims of violent crime, convicted persons, assessments imposed in addition to punishment, see § <cite path="§4-516">4-516</cite>.</annotation>
        <annotation>Compensation of victims of violent crime, “crime of violence,” “crime,” and “victim” defined, see § <cite path="§4-501">4-501</cite>.</annotation>
        <annotation>Criminal procedure, warrantless arrests, see § <cite path="§23-581">23-581</cite>.</annotation>
        <annotation>District of Columbia administration, drug and alcohol testing, implied consent of employees operating vehicles in the scope of employment, see § <cite path="§1-620.24">1-620.24</cite>.</annotation>
        <annotation>Traffic adjudication, violations prosecuted as criminal offenses, see § <cite path="§50-2302.02">50-2302.02</cite>.</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Section References</heading>
        <annotation>This section is referenced in § <cite path="§1-620.24">1-620.24</cite>, § <cite path="§4-501">4-501</cite>, § <cite path="§4-516">4-516</cite>, § <cite path="§7-2502.03">7-2502.03</cite>, § <cite path="§16-801">16-801</cite>, § <cite path="§23-581">23-581</cite>, § <cite path="§50-2201.27">50-2201.27</cite>, and § <cite path="§50-2302.02">50-2302.02</cite>.</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Prior Codifications</heading>
        <annotation>1981 Ed., § 40-716.</annotation>
        <annotation>1973 Ed., § 40-609.</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Effect of Amendments</heading>
        <annotation><cite doc="D.C. Law 13-238">D.C. Law 13-238</cite>, in subsec. (b), rewrote pars. (1) and (2), added the last sentence to par. (4), and added par. (6).</annotation>
        <annotation>Pub. L. 109-356 rewrote subsec. (b)(3).</annotation>
        <annotation><cite doc="D.C. Law 16-195">D.C. Law 16-195</cite> rewrote subsec. (b)(1): and, in subsec. (b)(2), substituted “person” for “individual”.</annotation>
        <annotation><cite doc="D.C. Law 16-306">D.C. Law 16-306</cite>, in subsec. (d), substituted “who is convicted or adjudicated a juvenile delinquent as a result of the commission in the District” for “who is convicted in the District”.</annotation>
        <annotation><cite doc="D.C. Law 17-353">D.C. Law 17-353</cite> validated a previously made technical correction in subsec. (b).</annotation>
        <annotation><cite doc="D.C. Law 18-88">D.C. Law 18-88</cite> rewrote subsecs. (b)(1)(B), (C), (D), and (b)(2).</annotation>
        <annotation><cite doc="D.C. Law 19-21">D.C. Law 19-21</cite>, in subsec. (b)(3), deleted “, shall be used by the District of Columbia exclusively for the enforcement and prosecution of the District traffic alcohol laws, and shall remain available until expended” following “District of Columbia”.</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Temporary Amendment of Section</heading>
        <annotation>For temporary (225 day) amendment of section, see § 3 of Underage Drinking Temporary Amendment Act of 1993 (<cite doc="D.C. Law 10-12">D.C. Law 10-12</cite>, September 11, 1993, law notification  40 DCR 6834).</annotation>
        <annotation>For temporary (225 day) amendment of section, see § 4 of Driving Under the Influence Repeat Offenders Temporary Amendment Act of 2000 (<cite doc="D.C. Law 13-198">D.C. Law 13-198</cite>, October 21, 2000, law notification  47 DCR 8988).</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Emergency Legislation</heading>
        <annotation>For temporary (90-day) amendment of section, see § 2 of the Driving Under the Influence Repeat Offenders Emergency Amendment Act of 2000 (D.C. Act 13-382, July 24, 2000,  47 DCR 6697).</annotation>
        <annotation>For temporary (90-day) repeal of expiration date of section, see § 4 of the Driving Under the Influence Repeat Offenders Emergency Amendment Act of 2000 (D.C. Act 13-382, July 24, 2000,  47 DCR 6697).</annotation>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 day) amendment of section, see §§ 2 and 4 of the Driving Under the Influence Repeat Offenders Congressional Review Emergency Amendment Act of 2000 (D.C. Act 13-437, October 20, 2000,  47 DCR 8737).</annotation>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 day) amendment of section, see § 228(a) of Omnibus Public Safety Emergency Amendment Act of 2006 (D.C. Act 16-445, July 19, 2006,  53 DCR 6443).</annotation>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 day) amendment of section, see § 4(e)(1) of Anti-Drunk Driving Clarification Emergency Amendment Act of 2006 (D.C. Act 16-469, July 31, 2006,  53 DCR 6764).</annotation>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 day) amendment of section, see § 228(a) of Omnibus Public Safety Congressional Review Emergency Amendment Act of 2006 (D.C. Act 16-490, October 18, 2006,  53 DCR 8686).</annotation>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 day) amendment of section, see § 8 of Anti-Drunk Driving Clarification Second Congressional Review Emergency Amendment Act of 2006 (D.C. Act 16-518, October 27, 2006,  53 DCR 9104).</annotation>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 day) amendment of section, see § 8(a) of Anti-Drunk Driving Clarification Congressional Review Emergency Amendment Act of 2007 (D.C. Act 17-6, January 16, 2007,  54 DCR 1452).</annotation>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 day) amendment of section, see § 228(a) of Omnibus Public Safety Congressional Review Emergency Amendment Act of 2007 (D.C. Act 17-10, January 16, 2007,  54 DCR 1479).</annotation>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 day) amendment of section, see § 228(a) of Omnibus Public Safety Second Congressional Review Emergency Amendment Act of 2007 (D.C. Act 17-25, April 19, 2007,  54 DCR 4036).</annotation>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 day) amendment of section, see § 228 of Omnibus Public Safety and Justice Emergency Amendment Act of 2009 (D.C. Act 18-181, August 6, 2009,  56 DCR 6903).</annotation>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 day) amendment of section, see § 228 of Omnibus Public Safety and Justice Congressional Review Emergency Amendment Act of 2009 (D.C. Act 18-227, October 21, 2009,  56 DCR 8668).</annotation>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 day) repeal of section, see § 102(e) of Comprehensive Impaired Driving and Alcohol Testing Program Emergency Amendment Act of 2012 (D.C. Act 19-429, July 30, 2012,  59 DCR 9387).</annotation>
        <annotation>For temporary repeal of section, see § 102(e) of the Comprehensive Impaired Driving and Alcohol Testing Program Congressional Review Emergency Amendment Act of 2012 (D.C. Act 19-508, October 26, 2012, 59 DCR 12774).</annotation>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 days) repeal of this section, see § 102(e) of the Comprehensive Impaired Driving and Alcohol Testing Program Congressional Review Emergency Act of 2013 (D.C. Act 20-3, January 29, 2013,  60 DCR 2762, 20 DCSTAT 410).</annotation>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 days) repeal of this section, see § 102(e) of the Comprehensive Impaired Driving and Alcohol Testing Program Second Congressional Review Emergency Act of 2013 (D.C. Act 20-51, April 17, 2013,  60 DCR 6344, 20 DCSTAT 1360).</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Short Title</heading>
        <annotation>Short title: Section 9001 of <cite doc="D.C. Law 19-21">D.C. Law 19-21</cite> provided that subtitle A of title IX of the act may be cited as “Fiscal Year 2012 Transfer of Special Purpose Funds Act of 2011”.</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Expiration of Law</heading>
        <text>Expiration of Law 12-212</text>
        <text>Section 8(b) of <cite doc="D.C. Law 12-212">D.C. Law 12-212</cite> providing that the act shall expire on September 30, 2000, was repealed by section 4 of <cite doc="D.C. Law 13-238">D.C. Law 13-238</cite>.</text>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>References in Text</heading>
        <annotation>“This act”, referred to at the end of subsection (b)(4), means the District of Columbia Traffic Act, 1925.</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Mayor's Orders</heading>
        <annotation>Implementation of authority under Law 4-145: See Mayor’s Order 83-234, September 30, 1983.</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Editor's Notes</heading>
        <text>Mayor authorized to issue rules: See Historical and Statutory Notes following § <cite path="§50-2205.02">50-2205.02</cite>.</text>
        <text>For present law, see subchapter III-A of this chapter generally, § <cite path="§50-2206.01">50-2206.01</cite> et seq.; and §§ <cite path="§50-2206.11">50-2206.11</cite>, <cite path="§50-2206.12">50-2206.12</cite>, <cite path="§50-2206.14">50-2206.14</cite>, and <cite path="§50-2206.16">50-2206.16</cite> specifically.</text>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Change in Government</heading>
        <annotation>This section originated at a time when local government powers were delegated to a Board of Commissioners of the District of Columbia (see Acts Relating to the Establishment of the District of Columbia and its Various Forms of Governmental Organization in Volume 1). Section 401 of Reorganization Plan No. 3 of 1967 (see Reorganization Plans in Volume 1) transferred all of the functions of the Board of Commissioners under this section to a single Commissioner. The District of Columbia Self-Government and Governmental Reorganization Act, 87 Stat. 818, § 711 ( D.C. Code, § <cite path="§1-207.11">1-207.11</cite>), abolished the District of Columbia Council and the Office of Commissioner of the District of Columbia. These branches of government were replaced by the Council of the District of Columbia and the Office of Mayor of the District of Columbia, respectively. Accordingly, and also pursuant to § 714(a) of such Act ( D.C. Code, § <cite path="§1-207.14">1-207.14</cite>(a)), appropriate changes in terminology were made in this section.</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section from-code="true">
    <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" path="|50|22|I|A"/>
    <num codify:value="50-2201.05a">10a</num>
    <heading>Establishment of Ignition Interlock Device Program.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>(a)</num>
      <text>Within 180 days of April 20, 2013, the Mayor shall establish an Ignition Interlock Device Program applicable to persons who have been convicted of an offense pursuant to § <cite path="§50-2206.11">50-2206.11</cite>, § <cite path="§50-2206.12">50-2206.12</cite>, or § <cite path="§50-2206.14">50-2206.14</cite>, note, or any succeeding emergency act establishing those sections in substantially similar language, or pursuant to § <cite path="§50-2206.11">50-2206.11</cite>, § <cite path="§50-2206.12">50-2206.12</cite> or § <cite path="§50-2206.14">50-2206.14</cite>, or whose operator’s permit has been revoked pursuant to § <cite path="§50-1403.01">50-1403.01</cite>(a) for driving while the person’s alcohol concentration is 0.08 grams or more either per 100 milliliters of blood or per 210 liters of breath or is 0.10 grams or more per 100 milliliters of urine, or while under the influence of intoxicating liquor or any drug or any combination thereof, or while the ability to operate a vehicle is impaired by the consumption of intoxicating liquor.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(b)</num>
      <text>For the purpose of this section, “Ignition Interlock Device” means ignition equipment designed to prevent a motor vehicle from being operated by a person whose blood alcohol level exceeds the calibrated setting on the device.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(c)</num>
      <text>The Mayor shall adopt rules to implement the provisions of this section.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>History</heading>
        <annotation>Mar. 3, 1925, 43 Stat. 1124, ch. 443, § 10a</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 13-238">as added Apr. 3, 2001, D.C. Law 13-238, § 2(b), 48 DCR 602</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 19-258">Apr. 20, 2013, D.C. Law 19-258, § 2, 60 DCR 1080</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Effect of Amendments</heading>
        <annotation>The 2013 amendment by <cite doc="D.C. Law 19-258">D.C. Law 19-258</cite> rewrote (a).</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Delegation of Authority</heading>
        <annotation>Delegation of Authority Over an Ignition Interlock Device Program Pursuant to the D.C. Traffic Act of 1925, see Mayor’s Order 2002-72, April 19, 2002 ( 49 DCR 3736).</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section from-code="true">
    <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" path="|50|22|I|A"/>
    <num codify:value="50-2201.05b">10b</num>
    <heading>Fleeing from a law enforcement officer in a motor vehicle.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>(a)</num>
      <text>For the purposes of this section, the term:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>“Law enforcement officer” means a sworn member of the Metropolitan Police Department or a sworn member of any other police force operating in the District of Columbia.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>“Signal” means a communication made by hand, voice, or the use of emergency lights, sirens, or other visual or aural devices.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(b)</num>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>An operator of a motor vehicle who knowingly fails or refuses to bring the motor vehicle to an immediate stop, or who flees or attempts to elude a law enforcement officer, following a law enforcement officer’s signal to bring the motor vehicle to a stop, shall be fined not more than not more than the amount set forth in § <cite path="§22-3571.01">22-3571.01</cite>, or imprisoned for not more than 180 days, or both.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>An operator of a motor vehicle who violates paragraph (1) of this subsection and while doing so drives the motor vehicle in a manner that would constitute reckless driving under § <cite path="§50-2201.04">50-2201.04</cite>(b), or causes property damage or bodily injury, shall be fined not more than not more than the amount set forth in § <cite path="§22-3571.01">22-3571.01</cite>, or imprisoned for not more than 5 years, or both.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(c)</num>
      <text>It is an affirmative defense under this section if the defendant can show, by a preponderance of the evidence, that the failure to stop immediately was based upon a reasonable belief that the defendant’s personal safety is at risk. In determining whether the defendant has met this burden, the court may consider the following factors:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The time and location of the event;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Whether the law enforcement officer was in a vehicle clearly identifiable by its markings, or if unmarked, was occupied by a law enforcement officer in uniform or displaying a badge or other sign of authority;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The defendant’s conduct while being followed by the law enforcement officer;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Whether the defendant stopped at the first available reasonably lighted or populated area; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Any other factor the court considers relevant.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(d)</num>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The Mayor or his designee, pursuant to § <cite path="§50-1403.01">50-1403.01</cite>, may suspend the operating permit of a person convicted under subsection (b)(1) of this section for a period of not more than 180 days and may suspend the operating permit of a person convicted under subsection (b)(2) of this section for a period of not more than 1 year.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A suspension of an operator’s permit under paragraph (1) of this subsection for a person who has been sentenced to a term of imprisonment for a violation of subsection (b)(1) or (2) of this section shall begin following the person’s release from incarceration.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(e)</num>
      <text>Prosecution for violations under this section shall be conducted in the name of the District of Columbia by the Attorney General for the District of Columbia, or his or her assistants, in the Superior Court of the District of Columbia.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>History</heading>
        <annotation>Mar. 3, 1925, ch. 443, § 10b</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 15-239">as added Mar. 16, 2005, D.C. Law 15-239, § 2(b), 51 DCR 9600</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 19-266">Apr. 27, 2013, D.C. Law 19-266, § 102(f), 59 DCR 12957</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 19-317">June 11, 2013, D.C. Law 19-317, § 271(c), 60 DCR 2064</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Effect of Amendments</heading>
        <annotation>The 2013 amendment by <cite doc="D.C. Law 19-266">D.C. Law 19-266</cite> substituted “$12,500” for “$5,000” in (b)(2).</annotation>
        <annotation>The 2013 amendment by <cite doc="D.C. Law 19-317">D.C. Law 19-317</cite> substituted “not more than the amount set forth in § <cite path="§22-3571.01">22-3571.01</cite>” for “not more than $1,000” in (b)(1), and for “not more than $5,000 [$12,500]” in (b)(2).</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Emergency Legislation</heading>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 day) addition, see § 2 of the Fleeing Law Enforcement Prohibition Emergency Amendment Act of 2004 (D.C. Act 15-495, July 19, 2004,  51 DCR 7841).</annotation>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 day) addition, see § 2 of Fleeing Law Enforcement Prohibition Congressional Review Emergency Amendment Act of 2004 (D.C. Act 15-546, October 12, 2004,  51 DCR 9842).</annotation>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 day) addition of section, see § 2 of Fleeing Law Enforcement Prohibition Second Congressional Review Emergency Amendment Act of 2004 (D.C. Act 15-726, January 13, 2005,  52 DCR 1950).</annotation>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 day) amendment of section, see § 102(f) of Comprehensive Impaired Driving and Alcohol Testing Program Emergency Amendment Act of 2012 (D.C. Act 19-429, July 30, 2012,  59 DCR 9387).</annotation>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 day) addition of sections, see § 102(g) of Comprehensive Impaired Driving and Alcohol Testing Program Emergency Amendment Act of 2012 (D.C. Act 19-429, July 30, 2012,  59 DCR 9387).</annotation>
        <annotation>For temporary amendment of (b)(2), see § 102(f) of the Comprehensive Impaired Driving and Alcohol Testing Program Congressional Review Emergency Amendment Act of 2012 (D.C. Act 19-508, October 26, 2012, 59 DCR 12774).</annotation>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 days) amendment of this section, see § 102(f) of the Comprehensive Impaired Driving and Alcohol Testing Program Congressional Review Emergency Act of 2013 (D.C. Act 20-3, January 29, 2013,  60 DCR 2762, 20 DCSTAT 410).</annotation>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 days) amendment of this section, see § 271(c) of the Criminal Fine Proportionality Emergency Act of 2013 (D.C. Act 20-45, April 1, 2013,  60 DCR 5400, 20 DCSTAT 1300).</annotation>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 days) amendment of this section, see § 102(f) of the Comprehensive Impaired Driving and Alcohol Testing Program Second Congressional Review Emergency Act of 2013 (D.C. Act 20-51, April 17, 2013,  60 DCR 6344, 20 DCSTAT 1360).</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Editor's Notes</heading>
        <annotation>Applicability of <cite doc="D.C. Law 19-317">D.C. Law 19-317</cite>: Section 401 of <cite doc="D.C. Law 19-317">D.C. Law 19-317</cite> provided that the act shall apply only to offenses committed on or after June 11, 2013.</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section from-code="true">
    <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" path="|50|22|I|A"/>
    <num codify:value="50-2201.05c">10c</num>
    <heading>Leaving after colliding.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>(a)</num>
      <text>Any person who operates or who is in physical control of a vehicle within the District who knows or has reason to believe that his or her vehicle has been in a collision shall immediately stop and:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Where another person is injured, call or cause another to call 911 or call or cause another to call for an ambulance or other emergency assistance if necessary, remain on the scene until law enforcement arrives, and provide identifying information to law enforcement and to the injured person;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Where real or personal property belonging to another is damaged or a domestic animal is injured, provide identifying information to the owner or operator of the property or the owner of the domestic animal or, where the owner or operator of the property or the owner of the domestic animal is not present, provide or cause another to provide identifying information and the location of the collision, to law enforcement or 911; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Where real or personal property or a wild or domestic animal, as a result of the collision, poses a risk to others, call or cause another to call 911 and provide identifying information, the location of the collision, and a description of the nature of the risk posed to others.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(b)</num>
      <text>It is an affirmative defense to a violation of subsection (a) of this section, which the defendant must show by a preponderance of the evidence, that the defendant’s failure to stop or his or her failure to remain on the scene was based on a reasonable belief that his or her personal safety, or the safety of another, was at risk and that he or she called 911, or otherwise notified law enforcement, as soon as it was safe to do so, provided identifying information, provided a description of the collision, including the location of the collision or event, and followed the instructions of the 911 operator or a law enforcement officer.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(c)</num>
      <text>It is not a defense to a violation of this section that the defendant:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Was intoxicated, impaired in any way, or distracted; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Was not at fault for the collision.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(d)</num>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <para>
          <num>(A)</num>
          <text>A person violating subsection (a)(1) of this section shall upon conviction for the first offense be fined not more than the amount set forth in § <cite path="§22-3571.01">22-3571.01</cite>, or incarcerated for not more than 180 days, or both.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(B)</num>
          <text>A person violating subsection (a)(1) of this section when the person has a prior offense under subsection (a)(1) of this section and is being sentenced on the current offense shall be fined not more than the amount set forth in § <cite path="§22-3571.01">22-3571.01</cite>, or imprisoned not more than one year, or both.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <para>
          <num>(A)</num>
          <text>A person violating subsection (a)(2) or (a)(3) of this section shall upon conviction for the first offense be fined not more than the amount set forth in § <cite path="§22-3571.01">22-3571.01</cite>, or incarcerated for not more than 30 days, or both.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(B)</num>
          <text>A person violating subsection (a)(2) or (3) of this section when the person has a prior offense under subsection (a)(2) or (a)(3) of this section and is being sentenced on the current offense shall be fined not more than the amount set forth in § <cite path="§22-3571.01">22-3571.01</cite>, or imprisoned not more than 90 days, or both.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>History</heading>
        <annotation>Mar. 3, 1925, 43 Stat. 1124, ch. 443, § 10c</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 19-266">as added Apr. 27, 2013, D.C. Law 19-266, § 102(g), 59 DCR 12957</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 19-317">June 11, 2013, D.C. Law 19-317, § 271(d), 59 DCR 12957</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Section References</heading>
        <annotation>This section is referenced in § <cite path="§50-2206.55">50-2206.55</cite>.</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Effect of Amendments</heading>
        <annotation>The 2013 amendment by <cite doc="D.C. Law 19-266">D.C. Law 19-266</cite> added this section.</annotation>
        <annotation>The 2013 amendment by <cite doc="D.C. Law 19-317">D.C. Law 19-317</cite> substituted “not more than the amount set forth in § <cite path="§22-3571.01">22-3571.01</cite>” for “not more than $1,000” in (d)(1)(A), for “not more than $2,500” in (d)(1)(B), for “not more than $250” in (d)(2)(A), and for “not more than $500” in (d)(2)(B).</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Emergency Legislation</heading>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 days) addition of section, see § 102(g) of the Comprehensive Impaired Driving and Alcohol Testing Program Congressional Review Emergency Amendment Act of 2012 (D.C. Act 19-508, October 26, 2012,  59 DCR 12774).</annotation>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 days) addition of this section, see § 102(g) of the Comprehensive Impaired Driving and Alcohol Testing Program Congressional Review Emergency Act of 2013 (D.C. Act 20-3, January 29, 2013,  60 DCR 2762, 20 DCSTAT 410).</annotation>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 days) amendment of this section, see § 271(d) of the Criminal Fine Proportionality Emergency Act of 2013 (D.C. Act 20-45, April 1, 2013,  60 DCR 5400, 20 DCSTAT 1300).</annotation>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 days) addition of this section, see § 102(g) of the Comprehensive Impaired Driving and Alcohol Testing Program Second Congressional Review Emergency Act of 2013 (D.C. Act 20-51, April 17, 2013,  60 DCR 6344, 20 DCSTAT 1360).</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Editor's Notes</heading>
        <annotation>Applicability of <cite doc="D.C. Law 19-317">D.C. Law 19-317</cite>: Section 401 of <cite doc="D.C. Law 19-317">D.C. Law 19-317</cite> provided that the act shall apply only to offenses committed on or after June 11, 2013.</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section from-code="true">
    <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" path="|50|22|I|A"/>
    <num codify:value="50-2201.05d">10d</num>
    <heading>Object falling or flying from vehicle.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>(a)</num>
      <text>Any person who operates or who is in physical control of a vehicle within the District who knows or has reason to believe that an object likely to cause damage has detached from, fallen, or flown from his or her vehicle shall immediately stop and:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Where another person is injured, call or cause another to call 911 or call or cause another to call for an ambulance or other emergency assistance if necessary, remain on the scene until law enforcement arrives, and provide identifying information to law enforcement and to the injured person;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Where real or personal property belonging to another is damaged or a domestic animal is injured, provide identifying information to the owner or operator of the property or the owner of the domestic animal or, where the owner or operator of the property or the owner of the domestic animal is not present, provide or cause another to provide identifying information and the location of the event, to law enforcement or 911; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Where real or personal property or a wild or domestic animal, as a result of the event, poses a risk to others, call or cause another to call 911 and provide identifying information, the location of the collision, and a description of the nature of the risk posed to others.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(b)</num>
      <text>It is an affirmative defense to a violation of subsection (a) of this section, which the defendant must show by a preponderance of the evidence, that the defendant’s failure to stop or his or her failure to remain on the scene was based on a reasonable belief that his or her personal safety, or the safety of another, was at risk and that he or she called 911, or otherwise notified law enforcement, as soon as it was safe to do so, provided identifying information, provided a description of the event, including the location of the event, and followed the instructions of the 911 operator or a law enforcement officer.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(c)</num>
      <text>It is not a defense to a violation of this section that the defendant:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Was intoxicated, impaired in any way, or distracted; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Was not at fault for the object falling from or flying from the vehicle.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(d)</num>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A person violating any provision of subsection (a) of this section shall upon conviction for the first offense be fined not more than the amount set forth in § <cite path="§22-3571.01">22-3571.01</cite>, or incarcerated for not more than 60 days, or both.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A person violating any provision of subsection (a) of this section when the person has a prior offense under subsection (a) of this section and is being sentenced on the current offense shall be fined not more than the amount set forth in § <cite path="§22-3571.01">22-3571.01</cite>, or imprisoned not more than 90 days, or both.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>History</heading>
        <annotation>Mar. 3, 1925, 43 Stat. 1124, ch. 443, § 10d</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 19-266">as added Apr. 27, 2013, D.C. Law 19-266, § 102(g), 59 DCR 12957</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Section References</heading>
        <annotation>This section is referenced in § <cite path="§50-2206.55">50-2206.55</cite>.</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Effect of Amendments</heading>
        <annotation>The 2013 amendment by <cite doc="D.C. Law 19-266">D.C. Law 19-266</cite> added this section.</annotation>
        <annotation>The 2013 amendment by <cite doc="D.C. Law 19-317">D.C. Law 19-317</cite> substituted “not more than the amount set forth in § <cite path="§22-3571.01">22-3571.01</cite>” for “not more than $500” in (d)(1) and (d)(2).</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Emergency Legislation</heading>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 days) addition of section, see § 102(g) of the Comprehensive Impaired Driving and Alcohol Testing Program Congressional Review Emergency Amendment Act of 2012 (D.C. Act 19-508, October 26, 2012,  59 DCR 12774).</annotation>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 days) addition of this section, see § 102(g) of the Comprehensive Impaired Driving and Alcohol Testing Program Congressional Review Emergency Act of 2013 (D.C. Act 20-3, January 29, 2013,  60 DCR 2762, 20 DCSTAT 410).</annotation>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 days) addition of this section, see § 102(g) of the Comprehensive Impaired Driving and Alcohol Testing Program Second Congressional Review Emergency Act of 2013 (D.C. Act 20-51, April 17, 2013,  60 DCR 6344, 20 DCSTAT 1360).</annotation>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 days) addition of this section, see § 102(g) of the Comprehensive Impaired Driving and Alcohol Testing Program Second Congressional Review Emergency Act of 2013 (D.C. Act 20-51, April 17, 2013,  60 DCR 6344, 20 DCSTAT 1360).</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Editor's Notes</heading>
        <annotation>Applicability of <cite doc="D.C. Law 19-317">D.C. Law 19-317</cite>: Section 401 of <cite doc="D.C. Law 19-317">D.C. Law 19-317</cite> provided that the act shall apply only to offenses committed on or after June 11, 2013.</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section from-code="true">
    <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" path="|50|22|I|A"/>
    <num codify:value="50-2201.06">12</num>
    <heading>Garage keeper to report cars damaged in accidents.</heading>
    <text>The individual in charge of any garage or repair shop to which is brought any motor vehicle which shows evidence of having been involved in an accident or struck by bullets shall report to a police station within 24 hours after such motor vehicle is received, giving the make of the motor vehicle, the engine number, the registry number, and the name and address of the owner or operator of such motor vehicle. Any such individual failing so to report shall, upon conviction thereof, be fined not less than $25 nor more than $100 for each offense.</text>
    <annotations>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>History</heading>
        <annotation>Mar. 3, 1925, 43 Stat. 1125, ch. 443, § 12</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 4-145">Sept. 14, 1982, D.C. Law 4-145, § 7, 29 DCR 3138</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Prior Codifications</heading>
        <annotation>1981 Ed., § 40-719.</annotation>
        <annotation>1973 Ed., § 40-611.</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Editor's Notes</heading>
        <annotation>Definitions applicable: For definitions applicable in this section, see § <cite path="§50-2201.02">50-2201.02</cite>.</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section>
    <num>16</num>
    <para from-code="true" codify:tag="section">
      <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" path="|50|22|I|A"/>
      <num codify:value="50-2201.07">(b)</num>
      <heading>Control over park system not affected by this part.</heading>
      <text>Nothing contained in this part shall be construed to interfere with the exclusive charge and control prior to March 3, 1925, committed to the Director of the National Park Service over the park system of the District, and he or she is hereby authorized and empowered to make and enforce all regulations for the control of vehicles and traffic, and limiting the speed thereof on roads, highways, and bridges within the public grounds in the District, under his or her control, subject to the penalties prescribed in this part.</text>
      <annotations>
        <annoGroup>
          <heading>History</heading>
          <annotation>Mar. 3, 1925, 43 Stat. 1126, ch. 443, § 16(b)</annotation>
          <annotation>July 3, 1926, 44 Stat. 835, ch. 760, § 3</annotation>
          <annotation doc="D.C. Law 19-266">Apr. 27, 2013, D.C. Law 19-266, § 102(h), 59 DCR 12957</annotation>
        </annoGroup>
        <annoGroup>
          <heading>Cross References</heading>
          <annotation>Parks and playgrounds, regulation of vehicles and traffic, see § <cite path="§10-105">10-105</cite>.</annotation>
        </annoGroup>
        <annoGroup>
          <heading>Prior Codifications</heading>
          <annotation>1981 Ed., § 40-721.</annotation>
          <annotation>1973 Ed., § 40-613.</annotation>
        </annoGroup>
        <annoGroup>
          <heading>Effect of Amendments</heading>
          <annotation>The 2013 amendment by <cite doc="D.C. Law 19-266">D.C. Law 19-266</cite> substituted “he and she” and “his or her” for “he” and “his,” respectively.</annotation>
        </annoGroup>
        <annoGroup>
          <heading>Emergency Legislation</heading>
          <annotation>For temporary (90 day) repeal of section, see § 102(h) of Comprehensive Impaired Driving and Alcohol Testing Program Emergency Amendment Act of 2012 (D.C. Act 19-429, July 30, 2012,  59 DCR 9387).</annotation>
          <annotation>For temporary amendment of section, see § 102(h) of the Comprehensive Impaired Driving and Alcohol Testing Program Congressional Review Emergency Amendment Act of 2012 (D.C. Act 19-508, October 26, 2012, 59 DCR 12774).</annotation>
          <annotation>For temporary (90 days) amendment of this section, see § 102(h) of the Comprehensive Impaired Driving and Alcohol Testing Program Congressional Review Emergency Act of 2013 (D.C. Act 20-3, January 29, 2013,  60 DCR 2762, 20 DCSTAT 410).</annotation>
          <annotation>For temporary (90 days) amendment of this section, see § 102(h) of the Comprehensive Impaired Driving and Alcohol Testing Program Second Congressional Review Emergency Act of 2013 (D.C. Act 20-51, April 17, 2013,  60 DCR 6344, 20 DCSTAT 1360).</annotation>
        </annoGroup>
        <annoGroup>
          <heading>Transfer of Functions</heading>
          <annotation>By Executive Order No. 6166, dated June 10, 1933, the Office of Public Buildings and Public Parks of the National Capital was changed to National Parks, Buildings, and Reservations. Act of March 2, 1934, 48 Stat. 389, ch. 38, § 1, abolished National Parks, Buildings, and Reservations and transferred its powers and duties to the National Park Service.</annotation>
        </annoGroup>
      </annotations>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section from-code="true">
    <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" path="|50|22|I|A"/>
    <num codify:value="50-2201.08">16</num>
    <heading>Repeal of certain prior laws; saving clause.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>(a)</num>
      <text>The provisions of the act entitled “An Act regulating the speed of automobiles in the District of Columbia, and for other purposes,” approved June 29, 1906 (34 Stat. 621, ch. 3615), and, in so far as they relate to the regulation of vehicles or vehicle traffic in the District, the provisions of the act entitled “An act to authorize the Commissioners of the District of Columbia to make police regulations for the government of said District,” approved January 26, 1887 (24 Stat. 369, ch. 49) and of the joint resolution entitled “Joint resolution to regulate licenses to proprietors of theaters in the city of Washington, District of Columbia, and for other purposes,” approved February 26, 1892 (27 Stat. 394, Res. 4, 7) and of the act entitled “An act making appropriations to provide for the expenses of the government of the District of Columbia for the fiscal year ending June 30th, 1918, and for other purposes,” approved March 3, 1917 (39 Stat. 1064, ch. 160), are repealed. The provisions of § 20 of the Act entitled “An Act to prevent the manufacture and sale of alcoholic liquors in the District of Columbia, and for other purposes,” approved March 3, 1917 (39 Stat. 1129, ch. 165), shall not apply to any person operating any motor vehicle in the District.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(b)</num>
      <text>Any violation of any provision of law or regulation issued thereunder which is repealed by this part and any liability arising under such provisions or regulations may, if the violation occurred or the liability arose prior to such repeal, be prosecuted to the same extent as if this part had not been enacted.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>History</heading>
        <annotation>Mar. 3, 1925, 43 Stat. 1125, ch. 443, § 16(a), (c)</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Prior Codifications</heading>
        <annotation>1981 Ed., § 40-722.</annotation>
        <annotation>1973 Ed., § 40-614.</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section from-code="true">
    <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" path="|50|22|I|A"/>
    <num codify:value="50-2201.09">18</num>
    <heading>Severability.</heading>
    <text>If any provision of this part is declared unconstitutional, or the applicability thereof to any person or circumstance is held invalid, the validity of the remainder of the part and the applicability of such provision to other persons and circumstances shall not be affected thereby.</text>
    <annotations>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>History</heading>
        <annotation>Mar. 3, 1925, 43 Stat. 1126, ch. 443, § 18</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Prior Codifications</heading>
        <annotation>1981 Ed., § 40-723.</annotation>
        <annotation>1973 Ed., § 40-615.</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section from-code="true">
    <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" path="|50|22|IV"/>
    <reason>Repealed</reason>
    <num codify:value="50-2207.01">11</num>
    <heading>Smoke screens prohibited.</heading>
    <text>Repealed.</text>
    <annotations>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>History</heading>
        <annotation>Mar. 3, 1925, 43 Stat. 1124, ch. 443, § 11</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 4-145">Sept. 14, 1982, D.C. Law 4-145, § 7, 29 DCR 3138</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 15-154">Apr. 29, 2004, D.C. Law 15-154, § 12, 50 DCR 10996</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Prior Codifications</heading>
        <annotation>1981 Ed., § 40-718.</annotation>
        <annotation>1973 Ed., § 40-610.</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Editor's Notes</heading>
        <annotation>Definitions applicable: For definitions applicable in this section, see § <cite path="§50-2201.02">50-2201.02</cite>.</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section from-code="true">
    <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" path="|50|22|IV"/>
    <num codify:value="50-2207.02">11a</num>
    <heading>Tinted windows prohibited.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>(a)</num>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Except as provided in subsection (b) of this section, no motor vehicle, other than a mini-van, may be operated or parked upon the public streets or spaces of the District of Columbia with:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(A)</num>
          <text>A front windshield or front side windows that allow less than 70% light transmittance; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(B)</num>
          <text>A rear windshield or rear side windows that allow less than 50% light transmittance.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Except as provided in subsection (b) of this section, no mini-van may be operated or parked upon the public streets or spaces of the District of Columbia with:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(A)</num>
          <text>A front windshield or front side windows that allow less than 55% light transmittance, or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(B)</num>
          <text>A rear windshield or rear side windows that allow less than 35% light transmittance.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(b)</num>
      <text>A motor vehicle may be operated or parked upon the public streets of the District of Columbia with a front windshield that allows less than 70% light transmittance above the AS-1 line, or within 5 inches from the top of the windshield.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(c)</num>
      <text>Any person who operates or parks a motor vehicle in violation of subsection (a) of this section shall be issued a $50 citation.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(d)</num>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Except as provided by subsection (f) of this section, any motor vehicle found to violate subsection (a) of this section shall be required to be inspected at an official District Inspection Station within 5 business days after the finding.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>If the motor vehicle is not brought into compliance with subsection (a) of this section by the end of the 5-day period, the owner of the vehicle shall be fined not more than $1,000.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(e)</num>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Except as provided by subsection (f) of this section, any motor vehicle found to violate subsection (a) of this section on a second or subsequent occasion shall be required to be inspected at an official District Inspection Station within 5 business days after the second or subsequent finding.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>If the motor vehicle is not brought into compliance with subsection (a) of this section by the end of the 5-day period, the owner of the vehicle may be fined not more than $5,000.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(f)</num>
      <text>Any police officer or other authorized government agent of the District may order the immediate removal of a motor vehicle from the public streets to an official District Inspection Station if the police officer or other authorized government agent determines that the health and safety of the public is at risk due to window tinting in violation of subsection (a) of this section.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(g)</num>
      <text>No person shall install window tinting on a motor vehicle which is not exempt pursuant to subsection (h) of this section, in the District of Columbia which would cause the motor vehicle to violate subsection (a) of this section if the vehicle were operated or parked on the public streets of the District of Columbia.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(h)</num>
      <text>This section shall not apply to:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Limousines, ambulances, buses, and hearses meeting the requirements of 18 DCMR § 413.10;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Church owned vehicles;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>All official government vehicles;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Vehicles with tinted windows installed by the manufacturer prior to purchase; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Vehicles exempted by the Director of the Department of Motor Vehicles because the owner of the vehicle has a medical condition requiring windows which allows less light than permitted pursuant to subsection (a) of this section.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(i)</num>
      <text>Nothing in this subchapter shall be construed to modify or affect any federal law concerning the window tinting of motor vehicles that is applicable to manufacturers, importers, dealers, or motor vehicle repair businesses for new or used motor vehicles and equipment.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(j)</num>
      <text>The Director of the Department of Motor Vehicles is authorized to promulgate rules to implement the provisions this section and to amend existing provisions of Title 18 of the District of Columbia Municipal Regulations to conform to its requirements. Rules promulgated or amended pursuant to this section shall be submitted to the Council for a 45-day period of review, excluding Saturdays, Sundays, holidays, and days of Council recess.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(k)</num>
      <text>Notice of an infraction issued pursuant to subsections (d)(2) or (e)(2) of this section shall be mailed by U.S. mail to the owner’s last known address in the Department of Motor Vehicles’ records.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(l)</num>
      <text>Violations of subsections (d)(2) and (e)(2) of this section shall be adjudicated as moving violations.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(m)</num>
      <text>Answers to notices sent pursuant to subsection (k) of this section shall be in accordance with § <cite path="§50-2302.05">50-2302.05</cite>(a), (b), (c), and (e)), and subsection (n) of this section.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(n)</num>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A person to whom a notice of infraction has been issued shall answer within 30 calendar days of the date the notice was mailed or within a greater period of time as prescribed by the Director by regulation.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>If a person fails to answer the notice within the 30-day period or within the period of time prescribed by the Director, the person’s registration certificate shall be suspended. The notice of the suspension shall be mailed by U.S. mail to the person’s address on the Department’s records. Suspension shall take effect 15 days after the date the notice of suspension was mailed.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The possession by the Department of a copy of the notice of suspension addressed to a person or a copy of the certificate or affidavit provided for in 18 DCMR § 307.7 shall establish a rebuttable presumption that the notice of suspension was received by the person by the date the suspension became effective.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>A suspension resulting from a failure to answer shall remain in effect until the person answers the notice, except that once the offense is deemed admitted the suspension may be lifted only by payment of the fine for the offense and any additional penalties imposed pursuant to § <cite path="§50-2301.05">50-2301.05</cite>, for failure to answer within the time required by paragraph (1) of this subsection.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(o)</num>
      <text>The Director shall reject any vehicles appearing for inspection pursuant to Chapter 11 of this title whose window tint violates subsections (a) or (b) of this section.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(p)</num>
      <text>No points shall be assessed for any violation of this section.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>History</heading>
        <annotation>Mar. 3, 1925, 43 Stat. 1119, ch. 443, § 11a</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 10-163">as added Aug. 26, 1994, D.C. Law 10-163, § 2, 41 DCR 4886</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 13-289">Apr. 27, 2001, D.C. Law 13-289, § 402, 48 DCR 2057</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 15-307">Apr. 8, 2005, D.C. Law 15-307, § 205(b), 52 DCR 1700</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Prior Codifications</heading>
        <annotation>1981 Ed., § 40-718.1.</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Effect of Amendments</heading>
        <annotation><cite doc="D.C. Law 13-289">D.C. Law 13-289</cite> rewrote subsecs. (a) and (h); and added subsec. (j).</annotation>
        <annotation><cite doc="D.C. Law 15-307">D.C. Law 15-307</cite> added subsecs. (k) to (p).</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Emergency Legislation</heading>
        <annotation>For temporary amendment of section, see § 1002 of the Fiscal Year 1999 Budget Support Emergency Act of 1998 (D.C. Act 12-401, July 13, 1998,  45 DCR 4794), § 1002 of the Fiscal Year 1999 Budget Support Congressional Review Emergency Act of 1998 (D.C. Act 12-564, January 12, 1999,  46 DCR 669), and § 1002 of the Fiscal Year 1999 Budget Support Congressional Review Emergency Act of 1999 (D.C. Act 13-41, March 31, 1999,  46 DCR 3446).</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
    </annotations>
  </section>
</document>
