<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<document xmlns:codify="http://code.dccouncil.us/schemas/codify" id="Pub. L. 69-2-ch58">
  <heading/>
  <meta>
    <effective>1926-03-16</effective>
    <cites>
      <law congress="69" session="2" chapter="58"/>
    </cites>
  </meta>
  <section from-code="true">
    <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" before="§4-107" path="|4|1"/>
    <num codify:value="4-105">5</num>
    <heading>Director of Public Welfare.</heading>
    <text>The Mayor of the District of Columbia, upon the nomination of the Board, is hereby authorized to appoint a Director of Public Welfare, which position is hereby authorized and created, who shall be the chief executive officer of the Board and shall be charged, subject to its general supervision, with the executive and administrative duties provided for in this act. The Director shall be a person of such training, experience, and capacity as will especially qualify him or her to discharge the duties of the office. The Director of Public Welfare may be discharged by the Mayor of the District of Columbia upon recommendation of the Board. The Mayor of the District of Columbia is authorized, upon the nomination of the Board, to appoint such personnel as may be necessary for the efficient performance of the duties of the Board.</text>
    <annotations>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>History</heading>
        <annotation>Mar. 16, 1926, 44 Stat. 209, ch. 58, § 5</annotation>
        <annotation>Dec. 20, 1941, 55 Stat. 849, ch. 605, § 1</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 2-139">Mar. 3, 1979, D.C. Law 2-139, § 3205(ss), 25 DCR 5740</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Cross References</heading>
        <annotation>Merit system, effective date provisions, see § <cite path="§1-636.02">1-636.02</cite>.</annotation>
        <annotation>Prostitution, duties of Director concerning persons found guilty, see § <cite path="§22-2703">22-2703</cite>.</annotation>
        <annotation>Regulations, protection of life, health, and property, Council and Mayor, authorization to make and enforce, see § <cite path="§1-303.03">1-303.03</cite>.</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Section References</heading>
        <annotation>This section is referenced in § <cite path="§1-636.02">1-636.02</cite>.</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Prior Codifications</heading>
        <annotation>1981 Ed., § 3-105.</annotation>
        <annotation>1973 Ed., § 3-105.</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>References in Text</heading>
        <text>“This act,” referred to at the end of the first sentence in this section, means the Act of March 16, 1926, 44 Stat. 209, ch. 58.</text>
        <text>Board of Public Welfare abolished: See note to § <cite path="§4-102">4-102</cite>.</text>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Change in Government</heading>
        <annotation>This section originated at a time when local government powers were delegated to a Board of Commissioners of the District of Columbia (see Acts Relating to the Establishment of the District of Columbia and its Various Forms of Governmental Organization in Volume 1). Section 401 of Reorganization Plan No. 3 of 1967 (see Reorganization Plans in Volume 1) transferred all of the functions of the Board of Commissioners under this section to a single Commissioner. The District of Columbia Self-Government and Governmental Reorganization Act, 87 Stat. 818, § 711 ( D.C. Code, § <cite path="§1-207.11">1-207.11</cite>), abolished the District of Columbia Council and the Office of Commissioner of the District of Columbia. These branches of government were replaced by the Council of the District of Columbia and the Office of Mayor of the District of Columbia, respectively. Accordingly, and also pursuant to § 714(a) of such Act ( D.C. Code, § <cite path="§1-207.14">1-207.14</cite>(a)), appropriate changes in terminology were made in this section.</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section from-code="true">
    <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" before="§4-107" path="|4|1"/>
    <num codify:value="4-106">6</num>
    <heading>Institutions placed under control of Board.</heading>
    <text>The Board shall have complete and exclusive control and management of the following institutions of the District of Columbia:</text>
    <para>
      <num>(1)</num>
      <text>The workhouse at Occoquan in the State of Virginia;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(2)</num>
      <text>The reformatory at Lorton in the State of Virginia;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(3)</num>
      <text>The Washington Asylum and Jail;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(4)</num>
      <text>The National Training School for Girls, in the District of Columbia and at Muirkirk in the State of Maryland;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(5)</num>
      <text>The Gallinger Municipal Hospital;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(6)</num>
      <text>The Tuberculosis Hospital;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(7)</num>
      <text>The Home for the Aged and Infirm;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(8)</num>
      <text>The Municipal Lodging House;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(9)</num>
      <text>The Industrial Home School;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(10)</num>
      <text>Industrial Home School for Colored Children; and</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(11)</num>
      <text>Forest Haven in Anne Arundel County, in the State of Maryland.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>History</heading>
        <annotation>Mar. 16, 1926, 44 Stat. 209, ch. 58, § 6</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Cross References</heading>
        <annotation>Forest Haven, control and supervision, see § <cite path="§44-1402">44-1402</cite> et seq.</annotation>
        <annotation>Industrial Home School, control and management, see § <cite path="§44-1301">44-1301</cite>.</annotation>
        <annotation>Management and regulation of workhouse, reformatory, asylum and jail, see § <cite path="§24-211.02">24-211.02</cite>.</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Section References</heading>
        <annotation>This section is referenced in § <cite path="§4-107">4-107</cite>.</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Prior Codifications</heading>
        <annotation>1981 Ed., § 3-106.</annotation>
        <annotation>1973 Ed., § 3-106.</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>References in Text</heading>
        <text>Board of Public Welfare abolished: See note to § <cite path="§4-102">4-102</cite>.</text>
        <text>The District Training School was redesignated as Forest Haven by § 1(1) of the Act of October 22, 1970, 84 Stat. 1087, Pub. L. 91-490.</text>
        <text>Statutory provisions for both the National Training School for Girls and the Industrial Home School for Colored Children were formerly codified in  D.C. Code, § 32-901 to 32-913 [1981 Ed.]. These provisions were omitted from codification as obsolete in the 1973 Edition of the D.C. Code in light of the Act of August 3, 1951, 62 Stat. 154, ch. 291, § 1, which provided that no new commitments to the National Training School for Girls should be made after August 3, 1951.</text>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Transfer of Functions</heading>
        <text>Management and regulation of the workhouse at Occoquan in the State of Virginia, the reformatory at Lorton in the State of Virginia, and the Washington Asylum and Jail was vested in the Department of Corrections by the Act of June 27, 1946, 60 Stat. 320, ch. 507, § 2. The Department of Corrections was abolished and another Department of Corrections established under direction and control of a Commissioner and headed by a Director to take care of persons committed to the workhouse, Lorton Reformatory, Women’s Reformatory and the D.C. Jail.</text>
        <text>The direction and control of the Gallinger Municipal Hospital and the Tuberculosis Hospital had been transferred to the Health Department of the District of Columbia by the Act of June 29, 1937, 50 Stat. 376, ch. 403, § 1. Reorganization Order No. 57, as amended, redesignated as Organization Order No. 141 and amended, established, under the direction and control of a Commissioner, a Department of Public Health headed by a Director, for the purpose of planning, implementing, and directing public health and hospital care programs, and for performing certain other allied medical functions. Prior to its redesignation the Order abolished the previously existing Gallinger Municipal Hospital and transferred all of its positions and functions to the new Department. It further provided that within the Department the District of Columbia General Hospital performs all functions previously performed by Gallinger Municipal Hospital. Functions of the Department of Public Welfare and of the Department of Public Health as set forth in Organization Order Nos. 140 and 141, respectively, were transferred to the Director of the Department of Human Resources by Commissioner’s Order No. 69-96, dated March 7, 1969, as amended by Commissioner’s Order No. 70-83, dated March 6, 1970. The Department of Human Resources was replaced by the Department of Human Services by Reorganization Plan No. 2 of 1979, dated February 21, 1980.</text>
      </annoGroup>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section from-code="true">
    <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" before="§4-111" path="|4|1"/>
    <num codify:value="4-110">10</num>
    <heading>Powers of Board of Charities transferred.</heading>
    <text>The following powers and duties prior to March 16, 1926, imposed by law upon the Board of Charities shall be vested in the Board, and the unexpended balance of all appropriations made for the purpose of discharging such powers and duties shall become available to the Board:</text>
    <para>
      <num>(1)</num>
      <text>To provide for the transportation to their respective places of residence of nonresident indigent persons, and to provide for indigent persons, who are legal residents of the District of Columbia, medical care and treatment when necessary, under contracts with such hospitals as are or may be designated by law;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(2)</num>
      <text>To provide for the transportation to their respective places of residence of nonresident persons with mental illness and to afford hospital care for indigent persons with mental illness who are legal residents of the District of Columbia in such hospital or hospitals as are or may be designated by law; and</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(3)</num>
      <text>To provide for all other aged, infirm, or needy persons, in the manner authorized by law or by appropriations enacted by the Congress.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>History</heading>
        <annotation>Mar. 16, 1926, 44 Stat. 210, ch. 58, § 10</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 1-87">Oct. 1, 1976, D.C. Law 1-87, § 5, 23 DCR 2544</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 16-305">Apr. 24, 2007, D.C. Law 16-305, § 15, 53 DCR 6198</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Cross References</heading>
        <annotation>Mentally ill, financial responsibility for care of hospitalized persons, see § <cite path="§21-586">21-586</cite>.</annotation>
        <annotation>Mentally ill, nonresidents, see § <cite path="§21-551">21-551</cite>.</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Prior Codifications</heading>
        <annotation>1981 Ed., § 3-110.</annotation>
        <annotation>1973 Ed., § 3-110.</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Effect of Amendments</heading>
        <annotation><cite doc="D.C. Law 16-305">D.C. Law 16-305</cite> substituted “persons with mental illness” for “insane persons”, throughout the section.</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>References in Text</heading>
        <annotation>Board of Public Welfare abolished: See note to § <cite path="§4-102">4-102</cite>.</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section from-code="true">
    <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" before="§4-116" path="|4|1"/>
    <num codify:value="4-114">11</num>
    <heading>Powers of Mayor over dependent children.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>(a)</num>
      <text>The Mayor of the District of Columbia (hereinafter referred to as the “Mayor”) may:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Make temporary provision for the care of children pending investigation of their status;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Have the care and legal guardianship, including the power to consent to or arrange for adoption in appropriate cases, of:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(A)</num>
          <text>Children who may be committed to the Mayor as wards of the District of Columbia by courts of competent jurisdiction; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(B)</num>
          <text>Children who are relinquished by their parents to the Mayor or whose relinquishment is transferred to the Mayor by a licensed child-placing agency under § <cite path="§4-1406">4-1406</cite>;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Make such provisions for the care and maintenance of such children in private homes, under contract, including adoption subsidy pursuant to § <cite path="§4-301">4-301</cite>, or in public or private institutions, as the welfare of such children may require; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Provide care and maintenance for children with substantial intellectual disabilities who may be received upon application or upon court commitment, in institutions or homes or other facilities equipped to receive them, within or without the District of Columbia.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(b)</num>
      <text>The Mayor shall cause the wards of the District of Columbia placed out under temporary care to be visited as often as may be required to safeguard their welfare.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(c)</num>
      <text>The Mayor may, where appropriate, secure an assignment of rights from a parent whose child is in the custody of a person or agency receiving foster care maintenance payments under Part E in Subchapter IV of the Social Security Act (42 U.S.C. § 670 et seq.).</text>
    </para>
    <annotations>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>History</heading>
        <annotation>Mar. 16, 1926, 44 Stat. 210, ch. 58, § 11</annotation>
        <annotation doc="Pub. L. 93-241">Jan. 2, 1974, 87 Stat. 1057, Pub. L. 93-241, § 1(a)(1)</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 6-166">Feb. 24, 1987, D.C. Law 6-166, § 33(e), 33 DCR 6710</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 19-169">Sept. 26, 2012, D.C. Law 19-169, § 8, 59 DCR 5567</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Cross References</heading>
        <annotation>Children, age of majority, see § <cite path="§46-101">46-101</cite>.</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Section References</heading>
        <annotation>This section is referenced in § <cite path="§4-115">4-115</cite>.</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Prior Codifications</heading>
        <annotation>1981 Ed., § 3-114.</annotation>
        <annotation>1973 Ed., § 3-114.</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Effect of Amendments</heading>
        <annotation>The 2012 amendment by <cite doc="D.C. Law 19-169">D.C. Law 19-169</cite> substituted “children with substantial intellectual disabilities” for “substantially retarded children” in (a)(4).</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Delegation of Authority</heading>
        <annotation>Delegation of authority pursuant to Law 6-166, see Mayor’s Order 87-273, December 10, 1987.</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Editor's Notes</heading>
        <annotation>Section 35 of <cite doc="D.C. Law 19-169">D.C. Law 19-169</cite> provided that no provision of the act shall impair any right or obligation existing under law.</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Change in Government</heading>
        <annotation>This section originated at a time when local government powers were delegated to a Board of Commissioners of the District of Columbia (see Acts Relating to the Establishment of the District of Columbia and its Various Forms of Governmental Organization in Volume 1). Section 401 of Reorganization Plan No. 3 of 1967 (see Reorganization Plans in Volume 1) transferred all of the functions of the Board of Commissioners under this section to a single Commissioner. The District of Columbia Self-Government and Government Reorganization Act, 87 Stat. 818, § 711 ( D.C. Code, § <cite path="§1-207.11">1-207.11</cite>), abolished the District of Columbia Council and the Office of Commissioner of the District of Columbia. These branches of government were replaced by the Council of the District of Columbia and the Office of Mayor of the District of Columbia, respectively. Accordingly, and also pursuant to § 714(a) of such Act ( D.C. Code, § <cite path="§1-207.14">1-207.14</cite>(a)), appropriate changes in terminology were made in this section.</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section from-code="true">
    <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" before="§4-122" path="|4|1"/>
    <num codify:value="4-120">12</num>
    <heading>Duties of Trustees of National Training School for Girls transferred.</heading>
    <text>The duties prior to March 16, 1926, imposed by law upon the Board of Trustees of the National Training School for Girls concerning the admission, care, parole, and discharge of inmates shall be vested in the Board.</text>
    <annotations>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>History</heading>
        <annotation>Mar. 16, 1926, 44 Stat. 210, ch. 58, § 12</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Prior Codifications</heading>
        <annotation>1981 Ed., § 3-121.</annotation>
        <annotation>1973 Ed., § 3-122.</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>References in Text</heading>
        <text>Board of Public Welfare abolished: See note to § <cite path="§4-102">4-102</cite>.</text>
        <text>Statutory provisions for the National Training School for Girls were formerly codified in  D.C. Code, §§ <cite path="§32-901">32-901</cite> to 32-913. These provisions were omitted from codification as obsolete in the 1973 Edition of the D.C. Code in light of the Act of August 3, 1951, 62 Stat. 154, ch. 291, § 1, which provided that no new commitments to the School should be made after August 3, 1951.</text>
      </annoGroup>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section from-code="true">
    <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" before="§4-122" path="|4|1"/>
    <num codify:value="4-121">13</num>
    <heading>Annual budget; report of activities; recommendations; study of social and environmental conditions.</heading>
    <text>It shall be the duty of the Board to prepare and submit to the Mayor of the District of Columbia, in such manner as he shall require, an annual budget itemizing the appropriations necessary to the proper discharge of the duties imposed by law upon the Board and for the support and maintenance of the institutions under its management. The Board shall also submit to the Mayor an annual report of its activities and the work carried on under its direction, together with its recommendations for securing more efficient and humane care for all persons in need of public assistance. The Board shall study from time to time the social and environmental conditions of the District of Columbia and shall incorporate in its reports the results thereof and recommendations designed to further safeguard the interests and well-being of the children of the District of Columbia and to diminish and ameliorate poverty and disease and to lessen crime. Except in the placement of children in institutions under the public control, the Board shall when practicable place them in institutions or homes of the same religious faith as the parents; provided, that whenever the Board shall for any reason place the child with any organization, institution, or individual other than of the same religious faith as that of the parents of the child, the Board shall set forth the reason for such action in the record of the case. Inmates of public institutions shall be given the fullest opportunity for the practice of their religion.</text>
    <annotations>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>History</heading>
        <annotation>Mar. 16, 1926, 44 Stat. 210, ch. 58, § 13</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Cross References</heading>
        <annotation>Age of majority, see § <cite path="§46-101">46-101</cite>.</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Prior Codifications</heading>
        <annotation>1981 Ed., § 3-122.</annotation>
        <annotation>1973 Ed., § 3-123.</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>References in Text</heading>
        <annotation>Board of Public Welfare abolished: See note to § <cite path="§4-102">4-102</cite>.</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Change in Government</heading>
        <annotation>This section originated at a time when local government powers were delegated to a Board of Commissioners of the District of Columbia (see Acts Relating to the Establishment of the District of Columbia and its Various Forms of Governmental Organization in Volume 1). Section 401 of Reorganization Plan No. 3 of 1967 (see Reorganization Plans in Volume 1) transferred all of the functions of the Board of Commissioners under this section to a single Commissioner. The District of Columbia Self-Government and Governmental Reorganization Act, 87 Stat. 818, § 711 ( D.C. Code, § <cite path="§1-207.11">1-207.11</cite>), abolished the District of Columbia Council and the Office of Commissioner of the District of Columbia. These branches of government were replaced by the Council of the District of Columbia and the Office of Mayor of the District of Columbia, respectively. Accordingly, and also pursuant to § 714(a) of such Act ( D.C. Code, § <cite path="§1-207.14">1-207.14</cite>(a)), appropriate changes in terminology were made in this section.</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
    </annotations>
  </section>
</document>
