<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<document xmlns:codify="http://code.dccouncil.us/schemas/codify" id="D.C. Law 11-128">
  <num type="law">11-128</num>
  <heading type="short">Insurance State of Entry Act of 1996</heading>
  <meta>
    <effective>1996-05-24</effective>
    <cites>
      <law lawId="128" period="11" url="./docs/11-128.pdf"/>
      <register page="1562" vol="43"/>
    </cites>
    <history url="http://lims.dccouncil.us/Legislation/B11-0391">
      <narrative>Law 11-128, the “Insurance State of Entry Act of 1996,” was introduced in Council and assigned Bill No. 11-391, which was referred to the Committee on Consumer and Regulatory Affairs. The Bill was adopted on first and second readings on February 6, 1996, and March 5, 1996, respectively. Signed by the Mayor on March 15, 1996, it was assigned Act No. 11-235 and transmitted to both Houses of Congress for its review. D.C. Law 11-128 became effective on May 24, 1996.</narrative>
    </history>
  </meta>
  <section from-code="true">
    <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" path="|31|22"/>
    <num codify:value="31-2201">2</num>
    <heading>Definitions.</heading>
    <text>For the purposes of this chapter, the term:</text>
    <para>
      <num>(1)</num>
      <text>“Commissioner” means the Commissioner of the Department of Insurance, Securities, and Banking.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(1A)</num>
      <text>“District” means the District of Columbia.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(2)</num>
      <text>“Non-U.S. insurer” means an insurer organized under the laws of a foreign country.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(3)</num>
      <text>Repealed.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(4)</num>
      <text>“United States Branch” or “U.S. Branch” means the business unit through which business is transacted within the United States by a non-U.S. insurer and the assets and liabilities of the insurer within the United States pertaining to such business.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>History</heading>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 11-128">May 24, 1996, D.C. Law 11-128, § 2, 43 DCR 1562</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 12-81">Mar. 24, 1998, D.C. Law 12-81, § 45(a), 45 DCR 745</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 15-166">June 11, 2004, D.C. Law 15-166, § 4(m), 51 DCR 2817</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Prior Codifications</heading>
        <annotation>1981 Ed., § 35-4401.</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Effect of Amendments</heading>
        <annotation><cite doc="D.C. Law 15-166">D.C. Law 15-166</cite>, in par. (1), substituted “Commissioner of the Department of Insurance, Securities, and Banking” for “Commissioner of Insurance and Securities”.</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Emergency Legislation</heading>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 day) amendment of section, see § 4(m) of Consolidation of Financial Services Emergency Amendment Act of 2004 (D.C. Act 15-381, February 27, 2004,  51 DCR 2653).</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section from-code="true">
    <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" path="|31|22"/>
    <num codify:value="31-2202">3</num>
    <heading>Authorization of entry.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>(a)</num>
      <text>A non-U.S. insurer may use the District as a state of entry to transact insurance in the United States through a U.S. branch by:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Qualifying as an insurer licensed to do business in the District; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Establishing a trust account, pursuant to a trust agreement approved by the Commissioner, with a U.S. bank approved by the Commissioner in an amount at least equal to the minimum capital and surplus required to be maintained by a domestic insurer licensed to do the same kind of insurance.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(b)</num>
      <text>Before authorizing the entry through the District of a U.S. branch of any non-U.S. insurer, the Commissioner shall require the non-U.S. insurer, in addition to the requirements of § <cite path="§31-2204">31-2204</cite> and any other requirement of the insurance law, to submit:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A copy of its charter and by-laws, if any, currently in force, and such other documents necessary to show the kinds of business which it is empowered to do in its domiciliary jurisdiction, attested to as accurate and complete by the insurance supervisory official in its home jurisdiction, and a full statement, subscribed and affirmed as true under the penalties of perjury by 2 officers or equivalent responsible representatives in such manner as the Commissioner shall prescribe, of its financial conditions as of the close of its latest fiscal year, showing its assets, liabilities, income disbursements, business transacted, and other facts required to be shown in its annual statement, as reported to the insurance supervisory official in its home jurisdiction, and an English language translation, as necessary, of any of the documents required herein; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>To an examination of the insurer’s affairs at its principal office within the United States. However, the Commissioner may instead accept a report of the insurance supervisory official of the insurer’s home jurisdiction.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>History</heading>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 11-128">May 24, 1996, D.C. Law 11-128, § 3, 43 DCR 1562</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 12-81">Mar. 24, 1998, D.C. Law 12-81, § 45(b), 45 DCR 745</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Section References</heading>
        <annotation>This section is referenced in § <cite path="§31-1371.01">31-1371.01</cite>.</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Prior Codifications</heading>
        <annotation>1981 Ed., § 35-4402.</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section from-code="true">
    <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" path="|31|22"/>
    <num codify:value="31-2203">4</num>
    <heading>Maintenance of trust account.</heading>
    <text>The assets in the trust account shall be known as trusteed assets and shall at all times be in an amount equal to the U.S. branch’s reserves and other liabilities plus the minimum capital and surplus required to be maintained by a domestic insurer licensed to do the same kind of insurance.</text>
    <annotations>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>History</heading>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 11-128">May 24, 1996, D.C. Law 11-128, § 4, 43 DCR 1562</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Section References</heading>
        <annotation>This section is referenced in § <cite path="§31-2204">31-2204</cite> and § <cite path="§31-2306">31-2306</cite>.</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Prior Codifications</heading>
        <annotation>1981 Ed., § 35-4403.</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section from-code="true">
    <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" path="|31|22"/>
    <num codify:value="31-2204">5</num>
    <heading>Requirements for trust agreement.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>(a)</num>
      <text>The deed of trust and all amendments thereto shall be authenticated in such form and manner as the Commissioner may prescribe and shall not be effective unless approved by the Commissioner upon a finding that:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A deed of trust or its amendments are sufficient in form and in conformity with law;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The trustee or trustees are eligible as such; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The deed of trust is adequate to protect the interest of the beneficiaries of the trust.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(b)</num>
      <text>If at any time the Commissioner finds, after reasonable notice and hearing, that the requisites for the approval no longer exist, the Commissioner may withdraw approval.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(c)</num>
      <text>The Commissioner may from time to time approve modifications of, or variations in any deed of trust, which in the Commissioner’s judgment are not prejudicial to the interest of the people of the District or the United States policyholders and creditors of the U.S. Branch.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(d)</num>
      <text>The deed of trust shall contain provisions which:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Vest legal title to trusteed assets in the trustees and their successors lawfully appointed;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Require that all assets deposited in the trust shall be continuously kept within the United States;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Provide for substitution of a new trustee or trustees in case of a vacancy by death, resignation, or otherwise, subject to the approval of the Commissioner;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Require that the trustee or trustees shall continuously maintain a record at all times sufficient to identify the assets of such fund;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Require that the trusteed assets shall consist of cash or investments eligible for investment of the funds of domestic insurers and accrued interest thereon if collectable by the trustee;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Require that the trust shall be for the exclusive benefit, security, and protection of the policyholders, or policyholders and creditors, of the U.S. Branch in the United States and that it shall be maintained as long as there is outstanding any liability of the non-U.S. insurer arising out of its insurance transactions in the United States; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>Provide, in substance, that no withdrawals of assets, other than income as specified in subsection (e) of this section shall be made or permitted by the trustee or trustees without the approval of the Commissioner except to:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(A)</num>
          <text>Make deposits required by law in any state for the security or benefit of all policyholders, or policyholders and creditors, of the U.S. Branch in the United States;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(B)</num>
          <text>Substitute other assets permitted by law and at least equal in value and quality to those withdrawn upon the specific written direction of the United States manager when duly empowered and acting pursuant to either general or specific written authority previously given or delegated by the board of directors; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(C)</num>
          <text>Transfer such assets to an official liquidator or rehabilitator pursuant to an order of a court of competent jurisdiction.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(e)</num>
      <text>The deed of trust may provide that income, earnings, dividends, or interest accumulations of the assets of the fund may be paid over to the United States manager of the U.S. branch upon request, provided that the total trusteed assets shall not thereby be less than the amount required to be maintained pursuant to § <cite path="§31-2203">31-2203</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(f)</num>
      <text>Upon withdrawal of trusteed assets deposited in another state in which the insurer is authorized to do business, it shall be sufficient if the deed of trust requires similar written approval of the insurance supervising official of that state in lieu of approval of the Commissioner provided that the total trusteed assets shall not thereby be less than the amount required to be maintained pursuant to § <cite path="§31-2203">31-2203</cite>. In all such cases, the U.S. Branch shall notify the Commissioner in writing of the nature and extent of the withdrawal.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(g)</num>
      <text>The Commissioner may from time to time:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Make examinations of the trusteed assets of any authorized U.S. Branch at the insurer’s expense; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Require the trustee or trustees to file a statement, in such form as the Commissioner may prescribe, certifying the assets of the trust fund and the amounts thereof.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(h)</num>
      <text>Refusal or neglect of any trustee to comply with the requirements of this section shall be grounds for the revocation of the insurer’s license or the liquidation of its United States Branch.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>History</heading>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 11-128">May 24, 1996, D.C. Law 11-128, § 5, 43 DCR 1562</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 12-81">Mar. 24, 1998, D.C. Law 12-81, § 45(c), 45 DCR 745</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Section References</heading>
        <annotation>This section is referenced in § <cite path="§31-2202">31-2202</cite>, § <cite path="§31-2205">31-2205</cite>, and § <cite path="§31-2306">31-2306</cite>.</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Prior Codifications</heading>
        <annotation>1981 Ed., § 35-4404.</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section from-code="true">
    <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" path="|31|22"/>
    <num codify:value="31-2205">6</num>
    <heading>Reporting requirements for U.S. Branches of non-U.S. insurers.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>(a)</num>
      <text>In addition to other requirements of this chapter, every authorized U.S. Branch shall, not later than the first day of March in each year and 45 days after the end of each of the first 3 calendar-year quarters, file the following with the Commissioner and with the National Association of Insurance Commissioners (“NAIC”):</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Annual and quarterly statements of the business transacted within the United States and the assets held by or for it within the United States for the protection of policy holders and creditors within the United States, and of the liabilities incurred against such assets. The forms shall not contain any statement in regard to its assets and business elsewhere. The statements shall be in the same format required of an insurer domiciled in the United States Branch’s state of entry state and licensed to write the same kinds of insurance; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A statement of trusteed surplus, in such form as the Commissioner may prescribe, as of the end of the same period covered by the statement filed pursuant to paragraph (1) of this subsection. The aggregate value of the insurer’s general state deposits and trusteed assets deposited with a trustee in compliance with § <cite path="§31-2204">31-2204</cite>, plus accrued investment income thereon where such interest is collected by the states for trustees, less the aggregate net amount of all of its reserves and other liabilities in the United States as determined in accordance with this section, shall be known as its trusteed surplus in the United States. In determining the net amount of the U.S. Branch’s liabilities in the United States to be reported in the statement of trusteed surplus, the U.S. Branch shall make adjustments to total liabilities reported on the accompanying annual or quarterly statements as follows:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(A)</num>
          <text>Add back liabilities used to offset admitted assets reported in the accompanying quarterly or annual statement; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(B)</num>
          <text>Deduct:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Unearned premiums on agent’s balances or uncollected premiums not more than 90 days past due;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Reinsurance on losses with authorized insurers, less unpaid reinsurance premiums;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Reinsurance recoverable on paid losses from unauthorized insurers that are included as an asset in the annual statement, but only to the extent a liability for such unauthorized recoverables is included in the liabilities report in the trusteed surplus statement;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iv)</num>
            <text>Special state deposits held for the exclusive benefit of policyholders, or policyholders and creditors, of any particular state not exceeding net liabilities reports for that state;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(v)</num>
            <text>Secured accrued retrospective premiums;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(vi)</num>
            <text>If a life insurer, the amount of its policy loans to policyholders within the United States, not exceeding the amount of legal reserve required on each such policy, and the net amount of uncollected and deferred premiums; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(vii)</num>
            <text>Any other nontrusteed asset which the Commissioner determines secures liabilities in a substantially similar manner; and</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Any additional information that the Commissioner may require relating to the total business or assets, or any portion thereof, of the non-U.S. insurer.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(b)</num>
      <text>The annual statement and trusteed surplus statement shall be signed and verified by the United States manager, attorney-in-fact, or a duly empowered assistant United States manager of the U.S. Branch. The items of securities and other property held under trust deeds shall be certified in the trusteed surplus statement by the United States trustee or trustees.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(c)</num>
      <text>Every report on examination of a U.S. Branch shall include a trusteed surplus statement as of the date of examination in addition to the general statement of the financial condition of the U.S. Branch.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>History</heading>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 11-128">May 24, 1996, D.C. Law 11-128, § 6, 43 DCR 1562</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 12-81">Mar. 24, 1998, D.C. Law 12-81, § 45(d), 45 DCR 745</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Prior Codifications</heading>
        <annotation>1981 Ed., § 35-4405.</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section from-code="true">
    <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" path="|31|22"/>
    <num codify:value="31-2206">7</num>
    <heading>Additional requirements for U.S. Branch license.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>(a)</num>
      <text>Before issuing any new or renewal license to any U.S. Branch, the Commissioner may require satisfactory proof, either in the non-U.S. insurer’s charter or by an agreement evidenced by a duly certified resolution of its board of directors, or otherwise as the Commissioner may require, that the insurer will not engage in any insurance business in contravention of the provisions of this chapter or not authorized by its charter.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(b)</num>
      <text>The Commissioner shall issue a renewal license to any U.S. Branch if satisfied, by such proof as required, that the insurer is not delinquent with respect to any requirement imposed by this chapter and that its continuance in business in the District will not be hazardous or prejudicial to the best interest of the people of the District.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(c)</num>
      <text>No U.S. Branch shall be licensed to do in the District any kind of insurance business, or any combination of kinds of insurance business, which are not permitted to be done by domestic insurers licensed under the provisions of this chapter. No U.S. Branch shall be authorized to do an insurance business in the District if it does anywhere within the United States any kind of business other than an insurance business and the business necessarily or properly incidental to the kinds of insurance business which it is authorized to do in the District.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(d)</num>
      <text>Except as otherwise specifically provided, no U.S. Branch, entering through the District or another state, shall be or continue to be authorized to do an insurance business in the District if it fails to comply substantially with any requirement or limitation of this chapter applicable to similar domestic insurers hereafter organized, which in the judgment of the Commissioner is reasonably necessary to protect the interest of the policyholders.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(e)</num>
      <text>No U.S. Branch that does outside of the District any kind or combination of kinds of insurance business not permitted to be done in the District by similar domestic insurers hereafter organized shall be or continue to be authorized to do an insurance business in the District, unless in the judgment of the Commissioner the doing of such kind or combination of kinds of insurance business will not be prejudicial to the best interest of the people of the District.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(f)</num>
      <text>No U.S. Branch shall be, or continue to be, authorized to do an insurance business in the District if it fails to keep full and correct entries of its transactions, which shall at all times be open to the inspection of persons invested by law with the rights of inspection and be maintained in its principal office within the District.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>History</heading>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 11-128">May 24, 1996, D.C. Law 11-128, § 7, 43 DCR 1562</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 12-81">Mar. 24, 1998, D.C. Law 12-81, § 45(e), 45 DCR 745</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Prior Codifications</heading>
        <annotation>1981 Ed., § 35-4406.</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section from-code="true">
    <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" path="|31|22"/>
    <num codify:value="31-2207">8</num>
    <heading>Authority of the Commissioner.</heading>
    <text>Whenever it appears to the Commissioner from any annual or quarterly statement, trusteed surplus statement, or any other report that a U.S. Branch’s trusteed surplus is reduced below minimum capital and surplus required to be maintained by a domestic insurer licensed to transact the same kinds of insurance, the Commissioner may proceed against the insurer pursuant to the provisions of District law as an insurer whose condition is such that its further transaction of business in the United States will be hazardous to its policyholders, its creditors, or the public in the United States.</text>
    <annotations>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>History</heading>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 11-128">May 24, 1996, D.C. Law 11-128, § 8, 43 DCR 1562</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 12-81">Mar. 24, 1998, D.C. Law 12-81, § 45(f), 45 DCR 745</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Prior Codifications</heading>
        <annotation>1981 Ed., § 35-4407.</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
    </annotations>
  </section>
</document>
