<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<document xmlns:codify="http://code.dccouncil.us/schemas/codify" id="Pub. L. 86-527">
  <num>86-527</num>
  <meta>
    <effective>1960-06-27</effective>
    <cites>
      <law session="86" lawId="527"/>
    </cites>
  </meta>
  <section from-code="true">
    <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" path="|2|11"/>
    <num codify:value="2-1101">2</num>
    <heading>Congressional declaration.</heading>
    <text>The Congress hereby declares that, because the District which is the seat of the government of the United States and has now become the urban center of a rapidly expanding Washington metropolitan region, the necessity for the continued and effective performance of the functions of the government of the United States at the seat of said government in the District of Columbia, the general welfare of the District of Columbia and the health and living standards of the people residing or working therein and the conduct of industry, trade, and commerce therein require that the development of the District of Columbia and the management of its public affairs shall, to the fullest extent practicable be coordinated with the development of the other areas of the Washington metropolitan region and with the management of the public affairs of such other areas, and that the activities of all of the departments, agencies, and instrumentalities of the federal government which may be carried out in, or in relation to, the other areas of the Washington metropolitan region shall, to the fullest extent practicable, be coordinated with the development of such other areas and with the management of their public affairs; all toward the end that, with the cooperation and assistance of the other areas of the Washington metropolitan region, all of the areas therein shall be so developed and the public affairs thereof shall be so managed as to contribute effectively toward the solution of the community development problems of the Washington metropolitan region on a unified metropolitan basis.</text>
    <annotations>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>History</heading>
        <annotation doc="Pub. L. 86-527">June 27, 1960, 74 Stat. 223, Pub. L. 86-527, § 2</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Section References</heading>
        <annotation>This section is referenced in § <cite path="§2-1102">2-1102</cite> and § <cite path="§2-1103">2-1103</cite>.</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Prior Codifications</heading>
        <annotation>1981 Ed., § 1-2101.</annotation>
        <annotation>1973 Ed., § 1-1301.</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section from-code="true">
    <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" path="|2|11"/>
    <num codify:value="2-1102">3</num>
    <heading>Congressional policy.</heading>
    <text>The Congress further declares that the policy to be followed for the attainment of the objective established by § <cite path="§2-1101">2-1101</cite>, and for the more effective exercise by the Congress, the executive branch of the federal government and the Mayor of the District of Columbia and all other officers and agencies and instrumentalities of the District of Columbia of their respective functions, powers, and duties in respect of the Washington metropolitan region, shall be that all such functions, powers, and duties shall be exercised and carried out in such manner as (with proper recognition of the sovereignty of the State of Maryland and the Commonwealth of Virginia in respect to those areas of the Washington metropolitan region as are situate within their respective jurisdictions) will best facilitate the attainment of such objective of the coordinated development of the areas of the Washington metropolitan region and coordinated management of their public affairs so as to contribute effectively to the solution of the community development problems of the Washington metropolitan region on a unified metropolitan basis.</text>
    <annotations>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>History</heading>
        <annotation doc="Pub. L. 86-527">June 27, 1960, 74 Stat. 223, Pub. L. 86-527, § 3</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Section References</heading>
        <annotation>This section is referenced in § <cite path="§2-1103">2-1103</cite>.</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Prior Codifications</heading>
        <annotation>1981 Ed., § 1-2102.</annotation>
        <annotation>1973 Ed., § 1-1302.</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Change in Government</heading>
        <annotation>This section originated at a time when local government powers were delegated to a Board of Commissioners of the District of Columbia (see Acts Relating to the Establishment of the District of Columbia and its Various Forms of Governmental Organization in Volume 1). Section 401 of Reorganization Plan No. 3 of 1967 (see Reorganization Plans in Volume 1) transferred all of the functions of the Board of Commissioners under this section to a single Commissioner. The District of Columbia Self-Government and Governmental Reorganization Act, 87 Stat. 818, § 711 ( D.C. Code, § <cite path="§1-207.11">1-207.11</cite>), abolished the District of Columbia Council and the Office of Commissioner of the District of Columbia. These branches of government were replaced by the Council of the District of Columbia and the Office of Mayor of the District of Columbia, respectively. Accordingly, and also pursuant to § 714(a) of such Act ( D.C. Code, § <cite path="§1-207.14">1-207.14</cite>(a)), appropriate changes in terminology were made in this section.</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section from-code="true">
    <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" path="|2|11"/>
    <num codify:value="2-1103">4</num>
    <heading>Priority projects.</heading>
    <text>The Congress further declares that, in carrying out the policy pursuant to § <cite path="§2-1102">2-1102</cite> for the attainment of the objective established by § <cite path="§2-1101">2-1101</cite>, priority should be given to the solution, on a unified metropolitan basis, of the problems of water supply, sewage disposal, and water pollution and transportation.</text>
    <annotations>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>History</heading>
        <annotation doc="Pub. L. 86-527">June 27, 1960, 74 Stat. 223, Pub. L. 86-527, § 4</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Prior Codifications</heading>
        <annotation>1981 Ed., § 1-2103.</annotation>
        <annotation>1973 Ed., § 1-1303.</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section from-code="true">
    <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" path="|2|11"/>
    <num codify:value="2-1104">5</num>
    <heading>Study of final report of Joint Committee on Washington Metropolitan Problems.</heading>
    <text>The Congress further declares that the officers, departments, agencies, and instrumentalities of the executive branch of the federal government and the Mayor of the District of Columbia and the other officers, agencies, and instrumentalities of the District of Columbia, and other agencies of government within the Washington metropolitan region are invited and encouraged to engage in an intensive study of the final report and recommendation of the Joint Committee on Washington Metropolitan Problems with a view to submitting to the Congress the specific recommendations of each of the agencies of government specified.</text>
    <annotations>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>History</heading>
        <annotation doc="Pub. L. 86-527">June 27, 1960, 74 Stat. 223, Pub. L. 86-527, § 5</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Prior Codifications</heading>
        <annotation>1981 Ed., § 1-2104.</annotation>
        <annotation>1973 Ed., § 1-1304.</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Change in Government</heading>
        <annotation>This section originated at a time when local government powers were delegated to a Board of Commissioners of the District of Columbia (see Acts Relating to the Establishment of the District of Columbia and its Various Forms of Governmental Organization in Volume 1). Section 401 of Reorganization Plan No. 3 of 1967 (see Reorganization Plans in Volume 1) transferred all of the functions of the Board of Commissioners under this section to a single Commissioner. The District of Columbia Self-Government and Governmental Reorganization Act, 87 Stat. 818, § 711 ( D.C. Code, § <cite path="§1-207.11">1-207.11</cite>), abolished the District of Columbia Council and the Office of Commissioner of the District of Columbia. These branches of government were replaced by the Council of the District of Columbia and the Office of Mayor of the District of Columbia, respectively. Accordingly, and also pursuant to § 714(a) of such Act ( D.C. Code, § <cite path="§1-207.14">1-207.14</cite>(a)), appropriate changes in terminology were made in this section.</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section from-code="true">
    <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" path="|2|11"/>
    <num codify:value="2-1105">6</num>
    <heading>“Washington metropolitan region” defined.</heading>
    <text>As used in this chapter, the term “Washington metropolitan region” includes the District of Columbia, the Counties of Montgomery and Prince Georges in the State of Maryland, the Counties of Arlington and Fairfax and the Cities of Alexandria and Falls Church in the Commonwealth of Virginia.</text>
    <annotations>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>History</heading>
        <annotation doc="Pub. L. 86-527">June 27, 1960, 74 Stat. 224, Pub. L. 86-527, § 6</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Prior Codifications</heading>
        <annotation>1981 Ed., § 1-2105.</annotation>
        <annotation>1973 Ed., § 1-1305.</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Editor's Notes</heading>
        <annotation>Because of the enactment of subchapter II of Chapter 22 of Title 1 subchapter IV of Chapter 12 of Title 2, 2001 Ed. by <cite doc="D.C. Law 5-89">D.C. Law 5-89</cite>, the preexisting text, including §§ <cite path="§1-2201">1-2201</cite> through <cite path="§1-2205">1-2205</cite> §§ <cite path="§2-1201.01">2-1201.01</cite> through <cite path="§2-1201.05">2-1201.05</cite>, 2001 Ed., has been designated as subchapter I.</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
    </annotations>
  </section>
</document>
