<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<document xmlns:codify="http://code.dccouncil.us/schemas/codify" id="29 Geo. 2, ch. 31">
  <heading/>
  <meta>
    <effective>1756-01-01</effective>
    <cites>
      <law session="29 Geo. 2" chapter="31"/>
    </cites>
  </meta>
  <section from-code="true">
    <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" before="§42-3229" path="|42|32"/>
    <num codify:value="42-3225">1</num>
    <heading>Lease held by an infant or person with a mental disability — Surrender and renewal; guardian or committee; court order.</heading>
    <text>In all cases where any person under the age of 18 years, or any person with mental illness, is or shall become interested in or entitled to any lease or leases made or granted, or to be made or granted, by any person or persons, bodies politic, corporate or collegiate, aggregate or sole, for the life or lives of 1 or more person or persons, or for any term of years, either absolute or determinable upon the death of 1 or more person or persons or otherwise, it shall and may be lawful for such person under the age of 18 years, or for his or her guardian or guardians, or other person or persons on his or her behalf, and for such person with mental illness, or his or her guardian or guardians, committee or committees of the estate, or other person or persons on his or her behalf, to apply to the court of chancery by petition or motion, in a summary way, and by the order and direction of the said court made, upon hearing all parties concerned, such person under the age of 18 years, and such persons with mental illness, or person or persons appointed by the said courts respectively, by deed or deeds only, shall and may be enabled, from time to time, to surrender such lease or leases, and accept and take, in the name, and for the benefit of such person under the age of 18 years, or person with mental illness, 1 or more new lease or leases of the premises comprised in such lease or leases surrendered by virtue of this section for and during such number of lives, or for such term or terms of years, determinable upon such number of lives, or for such term or terms of years absolute, as was or were mentioned or contained in such lease or leases so surrendered, at the making thereof respectively, or otherwise as the said court shall respectively direct.</text>
    <annotations>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>History</heading>
        <annotation>29 Geo. 2, ch. 31, § 1, 1756</annotation>
        <annotation>Kilty’s Rep. 253</annotation>
        <annotation>Alex. Br. Stat. 788</annotation>
        <annotation>Comp. Stat. D.C., 335, § 70</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 1-75">July 22, 1976, D.C. Law 1-75, § 4(j), 23 DCR 1182</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 16-305">Apr. 24, 2007, D.C. Law 16-305, § 64(d), 53 DCR 6198</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Prior Codifications</heading>
        <annotation>1981 Ed., § 45-1425.</annotation>
        <annotation>1973 Ed., § 45-927.</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Effect of Amendments</heading>
        <annotation><cite doc="D.C. Law 16-305">D.C. Law 16-305</cite>, in the section name line, substituted “person with a mental disability” for “mentally handicapped”; and substituted “person with mental illness” for “lunatic” and “persons with mental illness” for “lunatics”.</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section from-code="true">
    <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" before="§42-3229" path="|42|32"/>
    <num codify:value="42-3226">2</num>
    <heading>Lease held by an infant or person with a mental disability — Costs of renewal chargeable to estate of infant or person with a disability or deemed charge upon leasehold.</heading>
    <text>All and every sum and sums of money and other consideration, paid or advanced by any such guardian, trustee, committee or other person, for or on account of the renewal of any such lease or leases, and all reasonable charges incident thereto, shall be paid out of the estate or effects of the infant or person with a mental illness for whose benefit the said lease or leases shall be renewed, or shall be a charge and incumbrance upon the leasehold premises, together with interest for the same, as the said court shall direct and determine.</text>
    <annotations>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>History</heading>
        <annotation>29 Geo. 2, ch. 31, § 2, 1756</annotation>
        <annotation>Kilty’s Rep. 253</annotation>
        <annotation>Alex. Br. Stat. 789</annotation>
        <annotation>Comp. Stat. D.C., 335, § 71</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 16-305">Apr. 24, 2007, D.C. Law 16-305, § 64(e), 53 DCR 6198</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 19-169">Sept. 26, 2012, D.C. Law 19-169, § 26(b), 59 DCR 5567</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Prior Codifications</heading>
        <annotation>1981 Ed., § 45-1426.</annotation>
        <annotation>1973 Ed., § 45-928.</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Effect of Amendments</heading>
        <annotation><cite doc="D.C. Law 16-305">D.C. Law 16-305</cite> rewrote the section heading, which formerly read: “Lease held by infant or mentally handicapped—Costs of renewal chargeable to estate of infant or handicapped or deemed charge upon leasehold.”</annotation>
        <annotation>The 2012 amendment by <cite doc="D.C. Law 19-169">D.C. Law 19-169</cite> substituted “person with a mental illness” for “lunatic.”</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Editor's Notes</heading>
        <annotation>Section 35 of <cite doc="D.C. Law 19-169">D.C. Law 19-169</cite> provided that no provision of the act shall impair any right or obligation existing under law.</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section from-code="true">
    <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" before="§42-3229" path="|42|32"/>
    <num codify:value="42-3227">3</num>
    <heading>Lease held by an infant or person with a mental disability — New leases to be of same nature and subject to same liabilities as surrendered leases.</heading>
    <text>The respective leases to be so renewed, shall operate, and be to the same uses, and be liable to the same trusts, charges, incumbrances, dispositions, devises and conditions, as the leases to be, from time to time, surrendered as aforesaid, were or would have been subject to, in case such surrender had not been made.</text>
    <annotations>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>History</heading>
        <annotation>29 Geo. 2, ch. 31, § 3, 1756</annotation>
        <annotation>Kilty’s Rep. 253</annotation>
        <annotation>Alex. Br. Stat. 790</annotation>
        <annotation>Comp. Stat. D.C., 335, § 72</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 16-305">Apr. 24, 2007, D.C. Law 16-305, § 64(f), 53 DCR 6198</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Prior Codifications</heading>
        <annotation>1981 Ed., § 45-1427.</annotation>
        <annotation>1973 Ed., § 45-929.</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Effect of Amendments</heading>
        <annotation><cite doc="D.C. Law 16-305">D.C. Law 16-305</cite> rewrote the section heading, which formerly read: “Lease held by infant or mentally handicapped—New leases to be of same nature and subject to same liabilities as surrendered leases.”</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section from-code="true">
    <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" before="§42-3229" path="|42|32"/>
    <num codify:value="42-3228">4</num>
    <heading>Lease held by an infant or person with a mental disability — Renewed lease valid.</heading>
    <text>Every such surrender, and such lease or leases granted thereupon, shall be, and be deemed as valid and legal, to all intents and purposes, as if such surrender had been made by and on the behalf of a person of full age, or sane mind.</text>
    <annotations>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>History</heading>
        <annotation>29 Geo. 2, ch. 31, § 4, 1756</annotation>
        <annotation>Kilty’s Rep. 253</annotation>
        <annotation>Alex. Br. Stat. 790</annotation>
        <annotation>Comp. Stat. D.C., 336, § 73</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 16-305">Apr. 24, 2007, D.C. Law 16-305, § 64(g), 53 DCR 6198</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Prior Codifications</heading>
        <annotation>1981 Ed., § 45-1428.</annotation>
        <annotation>1973 Ed., § 45-930.</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Effect of Amendments</heading>
        <annotation><cite doc="D.C. Law 16-305">D.C. Law 16-305</cite> rewrote the section heading, which formerly read: “Lease held by infant or mentally handicapped—Renewed lease valid”.</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
    </annotations>
  </section>
</document>
