<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<document xmlns:codify="http://code.dccouncil.us/schemas/codify" id="Pub. L. 89-774">
  <num>89-774</num>
  <meta>
    <effective>1966-11-06</effective>
    <cites>
      <law session="89" lawId="774"/>
    </cites>
  </meta>
  <section from-code="true">
    <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" path="|9|11|IV"/>
    <num codify:value="9-1107.07">2</num>
    <heading>Mayor directed to execute Compact amendments; appropriations.</heading>
    <text>The Mayor of the District of Columbia is authorized and directed to enter into and execute an amendment to the Compact substantially as set forth above with the States of Virginia and Maryland and is further authorized and directed to carry out and effectuate the terms and provisions of said Title III, and there are hereby authorized to be appropriated out of District of Columbia funds such amounts as are necessary to carry out the obligations of the District of Columbia in accordance with the terms of the said Title III.</text>
    <annotations>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>History</heading>
        <annotation doc="Pub. L. 89-774">Nov. 6, 1966, 80 Stat. 1352, Pub. L. 89-774, § 2</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Prior Codifications</heading>
        <annotation>1981 Ed., § 1-2437.</annotation>
        <annotation>1973 Ed., § 1-1432.</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Change in Government</heading>
        <annotation>This section originated at a time when local government powers were delegated to a Board of Commissioners of the District of Columbia (see Acts Relating to the Establishment of the District of Columbia and its Various Forms of Governmental Organization in Volume 1). Section 401 of Reorganization Plan No. 3 of 1967 (see Reorganization Plans in Volume 1) transferred all of the functions of the Board of Commissioners under this section to a single Commissioner. The District of Columbia Self-Government and Governmental Reorganization Act, 87 Stat. 818, § 711 ( D.C. Code, § <cite path="§1-207.11">1-207.11</cite>), abolished the District of Columbia Council and the Office of Commissioner of the District of Columbia. These branches of government were replaced by the Council of the District of Columbia and the Office of Mayor of the District of Columbia, respectively. Accordingly, and also pursuant to § 714(a) of such Act ( D.C. Code, § <cite path="§1-207.14">1-207.14</cite>(a)), appropriate changes in terminology were made in this section.</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section from-code="true">
    <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" path="|9|11|IV"/>
    <num codify:value="9-1107.09">3</num>
    <heading>Transfer of functions, duties, property, and records of National Capital Transportation Agency to Washington Metropolitan Area Transit Authority.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>(a)</num>
      <text>To assure uninterrupted progress in the development of the facilities authorized by the National Capital Transportation Act of 1965, the transfer of the functions and duties of the National Capital Transportation Agency (herein referred to as the Agency) to the Washington Metropolitan Area Transit Authority (herein referred to as the Authority) as required by § <cite path="§1-1408">1-1408</cite>(b) shall take place on September 30, 1967.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(b)</num>
      <text>Upon the effective date of the transfer of functions and duties authorized by subsection (a) of this section, the President is authorized to transfer to the Authority such real and personal property, studies, reports, records, and other assets and liabilities as are appropriate in order that the Authority may assume the functions and duties of the Agency and, further, the President shall make provision for the transfer to the Authority of the unexpended balance of the appropriations, and of other funds, of the Agency for use by the Authority but such unexpended balances so transferred shall be used only for the purpose for which such appropriations were originally made. Subsequent to said effective date, there is authorized to be appropriated to the Department of Housing and Urban Development, for payment to the Authority, any unappropriated portion of the authorization specified in § <cite path="§9-1105.02">9-1105.02</cite>(1). There is also authorized to be appropriated to the District of Columbia out of the General Fund of the District of Columbia, for payment to the Authority, any unappropriated portion of the authorization specified in § <cite path="§9-1105.02">9-1105.02</cite>(2). Any such appropriations shall be used only for the purposes for which such authorizations were originally made.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(c)</num>
      <text>Pending the assumption by the Authority of the functions and duties of the Agency, the Agency is authorized and directed, in the manner herein set forth, fully to cooperate with and assist the Authority, the Northern Virginia Transportation Commission and the Washington Suburban Transit Commission in the development of plans for the extensions, new lines and related facilities required to expand the basic system authorized by the National Capital Transportation Act of 1965 into a regional system, but pending such transfer of functions and duties, nothing in this subchapter shall be construed to impair the performance by the Agency of the functions and duties imposed by the National Capital Transportation Act of 1965.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(d)</num>
      <text>In order to provide the cooperation and assistance specified in subsection (c) of this section, the Agency is authorized to perform, on a reimbursable basis, planning, engineering and such other services for the Authority, as the Authority may request, or to obtain such services by contract, but all such assistance and services shall be rendered in accordance with policy determinations made by the Authority and shall be advisory only.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(e)</num>
      <text>Amounts received by the Agency from the Authority as provided in subsection (d) of this section shall be available for expenditure by the Agency in performing services for the Authority.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>History</heading>
        <annotation doc="Pub. L. 89-774">Nov. 6, 1966, 80 Stat. 1352, Pub. L. 89-774, § 3</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Prior Codifications</heading>
        <annotation>1981 Ed., § 1-2438.</annotation>
        <annotation>1973 Ed., § 1433.</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>References in Text</heading>
        <text>“The National Capital Transportation Act of 1965,” referred to in subsections (a) and (c) of this section, is the Act of September 8, 1965, 79 Stat. 663, Pub. L. 89-173.</text>
        <text>former § <cite path="§1-1408">1-1408</cite>, referred to near the end of subsection (a) of this section, was repealed by the Act of December 9, 1969, 83 Stat. 322, Pub. L. 91-143, § 8(a)(1).</text>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Transfer of Functions</heading>
        <annotation>Section 1(a)(3) of Reorganization Plan No. 2 of 1968, transferred the functions of the Department of Housing and Urban Development, set forth in subsection (b) of this section, to the Secretary of Transportation.</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section from-code="true">
    <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" path="|9|11|IV"/>
    <num codify:value="9-1107.10">4</num>
    <heading>Jurisdiction of courts; removal of actions.</heading>
    <text>The United States district courts shall have original jurisdiction, concurrent with the courts of Maryland and Virginia, of all actions brought by or against the Authority and to enforce subpoenas issued pursuant to the provisions of Title III. Any such action initiated in a state court shall be removable to the appropriate United States district court in the manner provided by § 1446 of Title 28, United States Code  .</text>
    <annotations>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>History</heading>
        <annotation doc="Pub. L. 89-774">Nov. 6, 1966, 80 Stat. 1353, Pub. L. 89-774, § 4</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Prior Codifications</heading>
        <annotation>1981 Ed., § 1-2439.</annotation>
        <annotation>1973 Ed., § 1-1434.</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Editor's Notes</heading>
        <annotation>Appropriations authorized: Public Law 104-194, 110 Stat. 2362, the District of Columbia Appropriations Act, 1997, provided for construction projects an increase of $46,923,000 (including an increase of $34,000,000 for the highway trust fund, reallocations and rescissions for a net rescission of $120,496,000 from local funds appropriated under this heading in prior fiscal years and an additional $133,419,000 in Federal funds), as authorized by §§ <cite path="§34-2405.01">34-2405.01</cite> through <cite path="§34-2405.08">34-2405.08</cite>; §§ <cite path="§34-2413.08">34-2413.08</cite>, <cite path="§34-2413.10">34-2413.10</cite> and <cite path="§34-2304">34-2304</cite>; and §§ <cite path="§10-619">10-619</cite> and <cite path="§47-3404">47-3404</cite>; including acquisition of sites, preparation of plans and specifications, conducting preliminary surveys, erection of structures, including building improvement and alteration and treatment of grounds, to remain available until expended: Provided, That funds for use of each capital project implementing agency shall be managed and controlled in accordance with all procedures and limitations established under the Financial Management System: Provided further, That all funds provided by this appropriation title shall be available only for the specific projects and purposes intended: Provided further, That notwithstanding the foregoing, all authorizations for capital outlay projects, except those projects covered by the first sentence of section 23(a) of the Federal-Aid Highway Act of 1968, approved August 23, 1968 (82 Stat. 827; Public Law 90-495;  D.C. Code, sec. 9-107.01, note), for which funds are provided by this appropriation title, shall expire on September 30, 1998, except authorizations for projects as to which funds have been obligated in whole or in part prior to September 30, 1998: Provided further, That upon expiration of any such project authorization the funds provided herein for the project shall lapse.</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section>
    <num>5</num>
    <para from-code="true" codify:tag="section">
      <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" path="|9|11|IV"/>
      <num codify:value="9-1107.11">(a)</num>
      <heading>Amendment of laws and reorganization plans.</heading>
      <text>All laws or parts of laws of the United States and of the District of Columbia inconsistent with the provisions of Title III are hereby amended for the purpose of this subchapter to the extent necessary to eliminate such inconsistencies and to carry out the provisions of this subchapter and Title III and all laws or parts of laws and all reorganization plans of the United States are hereby amended and made applicable for the purpose of this subchapter to the extent necessary to carry out the provisions of this subchapter and Title III.</text>
      <annotations>
        <annoGroup>
          <heading>History</heading>
          <annotation doc="Pub. L. 89-774">Nov. 6, 1966, 80 Stat. 1353, Pub. L. 89-774, § 5(a)</annotation>
        </annoGroup>
        <annoGroup>
          <heading>Prior Codifications</heading>
          <annotation>1981 Ed., § 1-2440.</annotation>
          <annotation>1973 Ed., § 1-1435.</annotation>
        </annoGroup>
      </annotations>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section from-code="true">
    <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" path="|9|11|IV"/>
    <num codify:value="9-1107.12">6</num>
    <heading>Reservation of right to alter, amend or repeal subchapter; submission of reports; scope of Presidential and Congressional inquiry; audits.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>(a)</num>
      <text>The right to alter, amend or repeal this subchapter is hereby expressly reserved.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(b)</num>
      <text>The Authority shall submit to Congress and the President copies of all annual and special reports made to the Governors, the Mayor of the District of Columbia and/or the legislatures of the compacting States.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(c)</num>
      <text>The President and the Congress or any committee thereof shall have the right to require the disclosure and furnishing of such information by the Authority as they may deem appropriate. Further, the President and Congress or any of its committees shall have access to all books, records and papers of the Authority as well as the right of inspection of any facility used, owned, leased, regulated or under the control of said Authority.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(d)</num>
      <text>In carrying out the audits provided for in § 70(b) of the Compact, the representatives of the General Accounting Office shall have access to all books, accounts, financial records, reports, files, and all other papers, things, or property belonging to or in use by the Board and necessary to facilitate the audit, and they shall be afforded full facilities for verifying transactions with the balances or securities held by depositories, agents, and custodians.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>History</heading>
        <annotation doc="Pub. L. 89-774">Nov. 6, 1966, 80 Stat. 1353, Pub. L. 89-774, § 6</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Prior Codifications</heading>
        <annotation>1981 Ed., § 1-2441.</annotation>
        <annotation>1973 Ed., § 1-1436.</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Change in Government</heading>
        <annotation>This section originated at a time when local government powers were delegated to a Board of Commissioners of the District of Columbia (see Acts Relating to the Establishment of the District of Columbia and its Various Forms of Governmental Organization in Volume 1). Section 401 of Reorganization Plan No. 3 of 1967 (see Reorganization Plans in Volume 1) transferred all of the functions of the Board of Commissioners under this section to a single Commissioner. The District of Columbia Self-Government and Governmental Reorganization Act, 87 Stat. 818, § 711 ( D.C. Code, § <cite path="§1-207.11">1-207.11</cite>), abolished the District of Columbia Council and the Office of Commissioner of the District of Columbia. These branches of government were replaced by the Council of the District of Columbia and the Office of Mayor of the District of Columbia, respectively. Accordingly, and also pursuant to § 714(a) of such Act ( D.C. Code, § <cite path="§1-207.14">1-207.14</cite>(a)), appropriate changes in terminology were made in this section.</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
    </annotations>
  </section>
</document>
