<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<document xmlns:codify="http://code.dccouncil.us/schemas/codify" id="D.C. Law 10-246">
  <num type="law">10-246</num>
  <heading type="short">Recreation Act of 1994</heading>
  <meta>
    <effective>1995-03-23</effective>
    <cites>
      <law lawId="246" period="10" url="./docs/10-246.pdf"/>
      <register page="452" vol="42"/>
    </cites>
    <history url="http://lims.dccouncil.us/Legislation/B10-0741">
      <narrative>Law 10-246, the “Recreation Act of 1994,” was introduced in Council and assigned Bill No. 10-741, which was referred to the Committee on Public Services and Youth Affairs. The Bill was adopted on first and second readings on November 1, 1994, and December 6, 1994, respectively. Signed by the Mayor on January 13, 1995, it was assigned Act No. 10-393 and transmitted to both Houses of Congress for its review. D.C. Law 10-246 became effective on March 23, 1995.</narrative>
    </history>
  </meta>
  <section from-code="true">
    <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" path="|10|3"/>
    <num codify:value="10-301">2</num>
    <heading>Definitions.</heading>
    <text>For purposes of this chapter:</text>
    <para>
      <num>(1)</num>
      <text>The term “adopt” means to enter into a binding commitment to a program, site, or operation for not less than 1 year in duration.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(2)</num>
      <text>“Department” means the Department of Parks and Recreation.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(3)</num>
      <text>“Department activity” means an activity, event, class, program, operation, service, or product for the benefit, enjoyment, education, amusement, or convenience of the public.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(4)</num>
      <text>“Designated Organizations” means entities designated by the Director pursuant to § <cite path="§10-137.01">10-137.01</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(5)</num>
      <text>“Fee-based use permit” means a permit issued by the Department to a person for a fee-based Department activity.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(6)</num>
      <text>“Friends Groups” means an organization, qualified under section 501(c)(3) of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986, approved October 22, 1986 (100 Stat. 2085; 26 U.S.C. § 501(c)(3)), and registered under the park partner program, whose mission includes supporting an adopted park or recreation facility by advocating, fundraising, maintaining, and assisting in the planning process for the park or recreation facility adopted.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(7)</num>
      <text>“Park Partner Agreement” means the agreement between the Department and the Friends Group explaining the duties, rights, and obligations of the Friends Group.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(8)</num>
      <text>“Planned Unit Development” means a plan for the development of residential, institutional, and commercial developments, industrial parks, urban renewal projects, or a combination of these as defined in the Zoning Regulations of the District of Columbia (11 DCMR § 199).</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(9)</num>
      <text>The term “sponsor” means to pledge or promise support to a program, site, or operation on an intermittent, short-term or one-time basis.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>History</heading>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 10-246">Mar. 23, 1995, D.C. Law 10-246, § 2, 42 DCR 452</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 19-21">Sept. 14, 2011, D.C. Law 19-21, § 6042(a), 58 DCR 6226</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 19-275">Apr. 23, 2013, D.C. Law 19-275, § 2(a), 60 DCR 2058</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 19-280">Apr. 23, 2013, D.C. Law 19-280, § 2(a), 60 DCR 2124</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Prior Codifications</heading>
        <annotation>1981 Ed., § 8-301.</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Effect of Amendments</heading>
        <annotation><cite doc="D.C. Law 19-21">D.C. Law 19-21</cite> added pars. (1A) to (1D).</annotation>
        <annotation>The 2013 amendment by <cite doc="D.C. Law 19-275">D.C. Law 19-275</cite> substituted “whose mission includes supporting” for “whose primary mission is to support” in (6).</annotation>
        <annotation>The 2013 amendment by <cite doc="D.C. Law 19-280">D.C. Law 19-280</cite> added (2) and (3) and redesignated former (1A) as (4); added present (5); and redesignated former (1B) through (2) as (6) through (9), respectively.</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Emergency Legislation</heading>
        <annotation>For temporary addition of chapter, see §§ 2-7 of the Recreation Emergency Act of 1995 (D.C. Act 11-20, February 28, 1995,  42 DCR 1175).</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Short Title</heading>
        <annotation>Short title: Section 6041 of <cite doc="D.C. Law 19-21">D.C. Law 19-21</cite> provided that subtitle E of title VI of the act may be cited as “Department of Parks and Recreation Revenue Generation Amendment Act of 2011”.</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section from-code="true">
    <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" path="|10|3"/>
    <num codify:value="10-302">3</num>
    <heading>Authority of Department of Parks and Recreation.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>(a)</num>
      <text>The Department may accept donations, gifts by devise or bequest, grants, and any other type of asset from individuals, clubs, groups, corporations, partnerships, and other governmental entities, except that such acceptance must be approved by the Mayor before it occurs.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(b)</num>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Department buildings and grounds may be used for fund-raising activities by the Department, Friends Groups, Designated Organizations, and for-profit organizations contracted for and supervised by the Department, Friends Groups, or Designated Organizations; provided, that Friends Groups and Designated Organizations may use Department buildings and grounds for fundraising activities no more than 12 times per year.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Except with regard to fundraising activities by Friends Groups and Designated Organizations, the Department shall manage received property or funds in accordance with the provisions or conditions of the donation, gift, grant, or other type of transfer, including the investment of the principal of such property or funds. The Mayor shall consider the donor’s choice of which site, program, or operation should be the recipient of the property.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>All property and funds obtained by the Friends Groups and Designated Organizations shall be for the benefit of Department facilities or programs. All funds raised for or by Friends Groups and Designated Organizations shall be deposited in a dedicated bank account in the name of the Friends Group or Designated Organization and expended solely for improvements, costs, or services for the associated park, program, event, recreation facility, or other Department facility, in accordance with the terms of the Park Partner Agreement, if applicable.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Friends Groups and Designated Organizations shall provide semiannual accounting to the Department of all funds collected.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(b-1)</num>
      <text>On a property under its jurisdiction, control, or use, the Department may charge reasonable prices for department activities and issue fee-based use permits in accordance with § <cite path="§10-302.01">10-302.01</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(c)</num>
      <text>Department buildings and grounds shall not be used for any commercial, profit-making, fundraising, or other solicitation by any agency, individual, or organization, except as specifically provided in this section.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(d)</num>
      <text>Nothing in this section shall be construed as limiting the Department’s authority to issue permits pursuant to § <cite path="§10-137.01">10-137.01</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>History</heading>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 10-246">Mar. 23, 1995, D.C. Law 10-246, § 3, 42 DCR 452</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 19-21">Sept. 14, 2011, D.C. Law 19-21, § 6042(b), 58 DCR 6226</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 19-275">Apr. 23, 2013, D.C. Law 19-275, § 2(b), 60 DCR 2058</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 19-280">Apr. 23, 2013, D.C. Law 19-280, § 2(b), 60 DCR 2124</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 20-271">May 2, 2015, D.C. Law 20-271, § 304(a), 62 DCR 1884</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Section References</heading>
        <annotation>This section is referenced in § <cite path="§10-302.02">10-302.02</cite> and § <cite path="§10-307">10-307</cite>.</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Prior Codifications</heading>
        <annotation>1981 Ed., § 8-302.</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Effect of Amendments</heading>
        <annotation><cite doc="D.C. Law 19-21">D.C. Law 19-21</cite> rewrote subsec. (b); and added subsec. (c). Prior to amendment, subsec. (b) read as follows: “(b) The Department shall manage such property or funds in accordance with the provisions or conditions of the donation, gift, grant or other type of transfer, including but not limited to the investment of the principal of such property or funds. The Mayor shall consider the donor’s choice of which site, program or operation should be the recipient of the property.”</annotation>
        <annotation>The 2013 amendment by <cite doc="D.C. Law 19-275">D.C. Law 19-275</cite> rewrote (b)(3).</annotation>
        <annotation>The 2013 amendment by <cite doc="D.C. Law 19-280">D.C. Law 19-280</cite> substituted “Department” for “Department of Recreation and Parks (‘Department’ or ‘Departmental’)” in (a); and added (b-1) and (d).</annotation>
        <annotation>The 2015 amendment by <cite doc="D.C. Law 20-271">D.C. Law 20-271</cite> substituted “Department of Parks and Recreation” for “Department of Recreation and Parks” in the section heading.</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Emergency Legislation</heading>
        <annotation>See Historical and Statutory Notes following § <cite path="§10-301">10-301</cite>.</annotation>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 days) amendment of this section, see § 304(a) of the New Columbia Statehood Initiative, Omnibus Boards and Commissions, and Election Transition Reform Emergency Amendment Act of 2014 (D.C. Act 20-481, November 18, 2014, 61 DCR 12133, 20 STAT 4405).</annotation>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 days) amendment of this section, see § 304(a) of the New Columbia Statehood Initiative, Omnibus Boards and Commissions, and Election Transition Reform Congressional Review Emergency Amendment Act of 2015 (D.C. Act 21-7, Feb. 26, 2015,  62 DCR 2646, 21 STAT 807).</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>References in Text</heading>
        <annotation>Pursuant to Mayor’s Order 2000-20, the agency formerly known as the Department of Recreation and Parks shall be known as the Department of Parks and Recreation.</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Delegation of Authority</heading>
        <annotation>Delegation of authority pursuant to <cite doc="D.C. Law 10-246">D.C. Law 10-246</cite>, the Recreation Act of 1994, see Mayor’s Order 96-55, April 24, 1996 ( 43 DCR 2453).</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section from-code="true">
    <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" path="|10|3"/>
    <num codify:value="10-302.01">3a</num>
    <heading>Fee-based use permits.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>(a)</num>
      <text>The Department may issue a fee-based use permit on a property under its jurisdiction, control, or use, subject to such conditions as the Director may impose and only upon a determination that the use permit:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Will meet the mission of the Department; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Will not adversely impact the use and enjoyment of the area by other members of the public.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(b)</num>
      <text>Fee-based use permits shall not be issued solely for their revenue-producing potential.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>History</heading>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 10-246">Mar. 23, 1995, D.C. Law 10-246, § 3a</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 19-280">as added Apr. 23, 2013, D.C. Law 19-280, § 2(c), 60 DCR 2124</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Section References</heading>
        <annotation>This section is referenced in § <cite path="§10-302">10-302</cite>, § <cite path="§10-302.02">10-302.02</cite>, and § <cite path="§10-307">10-307</cite>.</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Effect of Amendments</heading>
        <annotation><cite doc="D.C. Law 19-280">D.C. Law 19-280</cite> added this section.</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section from-code="true">
    <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" path="|10|3"/>
    <num codify:value="10-302.02">3b</num>
    <heading>Nutrition at Department facilities.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>(a)</num>
      <text>Except as provided in subsection (b) of this section, all food and beverages sold, offered, or provided by the Department or its agents through vending machines, concessions, stores, or other food venues on buildings, grounds, or other facilities under the Department’s jurisdiction, control, or use shall meet the requirements of either:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The United States Department of Agriculture’s HealthierUS School Challenge program at the Gold Award Level for meals, competitive foods, and beverages as may be revised from time to time, notwithstanding any termination; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The Alliance for a Healthier Generation’s school competitive foods and beverage guidelines at the high school level, as may be revised from time to time, notwithstanding any termination.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(b)</num>
      <text>The requirements of this section shall not apply to:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>An event, such as a festival or carnival, if the Director exempts the event, in writing, from the requirements of this section and the food or beverages are not sold;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Foods or beverages offered or provided by Department employees for their own consumption;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>A farmers’ market or produce cart, stand, or truck; provided, that at least one-half of the items offered or provided is fresh fruits or vegetables;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Fund-raising activities held pursuant to § <cite path="§10-302">10-302</cite>(b); or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Foods or beverages sold, offered, or provided by a person as an ancillary part of its participation in a permitted activity or event; provided, that the person has applied for and received a fee-based use permit in accordance with § <cite path="§10-302.01">10-302.01</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(c)</num>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The Department shall seek to maximize its sponsorship of and the participation of eligible children and residents in federal nutrition programs.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>On or before June 1 of each year, the Department shall provide the manager or designated employee of each of its facilities with training and information on how to connect residents to nutrition supports, including the Supplemental Nutrition Assistance Program, federal child nutrition programs, nutrition education programs, and emergency food.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(d)</num>
      <text>The Department shall ensure that any foods or beverages sold, offered, or provided outside of federal nutrition programs do not negatively affect the participation of children and residents in federal nutrition programs.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(e)</num>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Food or beverages may only be advertised or marketed on Department property if the items meet the nutritional standards set forth in this section.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The requirements of this subsection shall apply to advertising:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(A)</num>
          <text>On scoreboards;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(B)</num>
          <text>On vending machines;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(C)</num>
          <text>At concession stands;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(D)</num>
          <text>On banners and signs;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(E)</num>
          <text>Through the sponsorship of teams, programs, and events; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(F)</num>
          <text>Other forms of promotion, marketing, and advertising.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>History</heading>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 10-246">Mar. 23, 1995, D.C. Law 10-246, § 3b</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 19-280">as added Apr. 23, 2013, D.C. Law 19-280, § 2(c), 60 DCR 2124</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Section References</heading>
        <annotation>This section is referenced in § <cite path="§10-307">10-307</cite>.</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Effect of Amendments</heading>
        <annotation><cite doc="D.C. Law 19-280">D.C. Law 19-280</cite> added this section.</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section from-code="true">
    <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" path="|10|3"/>
    <num codify:value="10-302.03">3c</num>
    <heading>Priority for Department programs and facilities.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>(a)</num>
      <text>The Department shall give preference to residents for enrollment and participation slots in sports leagues, teams, games, programs, and camps managed or sponsored by the Department for youth, adults, and seniors, before offering participation slots to non-residents.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(b)</num>
      <text>Within 180 days of April 23, 2013, the Department shall develop a plan to actively advertise and promote the activities listed in subsection (a) of this section to residents to encourage their participation.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>History</heading>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 10-246">Mar. 23, 1995, D.C. Law 10-246, § 3c</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 19-280">as added Apr. 23, 2013, D.C. Law 19-280, § 2(c), 60 DCR 2124</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Effect of Amendments</heading>
        <annotation><cite doc="D.C. Law 19-280">D.C. Law 19-280</cite> added this section.</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section from-code="true">
    <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" path="|10|3"/>
    <num codify:value="10-303">4</num>
    <heading>Creation of Fund; accounting and investment.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>(a)</num>
      <text>The Mayor shall establish for accounting and financial reporting purposes a Recreation Enterprise Fund (“Fund”) in accordance with generally accepted accounting principles.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(b)</num>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>There is hereby authorized a direct appropriation to the Fund equal to the amount collected from fees, concessions, and services and payments by developers seeking relief from zoning laws by way of the Planned Unit Development process considered part of the required community benefits package of the proposed Planned Unit Development. Revenue deposited into the Fund account shall be expended by the Department for the administration, improvement, and maintenance of property and programs managed by the Department and shall supplement, but not replace, services provided by the Department; provided, that payments by developers seeking relief from zoning laws in accordance with the Zoning Regulations of the District of Columbia (11 DCMR § 100 et seq.) and the Planned Unit Development process shall be expended on Department property within the boundaries of the Advisory Neighborhood Commission in which the Planned Unit Development is located. The Fund shall not be used to provide funding to other District government agencies, except to pay the principal and interest on bonds in accordance with § <cite path="§10-304">10-304</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Proceeds from the Recreation Enterprise Fund may be used to purchase food, snacks, and non-alcoholic beverages for the general public, Department of Parks and Recreation program participants, and District government employees.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(c)</num>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Once each year, the Department shall publish in the District of Columbia Register a specific accounting of how monies in the Fund have been spent and an accounting as to the amount remaining in the Fund. The accounting shall include the name of the donor or an anonymous contribution, the amount of the contribution, a description of the property donated and the name of the program or recreation center upon which the funds have been expended.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The money deposited into the Fund, and interest earned, shall not revert to the unrestricted fund balance of the General Fund of the District of Columbia at the end of a fiscal year, or at any other time.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(d)</num>
      <text>Proceeds of the Fund may be invested in a prudent and reasonable manner consistent with applicable District government policies and procedures.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(e)</num>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Notwithstanding any other provision of law, the Department may contract for advertisements and sponsorships for programs, events, recreation centers, fields, pools, play courts, and other Department facilities within the Department’s inventory.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The Department shall not delegate the authority to contract for advertisements or sponsorships granted to it pursuant to paragraph (1) of this subsection to any other party.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>All proceeds received from advertisements and sponsorships shall be deposited into the Fund pursuant to this section.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>History</heading>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 10-246">Mar. 23, 1995, D.C. Law 10-246, § 4, 42 DCR 452</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 11-110">Apr. 18, 1996, D.C. Law 11-110, § 20(a), 43 DCR 530</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 18-111">Mar. 3, 2010, D.C. Law 18-111, § 5091, 57 DCR 181</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 19-21">Sept. 14, 2011, D.C. Law 19-21, §§ 6042(c), 9064, 58 DCR 6226</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 19-275">Apr. 23, 2013, D.C. Law 19-275, § 2(c), 60 DCR 2058</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 20-61">Dec. 24, 2013, D.C. Law 20-61, § 5102, 60 DCR 12472</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 20-271">May 2, 2015, D.C. Law 20-271, § 259(a), 62 DCR 1884</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Section References</heading>
        <annotation>This section is referenced in § <cite path="§10-306">10-306</cite>.</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Prior Codifications</heading>
        <annotation>1981 Ed., § 8-303.</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Effect of Amendments</heading>
        <annotation><cite doc="D.C. Law 18-111">D.C. Law 18-111</cite>, in subsec. (b), designated the existing text as par. (1) and added par. (2).</annotation>
        <annotation><cite doc="D.C. Law 19-21">D.C. Law 19-21</cite>, in subsec. (b)(1), substituted “and services and payments by developers seeking relief from zoning laws by way of the Planned Unit Development process considered part of the required community benefits package of the proposed Planned Unit Development.” for “and services.”, and substituted “provided by the Department; provided, that payments by developers seeking relief from zoning laws in accordance with the Zoning Regulations of the District of Columbia ( 11 DCMR § 100 et seq.) and the Planned Unit Development process shall be expended on Department property within the boundaries of the Advisory Neighborhood Commission in which the Planned Unit Development is located.”; in subsec. (c), designated the existing text as par. (1) and added par. (2); and added subsec. (e).</annotation>
        <annotation>The 2013 amendment by <cite doc="D.C. Law 19-275">D.C. Law 19-275</cite> rewrote (e)(1).</annotation>
        <annotation>The 2013 amendment by <cite doc="D.C. Law 20-61">D.C. Law 20-61</cite> rewrote (c)(2).</annotation>
        <annotation>The 2015 amendment by <cite doc="D.C. Law 20-271">D.C. Law 20-271</cite> deleted “with recommendations from the Recreation Assistance Board established by § <cite path="§10-306">10-306</cite>” from the end of (d).</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Temporary Legislation</heading>
        <annotation>Section 2 of <cite doc="D.C. Law 17-239">D.C. Law 17-239</cite>, in subsec. (b), designated the existing text as par. (1); and added par. (2) to read as follows:</annotation>
        <annotation>“(2) Proceeds from the Recreation Enterprise Fund may be used to purchase food, snacks, and non-alcoholic beverages for the general public, Department of Parks and Recreation program participants, and District government employees.”.</annotation>
        <annotation>Section 4(b) of <cite doc="D.C. Law 17-239">D.C. Law 17-239</cite> provided that the act shall expire after 225 days of its having taken effect.</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Emergency Legislation</heading>
        <annotation>See Historical and Statutory Notes following § <cite path="§10-301">10-301</cite>.</annotation>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 day) amendment, see § 2 of Recreation Enterprise Fund Emergency Amendment Act of 2008 (D.C. Act 17-425, July 16, 2008,  55 DCR 8246).</annotation>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 day) amendment of section, see § 2 of Recreation Enterprise Fund Congressional Review Emergency Amendment Act of 2008 (D.C. Act 17-549, October 24, 2008,  55 DCR 11981).</annotation>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 day) amendment of section, see § 5091 of Fiscal Year 2010 Budget Support Second Emergency Act of 2009 (D.C. Act 18-207, October 15, 2009,  56 DCR 8234).</annotation>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 day) amendment of section, see § 5091 of Fiscal Year Budget Support Congressional Review Emergency Amendment Act of 2009 (D.C. Act 18-260, January 4, 2010,  57 DCR 345).</annotation>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 day) amendment of section, see § 2 of Department of Parks and Recreation Advertisement Authority Emergency Amendment Act of 2009 (D.C. Act 18-303, January 26, 2010,  57 DCR 1224).</annotation>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 days) amendment of this section, see § 5102 of the Fiscal Year 2014 Budget Support Emergency Act of 2013 (D.C. Act 20-130, July 30, 2013,  60 DCR 11384, 20 DCSTAT 1827).</annotation>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 days) amendment of this section, see § 5102 of the Fiscal Year 2014 Budget Support Congressional Review Emergency Act of 2013 (D.C. Act 20-204, October 17, 2013,  60 DCR 15341, 20 DCSTAT 2311).</annotation>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 days) amendment of this section, see § 259(a) of the New Columbia Statehood Initiative, Omnibus Boards and Commissions, and Election Transition Reform Emergency Amendment Act of 2014 (D.C. Act 20-481, Nov. 18, 2014, 61 DCR 12133, 20 STAT 4405).</annotation>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 days) amendment of this section, see § 259(a) of the New Columbia Statehood Initiative, Omnibus Boards and Commissions, and Election Transition Reform Congressional Review Emergency Amendment Act of 2015 (D.C. Act 21-7, Feb. 26, 2015,  62 DCR 2646, 21 STAT 807).</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Short Title</heading>
        <text>Short title: Section 5090 of <cite doc="D.C. Law 18-111">D.C. Law 18-111</cite> provided that subtitle J of title V of the act may be cited as the “Recreation Enterprise Fund Amendment Act of 2009”.</text>
        <text>Section 5101 of <cite doc="D.C. Law 20-61">D.C. Law 20-61</cite> provided that Subtitle I of Title V of the act may be cited as the “Department of Parks and Recreation O-Type Amendment Act of 2013”.</text>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Editor's Notes</heading>
        <annotation>Applicability of <cite doc="D.C. Law 20-61">D.C. Law 20-61</cite>: Section 11001 of <cite doc="D.C. Law 20-61">D.C. Law 20-61</cite> provided that, except as otherwise provided, the act shall apply as of October 1, 2013.</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section from-code="true">
    <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" path="|10|3"/>
    <num codify:value="10-304">5</num>
    <heading>Park adoptions and sponsorships.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>(a)</num>
      <text>Individuals, associations, corporations, partnerships, neighborhood and civic groups, nonprofit organizations, or other governmental entities may adopt or sponsor Departmental programs, sites, facilities, fields, or operations. The form of such adoption or sponsorship may be made by a donation of funds to the Fund, services, equipment, or any other asset with intrinsic value. The Department may form partnerships with any of the above stated groups to accomplish a stated goal or mission of the Department.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(b)</num>
      <text>The Department shall, within 1 year from March 23, 1995, promulgate regulations appropriate for the full implementation of this chapter including regulations related to park adoptions and sponsorships, vending and concessions fees, and permits.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>History</heading>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 10-246">Mar. 23, 1995, D.C. Law 10-246, § 5, 42 DCR 452</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 11-110">Apr. 18, 1996, D.C. Law 11-110, § 20(b), 43 DCR 530</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 21-68">Feb. 26, 2016, D.C. Law 21-68, § 3, 62 DCR 16266</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Section References</heading>
        <annotation>This section is referenced in § <cite path="§10-303">10-303</cite>.</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Prior Codifications</heading>
        <annotation>1981 Ed., § 8-304.</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Effect of Amendments</heading>
        <annotation>The 2016 amendment by <cite doc="D.C. Law 21-68">D.C. Law 21-68</cite> substituted “neighborhood and civic groups, nonprofit organizations, or other governmental entities may adopt or sponsor Departmental programs, sites, facilities, fields, or operations” for “neighborhood and civic groups or other governmental entities may adopt or sponsor Departmental programs, sites, or operations” in (a).</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Emergency Legislation</heading>
        <annotation>See Historical and Statutory Notes following § <cite path="§10-301">10-301</cite>.</annotation>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 days) amendment of section, see § 3 of the Athletic Field Naming and Sponsorship Emergency Amendment Act of 2015 (D.C. Act 21-201, Nov. 23, 2015,  62 DCR 15274).</annotation>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 days) amendment of this section, see § 3 of the Athletic Field Naming and Sponsorship Congressional Review Emergency Amendment Act of 2016 (D.C. Act 21-302, Feb. 18, 2016,  63 DCR 2171).</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section from-code="true">
    <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" path="|10|3"/>
    <num codify:value="10-305">6</num>
    <heading>Mega recreation centers.</heading>
    <text>The Mayor shall develop, construct, and implement mega recreation centers in strategic locations throughout the District of Columbia. Such centers shall be spacious enough to accommodate several indoor activities simultaneously and contain state of the art equipment and apparatus.</text>
    <annotations>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>History</heading>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 10-246">Mar. 23, 1995, D.C. Law 10-246, § 6, 42 DCR 452</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Prior Codifications</heading>
        <annotation>1981 Ed., § 8-305.</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Emergency Legislation</heading>
        <annotation>See Historical and Statutory Notes following § <cite path="§10-301">10-301</cite>.</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section from-code="true">
    <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" path="|10|3"/>
    <reason>Repealed</reason>
    <num codify:value="10-306">7</num>
    <heading>Establishment of Recreation Assistance Board.</heading>
    <text>Repealed.</text>
    <annotations>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>History</heading>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 10-246">Mar. 23, 1995, D.C. Law 10-246, § 7, 42 DCR 452</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 11-110">Apr. 18, 1996, D.C. Law 11-110, § 20(c), 43 DCR 530</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 12-285">June 12, 1999, D.C. Law 12-285, § 4(l), 46 DCR 1355</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 18-111">Mar. 3, 2010, D.C. Law 18-111, § 2082(k), 57 DCR 181</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 18-356">Apr. 8, 2011, D.C. Law 18-356, § 4, 58 DCR 760</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 20-271">May 2, 2015, D.C. Law 20-271, §§  259(b) and 304(b), 62 DCR 1884</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Section References</heading>
        <annotation>This section is referenced in § <cite path="§10-303">10-303</cite>.</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Prior Codifications</heading>
        <annotation>1981 Ed., § 8-306.</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Effect of Amendments</heading>
        <annotation><cite doc="D.C. Law 18-111">D.C. Law 18-111</cite> rewrote subsec. (a)(6), which had as follows: “(6) The Executive Director of the District of Columbia Sports Commission; and”</annotation>
        <annotation><cite doc="D.C. Law 18-356">D.C. Law 18-356</cite> rewrote subsec. (a)(6), which formerly read:</annotation>
        <annotation>“(6) The Chief Executive Officer and General Manager of the Washington Convention and Sports Authority; and”</annotation>
        <annotation>Section 259(b) of <cite doc="D.C. Law 20-271">D.C. Law 20-271</cite> repealed this section; Section 304(b) of <cite doc="D.C. Law 20-271">D.C. Law 20-271</cite> purported to amend the repealed section.</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Temporary Legislation</heading>
        <annotation>Section 3 of <cite doc="D.C. Law 18-266">D.C. Law 18-266</cite> rewrote subsec. (a)(6) to read as follows:</annotation>
        <annotation>“(6) The President and Chief Executive Officer of the Washington Convention and Sports Authority; and”.</annotation>
        <annotation>Section 5(b) of <cite doc="D.C. Law 18-266">D.C. Law 18-266</cite> provided that the act shall expire after 225 days of its having taken effect.</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Emergency Legislation</heading>
        <annotation>See Historical and Statutory Notes following § <cite path="§10-301">10-301</cite>.</annotation>
        <annotation>For temporary amendment of section, see § 4(l) of the Confirmation Emergency Amendment Act of 1999 (D.C. Act 13-25, March 15, 1999,  46 DCR 2971).</annotation>
        <annotation>Section 6 of D.C. Act 13-25 provides for the application of the act.</annotation>
        <annotation>For temporary (90-day) amendment of section, see § 4(l) of the Confirmation Act Congressional Review Emergency Amendment Act of 1999 (D.C. Act 13-92, June 4, 1999,  46 DCR 5330).</annotation>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 day) amendment of section, see § 2082(k) of Fiscal Year 2010 Budget Support Second Emergency Act of 2009 (D.C. Act 18-207, October 15, 2009,  56 DCR 8234).</annotation>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 day) amendment of section, see § 2082(k) of Fiscal Year Budget Support Congressional Review Emergency Amendment Act of 2009 (D.C. Act 18-260, January 4, 2010,  57 DCR 345).</annotation>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 day) amendment of section, see § 3 of Washington Convention and Sports Authority Emergency Amendment Act of 2010 (D.C. Act 18-504, July 30, 2010,  57 DCR 7578).</annotation>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 day) amendment of section, see § 3 of Washington Convention and Sports Authority Congressional Review Emergency Amendment Act of 2010 (D.C. Act 18-580, October 19, 2010,  57 DCR 10113).</annotation>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 days) repeal of this section, see § 259(b) of the New Columbia Statehood Initiative, Omnibus Boards and Commissions, and Election Transition Reform Emergency Amendment Act of 2014 (D.C. Act 20-481, Nov. 18, 2014, 61 DCR 12133, 20 STAT 4405).</annotation>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 days) amendment of this section, see § 304(b) of the New Columbia Statehood Initiative, Omnibus Boards and Commissions, and Election Transition Reform Emergency Amendment Act of 2014 (D.C. Act 20-481, November 18, 2014, 61 DCR 12133, 20 STAT 4405).</annotation>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 days) repeal of this section, see § 259(b) of the New Columbia Statehood Initiative, Omnibus Boards and Commissions, and Election Transition Reform Congressional Review Emergency Amendment Act of 2015 (D.C. Act 21-7, Feb. 26, 2015,  62 DCR 2646, 21 STAT 807).</annotation>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 days) amendment of this section, see § 304(b) of the New Columbia Statehood Initiative, Omnibus Boards and Commissions, and Election Transition Reform Congressional Review Emergency Amendment Act of 2015 (D.C. Act 21-7, Feb. 26, 2015,  62 DCR 2646, 21 STAT 807).</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>References in Text</heading>
        <annotation>Pursuant to Mayor’s Order 2000-20, the agency formerly known as the Department of Recreation and Parks shall be known as the Department of Parks and Recreation.</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section from-code="true">
    <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" path="|10|3"/>
    <num codify:value="10-307">7a</num>
    <heading>Rules.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>(a)</num>
      <text>The Mayor, pursuant to subchapter I of Chapter 5 of Title 2 [§ <cite path="§2-501">2-501</cite> et seq.], may issue rules to implement the provisions of this chapter. The proposed rules shall be submitted to the Council for a 30-day period of review, excluding Saturdays, Sundays, holidays, and days of Council recess. If the Council does not approve or disapprove the proposed rules, by resolution, within the 30-day review period, the proposed rules shall be deemed approved.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(b)</num>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Within 180 days of April 23, 2013, the Mayor shall issue rules, which shall:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(A)</num>
          <text>Ensure maximum permissible use of Department areas and facilities by appropriate distribution of users, with special attention to the balance of uses between Department programs, community uses, and fee-based uses;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(B)</num>
          <text>Ensure equitable access to fee-based uses through provisions for modest, reduced, or waived fees;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(C)</num>
          <text>Ensure proper, orderly, and equitable use through scheduling;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(D)</num>
          <text>Ensure protection and preservation of areas and facilities by not overtaxing facilities;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(E)</num>
          <text>Promote the health, safety, and welfare of users;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(F)</num>
          <text>Establish clear procedures for obtaining permits and revocation of permits; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(G)</num>
          <text>Update the entire Department fee and permit schedules, maintaining a lower cost for residents.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The authority granted to the Department in § <cite path="§10-302">10-302</cite>(b-1) and (d) and § <cite path="§10-302.01">10-302.01</cite> shall not be exercised until the rules required by paragraph (1) of this subsection have been adopted.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>History</heading>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 10-246">Mar. 23, 1995, D.C. Law 10-246, § 7a</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 19-21">as added Sept. 14, 2011, D.C. Law 19-21, § 6042(d), 58 DCR 6226</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 19-280">Apr. 23, 2013, D.C. Law 19-280, § 2(d), 60 DCR 2124</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 20-216">Mar. 11, 2015, D.C. Law 20-216, § 2, 61 DCR 13104</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Effect of Amendments</heading>
        <annotation>The 2013 amendment by <cite doc="D.C. Law 19-280">D.C. Law 19-280</cite> redesignated the existing paragraph as (a); and added (b).</annotation>
        <annotation>The 2015 amendment by <cite doc="D.C. Law 20-216">D.C. Law 20-216</cite> substituted “§ <cite path="§10-302">10-302</cite>(b-1) and (d) and § <cite path="§10-302.01">10-302.01</cite>” for “§ <cite path="§10-302">10-302</cite>(b-1) and (d), § <cite path="§10-302.01">10-302.01</cite>, and § <cite path="§10-302.02">10-302.02</cite>” in (b)(2).</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Temporary Legislation</heading>
        <annotation>For temporary (225 days) amendment of this section, see § 2 of the Department of Parks and Recreation Feebased Use Permit Authority Clarification Temporary Amendment Act of 2014 (<cite doc="D.C. Law 20-113">D.C. Law 20-113</cite>, June 21, 2014,  61 DCR 4332).</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Emergency Legislation</heading>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 days) amendment of this section, see § 2 of the Department of Parks and Recreation Fee-based Use Permit Authority Clarification Emergency Amendment Act of 2014 (D.C. Act 20-299, March 14, 2014,  61 DCR 2570, 20 DCSTAT 3068).</annotation>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 days) amendment of this section, see §§  2 and 3 of the Department of Parks and Recreation Fee-based Use Permit Authority Clarification Congressional Review Emergency Amendment Act of 2014, (D.C. Act 20-353, June 17, 2014, 61 DCR 6334).</annotation>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 days) amendment of this section, see § 2 of the Department of Parks and Recreation Fee-based Use Permit Authority Clarification Emergency Amendment Act of 2015 (D.C. Act 21-5, Feb. 23, 2015,  62 DCR 2472, 21 STAT 804).</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section from-code="true">
    <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" path="|10|3"/>
    <num codify:value="10-308">7b</num>
    <heading>Athletic Field Permit Coordination Committee.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>(a)</num>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Within 90 days of February 26, 2015, the Department shall establish an Athletic Field Permit Coordination Committee (“Committee”) to advise the Department on how to develop a collaborative permitting system for athletic fields located on property owned by the District of Columbia.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The Committee shall include representatives from the following:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(A)</num>
          <text>The Department;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(B)</num>
          <text>The Department of General Services;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(C)</num>
          <text>The District of Columbia Public Schools;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(D)</num>
          <text>The District of Columbia Public Charter School Board; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(E)</num>
          <text>The National Park Service.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The Department shall assign an employee from the Department to perform duties, including the following:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(A)</num>
          <text>Coordinating and securing a location for Committee meetings;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(B)</num>
          <text>Ensuring administrative support for the Committee, such as circulating meeting notices and keeping meeting minutes; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(C)</num>
          <text>Developing an agenda for meetings and ensuring that the Committee issues the comprehensive report described in subsection (b) of this section.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(b)</num>
      <text>By March 31, 2015, the Committee shall transmit to the Mayor and to the Council, and make publicly available, a comprehensive report containing the following:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>An analysis of public field availability throughout the District;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>An analysis of whether it is feasible to create a singular office for permitting public athletic field space located throughout the District;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>A recommendation of how to proportionately allocate permit revenue to the District government entities whose fields are being used, as opposed to all funds being deposited into the General Fund of the District of Columbia; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>A list of underutilized public fields that the Department, in collaboration with the Department of General Services, may convert to usable and sustainable fields.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(c)</num>
      <text>By March 31, 2016, and each year thereafter, the Committee shall transmit to the Mayor and to the Council, and make publicly available, a report containing the following:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>An update on the progress of the analysis conducted and recommendations provided in previous reports created by the Committee;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Actions taken by the Committee in the preceding year; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Recommendations for methods to develop and provide a collaborative permitting system for athletic fields owned by the District of Columbia.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>History</heading>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 10-246">Mar. 23, 1995, D.C. Law 10-246, § 7b</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 20-155">as added Feb. 26, 2015, D.C. Law 20-155, §  6072, 61 DCR 9990</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Emergency Legislation</heading>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 days) addition of <cite doc="D.C. Law 10-246">D.C. Law 10-246</cite>, § 7b, see §  6082 of the Fiscal Year 2015 Budget Support Emergency Act of 2014 (D.C. Act 20-377, July 14, 2014, 61 DCR 7598, 20 STAT 3696).</annotation>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 days) addition of <cite doc="D.C. Law 10-246">D.C. Law 10-246</cite>, § 7b, see §  6072 of the Fiscal Year 2015 Budget Support Congressional Review Emergency Act of 2014 (D.C. Act 20-449, October 10, 2014, 61 DCR 10915, 20 STAT 4188).</annotation>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 days) addition of <cite doc="D.C. Law 10-246">D.C. Law 10-246</cite>, § 7b, see §  6072 of the Fiscal Year 2015 Budget Support Second Congressional Review Emergency Act of 2014 (D.C. Act 20-566, January 9, 2015, 62 DCR 884, 21 STAT 541).</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
    </annotations>
  </section>
</document>
