<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<document xmlns:codify="http://code.dccouncil.us/schemas/codify" id="D.C. Law 10-42">
  <num type="law">10-42</num>
  <heading type="short">Required Annual Financial Statements and Participation in the NAIC Insurance Regulatory Information System Act of 1993</heading>
  <meta>
    <effective>1993-10-21</effective>
    <cites>
      <law lawId="42" period="10" url="./docs/10-42.pdf"/>
      <register page="6020" vol="40"/>
    </cites>
    <history url="http://lims.dccouncil.us/Legislation/B10-0129">
      <narrative>Law 10-42, the “Required Annual Financial Statements and Participation in the NAIC Insurance Regulatory Information System Act of 1993,” was introduced in Council and assigned Bill No. 10-129, which was referred to the Committee on Consumer and Regulatory Affairs. The Bill was adopted on first and second readings on June 29, 1993, and July 13, 1993, respectively. Signed by the Mayor on August 4, 1993, it was assigned Act No. 10-77 and transmitted to both Houses of Congress for its review. D.C. Law 10-42 became effective on October 21, 1993.</narrative>
    </history>
  </meta>
  <section>
    <num>7</num>
    <para from-code="true" codify:tag="section">
      <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" before="§31-204" path="|31|2"/>
      <reason>Repealed</reason>
      <num codify:value="31-203">(a)</num>
      <heading>Required annual financial statements of companies or associations — Contents; publication.</heading>
      <text>Repealed.</text>
      <annotations>
        <annoGroup>
          <heading>History</heading>
          <annotation doc="D.C. Law 10-42">Oct. 21, 1993, D.C. Law 10-42, § 7(a), 40 DCR 6020</annotation>
        </annoGroup>
        <annoGroup>
          <heading>Section References</heading>
          <annotation>This section is referenced in § <cite path="§31-4901">31-4901</cite>.</annotation>
        </annoGroup>
        <annoGroup>
          <heading>Prior Codifications</heading>
          <annotation>1981 Ed., § 35-103.</annotation>
        </annoGroup>
      </annotations>
    </para>
    <para from-code="true" codify:tag="section">
      <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" before="§31-2502.09" path="|31|25|II"/>
      <reason>Repealed</reason>
      <num codify:value="31-2502.08">(c)</num>
      <heading>Required annual financial statements.</heading>
      <text>Repealed.</text>
      <annotations>
        <annoGroup>
          <heading>History</heading>
          <annotation doc="D.C. Law 10-42">Oct. 21, 1993, D.C. Law 10-42, § 7(c), 40 DCR 6020</annotation>
        </annoGroup>
        <annoGroup>
          <heading>Prior Codifications</heading>
          <annotation>1981 Ed., § 35-1511.</annotation>
        </annoGroup>
      </annotations>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section from-code="true">
    <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" path="|31|19"/>
    <num codify:value="31-1901">2</num>
    <heading>Filing requirements.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>(a)</num>
      <text>Every company or association authorized to transact insurance business in the District shall file annually with the Mayor, before March 1st of each year, a financial statement for the year ending December 31st immediately preceding on forms furnished by the Mayor. The Mayor may extend the time for filing the statement by any company for reasons which the Mayor shall deem sufficient. Such a statement shall be verified by the oath of the president and secretary of the company, or, in their absence, by 2 other principal officers. The Mayor shall annually, in the month of December, furnish to each of the companies and associations authorized to do insurance business in the District forms necessary for filing the annual financial statement required by this section. The forms shall conform substantially to the form of statement adopted by the National Association of Insurance Commissioners (“NAIC”). The filing of these statements shall be in accordance with the NAIC Accounting Practices and Procedures Manual. The Mayor shall have power to make modifications and additions in the financial statement forms as the Mayor may deem necessary to ascertain the condition and affairs of the company. The Mayor may also require that at least once in the month of March in each year a summary of the annual statement by the company be published in a daily newspaper in the District.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(b)</num>
      <text>Each domestic, foreign, and alien insurer authorized to transact insurance in the District shall annually, on or before March 1st of each year, file with the NAIC, and pay the fee established by the NAIC for filing, reviewing, or processing the information, a copy of its annual statement convention form, along with any additional filings prescribed by the Mayor for the preceding year. The information filed with the NAIC shall be in the same format and scope as that required by the Mayor and shall include the signed jurat page and the actuarial certification. Any amendments and addendums to the annual statement filing subsequently filed with the Mayor shall also be filed with the NAIC.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(c)</num>
      <text>Foreign insurers domiciled in a state which has a law substantially similar to subsection (a) of this section shall be deemed in compliance with this section if they file their annual statements in compliance with that jurisdiction’s law.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>History</heading>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 10-42">Oct. 21, 1993, D.C. Law 10-42, § 2, 40 DCR 6020</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Cross References</heading>
        <annotation>Hospital and medical services corporation, additional required reports, see § <cite path="§31-3513">31-3513</cite>.</annotation>
        <annotation>Hospital and medical services corporation, real property investments, see § <cite path="§31-3510">31-3510</cite>.</annotation>
        <annotation>Hospital and medical services corporations, open enrollment statement, see § <cite path="§31-3514">31-3514</cite>.</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Section References</heading>
        <annotation>This section is referenced in § <cite path="§31-303">31-303</cite>, § <cite path="§31-2502.26b">31-2502.26b</cite>, § <cite path="§31-3510">31-3510</cite>, § <cite path="§31-3513">31-3513</cite>, and § <cite path="§31-5031.08">31-5031.08</cite>.</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Prior Codifications</heading>
        <annotation>1981 Ed., § 35-3401.</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Delegation of Authority</heading>
        <annotation>Delegation of authority pursuant to <cite doc="D.C. Law 10-42">D.C. Law 10-42</cite>, the Required Annual Financial Statements and Participation in the NAIC Insurance Regulatory Information System Act of 1993, see Mayor’s Order 94-54, March 7, 1994 ( 41 DCR 1433).</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Editor's Notes</heading>
        <annotation>Mayor authorized to issue rules: Section 6 of <cite doc="D.C. Law 10-42">D.C. Law 10-42</cite> provided that the Mayor shall, pursuant to subchapter I of Chapter 15 of Title 1 [subchapter I of Chapter 5 of Title 2, 2001 Ed.], issue rules to implement the provisions of this chapter.</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section from-code="true">
    <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" path="|31|19"/>
    <num codify:value="31-1902">3</num>
    <heading>Immunity.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>(a)</num>
      <text>In the absence of fraud, actual malice, or bad faith, members of the NAIC, their duly authorized committees, subcommittees, and task forces, their delegates, NAIC employees, and all others, including District employees, charged with the responsibility of collecting, reviewing, analyzing, and disseminating the information developed from the filing of the annual statement convention blanks shall be acting as agents of the Mayor under the authority of this chapter, and shall not be subject to civil liability for libel, slander, or any other cause of action by virtue of their collection, review, and analysis or dissemination of the data and information collected from the filings required by this chapter.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(b)</num>
      <text>Nothing in this section is intended to abrogate or modify in any way any common law or statutory privilege or immunity enjoyed by any person prior to this chapter.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>History</heading>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 10-42">Oct. 21, 1993, D.C. Law 10-42, § 3, 40 DCR 6020</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Prior Codifications</heading>
        <annotation>1981 Ed., § 35-3402.</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section from-code="true">
    <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" path="|31|19"/>
    <num codify:value="31-1903">4</num>
    <heading>Confidentiality.</heading>
    <text>All financial analysis ratios and examination synopses and related information concerning insurance companies that are submitted to the Mayor by the NAIC Insurance Regulatory Information System are confidential and may not be disclosed by the Mayor or any member of the Department of Insurance, Securities, and Banking. This information shall not be subject to disclosure under the District of Columbia Freedom of Information Act or any other District law relating to disclosure of information.</text>
    <annotations>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>History</heading>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 10-42">Oct. 21, 1993, D.C. Law 10-42, § 4, 40 DCR 6020</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 11-268">May 21, 1997, D.C. Law 11-268, § 10(dd), 44 DCR 1730</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 15-166">June 11, 2004, D.C. Law 15-166, § 4(k), 51 DCR 2817</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Prior Codifications</heading>
        <annotation>1981 Ed., § 35-3403.</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Effect of Amendments</heading>
        <annotation><cite doc="D.C. Law 15-166">D.C. Law 15-166</cite> substituted “Department of Insurance, Securities, and Banking” for “Department of Insurance and Securities Regulation”.</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Emergency Legislation</heading>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 day) amendment of section, see § 4(k) of Consolidation of Financial Services Emergency Amendment Act of 2004 (D.C. Act 15-381, February 27, 2004,  51 DCR 2653).</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>References in Text</heading>
        <annotation>The “District of Columbia Freedom of Information Act,” referred to in this section, is <cite doc="D.C. Law 1-96">D.C. Law 1-96</cite>, codified at § <cite path="§2-531">2-531</cite> et seq.</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section from-code="true">
    <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" path="|31|19"/>
    <num codify:value="31-1904">5</num>
    <heading>Revocation of Certificate of Authority.</heading>
    <text>The Mayor may fine insurance companies or suspend, revoke, or refuse to renew the Certificate of Authority of any insurer failing to file its annual statement when due or within any extension of time which the Mayor, for good cause, may have granted.</text>
    <annotations>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>History</heading>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 10-42">Oct. 21, 1993, D.C. Law 10-42, § 5, 40 DCR 6020</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Prior Codifications</heading>
        <annotation>1981 Ed., § 35-3404.</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
    </annotations>
  </section>
</document>
