<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<document xmlns:codify="http://code.dccouncil.us/schemas/codify" id="D.C. Law 13-172">
  <num type="law">13-172</num>
  <heading type="short">Fiscal Year 2001 Budget Support Act of 2000</heading>
  <meta>
    <effective>2000-10-19</effective>
    <cites>
      <law lawId="172" period="13" url="./docs/13-172.pdf"/>
      <register page="6308" vol="47"/>
    </cites>
    <history url="http://lims.dccouncil.us/Legislation/B13-0679">
      <narrative>Law 13-172, the “Fiscal Year 2001 Budget Support Act of 2000,” was introduced in Council and assigned Bill No. 13-679, which was referred to the Committee of the Whole. The Bill was adopted on first and second readings on May 18, 2000, and June 6, 2000, respectively. Signed by the Mayor on June 26, 2000, it was assigned Act No. 13-375 and transmitted to both Houses of Congress for its review. D.C. Law 13-172 became effective on October 19, 2000.</narrative>
    </history>
  </meta>
  <section from-code="true">
    <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" path="|42|36|I"/>
    <num codify:value="42-3601">1302</num>
    <heading>Definitions.</heading>
    <text>For the purposes of this subchapter, the term:</text>
    <para>
      <num>(1)</num>
      <text>“Civic association” means:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(A)</num>
        <text>A nonprofit association, corporation, or other organization that is:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(i)</num>
          <text>Comprised of residents of a community within which a nuisance is located;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(ii)</num>
          <text>Operated exclusively for the promotion of social welfare and general neighborhood improvement and enhancement; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(iii)</num>
          <text>Exempt from taxation under § 501(c)(3) or (4) of the Internal Revenue Code; or</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(B)</num>
        <text>A nonprofit association, corporation, or other organization that is:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(i)</num>
          <text>Comprised of residents of a contiguous community that is defined by specific geographic boundaries, within which a nuisance is located; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(ii)</num>
          <text>Operated for the promotion of the welfare, improvement, and enhancement of that community.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(2)</num>
      <text>“Closure” means the closing of a rental unit or housing accommodation.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(3)</num>
      <text>“Community association” means:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(A)</num>
        <text>A nonprofit association, corporation, or other organization that is:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(i)</num>
          <text>Comprised of residents of a community within which a nuisance is located;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(ii)</num>
          <text>Operated exclusively for the promotion of social welfare and general neighborhood improvement and enhancement; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(iii)</num>
          <text>Exempt from taxation under § 501(c)(3) or (4) of the Internal Revenue Code; or</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(B)</num>
        <text>A nonprofit association, corporation, or other organization that is:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(i)</num>
          <text>Comprised of residents of a contiguous community that is defined by specific geographic boundaries, within which a nuisance is located; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(ii)</num>
          <text>Operated for the promotion of the welfare, improvement, and enhancement of that community.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(4)</num>
      <text>“Controlled dangerous substance” means any of the controlled dangerous substances as defined in § <cite path="§48-901.02">48-901.02</cite>(4).</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(5)</num>
      <text>“Controlled Substances Act” means the Controlled Substances Act of 1970, approved October 27, 1970 (84 Stat. 1243; 21 U.S.C. § 801 et seq.).</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(6)</num>
      <text>“Court” means the Landlord and Tenant Branch of the Civil Division of the Superior Court.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(7)</num>
      <text>“District” means the District of Columbia.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(8)</num>
      <text>“Drug haven” means a housing accommodation, or land appurtenant to or common areas of a housing accommodation where drugs are illegally stored, manufactured, used, or distributed.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(9)</num>
      <text>“Drug-related eviction” means an eviction pursuant to this subchapter.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(10)</num>
      <text>“Drug” means a controlled substance as defined in § <cite path="§33-504">33-504</cite>(4) [repealed] or the Controlled Substances Act.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(11)</num>
      <text>“Housing accommodation” means a building that is or contains at least one rental unit and the land appurtenant to the building.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(12)</num>
      <text>“Housing provider” means:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(A)</num>
        <text>A landlord, owner, lessor, sublessor, or assignee;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(B)</num>
        <text>The agent of a landlord, owner, lessor, sublessor, or assignee; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(C)</num>
        <text>A person entitled to receive compensation for the use or occupancy of a rental unit within a housing accommodation.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(13)</num>
      <text>“Internal Revenue Code” means the Internal Revenue Code of 1986, approved October 22, 1986 (100 Stat. 2085; 26 U.S.C. § 1 et seq.).</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(14)</num>
      <text>“Manufacture” shall have the same meaning as that term has in § <cite path="§48-901.02">48-901.02</cite>(13) or the Controlled Substances Act.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(15)</num>
      <text>“Nuisance” means a property that is used:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(A)</num>
        <text>By persons who assemble for the specific purpose of illegally using a controlled dangerous substance;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(B)</num>
        <text>For the illegal manufacture or distribution of:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(i)</num>
          <text>A controlled dangerous substance; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(ii)</num>
          <text>Drug paraphernalia, as defined in § <cite path="§48-1101">48-1101</cite>(3); or</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(C)</num>
        <text>For the illegal storage or concealment of a controlled dangerous substance in sufficient quantity to reasonably indicate under all the circumstances an intent to manufacture, distribute, or dispense:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(i)</num>
          <text>A controlled dangerous substance; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(ii)</num>
          <text>Drug paraphernalia, as defined in § <cite path="§48-1101">48-1101</cite>(3).</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(16)</num>
      <text>“Occupant” means a person authorized by the tenant or housing provider to be on the premises of the rental unit.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(17)</num>
      <text>“Rental unit” means an apartment, room, or part of a publicly or privately owned housing accommodation that is rented or offered for rent for residential occupancy, and the land appurtenant to the apartment, room, or part of the housing accommodation.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(18)</num>
      <text>“Resident association” means an organization of residents of a multifamily building or a single complex of jointly managed multifamily buildings.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(19)</num>
      <text>“Tenant” means a lessee, sublessee, or other person entitled to the possession or occupancy of a rental unit.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(20)</num>
      <text>“Uniform Controlled Substances Act” means Chapter 9 of Title 48.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>History</heading>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 13-172">Oct. 19, 2000, D.C. Law 13-172, § 1302, 47 DCR 6308</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 13-281">Apr. 27, 2001, D.C. Law 13-281, § 107, 48 DCR 1888</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 14-213">Oct. 19, 2002, D.C. Law 14-213, § 32(b), 49 DCR 8140</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Effect of Amendments</heading>
        <annotation><cite doc="D.C. Law 13-281">D.C. Law 13-281</cite> rewrote par. (4) which had read:</annotation>
        <annotation>“(4) ‘Controlled dangerous substance’ means any of the controlled substances as defined in § <cite path="§48-902.04">48-902.04</cite>(1) and (2).”</annotation>
        <annotation><cite doc="D.C. Law 14-213">D.C. Law 14-213</cite>, in par. (4), validated a previously made technical correction.</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Emergency Legislation</heading>
        <annotation>For temporary (90-day) addition of section, see § 1302 of the Fiscal Year 2001 Budget Support Emergency Act of 2000 (D.C. Act 13-376, July 24, 2000,  47 DCR 6574).</annotation>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 day) amendment of section, see § 1302 of the Fiscal Year 2001 Budget Support Congressional Review Emergency Act of 2000 (D.C. Act 13-438, October 20, 2000,  47 DCR 8740).</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>References in Text</heading>
        <annotation>Section 33-504, referred to in par. (10), did not exist in the 1981 Edition at the time of the recodification into the 2001 Edition.</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section from-code="true">
    <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" path="|42|36|I"/>
    <num codify:value="42-3602">1303</num>
    <heading>Action for possession of rental unit used as a drug haven.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>(a)</num>
      <text>Notwithstanding any provision of § <cite path="§16-1501">16-1501</cite>, or § <cite path="§42-3505.01">42-3505.01</cite>, a housing provider may commence an action in the Court to recover possession of a rental unit or the Mayor may commence an action in the Court to evict a tenant or occupant in a rental unit. The following persons may commence an action to abate a nuisance in the Court: the Mayor, the United States Attorney for the District of Columbia, the civic association within whose boundaries the nuisance is located, or the community association within whose boundaries the nuisance is located. The recovery or eviction shall be ordered if the Court has determined, by a preponderance of the evidence, that the rental unit is a drug haven or that a nuisance exists. In making the determination that the rental unit is a drug haven or that a nuisance exists, the Court shall consider:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Whether a tenant or occupant of the rental unit has been charged with a violation of the Uniform Controlled Substances Act or the Controlled Substances Act due to activities that occurred within the housing accommodation that contains the rental unit, or has violated a term of parole or probation for a previous conviction under the Uniform Controlled Substances Act or the Controlled Substances Act;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Whether the rental unit has been the subject of more than one drug-related search or seizure that has resulted in the arrest of a tenant or occupant;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Whether a firearm has been discharged within the rental unit;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The testimony of a witness concerning the possession, manufacture, storage, distribution, use, or the attempted possession, manufacture, storage, distribution, or use of an illegal drug by a tenant or occupant in the housing accommodation that contains the rental unit;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>The general reputation of the property to corroborate testimony based on personal knowledge or observation, or evidence seized during the execution of a search and seizure warrant; provided, that this shall not, in and of itself, be sufficient to establish the existence of a drug haven or nuisance;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Evidence that the drug haven or nuisance had been discontinued at the time of the filing of the complaint or at the time of the hearing, which evidence will not bar the granting of appropriate relief by the Court; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>Any other relevant and admissible evidence that demonstrates that the rental unit is or is not a drug haven or nuisance.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(b)</num>
      <text>A notice of the action shall be served upon the tenant or occupant and housing provider at least 5 days prior to a hearing.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>History</heading>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 13-172">Oct. 19, 2000, D.C. Law 13-172, § 1303, 47 DCR 6308</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Section References</heading>
        <annotation>This section is referenced in § <cite path="§42-3603">42-3603</cite>, § <cite path="§42-3604">42-3604</cite>, and § <cite path="§42-3606">42-3606</cite>.</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Emergency Legislation</heading>
        <annotation>For temporary (90-day) addition of section, see § 1303 of the Fiscal Year 2001 Budget Support Emergency Act of 2000 (D.C. Act 13-376, July 24, 2000,  47 DCR 6574).</annotation>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 day) amendment of section, see § 1303 of the Fiscal Year 2001 Budget Support Congressional Review Emergency Act of 2000 (D.C. Act 13-438, October 20, 2000,  47 DCR 8740).</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section from-code="true">
    <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" path="|42|36|I"/>
    <num codify:value="42-3603">1304</num>
    <heading>Preliminary injunction review.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>(a)</num>
      <text>After commencement of an action under § <cite path="§42-3602">42-3602</cite> and upon request of a party, the Court shall hold a hearing to determine if a preliminary injunction should be granted to prevent a tenant from directly or indirectly maintaining a drug haven or nuisance.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(b)</num>
      <text>The Court may grant a motion for a preliminary injunction if the plaintiff meets the necessary legal requirements for a preliminary injunction. The factors that the Court shall consider in determining whether the plaintiff is entitled to a preliminary injunction are:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Whether the plaintiff is likely to prevail on the merits of the case;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Whether, in the absence of relief, the plaintiff will suffer irreparable harm;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Whether there will be substantial harm to the defendant or another party if relief is granted; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Whether the public interest favors granting relief.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(c)</num>
      <text>The housing provider and the Mayor shall not be required to give bond to obtain an injunction.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>History</heading>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 13-172">Oct. 19, 2000, D.C. Law 13-172, § 1304, 47 DCR 6308</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Section References</heading>
        <annotation>This section is referenced in § <cite path="§42-3606">42-3606</cite>.</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Emergency Legislation</heading>
        <annotation>For temporary (90-day) addition of section, see § 1304 of the Fiscal Year 2001 Budget Support Emergency Act of 2000 (D.C. Act 13-376, July 24, 2000,  47 DCR 6574).</annotation>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 day) amendment of section, see § 1304 of the Fiscal Year 2001 Budget Support Congressional Review Emergency Act of 2000 (D.C. Act 13-438, October 20, 2000,  47 DCR 8740).</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section from-code="true">
    <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" path="|42|36|I"/>
    <num codify:value="42-3604">1305</num>
    <heading>Full hearing.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>(a)</num>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Within 10 days of the issuance of the preliminary injunction, excluding Saturdays, Sundays, and legal holidays, the Court shall hold a full hearing on the merits of the eviction action. If a hearing for a preliminary injunction has not been requested, the Court shall expeditiously schedule a full hearing. If it is determined by a preponderance of the evidence, after consideration of the factors set forth in § <cite path="§42-3602">42-3602</cite>, that the rental unit is a drug haven, the Court shall issue a final order that mandates one or more of the following:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(A)</num>
          <text>Eviction of the tenant or occupant within 72 hours; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(B)</num>
          <text>Closure of the rental unit for a period of time to be decided by the Court.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The Court may order the owner of the property to submit for court approval a plan of correction to ensure, to the extent reasonably possible, that the property will not again be used for a drug haven or nuisance.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(b)</num>
      <text>Execution of a final order shall occur within 5 days of the issuance of the final order, excluding Saturdays, Sundays, and legal holidays. If the United States Marshal of the District of Columbia has not executed the final order within 5 days of issuance of the final order, the final order shall continue to be executable and valid, in accordance with Rule 16(a) of the Court Rules of Civil Procedure.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(c)</num>
      <text>The Court shall not enter a final order to evict a tenant or occupant against whom the action was filed if the tenant or occupant shows by a preponderance of the evidence that the events or actions upon which the judgment may be granted:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Could not reasonably have been known to the tenant or occupant;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Were not part of a pattern and practice of the tenant or occupant of the unit; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Were reported to the Metropolitan Police Department by the tenant or occupant.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>History</heading>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 13-172">Oct. 19, 2000, D.C. Law 13-172, § 1305, 47 DCR 6308</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Emergency Legislation</heading>
        <annotation>For temporary (90-day) addition of section, see § 1305 of the Fiscal Year 2001 Budget Support Emergency Act of 2000 (D.C. Act 13-376, July 24, 2000,  47 DCR 6574).</annotation>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 day) amendment of section, see § 1305 of the Fiscal Year 2001 Budget Support Congressional Review Emergency Act of 2000 (D.C. Act 13-438, October 20, 2000,  47 DCR 8740).</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section from-code="true">
    <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" path="|42|36|I"/>
    <num codify:value="42-3605">1306</num>
    <heading>Default judgment.</heading>
    <text>The Court shall not enter a default judgment to evict a tenant or occupant who has failed to plead or otherwise defend unless, based upon evidence presented by the plaintiff, the Court determines that the rental unit is a drug haven or nuisance.</text>
    <annotations>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>History</heading>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 13-172">Oct. 19, 2000, D.C. Law 13-172, § 1306, 47 DCR 6308</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Emergency Legislation</heading>
        <annotation>For temporary (90-day) addition of section, see § 1306 of the Fiscal Year 2001 Budget Support Emergency Act of 2000 (D.C. Act 13-376, July 24, 2000,  47 DCR 6574).</annotation>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 day) amendment of section, see § 1306 of the Fiscal Year 2001 Budget Support Congressional Review Emergency Act of 2000 (D.C. Act 13-438, October 20, 2000,  47 DCR 8740).</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section from-code="true">
    <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" path="|42|36|I"/>
    <num codify:value="42-3606">1307</num>
    <heading>Complaint by affected tenant or resident association.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>(a)</num>
      <text>To initiate an action pursuant to § <cite path="§42-3602">42-3602</cite>, an affected tenant, resident, or resident association may submit a petition accompanied by a complaint for review by the Mayor. The housing provider may be named as party plaintiff in the petition. The review of the petition by the Mayor shall be completed within 7 days of receipt of the petition.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(b)</num>
      <text>The petition shall set forth the following:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The date and time the affected tenant, resident, or resident association witnessed the possession, manufacture, storage, distribution, use, or attempted possession, manufacture, storage, distribution, or use of an illegal drug in the rental unit by a tenant or occupant;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The name, address, and telephone number of any corroborating witness; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Any other information relevant to the petition that can be verified by a named witness or independent authority, including the Metropolitan Police Department.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(c)</num>
      <text>If, upon review, the Mayor determines that a petition and complaint are complete, the affected tenant, resident, or resident association may file the complaint with the Court to commence an action pursuant to § <cite path="§42-3602">42-3602</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(d)</num>
      <text>The Court shall proceed to consider the complaint under §§ <cite path="§42-3602">42-3602</cite> and <cite path="§42-3603">42-3603</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>History</heading>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 13-172">Oct. 19, 2000, D.C. Law 13-172, § 1307, 47 DCR 6308</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Emergency Legislation</heading>
        <annotation>For temporary (90-day) addition of section, see § 1307 of the Fiscal Year 2001 Budget Support Emergency Act of 2000 (D.C. Act 13-376, July 24, 2000,  47 DCR 6574).</annotation>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 day) amendment of section, see § 1307 of the Fiscal Year 2001 Budget Support Congressional Review Emergency Act of 2000 (D.C. Act 13-438, October 20, 2000,  47 DCR 8740).</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section from-code="true">
    <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" path="|42|36|I"/>
    <num codify:value="42-3607">1308</num>
    <heading>Mayor’s authority and responsibility.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>(a)</num>
      <text>The Mayor shall establish within the Metropolitan Police Department a division to provide assistance to, supervision of, or protection to a plaintiff who has obtained an eviction order or other relief pursuant to this subchapter.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(b)</num>
      <text>The Mayor shall report to the Council on an annual basis on the effectiveness of this subchapter.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>History</heading>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 13-172">Oct. 19, 2000, D.C. Law 13-172, § 1308, 47 DCR 6308</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Emergency Legislation</heading>
        <annotation>For temporary (90-day) addition of section, see § 1308 of the Fiscal Year 2001 Budget Support Emergency Act of 2000 (D.C. Act 13-376, July 24, 2000,  47 DCR 6574).</annotation>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 day) amendment of section, see § 1308 of the Fiscal Year 2001 Budget Support Congressional Review Emergency Act of 2000 (D.C. Act 13-438, October 20, 2000,  47 DCR 8740).</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Delegation of Authority</heading>
        <annotation>Delegation of Authority Pursuant to <cite doc="D.C. Law 13-172">D.C. Law 13-172</cite>, the Residential Drug-Related Evictions Re-enactment Act of 2000, see Mayor’s Order 2006-206, December 30, 2005  53 DCR 2701).</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section from-code="true">
    <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" path="|42|36|I"/>
    <num codify:value="42-3608">1309</num>
    <heading>Court costs and attorney’s fees.</heading>
    <text>The Court may award court costs and reasonable attorney’s fees to a civic association, community association, or resident association that is the prevailing plaintiff in an action brought under this subchapter.</text>
    <annotations>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>History</heading>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 13-172">Oct. 19, 2000, D.C. Law 13-172, § 1309, 47 DCR 6308</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Emergency Legislation</heading>
        <annotation>For temporary (90-day) addition of section, see § 1309 of the Fiscal Year 2001 Budget Support Emergency Act of 2000 (D.C. Act 13-376, July 24, 2000,  47 DCR 6574).</annotation>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 day) amendment of section, see § 1309 of the Fiscal Year 2001 Budget Support Congressional Review Emergency Act of 2000 (D.C. Act 13-438, October 20, 2000,  47 DCR 8740).</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section from-code="true">
    <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" path="|42|36|I"/>
    <num codify:value="42-3609">1310</num>
    <heading>Availability of other remedies.</heading>
    <text>The provisions of this subchapter shall not limit the availability of other remedies under law or other equitable relief whether or not an adequate remedy exists at law.</text>
    <annotations>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>History</heading>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 13-172">Oct. 19, 2000, D.C. Law 13-172, § 1310, 47 DCR 6308</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Emergency Legislation</heading>
        <annotation>For temporary (90-day) addition of section, see § 1310 of the Fiscal Year 2001 Budget Support Emergency Act of 2000 (D.C. Act 13-376, July 24, 2000,  47 DCR 6574).</annotation>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 day) amendment of section, see § 1310 of the Fiscal Year 2001 Budget Support Congressional Review Emergency Act of 2000 (D.C. Act 13-438, October 20, 2000,  47 DCR 8740).</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section from-code="true">
    <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" path="|42|36|I"/>
    <num codify:value="42-3610">1311</num>
    <heading>Rules.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>(a)</num>
      <text>The Mayor shall issue proposed rules to implement the provisions of this subchapter. The proposed rules shall be submitted to the Council for a 45-day period of review, excluding Saturdays, Sundays, legal holidays, and days of Council recess. If the Council does not approve or disapprove the proposed rules, in whole or in part, by resolution within this 45-day review period, the proposed rules shall be deemed approved. Nothing in this section shall affect any requirements imposed upon the Mayor by subchapter I of Chapter 5 of Title 2.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(b)</num>
      <text>The Mayor may issue emergency rules without prior Council approval, which shall be effective for not more than 120 days.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>History</heading>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 13-172">Oct. 19, 2000, D.C. Law 13-172, § 1311, 47 DCR 6308</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Emergency Legislation</heading>
        <annotation>For temporary (90-day) addition of section, see § 1311 of the Fiscal Year 2001 Budget Support Emergency Act of 2000 (D.C. Act 13-376, July 24, 2000,  47 DCR 6574).</annotation>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 day) amendment of section, see § 1311 of the Fiscal Year 2001 Budget Support Congressional Review Emergency Act of 2000 (D.C. Act 13-438, October 20, 2000,  47 DCR 8740).</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Resolutions</heading>
        <annotation>Resolution 16-614, the “Residential Drug-Related Evictions Regulations Approval Resolution of 2006”, was approved effective April 18, 2006.</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section from-code="true">
    <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" path="|7|18|III"/>
    <num codify:value="7-1831.01">3702</num>
    <heading>Definitions.</heading>
    <text>For the purposes of this subchapter, the term:</text>
    <para>
      <num>(1)</num>
      <text>“Bonds” means the taxable or tax-exempt revenue bonds, notes, or other  obligations (including refunding bonds, notes, and other obligations), which may be issued on a senior or subordinate basis and would include any instrument evidencing the Corporation’s obligations relating to the Residual Interest, authorized to be issued by the Corporation pursuant to this subchapter.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(2)</num>
      <text>“Corporation” means the District of Columbia Tobacco Settlement Financing Corporation established by § <cite path="§7-1831.03">7-1831.03</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(3)</num>
      <text>“District” means the District of Columbia.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(4)</num>
      <text>“Master Settlement Agreement” means the settlement agreement (and related documents), as may be amended from time to time, entered into on November 23, 1998 by the District and leading United States tobacco product manufacturers.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(5)</num>
      <text>“Purchase Agreement” means a contract, as authorized under § <cite path="§7-1831.03">7-1831.03</cite>, between the Corporation and the District, under which the District sells to the Corporation all of the District’s right, title, and interest in and to the Master Settlement Agreement, including all the moneys, and any interest thereon, payable to or received by the District thereunder (except for the first payment of $16.05 million which has already been received by the District), in exchange for a cash payment from the net proceeds of the sale of the Bonds (other than the Residual Bond), the Residual Bond, and the agreement of the Corporation to repay certain indebtedness of the District.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(5A)</num>
      <text>“Remainder Certificate” means a certificate evidencing an interest in the payments to be made under the Residual Bond after payment in full of all outstanding Bonds secured thereby.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(6)</num>
      <text>“Residual Bond” means a Bond evidencing the Residual Interest.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(6A)</num>
      <text>“Residual Bond Purchase Agreement” means a contract, as authorized under § <cite path="§7-1831.03">7-1831.03</cite>, between the Corporation and the Fund, under which the Fund sells to the Corporation all or a portion of the Fund’s right, title, and interest in and to the Residual Bond, including all the moneys, and any interest thereon, payable to or received by the Fund thereunder, in exchange for a cash payment from the net proceeds of the sale of the Bonds (other than the Residual Bond) and the Remainder Certificate, if any.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(7)</num>
      <text>“Residual Interest” means that portion of any payments received by the Corporation under the Master Settlement Agreement which is not annually required to:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(A)</num>
        <text>Defease certain indebtedness of the District pursuant to the provisions of the Purchase Agreement;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(B)</num>
        <text>Repay the holders of the Bonds (other than the Residual Bond);</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(C)</num>
        <text>Establish, maintain, or replenish any reserve funds created in connection with the issuance of the Bonds (other than the Residual Bond);</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(D)</num>
        <text>Pay any other obligations of the Corporation (other than the Residual Bond) incurred in connection with the issuance of the Bonds; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(E)</num>
        <text>Pay the actual, reasonable, and necessary expenses of the Corporation.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>History</heading>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 13-172">Oct. 19, 2000, D.C. Law 13-172, § 3702, 47 DCR 6308</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 16-142">July 25, 2006, D.C. Law 16-142, § 3(a), 53 DCR 4412</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Section References</heading>
        <annotation>This section is referenced in § <cite path="§7-1811.01">7-1811.01</cite>.</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Effect of Amendments</heading>
        <annotation><cite doc="D.C. Law 16-142">D.C. Law 16-142</cite>, in par. (1), substituted “obligations), which may be issued on a senior or subordinate basis and would include” for “obligations), which would include”; and added pars. (5A) and (6A).</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Emergency Legislation</heading>
        <annotation>For temporary (90-day) addition of §§ <cite path="§7-1831.01">7-1831.01</cite> to 7-1831.06, see §§ 3702 to 3707 of the Fiscal Year 2001 Budget Support Emergency Act of 2000 (D.C. Act 13-376, July 24, 2000,  47 DCR 6574).</annotation>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 day) amendment of section, see §§ 3702 to 3707 of the Fiscal Year 2001 Budget Support Congressional Review Emergency Act of 2000 (D.C. Act 13-438, October 20, 2000,  47 DCR 8740).</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section from-code="true">
    <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" path="|7|18|III"/>
    <num codify:value="7-1831.02">3703</num>
    <heading>Sale of rights under Master Settlement Agreement.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>(a)</num>
      <text>For the purpose of financing the costs of the National Capital Medical Center, healthcare related issues, or other capital projects, and the repayment of outstanding indebtedness issued for certain capital projects and other undertakings of the District, the District may sell to the Corporation all of the District’s right, title, and interest in and to the Master Settlement Agreement, including all the moneys, and any interest thereon, payable to or received by the District thereunder (except for the first payment of $16.05 million which has already been received by the District), in exchange for: (1) a cash payment in the amount of the net sales proceeds of the Bonds (other than the Residual Bond); (2) the Residual Bond; and (3) the agreement of the Corporation to repay certain indebtedness of the District.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(b)</num>
      <text>Subject to the authorization and restrictions of this subchapter, the terms and conditions of the Purchase Agreement or the Residual Bond Purchase Agreement shall be determined by the Mayor, which determination shall be conclusively evidenced by his execution of the Purchase Agreement or the Residual Bond Purchase Agreement. The Mayor may execute and deliver any administrative or other documents or agreements which are necessary or desirable relating to the sale of the District’s right, title, and interest in and to the Master Settlement Agreement or in connection with the issuance of the Bonds. Proceeds from the sale of the Bonds and other moneys received by the Corporation pursuant to the Purchase Agreement or the Residual Bond Purchase Agreement will be used to repay certain outstanding indebtedness of the District, to finance or refinance the National Capital Medical Center, healthcare related issues, or other capital projects or undertakings of the District, as well as to pay costs of issuance of the Bonds, to establish and fund reserve funds, and to pay other expenses and fees related to the issuance of the Bonds.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(c)</num>
      <text>For the purpose of financing the costs of the National Capital Medical Center, healthcare related issues, or other capital projects, and repayment of outstanding indebtedness issued for certain capital projects and other undertakings of the District, the Fund may sell to the Corporation all of the Fund’s right, title, and interest in and to the Residual Bond, including all the moneys, and any interest thereon, payable to or received by the Fund thereunder, in exchange for:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A cash payment in the amount of the net sales proceeds of Bonds secured by the Residual Bond; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The Remainder Certificate, if any.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>History</heading>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 13-172">Oct. 19, 2000, D.C. Law 13-172, § 3703, 47 DCR 6308</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 16-142">July 25, 2006, D.C. Law 16-142, § 3(b), 53 DCR 4412</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 17-353">Mar. 25, 2009, D.C. Law 17-353, § 120, 56 DCR 1117</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Section References</heading>
        <annotation>This section is referenced in § <cite path="§7-1811.01">7-1811.01</cite>, § <cite path="§7-1811.03">7-1811.03</cite>, and § <cite path="§7-1831.03">7-1831.03</cite>.</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Effect of Amendments</heading>
        <annotation><cite doc="D.C. Law 16-142">D.C. Law 16-142</cite>, in subsec. (a), substituted “For the purpose of financing the costs of the National Capital Medical Center, healthcare related issues, or other capital projects, and the repayment” for “For the purpose of the repayment”; in subsec. (b), substituted “Purchase Agreement or the Residual Bond Purchase Agreement” for “Purchase Agreement” and substituted “indebtedness of the District, to finance or refinance the National Capital Medical Center, healthcare related issues, or other capital projects or undertakings of the District,” for “indebtedness of the District”; and added subsec. (b-1).</annotation>
        <annotation><cite doc="D.C. Law 17-353">D.C. Law 17-353</cite> redesignated subsec. (b-1) as subsec. (c).</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Emergency Legislation</heading>
        <annotation>For temporary (90-day) addition of section, see notes following § <cite path="§7-1831.01">7-1831.01</cite>.</annotation>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 day) amendment of section, see §§ 3702 to 3707 of the Fiscal Year 2001 Budget Support Congressional Review Emergency Act of 2000 (D.C. Act 13-438, October 20, 2000,  47 DCR 8740).</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section from-code="true">
    <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" path="|7|18|III"/>
    <num codify:value="7-1831.03">3704</num>
    <heading>Establishment of the District of Columbia Tobacco Settlement Financing Corporation; powers and authority.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>(a)</num>
      <text>The District of Columbia Tobacco Settlement Financing Corporation is established as a special purpose, independent instrumentality of the District government. The Corporation shall be a corporate body, intended, created, and empowered to effectuate the purposes stated in this subchapter, and shall have a legal existence separate from the District government.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(b)</num>
      <text>The purpose of the Corporation is to purchase all of the District’s right, title, and interest in the Master Settlement Agreement, including all the moneys, and any interest thereon, payable to or received by the District thereunder (except for the first payment of $16.05 million which has already been received by the District) and the Residual Bond, issuing Bonds to pay the purchase price therefor, and to repay certain of the outstanding indebtedness of the District issued for capital projects and other undertakings. The Corporation may enter into the Purchase Agreement or the Residual Bond Purchase Agreement  and may perform any acts necessary or convenient to effectuate its purposes, including financing the costs of the National Capital Medical Center indebtedness of the District, to finance or refinance the National Capital Medical Center, healthcare related issues, or other capital projects or undertakings of the District, or other capital projects, repayment, refinancing, or defeasance of certain indebtedness issued for capital projects and other undertakings.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(c)</num>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Pursuant to § <cite path="§1-204.90">1-204.90</cite>, subject to the restrictions of this subchapter, the Council delegates to the Corporation the power to issue revenue bonds, notes, and other obligations, including refunding revenue bonds at or before maturity, to finance or refinance, or assist in the financing or refinancing of the National Capital Medical Center, healthcare  related issues, or other capital projects or undertakings of the District, which obligations shall be payable solely from, and secured by, the payments under the Master Settlement Agreement sold under § <cite path="§7-1831.02">7-1831.02</cite>, including the power to provide for the authorization, securing, sale, and issuance of the Bonds consistent with this subchapter. This delegation is not exclusive and does not restrict, impair, or supersede the authority otherwise vested by law in any District instrumentality.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <para>
          <num>(A)</num>
          <text>The Corporation, by resolution of its board, may authorize the issuance of the Bonds. The resolution may stipulate the terms of the Bonds, including the following:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>The date a Bond bears;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>The date a Bond matures and, if different, such other date on which a Bond may be paid;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Whether Bonds are issued as serial bonds, term bonds, or as a combination of the two;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iv)</num>
            <text>The denominations;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(v)</num>
            <text>The interest rate or rates, or variable rate or rates changing from time to time, as provided in, or determined pursuant to, authorization under the resolution;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(vi)</num>
            <text>The method and terms of sale;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(vii)</num>
            <text>The method for payment;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(viii)</num>
            <text>Security for the Bonds;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ix)</num>
            <text>The terms of redemption;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(x)</num>
            <text>The establishment of reserves and debt service funds and the use of proceeds of the Bonds for costs of issuance and otherwise in accordance with this subchapter; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(xi)</num>
            <text>Any other terms which, in the opinion of the board or its advisors, may be necessary or desirable for the sale of the Bonds.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(B)</num>
          <text>The resolution authorizing the issuance of the Bonds shall include a statement as to:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Whether the Bonds are intended to be sold by competitive bid or by negotiated sale and, if the Bonds are intended to be sold by negotiated sale, a statement of the reasons that sale by competitive bid is not feasible or is not in the best interests of the Corporation;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Whether the Bonds are intended to be issued on a tax-exempt or taxable basis; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Whether the Bonds are intended to be issued on a senior or subordinate basis.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(C)</num>
          <text>The Corporation shall send a copy of the resolution authorizing the issuance of the Bonds to the Council within 3 days of its adoption.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The board may delegate to the Chief Financial Officer as a member of the board the authority to prescribe the terms and conditions of the Bonds, including those referred to in § <cite path="§7-1831.03">7-1831.03</cite>(c)(2), except that the terms and conditions of the Residual Bond shall be consistent with the provisions of the Purchase Agreement and shall provide that the Residual Interest shall be paid to the Tobacco Settlement Trust Fund established by subchapter II of this chapter, and the terms and conditions of the Remainder Certificate, if any, shall be consistent with the provisions of the Residual Bond Purchase Agreement and shall provide that the payments under the Master Settlement Agreement after payment in full of all Bonds outstanding shall be paid to the Tobacco Settlement Trust Fund established by subchapter II of this chapter.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>A pledge by the Corporation of contract rights, general intangibles, or revenues collected by or on behalf of the Corporation as security for the Bonds shall be valid and binding from the time the pledge is made. The contract rights, general intangibles, or revenues pledged shall immediately be subject to the lien of the pledge without physical delivery or further act, and the lien of any pledge shall be valid and binding against any person having a claim of any kind in tort, contract, or otherwise against the Corporation or the District government irrespective of whether the person has notice. Notwithstanding any law, the filing or recording of a resolution, trust, agreement, financing statement, continuation statement, or other instrument adopted or entered into by the Corporation in any public record is not required to perfect the lien against third parties.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>The Bonds shall be legal instruments in which public officers and public bodies of the District, insurance companies, insurance company associations, and other persons carrying on an insurance business, banks, bankers, banking institutions including savings and loan associations, building and loan associations, trust companies, savings banks, savings associations, investment companies, and other persons carrying on a banking business, administrators, guardians, executors, trustees, and other fiduciaries, and other persons authorized to invest in bonds or in other obligations of the District, may  legally invest funds, including capital, in their control. The Bonds are also securities which legally may be deposited with and received by public officers and public bodies of the District or any agency of the District for any purpose for which the deposit of bonds or other obligations of the District is  authorized by law.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>The Bonds shall not constitute an indebtedness of the District. The Bonds are not general obligations of the District and are not secured by a pledge of the full faith and credit of the District and the holders of the Bonds may not require the levy or imposition of taxes. The Bonds issued to purchase the District’s right, title, and interest in the Master Settlement Agreement are special obligations of the Corporation payable solely from, and secured by, the payments received under the Master Settlement Agreement. The Bonds issued to purchase the Fund’s right, title, and interest in the Residual Bond are obligations of the Corporation payable solely from, and secured by, the payments received under the Residual Bond. The Corporation has no taxing power. The Bonds shall contain on their face a statement containing all of the above. Nothing contained in the Bonds, or in the related financing or closing documents, shall create an obligation on the part of the Corporation or the  District to make payments with respect to the Bonds from sources other than the payments received by the Corporation under the Master Settlement Agreement or under the Fund under the Residual Bond.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>Regardless of their form or character, the Bonds are negotiable instruments for all purposes of Title 28, subject only to the provisions of the bonds and notes for registration.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>No official, employee, or agent of the Corporation or the District shall be held personally liable solely because the Bonds are issued.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>The District pledges, which pledge the Corporation may include in any agreement with the holders of the Bonds, to the Corporation that the District will:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(i)</num>
          <text>Continue to diligently enforce the Model Statute against all tobacco product manufacturers selling tobacco products in the District that are not signatories to the Master Settlement Agreement;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(ii)</num>
          <text>Enforce the District’s rights to receive the payments to be made to the District pursuant to the Master Settlement Agreement to the full extent permitted by the terms of the Master Settlement Agreement;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(iii)</num>
          <text>Not amend the Master Settlement Agreement in any way that would materially impair the rights of the holders of Bonds;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(iv)</num>
          <text>Not limit or alter rights vested in the Corporation to fulfill agreements made with holders of the Bonds; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(v)</num>
          <text>Not in any way impair the rights and remedies of the holders of the Bonds until the Bonds, together with the interest thereon, with interest on any unpaid installments of interest, and all costs and expenses in connection with any action or proceedings by or on behalf of the holders of the Bonds are fully met and discharged.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(10)</num>
        <text>The signature of an officer of the Corporation that appears on the Bonds, including Bonds not yet issued or delivered, shall remain valid notwithstanding that the person has ceased to hold that office.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(11)</num>
        <text>The Bonds, and the interest thereon, shall be exempt from District taxation, except estate, inheritance, and gift taxes.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(12)</num>
        <text>During a control period (as defined in § <cite path="§47-392.09">47-392.09</cite>), a resolution of the board of directors of Corporation authorizing the issuance of the Bonds shall be submitted to the District of Columbia Financial Responsibility and Management Assistance Authority (“Authority”) for certification in accordance with § <cite path="§47-392.04">47-392.04</cite>. A certification issued by the Authority during a control period shall be effective for purposes of this subsection for Bonds issued pursuant to the resolution of the board of directors of the Corporation whether the Bonds are issued during or after the control period.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(d)</num>
      <text>In addition to any other powers or authority conferred by this section or subchapter, the Corporation shall have all the powers of a corporate body under the laws of the District to the extent not inconsistent with or restricted by the provisions of this section or subchapter, including the power to:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Adopt, amend, repeal, and enforce bylaws, rules, regulations, and procedures as it determines appropriate to the governance of its affairs and the conduct of its business and which are not inconsistent with this section;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Sue and be sued, and to complain and defend, in its own name;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Adopt, alter, and use a corporate seal, which shall be judicially noticed; provided, that the absence of the seal on a contract or other document shall not affect its validity;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Acquire, purchase, hold, lease, sell, assign, pledge, or convey real and personal property, contract rights, general intangibles, revenues, moneys, and accounts as may be proper or expedient to carry out the purposes of the Corporation and this subchapter, and to assign, convey, sell, transfer, lease, or otherwise dispose of such property;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Elect, appoint, and employ such officers, agents, and employees as the Corporation deems advisable to operate and manage the affairs of the Corporation, and to define their duties and fix, adjust, and define their compensation as it determines to be appropriate;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Make, execute, or perform contracts, commitments, agreements, trust indentures, and other instruments and agreements, including, as approved by its board of directors, investment contracts, swap agreements and other hedging transactions, liquidity facilities, insurance agreements, or reinsurance agreements, necessary, or convenient to accomplish the purposes of the Corporation and this subchapter;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>Select, retain, and employ professionals, contractors, or agents which are necessary, or convenient to enable or assist the Corporation in carrying out the purposes of the Corporation;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>Indemnify or insure members of the board and officers of the Corporation as it determines appropriate;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>Purchase insurance or self-insure against loss in connection with its property and other assets or other risks, in such amounts and from such insurers as it determines appropriate; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(10)</num>
        <text>Perform any act not inconsistent with federal or District law necessary or convenient to carry out the purposes of the Corporation.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(e)</num>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The Corporation shall be governed by a board of directors consisting of 5 members. One member shall be the Chief Financial Officer (or, if the office is vacated, and until a successor is appointed, the acting Chief Financial Officer), one member shall be the Mayor or his designee (or, if the office is vacated, and until a successor is appointed, the acting Mayor or his designee), one member shall be the Chairman of the Council of the District or his designee (or, if the position is vacated, and until a successor is appointed, the acting Chairman), and 2 members shall be private citizens (“independent members”). Actions of the board shall be determined by a majority vote of the members unless a unanimous vote of all of the members will be required by the by-laws of the Corporation for certain purposes; provided, that the affirmative vote of the independent members shall be required for the issuance of the Bonds.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>One of the independent members of the board of directors shall be appointed by the Mayor and one shall be appointed by the Council within 30 calendar days after October 19, 2000, or 180 days after the date of a vacancy. Each of the independent members of the board shall serve a term of 4 years, except that an independent member selected to fill a vacancy occurring before the end of the term for which his predecessor was selected shall only serve until the end of the term. A member may serve after the expiration of his term until his successor has taken office.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The members shall serve without compensation for their membership, but may receive, or be reimbursed for, the actual, reasonable, and necessary expenses incurred in the performance of their official duties.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(f)</num>
      <text>All operating and administrative expenses of the Corporation and costs of issuance of the Bonds shall be paid by the Corporation out of payments received by the Corporation under the Master Settlement Agreement and from the proceeds of the Bonds.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(g)</num>
      <text>Upon the request of the Corporation, the Mayor and the governing officer or body of each instrumentality of the District, by delegation, contract, or agreement, may direct that personnel or other resources of a District department, office, agency, establishment, or instrumentality be made available to the Corporation on a full cost reimbursable basis to carry out the Corporation’s duties. Personnel detailed to the Corporation under this subsection shall not be considered employees of the Corporation, but shall remain employees of the department, agency, establishment, or instrumentality from which the employees were detailed. With the consent of an executive agency, department, or independent agency of the federal government or the District government, the Corporation may use the information, services, staff, and facilities of the department or agency on a full cost reimbursable basis.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(h)</num>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The existence of the Corporation shall be perpetual; provided, that the board of directors, by majority vote (including both of the independent members), may dissolve the Corporation when the Bonds and all other obligations of the Corporation incurred with respect to the issuance of the Bonds have been repaid, or their repayment has been provided for fully, and the existence of the Corporation shall terminate when adequate provision has been made for all other debts and obligations, and the winding up of the affairs, of the Corporation. No assets or earnings of the Corporation shall inure to a private person or entity.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>As long as the Bonds are outstanding:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(A)</num>
          <text>The Corporation shall not dissolve or file a voluntary petition under any bankruptcy legislation in effect from time to time or sell all, or substantially all, of its assets;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(B)</num>
          <text>No public officer, organization, entity, or other person may authorize the Corporation to be or become a debtor under any bankruptcy legislation in effect from time to time; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(C)</num>
          <text>The Corporation shall not take any action that materially and adversely affects the rights of the holders of the Bonds or other obligations issued by it.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(i)</num>
      <text>All assets and income of the Corporation shall be exempt from District taxation.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(j)</num>
      <text>The Corporation shall have the same fiscal year as the District.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(k)</num>
      <text>An independent accountant, appointed by the board of directors of the Corporation, shall conduct an annual audit of the accounts and records of the Corporation.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(l)</num>
      <text>No District laws, rules, or orders governing procurement or administrative procedures or personnel shall apply to the Corporation, its activities, board members, officers, or employees, except as otherwise provided for in this subchapter.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(m)</num>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Notwithstanding any other provisions of this section, the Corporation shall select the underwriter or placement agent for the Bonds (not including the Residual Bond) and legal counsel, including bond counsel, by competitive sealed bidding. The contracts shall be awarded on the basis of lowest evaluated bid price (as the term is defined in § <cite path="§2-351.04">2-351.04</cite>(31)). In evaluating the bids, the following factors shall be considered:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(A)</num>
          <text>The type of business or organization and its history;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(B)</num>
          <text>The resumes and professional qualifications of the business or organization’s staff, including relevant professional licenses, affiliations, and specialties;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(C)</num>
          <text>Information attesting to financial capability, including financial statements;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(D)</num>
          <text>A summary of similar contracts awarded to the bidder, and the bidder’s performance of those contracts;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(E)</num>
          <text>A statement attesting to compliance with wage, hour, workplace safety, and other standards of labor law;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(F)</num>
          <text>A statement attesting to compliance with federal and District equal employment opportunity law; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(G)</num>
          <text>Information about pending lawsuits or investigations, and judgments, indictments, or convictions against the bidder or its proprietors, partners, directors, officers, or managers.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The invitation for bids shall state that the selection shall be made on the basis of the lowest evaluated bid price. The Corporation shall provide public notice of the invitation for bids of not less than 10 working days. Public notice of an invitation for bids shall include publication in a newspaper of general circulation, and in trade publications considered to be appropriate by the Corporation to give adequate public notice.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Bids shall be opened publicly at the time and place designated in the invitation for bids. Each bid, with the name of the bidder, shall be recorded and be open to public inspection. The contract shall be awarded with reasonable promptness by written notice to the responsive and responsible bidder whose bid will be most advantageous to the Corporation, considering price and other factors as set forth in paragraph (1) of this subsection.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>History</heading>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 13-172">Oct. 19, 2000, D.C. Law 13-172, § 3704, 47 DCR 6308</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 13-176">Oct. 21, 2000, D.C. Law 13-176, § 8(d)(3), 47 DCR 6835</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 16-142">July 25, 2006, D.C. Law 16-142, § 3(c), 53 DCR 4412</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 16-294">Mar. 14, 2007, D.C. Law 16-294, § 10, 54 DCR 1086</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 19-171">Sept. 26, 2012, D.C. Law 19-171, § 211, 59 DCR 6190</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Section References</heading>
        <annotation>This section is referenced in § <cite path="§7-1831.01">7-1831.01</cite>.</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Effect of Amendments</heading>
        <annotation><cite doc="D.C. Law 13-176">D.C. Law 13-176</cite>, in par. (m)(2), substituted “10 working days” for “30 days”.</annotation>
        <annotation>Section 9 of <cite doc="D.C. Law 13-176">D.C. Law 13-176</cite> provided: “Rule of construction. ”To the extent that provisions of this act conflict with any order of the Financial Responsibility and Management Assistance Authority (’Financial Authority’), issued pursuant to section 207(d) of the District of Columbia Financial Responsibility and Management Assistance Act of 1995 the provisions of the Financial Authority Order shall govern.”</annotation>
        <annotation><cite doc="D.C. Law 16-142">D.C. Law 16-142</cite>, in subsec. (b), substituted “by the District and the Residual Bond, issuing” for “by the District), issuing”, substituted “Purchase Agreement or the Residual Bond Purchase Agreement and” for “Purchase Agreement and”, and substituted “including financing the costs of the National Capital Medical Center indebtedness of the District, to finance or refinance the National Capital Medical Center, healthcare related issues, or other capital projects or undertakings of the District, or other capital projects, repayment, refinancing,” for “including repayment, refinancing,”; in par. (c)(1), substituted “to finance or refinance” for “to refinance”, substituted “the financing or refinancing of the National Capital Medical Center, healthcare related issues, or other capital projects or undertakings” for “the refinancing of, capital projects and other undertakings” and deleted the last sentence which had read: ’The refinancing of capital projects and other undertakings of the District shall include the refinancing, repayment, or defeasance of general obligation debt of the District incurred for capital projects and other undertakings.“; in subpar. (c)(2)(B)(i), substituted ”Corporation;“ for ”Corporation; and“; in subpar. (c)(2)(B)(ii), substituted ”taxable basis; and“ for ”taxable basis.“; added subpar. (c)(2)(B)(iii); in par. (c)(3), substituted ”subchapter II of this chapter, and the terms and conditions of the Remainder Certificate, if any, shall be consistent with the provisions of the Residual Bond Purchase Agreement and shall provide that the payments under the Master Settlement Agreement after payment in full of all Bonds outstanding shall be paid to the Tobacco Settlement Trust Fund established by subchapter II of this chapter.“ for ”subchapter II of this chapter.“; in par. (c)(6), substituted ”The Bonds issued to purchase the District’s right, title, and interest in the Master Settlement Agreement are special obligations of the Corporation payable solely from, and secured by, the payments received under the Master Settlement Agreement. The Bonds issued to purchase the Fund’s right, title, and interest in the Residual Bond are obligations of the Corporation payable solely from, and secured by, the payments received under the Residual Bond.“ for ”The Bonds are special obligations of the Corporation payable solely from, and secured by, the payments received under the Master Settlement Agreement.“, and substituted ”Settlement Agreement or under the Fund under the Residual Bond.“ for ”Settlement Agreement.“ in the last sentence; and rewrote par. (c)(9), which had read as follows: ”(9) The District pledges to the Corporation and the holders of the Bonds that the District will not limit or alter rights vested in the Corporation to fulfill agreements made with holders of the Bonds, or in any way impair the rights and remedies of the holders of the Bonds until the Bonds, together with the interest thereon, with interest on any unpaid installments of interest, and all costs and expenses in connection with any action or proceedings by or on behalf of the holders of the Bonds are fully met and discharged. The Corporation may include this pledge of the District in any agreement with the holders of the Bonds.”</annotation>
        <annotation><cite doc="D.C. Law 16-294">D.C. Law 16-294</cite>, in subsec. (b), substituted “District) and the Residual Bond” for “District and the Residual Bond)”.</annotation>
        <annotation>The 2012 amendment by <cite doc="D.C. Law 19-171">D.C. Law 19-171</cite> substituted “§ <cite path="§2-351.04">2-351.04</cite>(31)” for “§ <cite path="§2-301.07">2-301.07</cite>(25)” in (m)(1).</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Temporary Amendment of Section</heading>
        <annotation>For temporary (225 day) amendment of the Fiscal Year 2001 Budget Support Temporary Amendment Act of 2000, see §§ 2(d), 3(d) of (<cite doc="D.C. Law 13-197">D.C. Law 13-197</cite>, October 21, 2000, law notification  47 DCR 8987).</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Emergency Legislation</heading>
        <annotation>For temporary (90-day) addition of section, see notes following § <cite path="§7-1831.01">7-1831.01</cite>.</annotation>
        <annotation>For temporary (90-day) amendment of section, see §§ 2(c) and 3(c) of the Fiscal Year 2001 Budget Support Emergency Amendment Act of 2000 (D.C. Act 13-381, July 24, 2000,  47 DCR 6695).</annotation>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 day) additions, see §§ 3702 to 3707 of the Fiscal Year 2001 Budget Support Congressional Review Emergency Act of 2000 (D.C. Act 13-438, October 20, 2000,  47 DCR 8740).</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section from-code="true">
    <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" path="|7|18|III"/>
    <num codify:value="7-1831.04">3705</num>
    <heading>True sale.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>(a)</num>
      <text>The transfer of the District’s right, title, and interest in and to the Master Settlement Agreement to the Corporation or any assignee which the parties have in the governing documentation expressly stated to be a sale or other absolute transfer shall be treated as an absolute transfer of all of the District’s right, title, and interest, as in a true sale, and not as a pledge or other financing, of the District’s right, title, and interest in and to the Master Settlement Agreement, including the moneys payable or received thereunder and any interest thereon (except for the first payment of $16.05 million which has already been received by the District). The grant to the holders of the Bonds of a security interest in, and a lien on, all of the Corporation’s right, title, and interest in and to the Master Settlement Agreement, including the moneys payable or received thereunder and any interest thereon (except for the first payment of $16.05 million which has already been received by the District), the provision by the District of any credit enhancement with respect to the Bonds, or the characterization of the transaction for accounting purposes or securities regulation shall not impair or negate the characterization of any transfer as a true sale. The transfer of the District’s right, title, and interest in and to the Master Settlement Agreement to the Corporation or any assignee shall be deemed perfected as against third persons having claims in tort, contract, or otherwise, including any judicial lien creditors, when a sale or transfer of the right, title, and interest in and to the Master Settlement Agreement in writing has been executed and delivered by the District to the Corporation or any assignee.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(b)</num>
      <text>The transfer of the Fund’s right, title, and interest in and to the Residual Bond to the Corporation or any assignee that the parties have in the governing documentation expressly stated to be a sale or other absolute transfer shall be treated as an absolute transfer of all of the Fund’s right, title, and interest, as in a true sale, and not as a pledge or other financing, of the Fund’s right, title, and interest in and to the Residual Bond, including the moneys payable or received thereunder and any interest thereon. The grant to the holders of the Bonds of a security interest in, and a lien on, all of the Fund’s right, title, and interest in and to the Residual Bond, including the moneys payable or received thereunder and any interest thereon, the provision by the Fund or the District of any credit enhancement with respect to the Bonds (other than the Residual Bond), or the characterization of the transaction for accounting purposes or securities regulation shall not impair or negate the characterization of any transfer as a true sale. The transfer of the Fund’s right, title, and interest in and to the Residual Bond to the Corporation or any assignee shall be deemed perfected as against third persons having claims in tort, contract, or otherwise, including any judicial lien creditors, when a sale or transfer of the right, title, and interest in and to the Residual Bond in writing has been executed and delivered by the Fund to the Corporation or any assignee.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>History</heading>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 13-172">Oct. 19, 2000, D.C. Law 13-172, § 3705, 47 DCR 6308</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 16-142">July 25, 2006, D.C. Law 16-142, § 3(d), 53 DCR 4412</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Effect of Amendments</heading>
        <annotation><cite doc="D.C. Law 16-142">D.C. Law 16-142</cite>, designated the existing text of section as subsec. (a); and added subsec. (b).</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Emergency Legislation</heading>
        <annotation>For temporary (90-day) addition of section, see notes following § <cite path="§7-1831.01">7-1831.01</cite>.</annotation>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 day) amendment of section, see §§ 3702 to 3707 of the Fiscal Year 2001 Budget Support Congressional Review Emergency Act of 2000 (D.C. Act 13-438, October 20, 2000,  47 DCR 8740).</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section from-code="true">
    <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" path="|7|18|III"/>
    <num codify:value="7-1831.05">3706</num>
    <heading>Severability.</heading>
    <text>If a provision of this subchapter or its application to a person or circumstance is held invalid, the invalidity shall not affect other provisions or applications of this subchapter which can be given effect without the invalid provisions or application.</text>
    <annotations>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>History</heading>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 13-172">Oct. 19, 2000, D.C. Law 13-172, § 3706, 47 DCR 6308</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Emergency Legislation</heading>
        <annotation>For temporary (90-day) addition of section, see notes following § <cite path="§7-1831.01">7-1831.01</cite>.</annotation>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 day) amendment of section, see §§ 3702 to 3707 of the Fiscal Year 2001 Budget Support Congressional Review Emergency Act of 2000 (D.C. Act 13-438, October 20, 2000,  47 DCR 8740).</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section from-code="true">
    <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" path="|7|18|III"/>
    <num codify:value="7-1831.06">3707</num>
    <heading>Termination.</heading>
    <text>This subchapter shall expire on September 30, 2001, if the Bonds (other than the Residual Bond) are not sold and issued. In the event of such expiration, all the assets of the Corporation shall vest in the District.</text>
    <annotations>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>History</heading>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 13-172">Oct. 19, 2000, D.C. Law 13-172, § 3707, 47 DCR 6308</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Emergency Legislation</heading>
        <annotation>For temporary (90-day) addition of section, see notes following § <cite path="§7-1831.01">7-1831.01</cite>.</annotation>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 day) amendment of section, see §§ 3702 to 3707 of the Fiscal Year 2001 Budget Support Congressional Review Emergency Act of 2000 (D.C. Act 13-438, October 20, 2000,  47 DCR 8740).</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section from-code="true">
    <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" path="|38|12"/>
    <num codify:value="38-1231.01">2407</num>
    <heading>Biennial audits of UDC Endowment Fund.</heading>
    <text>Beginning February 1, 2001, the District of Columbia Auditor shall conduct biennial audits of the University of the District of Columbia’s Endowment Fund (“Fund”). The Auditor shall provide the Council with a report on the status of the Fund not later than February 1 of each year of the biennial audit.</text>
    <annotations>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>History</heading>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 13-172">Oct. 19, 2000, D.C. Law 13-172, § 2407, 47 DCR 6308</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Emergency Legislation</heading>
        <annotation>For temporary (90-day) authorization of biennial audits of endowment fund, see § 2407 of the Fiscal Year 2001 Budget Support Emergency Act of 2000 (D.C. Act 13-376, July 24, 2000,  47 DCR 6574).</annotation>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 day) amendment of section, see § 2407 of the Fiscal Year 2001 Budget Support Congressional Review Emergency Act of 2000 (D.C. Act 13-438, October 20, 2000,  47 DCR 8740).</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section from-code="true">
    <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" path="|1|3|XII|A"/>
    <reason>Repealed</reason>
    <num codify:value="1-327.01">1002</num>
    <heading>Establishment of the Citywide Call Center.</heading>
    <text>Repealed.</text>
    <annotations>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>History</heading>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 13-172">Oct. 19, 2000, D.C. Law 13-172, § 1002, 47 DCR 6308</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 14-190">Oct. 1, 2002, D.C. Law 14-190, § 1203(b)(2), 49 DCR 6968</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Prior Codifications</heading>
        <annotation>1981 Ed., § 1-368.1.</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Emergency Legislation</heading>
        <annotation>For temporary (90-day) addition of section, see § 1002 of the Fiscal Year 2001 Budget Support Emergency Act of 2000 (D.C. Act 13-376, July 24, 2000,  47 DCR 6574).</annotation>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 day) amendment of section, see § 1002 of the Fiscal Year 2001 Budget Support Congressional Review Emergency Act of 2000 (D.C. Act 13-438, October 20, 2000,  47 DCR 8740).</annotation>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 day) repeal of section, see § 1204 of Fiscal Year 2003 Budget Support Emergency Act of 2002 (D.C. Act 14-453, July 23, 2002,  49 DCR 8026).</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Editor's Notes</heading>
        <text>Section 1203(b)(1) of <cite doc="D.C. Law 14-190">D.C. Law 14-190</cite> abolished the Citywide Call Center, established by § <cite path="§1-327.01">1-327.01</cite>.</text>
        <text>Section 17 of <cite doc="D.C. Law 15-105">D.C. Law 15-105</cite> made a technical amendment to <cite doc="D.C. Law 14-190">D.C. Law 14-190</cite> that did not affect this section.</text>
      </annoGroup>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section from-code="true">
    <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" path="|1|3|XII|A"/>
    <reason>Repealed</reason>
    <num codify:value="1-327.02">1003</num>
    <heading>Duties.</heading>
    <text>Repealed.</text>
    <annotations>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>History</heading>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 13-172">Oct. 19, 2000, D.C. Law 13-172, § 1003, 47 DCR 6308</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 14-190">Oct. 1, 2002, D.C. Law 14-190, § 1203(b)(2), 49 DCR 6968</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Prior Codifications</heading>
        <annotation>1981 Ed., § 1-368.2.</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Emergency Legislation</heading>
        <annotation>For temporary (90-day) addition of section, see § 1003 of the Fiscal Year 2001 Budget Support Emergency Act of 2000 (D.C. Act 13-376, July 24, 2000,  47 DCR 6574).</annotation>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 day) amendment of section, see § 1003 of the Fiscal Year 2001 Budget Support Congressional Review Emergency Act of 2000 (D.C. Act 13-438, October 20, 2000,  47 DCR 8740).</annotation>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 day) addition of §§ <cite path="§1-328.01">1-328.01</cite> to 1-328.03, 1-328.04 see §§ 1201 to 1203, 1205 of Fiscal Year 2003 Budget Support Emergency Act of 2002 (D.C. Act 14-453, July 23, 2002,  49 DCR 8026).</annotation>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 day) repeal of section, see § 1204 of Fiscal Year 2003 Budget Support Emergency Act of 2002 (D.C. Act 14-453, July 23, 2002,  49 DCR 8026).</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section from-code="true">
    <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" path="|1|5|I"/>
    <num codify:value="1-509">3202</num>
    <heading>Allowances for privately owned vehicles for employees.</heading>
    <text>The Mayor may establish rates and reimburse employees, by regulation, for privately owned automobiles and motorcycles used for the performance of official duties. The rates established by the Mayor shall not exceed the maximum prevailing rates for such vehicles as prescribed in the Federal Property Management Regulations 101-7 (Federal Travel Regulations). The proposed regulations shall be submitted to the Council for a 45-day period of review, excluding Saturdays, Sundays, legal holidays, and days of Council recess. If the Council does not approve or disapprove the regulations, in whole or in part, by resolution within the 45-day review period, the proposed rules shall be deemed approved.</text>
    <annotations>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>History</heading>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 13-172">Oct. 19, 2000, D.C. Law 13-172, § 3202, 47 DCR 6308</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Prior Codifications</heading>
        <annotation>1981 Ed., § 1-518.</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Emergency Legislation</heading>
        <annotation>For temporary (90-day) addition of section, see § 3202 of the Fiscal Year 2001 Budget Support Emergency Act of 2000 (D.C. Act 13-376, July 24, 2000,  47 DCR 6574).</annotation>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 day) amendment of section, see § 3202 of the Fiscal Year 2001 Budget Support Congressional Review Emergency Act of 2000 (D.C. Act 13-438, October 20, 2000,  47 DCR 8740).</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section from-code="true">
    <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" path="|5|1|I"/>
    <num codify:value="5-101.04">842</num>
    <heading>Police Services Areas.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>(a)</num>
      <text>By January 1, 2001, the Chief of the Metropolitan Police Department (“MPD”) shall submit to the Council a study performed by MPD on the efficacy of the Police Service Area (“PSA”) model, including:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Whether re-engineering of the model is necessary;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Whether PSA boundaries need to be redrawn; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Whether PSA staffing is appropriate.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(b)</num>
      <text>By April 1, 2001, the Chief of MPD shall submit a plan to the Council for redeploying sworn officers into the PSA system. Pursuant to this redeployment plan, a minimum of 60% of all sworn officers who are available for full duty would be assigned to the PSA system. For this purpose, these officers would be assigned to street patrol and available to respond to calls for service.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(c)</num>
      <text>The requirement set forth in subsection (b) of this section does not preclude the Chief of Police from also submitting alternatives to the redeployment plan required by the Council.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(d)</num>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Until MPD attains 3,700 sworn officers, the Chief of the MPD shall deploy sworn officers as necessary to ensure that a minimum of 62% of all sworn police personnel are assigned to direct service delivery in the PSAs. Sworn officers assigned to PSAs shall not be deployed outside of their respective PSAs at any time, unless responding to an emergency situation.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>For the purposes of this subsection, the term:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(A)</num>
          <text>“Sworn police personnel” is limited to all of the sworn lieutenants, sergeants, and officers.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(B)</num>
          <text>Emergency situation” means any extraordinary occurrence in the District of Columbia which requires the use of sworn police personnel to protect the health and safety of residents and visitors, including civil disorder, riots, acts of terrorism, or natural disasters.”</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(e)</num>
      <text>The deployment of sworn officers to the PSAs shall be based on the following considerations:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The number of Part 1 offenses;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Drug activities;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The number of arrests;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The need for traffic enforcement; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>The number of calls for service.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(f)</num>
      <text>Until MPD attains 3,800 sworn officers, all newly sworn officers who were recruited by MPD to become police officers shall be assigned to neighborhood patrols in the PSAs.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>History</heading>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 13-172">Oct. 19, 2000, D.C. Law 13-172, § 842, 47 DCR 6308</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 15-39">Nov. 13, 2003, D.C. Law 15-39, § 3002, 50 DCR 5668</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 15-354">Apr. 13, 2005, D.C. Law 15-354, § 97, 52 DCR 2638</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Effect of Amendments</heading>
        <annotation><cite doc="D.C. Law 15-39">D.C. Law 15-39</cite> added subsecs. (d), (e), and (f).</annotation>
        <annotation><cite doc="D.C. Law 15-354">D.C. Law 15-354</cite> substituted “Police Services Area” for “Patrol Services Area”.</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Temporary Addition of Section</heading>
        <annotation>For temporary (225 day) addition, see § 2 of PSA Restructuring Council Review Temporary Act of 2003 (<cite doc="D.C. Law 15-79">D.C. Law 15-79</cite>, March 10, 2004, law notification  51 DCR 3371).</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Emergency Legislation</heading>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 day) amendment of section, see § 842 of the Fiscal Year 2001 Budget Support Congressional Review Emergency Act of 2000 (D.C. Act 13-438, October 20, 2000,  47 DCR 8740).</annotation>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 day) amendment of section, see § 2 of the Public Safety Crisis Emergency Amendment Act of 2003 (D.C. Act 15-26, February 24, 2003,  50 DCR 2148).</annotation>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 day) amendment of section, see § 2902 of Fiscal Year 2004 Budget Support Emergency Act of 2003 (D.C. Act 15-105, June 20, 2003,  50 DCR 5613).</annotation>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 day) amendment of section, see § 2902 of Fiscal Year 2004 Budget Support Congressional Review Emergency Act of 2003 (D.C. Act 15-149, September 22, 2003,  50 DCR 8360).</annotation>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 day) prohibition of implementation of Metropolitan Police Department’s Police Service Areas restructuring plan prior to Council review, see § 2 of PSA Restructuring Council Review Emergency Act of 2003 (D.C. Act 15-206, October 24, 2003,  50 DCR 9850).</annotation>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 day) prohibition of implementation of Metropolitan Police Department’s Police Service Areas restructuring plan prior to Council review, see § 2 of PSA Restructuring Council Review Congressional Review Emergency Act of 2004 (D.C. Act 15-337,  January 29, 2004,  51 DCR 1813).</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Short Title</heading>
        <annotation>Short title of title XXX of Law 15-39: Section 3001 of <cite doc="D.C. Law 15-39">D.C. Law 15-39</cite> provided that title XXX of the act may be cited as the Neighborhood Safety Amendment Act of 2003.</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Editor's Notes</heading>
        <annotation>Applicability: Section 3003 of <cite doc="D.C. Law 15-39">D.C. Law 15-39</cite> provided: “This title shall apply as of October 1, 2003. The delayed applicability of the title shall not be construed as prohibiting the Chief of the Metropolitan Police Department from implementing the changes mandated by the title prior to October 1, 2003.”</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section from-code="true">
    <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" path="|5|1|XVII"/>
    <num codify:value="5-133.18">802</num>
    <heading>Proceeds from sales of excess vehicles.</heading>
    <text>Effective October 19, 2000, and notwithstanding any other provision of law, police vehicles purchased for the Metropolitan Police Department (“MPD”) which have been declared excess, either through age or mechanical faults, shall be auctioned, or otherwise disposed of by the MPD. Revenue not to exceed $500,000 generated by auction or other means of disposal shall be returned to the MPD as Other Revenue, to be used expressly for the purchase of specialty replacement vehicles, including motorcycles. Any revenue in excess of $500,000 shall revert to the General Fund.</text>
    <annotations>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>History</heading>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 13-172">Oct. 19, 2000, D.C. Law 13-172, § 802, 47 DCR 6308</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Emergency Legislation</heading>
        <annotation>For temporary (90-day) addition of section, see § 802 of the Fiscal Year 2001 Budget Support Emergency Act of 2000 (D.C. Act 13-376, July 24, 2000,  47 DCR 6574).</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section from-code="true">
    <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" path="|5|14"/>
    <num codify:value="5-1401">2902</num>
    <heading>Definitions.</heading>
    <text>For the purposes of this chapter, the term:</text>
    <para>
      <num>(1)</num>
      <text>“District” means the District of Columbia.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(2)</num>
      <text>“Legal custody” includes imprisonment, jail, or detention.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(3)</num>
      <text>“Ward” means any person in the official custody of the District government, on a temporary or permanent basis, because of neglect, abuse, mental illness or intellectual disability.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>History</heading>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 13-172">Oct. 19, 2000, D.C. Law 13-172, § 2902, 47 DCR 6308</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 19-169">Sept. 26, 2012, D.C. Law 19-169, § 13, 59 DCR 5567</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Effect of Amendments</heading>
        <annotation>The 2012 amendment by <cite doc="D.C. Law 19-169">D.C. Law 19-169</cite> substituted “intellectual disability” for “mental retardation” in (3).</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Emergency Legislation</heading>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 day) addition of applicability provision, see § 2920 of the Fiscal Year 2001 Budget Support Congressional Review Emergency Act of 2000 (D.C. Act 13-438, October 20, 2000,  47 DCR 8740).</annotation>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 day) addition of section, see § 2902 of the Fiscal Year 2001 Budget Support Congressional Review Emergency Act of 2000 (D.C. Act 13-438, October 20, 2000,  47 DCR 8740).</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Mayor's Orders</heading>
        <text>Autopsies of Deceased Clients of the Mental Retardation and Developmental Disability Administration, see Mayor’s Order 2004-76, May 13, 2004 ( 51 DCR 5278).</text>
        <text>Autopsies of Deceased Consumers of the Mental Retardation and Developmental Disabilities Administration, see Mayor’s Order 2006-123, September 28, 2006 ( 53 DCR 9314).</text>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Editor's Notes</heading>
        <annotation>Section 35 of <cite doc="D.C. Law 19-169">D.C. Law 19-169</cite> provided that no provision of the act shall impair any right or obligation existing under law.</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section from-code="true">
    <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" path="|5|14"/>
    <num codify:value="5-1402">2903</num>
    <heading>Establishment of the Office of the Chief Medical Examiner; appointments, qualifications, and compensation.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>(a)</num>
      <text>There is established as a subordinate agency in the executive branch of the government of the District of Columbia, the Office of the Chief Medical Examiner (“OCME”).</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(b)</num>
      <text>The Mayor shall nominate, with the advice and consent of the Council, a person to serve as the Chief Medical Examiner (“CME”) within the OCME pursuant to § <cite path="§1-523.01">1-523.01</cite>(a). The CME shall be responsible for the management and operation of the OCME. The CME shall appoint a Deputy CME, to be paid at an annual rate of $206,000, and any other medical examiners the CME finds necessary to carry out the duties of the OCME.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(c)</num>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The CME, the Deputy CME, and any medical examiners appointed pursuant to subsection (b) of this section shall be physicians licensed to practice medicine in the District of Columbia.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Except as provided in paragraph (3) of this subsection, the CME, the Deputy CME, and any medical examiners appointed after October 19, 2000, shall be certified in forensic pathology by the American Board of Pathology or be eligible for such certification.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The certification requirement of paragraph (2) of this subsection may be waived by the Mayor for the CME appointed to fill the term beginning on May 1, 2007, and ending on April 30, 2013.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(d)</num>
      <text>The Mayor shall fix the compensation of the CME pursuant to subchapter X-A of Chapter 6 of Title 1 [§ <cite path="§1-610.51">1-610.51</cite> et seq.]. The Mayor shall fix the compensation of all medical examiners appointed by the CME pursuant to this section.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(e)</num>
      <text>The CME shall be appointed for a 6-year term.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(f)</num>
      <text>If a vacancy in the position of Chief Medical Examiner occurs as a consequence of resignation, disability, death, or a reason other than the expiration of the term of the Chief Medical Examiner, the Mayor shall appoint a replacement to fill the unexpired term in the same manner provided in § <cite path="§1-523.01">1-523.01</cite>(a). A person appointed to fill the unexpired term shall serve only for the remainder of the term.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>History</heading>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 13-172">Oct. 19, 2000, D.C. Law 13-172, § 2903, 47 DCR 6308</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 15-339">Apr. 12, 2005, D.C. Law 15-339, § 2, 52 DCR 2283</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 17-115">Mar. 20, 2008, D.C. Law 17-115, § 2, 55 DCR 1278</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 18-88">Dec. 10, 2009, D.C. Law 18-88, § 203, 56 DCR 7413</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 20-155">Feb. 26, 2015, D.C. Law 20-155, § 3042, 61 DCR 9990</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Section References</heading>
        <annotation>This section is referenced in § <cite path="§5-1416">5-1416</cite>.</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Prior Codifications</heading>
        <annotation>1981 Ed., § 11-2301.</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Effect of Amendments</heading>
        <annotation><cite doc="D.C. Law 15-339">D.C. Law 15-339</cite> rewrote subsec. (c); and added subsec. (f). Prior to amendment, subsec. (c) read as follows: “(c) The CME, the Deputy CME, and any medical examiners appointed pursuant to subsection (b) of this section shall be physicians licensed to practice medicine in the District of Columbia. The CME, the Deputy CME, and any medical examiners appointed after the effective date of this chapter shall be certified in forensic pathology by the American Board of Pathology or be eligible for such certification.”</annotation>
        <annotation><cite doc="D.C. Law 17-115">D.C. Law 17-115</cite> rewrote subsec. (c) which had read as follows: “(c) The CME, the Deputy CME, and any medical examiners appointed pursuant to subsection (b) of this section shall be physicians licensed to practice medicine in the District of Columbia. The CME, the Deputy CME, and any medical examiners appointed after October 19, 2000, shall be certified in forensic pathology by the American Board of Pathology or be eligible for such certification, except that the Mayor may waive the certification requirement for any individual appointed as CME to fill the unexpired term ending on April 30, 2007.”</annotation>
        <annotation><cite doc="D.C. Law 18-88">D.C. Law 18-88</cite> rewrote subsec. (c)(3), which had read as follows: “(3) The certification requirement of paragraph (2) of this subsection may be waived by the Mayor until October 1, 2008 for the CME. Any individual appointed as the CME to fill the term beginning on May 1, 2007, and ending on April 30, 2013, pursuant to this waiver shall not be eligible to serve as CME after October 1, 2008, and shall not be eligible to serve in a holdover status after October 1, 2008, unless he or she meets the certification requirement.”</annotation>
        <annotation>The 2015 amendment by <cite doc="D.C. Law 20-155">D.C. Law 20-155</cite> added “to be paid at an annual rate of $ 206,000” in (b).</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Temporary Legislation</heading>
        <annotation>For temporary (225 day) amendment of section, see § 2 of Appointment of the Chief Medical Examiner Temporary Amendment Act of 2007 (<cite doc="D.C. Law 17-70">D.C. Law 17-70</cite>, January 23, 2008, law notification  55 DCR 1450).</annotation>
        <annotation>Section 2 of <cite doc="D.C. Law 17-335">D.C. Law 17-335</cite> amended subsec. (c)(3) to read as follows: “(3) The certification requirement of paragraph (2) of this subsection may be waived by the Mayor for the CME appointed to fill the term beginning on May 1, 2007 and ending on April 30, 2013.”</annotation>
        <annotation>Section 4(b) of <cite doc="D.C. Law 17-335">D.C. Law 17-335</cite> provided that the act shall expire after 225 days of its having taken effect.</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Emergency Legislation</heading>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 day) addition of section, see § 2903 of the Fiscal Year 2001 Budget Support Congressional Review Emergency Act of 2000 (D.C. Act 13-438, October 20, 2000,  47 DCR 8740).</annotation>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 day) amendment of section, see § 2 of Appointment of the Chief Medical Examiner Emergency Amendment Act of 2004 (D.C. Act 15-643, December 20, 2004,  51 DCR 11833).</annotation>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 day) amendment of section, see § 2 of Appointment of the Chief Medical Examiner Emergency Amendment Act of 2007 (D.C. Act 17-136, October 17, 2007,  54 DCR 10725).</annotation>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 day) amendment of section, see § 2 of Appointment of the Chief Medical Examiner Congressional Review Emergency Amendment Act of 2007 (D.C. Act 17-253, January 23, 2008,  55 DCR 1266).</annotation>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 day) amendment of section, see § 2 of Appointment of the Chief Medical Examiner Emergency Amendment Act of 2008 (D.C. Act 17-600, December 12, 2008,  56 DCR 7).</annotation>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 day) amendment of section, see § 2 of Appointment of the Chief Medical Examiner Congressional Review Emergency Amendment Act of 2009 (D.C. Act 18-4, January 23, 2009,  56 DCR 1627).</annotation>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 day) amendment of section, see § 203 of Omnibus Public Safety and Justice Emergency Amendment Act of 2009 (D.C. Act 18-181, August 6, 2009,  56 DCR 6903).</annotation>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 day) amendment of section, see § 203 of Omnibus Public Safety and Justice Congressional Review Emergency Amendment Act of 2009 (D.C. Act 18-227, October 21, 2009,  56 DCR 8668).</annotation>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 days) amendment of this section, see § 3042 of the Fiscal Year 2015 Budget Support Emergency Act of 2014 (D.C. Act 20-377, July 14, 2014, 61 DCR 7598, 20 STAT 3696).</annotation>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 days) amendment of this section, see § 3042 of the Fiscal Year 2015 Budget Support Congressional Review Emergency Act of 2014 (D.C. Act 20-449, October 10, 2014, 61 DCR 10915, 20 STAT 4188).</annotation>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 days) amendment of this section, see § 3042 of the Fiscal Year 2015 Budget Support Second Congressional Review Emergency Act of 2014 (D.C. Act 20-566, January 9, 2015, 62 DCR 884, 21 STAT 541).</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section from-code="true">
    <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" path="|5|14"/>
    <num codify:value="5-1403">2904</num>
    <heading>Supporting services and facilities.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>(a)</num>
      <text>The CME shall appoint such qualified professional, investigative, technical and clerical personnel as the OCME may require, including administrators, medicolegal investigators, and a General Counsel. The General Counsel shall be appointed pursuant to subchapter VIII-B of Chapter 6 of Title 1.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(b)</num>
      <text>The Mayor shall provide such facilities and equipment, as the OCME shall require. The Chief Medical Examiner may arrange or contract for such services, equipment and facilities as deemed necessary to carry out the duties and responsibilities of the OCME, pursuant to Chapter 3 of Title 2.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>History</heading>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 13-172">Oct. 19, 2000, D.C. Law 13-172, § 2904, 47 DCR 6308</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Prior Codifications</heading>
        <annotation>1981 Ed., § 11-2302.</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Emergency Legislation</heading>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 day) addition of section, see § 2904 of the Fiscal Year 2001 Budget Support Congressional Review Emergency Act of 2000 (D.C. Act 13-438, October 20, 2000,  47 DCR 8740).</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section from-code="true">
    <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" path="|5|14"/>
    <num codify:value="5-1404">2905</num>
    <heading>Former duties of coroner; oaths; teaching; other duties.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>(a)</num>
      <text>The CME shall be responsible for all the medical functions formerly performed by the coroner in the District of Columbia consistent with the provisions of this chapter. The CME and such other medical examiners as may be appointed may administer oaths and affirmations and take affidavits in connection with the performance of their duties.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(b)</num>
      <text>The CME, other medical examiners, medicolegal investigators and toxicologists as he or she may appoint, may be authorized by the CME to teach medical and law school classes, to conduct special classes for law enforcement personnel and to engage in other activities related to their work.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(c)</num>
      <text>The CME shall inform the Registrar of Vital Records of all deaths of children 18 years of age or younger as soon as practicable, but in any event within 5 business days.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(d)</num>
      <text>The CME, or his or her designee, shall attend all reviews of child deaths by the Child Fatality Review Committee. The CME shall coordinate with the Child Fatality Review Committee in its investigations of child deaths.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>History</heading>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 13-172">Oct. 19, 2000, D.C. Law 13-172, § 2905, 47 DCR 6308</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 14-28">Oct. 3, 2001, D.C. Law 14-28, § 4619(a), 48 DCR 6981</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Prior Codifications</heading>
        <annotation>1981 Ed., § 11-2303.</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Effect of Amendments</heading>
        <annotation><cite doc="D.C. Law 14-28">D.C. Law 14-28</cite> added subsecs. (c) and (d).</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Temporary Amendment of Section</heading>
        <annotation>For temporary (225 day) amendment of section, see § 19(a) of Child Fatality Review Committee Establishment Temporary Act of 2001 (<cite doc="D.C. Law 14-20">D.C. Law 14-20</cite>, September 6, 2001, law notification  48 DCR 9090).</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Emergency Legislation</heading>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 day) addition of section, see § 2905 of the Fiscal Year 2001 Budget Support Congressional Review Emergency Act of 2000 (D.C. Act 13-438, October 20, 2000,  47 DCR 8740).</annotation>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 day) amendment of section, see § 19(a) of Child Fatality Review Committee Establishment Emergency Act of 2001 (D.C. Act 14-40, April 25, 2001,  48 DCR 5917).</annotation>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 day) amendment of section, see § 19(a) of Child Fatality Review Committee Establishment Legislative Review Emergency Act of 2001 (D.C. Act 14-82, July 9, 2001,  48 DCR 6355).</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section from-code="true">
    <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" path="|5|14"/>
    <num codify:value="5-1405">2906</num>
    <heading>Deaths — determinations and investigations; cremations.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>(a)</num>
      <text>The CME, other medical examiners, and medicolegal investigators (physician assistants or advanced practice registered nurses) licensed under subchapter V of Chapter 12 of Title 3, are authorized to make determinations of death.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(b)</num>
      <text>Pursuant to regulations established by the Mayor, the following types of human deaths occurring in the District of Columbia shall be investigated by the OCME:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Violent deaths, whether apparently homicidal, suicidal or accidental  including deaths due to thermal, chemical, electrical or radiation injury and  deaths due to criminal abortion, whether apparently self-induced or not;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Sudden, unexpected or unexplained deaths not caused by readily  recognizable disease, including sudden infant deaths or apparent sudden infant  death syndrome (SIDS) for infants one year of age and younger;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Deaths under suspicious circumstances;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Deaths of persons whose bodies are to be cremated, dissected, buried at  sea or otherwise disposed of so as to be thereafter unavailable for  examination;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Deaths related to disease resulting from employment or on-the-job injury  or illness;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Deaths related to disease which might constitute a threat to public  health;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>Deaths of persons who are wards of the District of Columbia government;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>Deaths related to medical or surgical intervention, including operative,  peri-operative, anesthesia, medication reactions or deaths associated with  diagnostic or therapeutic procedures;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>Deaths of persons while in legal custody of the District;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(10)</num>
        <text>Fetal deaths related to maternal trauma including substance abuse, and  extra-mural deliveries;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(11)</num>
        <text>Deaths for which the Metropolitan Police Department, or other law  enforcement agency, or the United States Attorney’s Office requests, or a  court orders investigation; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(12)</num>
        <text>Dead bodies brought within the District of Columbia without proper  medical certification.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(c)</num>
      <text>Clearances by the CME shall be required for all deaths occurring in the District of Columbia for which cremations are requested regardless of where the cremation will occur.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(d)</num>
      <text>The Mayor shall, by regulation, prescribe procedures for taking possession of a dead body following a death subject to investigation under subsection (b) of this section and for obtaining all essential facts concerning the medical causes of death and the names and addresses of as many witnesses as it is practicable to obtain.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>History</heading>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 13-172">Oct. 19, 2000, D.C. Law 13-172, § 2906, 47 DCR 6308</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 14-28">Oct. 3, 2001, D.C. Law 14-28, § 4619(b), 48 DCR 6981</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Section References</heading>
        <annotation>This section is referenced in § <cite path="§5-1406">5-1406</cite> and § <cite path="§5-1408">5-1408</cite>.</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Prior Codifications</heading>
        <annotation>1981 Ed., § 11-2304.</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Effect of Amendments</heading>
        <annotation><cite doc="D.C. Law 14-28">D.C. Law 14-28</cite>, in subsec. (b)(2), inserted “for infants one year of age and younger” before the semicolon.</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Temporary Amendment of Section</heading>
        <annotation>For temporary (225 day) amendment of section, see § 19(b) of Child Fatality Review Committee Establishment Temporary Act of 2001 (<cite doc="D.C. Law 14-20">D.C. Law 14-20</cite>, September 6, 2001, law notification  48 DCR 9090).</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Emergency Legislation</heading>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 day) addition of section, see § 2906 of the Fiscal Year 2001 Budget Support Congressional Review Emergency Act of 2000 (D.C. Act 13-438, October 20, 2000,  47 DCR 8740).</annotation>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 day) amendment of section, see § 19(b) of Child Fatality Review Committee Establishment Emergency Act of 2001 (D.C. Act 14-40, April 25, 2001,  48 DCR 5917).</annotation>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 day) amendment of section, see § 19(b) of Child Fatality Review Committee Establishment Legislative Review Emergency Act of 2001 (D.C. Act 14-82, July 9, 2001,  48 DCR 6355).</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Delegation of Authority</heading>
        <annotation>Delegation of Authority Pursuant to Title XXIX of <cite doc="D.C. Law 13-172">D.C. Law 13-172</cite>, the “Fiscal Year 2001 Budget Support Act of 2000” Creating the Office of the Chief Medical Examiner, see Mayor’s Order 2001-04, January 5, 2001 ( 48 DCR 938).</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section from-code="true">
    <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" path="|5|14"/>
    <num codify:value="5-1406">2907</num>
    <heading>Deaths — Notification; penalties for noncompliance.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>(a)</num>
      <text>For all deaths described in § <cite path="§5-1405">5-1405</cite>(b), the CME shall take charge of the body upon the mandatory and direct notification of the death required by subsection (b) of this section. The CME, or duly authorized representatives of the CME, shall have authority to respond to the scene of the death. The body of the decedent shall not be disturbed unless the CME, or the CME’s designee, grants permission to do so.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(b)</num>
      <text>All law enforcement officers, emergency medical service (EMS) personnel, physicians, nurses, health care institutions, nursing homes, community residential facilities, prisons and jails, funeral directors, embalmers and other persons shall promptly notify the OCME of the occurrence of all deaths coming to their attention which are subject to investigation under § <cite path="§5-1405">5-1405</cite>(b) and shall assist in making the bodies and related evidence available to a medical examiner for investigation and autopsy.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(c)</num>
      <text>Any person subject to the reporting requirements in subsection (b) of this section who willfully fails to comply with this section shall be guilty of a misdemeanor and upon conviction shall be fined not less than $100 nor more than $1,000.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>History</heading>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 13-172">Oct. 19, 2000, D.C. Law 13-172, § 2907, 47 DCR 6308</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Prior Codifications</heading>
        <annotation>1981 Ed., § 11-2304.</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Emergency Legislation</heading>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 day) addition of section, see § 2907 of the Fiscal Year 2001 Budget Support Congressional Review Emergency Act of 2000 (D.C. Act 13-438, October 20, 2000,  47 DCR 8740).</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section from-code="true">
    <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" path="|5|14"/>
    <num codify:value="5-1407">2908</num>
    <heading>Subpoena power for access to confidential medical records.</heading>
    <text>The CME is authorized to issue a subpoena for confidential medical records and relevant information from physicians, hospitals, nursing homes, residential care facilities and other health care providers as in his or her opinion is necessary for investigating deaths under this chapter. Any such subpoena issued by the CME may be enforced by order of the Superior Court. The Mayor shall, by regulation, prescribe procedures for issuing administrative subpoenas pursuant to this section.</text>
    <annotations>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>History</heading>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 13-172">Oct. 19, 2000, D.C. Law 13-172, § 2908, 47 DCR 6308</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Emergency Legislation</heading>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 day) addition of section, see § 2908 of the Fiscal Year 2001 Budget Support Congressional Review Emergency Act of 2000 (D.C. Act 13-438, October 20, 2000,  47 DCR 8740).</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Delegation of Authority</heading>
        <annotation>Delegation of Authority Pursuant to Title XXIX of <cite doc="D.C. Law 13-172">D.C. Law 13-172</cite>, the “Fiscal Year 2001 Budget Support Act of 2000” Creating the Office of the Chief Medical Examiner, see Mayor’s Order 2001-04, January 5, 2001 ( 48 DCR 938).</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section from-code="true">
    <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" path="|5|14"/>
    <num codify:value="5-1408">2909</num>
    <heading>Possession of evidence and property.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>(a)</num>
      <text>At the scene of any death subject to investigation under § <cite path="§5-1405">5-1405</cite>(b), the medical examiner, a medicolegal investigator, or a law enforcement officer shall take possession of any objects or articles which, in his or her opinion, may be useful in establishing the cause and manner of death or the identity of the decedent and shall hold them as evidence. The Mayor shall issue regulations concerning the evidence in the possession of the CME and the transfer of that evidence to law enforcement agencies or the United States Attorney’s Office. The regulations shall include requirements on the length of time evidence shall be preserved by the CME, and shall require that toxicology and histology specimens be preserved for periods of time consistent with the accreditation requirements of the National Association of Medical Examiners.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(b)</num>
      <text>In the absence of the next of kin, a police officer, a medical examiner or a medicolegal investigator may take possession of all property of value found on or in the custody of the decedent. If possession is taken of the property, the police officer, medical examiner or medicolegal investigator shall make an exact inventory of it and deliver the property to the Property Clerk of the Metropolitan Police Department. The Mayor shall issue regulations concerning the transfer of any such property from the OCME.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>History</heading>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 13-172">Oct. 19, 2000, D.C. Law 13-172, § 2909, 47 DCR 6308</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 15-174">July 15, 2004, D.C. Law 15-174, § 201(a), 51 DCR 3677</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Prior Codifications</heading>
        <annotation>1981 Ed., § 11-2305.</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Effect of Amendments</heading>
        <annotation><cite doc="D.C. Law 15-174">D.C. Law 15-174</cite> added the last sentence to subsec. (a).</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Emergency Legislation</heading>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 day) addition of section, see § 2909 of the Fiscal Year 2001 Budget Support Congressional Review Emergency Act of 2000 (D.C. Act 13-438, October 20, 2000,  47 DCR 8740).</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Delegation of Authority</heading>
        <annotation>Delegation of Authority Pursuant to Title XXIX of <cite doc="D.C. Law 13-172">D.C. Law 13-172</cite>, the “Fiscal Year 2001 Budget Support Act of 2000” Creating the Office of the Chief Medical Examiner, see Mayor’s Order 2001-04, January 5, 2001 ( 48 DCR 938).</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section from-code="true">
    <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" path="|5|14"/>
    <num codify:value="5-1409">2910</num>
    <heading>Examination; further investigation and autopsy.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>(a)</num>
      <text>If, in the opinion of the CME, the cause and manner of death are established with a reasonable medical certainty, the CME shall complete a report of the medical examination of the decedent.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(b)</num>
      <text>If, in the opinion of the CME, or the United States Attorney, further investigation as to the cause or manner of death is required or the public interest so requires, a medical examiner shall either perform, or the CME shall arrange for a qualified pathologist to perform, an autopsy on the body of the decedent and to retain tissues and biological specimens deemed necessary to an investigation. No consent of the next of kin shall be required for an autopsy to be performed under this section.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(c)</num>
      <text>The medical examiner performing the autopsy shall make a complete record of the findings and conclusions of any autopsy and shall prepare a report thereon.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>History</heading>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 13-172">Oct. 19, 2000, D.C. Law 13-172, § 2910, 47 DCR 6308</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Prior Codifications</heading>
        <annotation>1981 Ed., § 11-2306.</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Emergency Legislation</heading>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 day) addition of section, see § 2910 of the Fiscal Year 2001 Budget Support Congressional Review Emergency Act of 2000 (D.C. Act 13-438, October 20, 2000,  47 DCR 8740).</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section from-code="true">
    <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" path="|5|14"/>
    <num codify:value="5-1410">2911</num>
    <heading>Autopsy by pathologist other than a medical examiner.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>(a)</num>
      <text>If an autopsy is performed by a pathologist other than a medical examiner by request of the CME, the pathologist shall furnish to the CME, a complete record of the findings and conclusions of the autopsy. The CME, or assigned medical examiner, shall thereupon prepare a report, indicating the name of the pathologist performing the autopsy, the pathologist’s findings and conclusions, and the CME’s, or assigned medical examiner’s, own comments, if appropriate.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(b)</num>
      <text>A pathologist other than a medical examiner who performs an autopsy at the request of the CME shall be compensated in accordance with a fee rate established by the Mayor by regulation.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>History</heading>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 13-172">Oct. 19, 2000, D.C. Law 13-172, § 2911, 47 DCR 6308</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Prior Codifications</heading>
        <annotation>1981 Ed., § 11-2307.</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Emergency Legislation</heading>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 day) addition of section, see § 2911 of the Fiscal Year 2001 Budget Support Congressional Review Emergency Act of 2000 (D.C. Act 13-438, October 20, 2000,  47 DCR 8740).</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Delegation of Authority</heading>
        <annotation>Delegation of Authority Pursuant to Title XXIX of <cite doc="D.C. Law 13-172">D.C. Law 13-172</cite>, the “Fiscal Year 2001 Budget Support Act of 2000” Creating the Office of the Chief Medical Examiner, see Mayor’s Order 2001-04, January 5, 2001 ( 48 DCR 938).</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section from-code="true">
    <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" path="|5|14"/>
    <num codify:value="5-1411">2912</num>
    <heading>Delivery of body; expenses.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>(a)</num>
      <text>Following investigation or autopsy, the CME shall release the body of the decedent to the person having the right to the body for the purpose of burial or other disposition pursuant to law. If after a reasonable time, established by regulation by the Mayor, no authorized person claims the body of the decedent, the CME shall dispose of the body in accordance with the law.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(b)</num>
      <text>Expenses of transportation of bodies and autopsies performed pursuant to this chapter shall be borne by the District of Columbia.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(c)</num>
      <text>Only the CME shall dispose unclaimed bodies in the District without of next of kin or other means of disposition. The Mayor shall prescribe fees and regulations for the storage and disposal of unclaimed bodies.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>History</heading>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 13-172">Oct. 19, 2000, D.C. Law 13-172, § 2912, 47 DCR 6308</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Prior Codifications</heading>
        <annotation>1981 Ed., § 11-2308.</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Emergency Legislation</heading>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 day) addition of section, see § 2912 of the Fiscal Year 2001 Budget Support Congressional Review Emergency Act of 2000 (D.C. Act 13-438, October 20, 2000,  47 DCR 8740).</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Delegation of Authority</heading>
        <annotation>Delegation of Authority Pursuant to Title XXIX of <cite doc="D.C. Law 13-172">D.C. Law 13-172</cite>, the “Fiscal Year 2001 Budget Support Act of 2000” Creating the Office of the Chief Medical Examiner, see Mayor’s Order 2001-04, January 5, 2001 ( 48 DCR 938).</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section from-code="true">
    <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" path="|5|14"/>
    <num codify:value="5-1412">2913</num>
    <heading>Maintenance of records; annual report.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>(a)</num>
      <text>The CME shall be responsible for maintaining full and complete records and files, properly indexed, giving the name, if known, of every person whose death is investigated, the place where the body was found, the date, cause and manner of death and all other relevant information and reports of the medical examiner concerning the death. The CME shall issue a death certificate in all appropriate cases.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(a-1)</num>
      <text>Records and files related to an open investigation of a homicide shall be retained for 65 years from the date the CME initiates its investigation of the homicide. Other records and files maintained under subsection (a) of this section shall be retained by the CME for periods of time established by regulations issued pursuant to § <cite path="§5-1417">5-1417</cite>. For the purposes of this subsection, the term “open investigation” shall have the same meaning as provided in § <cite path="§5-113.31">5-113.31</cite>(10).</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(b)</num>
      <text>The records and files maintained under the provisions of subsection (a) of this section shall be open to inspection by the Mayor, or Mayor’s authorized representative, the United States Attorney and the United States Attorney’s assistants, the Metropolitan Police Department, or any other law enforcement agency or official, and the Child Fatality Review Committee when necessary for the discharge of its official duties; upon request, to such persons, the CME shall promptly deliver to such persons copies of records relating to the deaths as to which further investigation may be advisable.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(c)</num>
      <text>Any other person with a legitimate interest may obtain copies of records maintained pursuant to subsection (a) of this section upon such conditions and payment of such fees as may be prescribed by regulation by the Mayor. If such person fails to meet the prescribed conditions, such person may obtain copies of such records pursuant to court order if the court is satisfied that such person has a legitimate interest.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(d)</num>
      <text>The CME shall prepare an annual report to the Mayor which includes information on the number of autopsies performed, statistics as to the causes of deaths, and any other relevant information the Mayor may require. The annual report shall be open to inspection by the public. The annual report shall not identify by name, deceased persons examined.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>History</heading>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 13-172">Oct. 19, 2000, D.C. Law 13-172, § 2913, 47 DCR 6308</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 14-28">Oct. 3, 2001, D.C. Law 14-28, § 4619(c), 48 DCR 6981</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 15-174">July 15, 2004, D.C. Law 15-174, § 201(b), 51 DCR 3677</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Section References</heading>
        <annotation>This section is referenced in § <cite path="§5-1413">5-1413</cite>.</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Prior Codifications</heading>
        <annotation>1981 Ed., § 11-2309.</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Effect of Amendments</heading>
        <annotation><cite doc="D.C. Law 14-28">D.C. Law 14-28</cite> substituted “official, and the Child Fatality Review Committee when necessary for the discharge of its official duties” for “official” in subsec. (b).</annotation>
        <annotation><cite doc="D.C. Law 15-174">D.C. Law 15-174</cite> added subsec. (a-1).</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Temporary Amendment of Section</heading>
        <annotation>For temporary (225 day) amendment of section, see § 19(c) of Child Fatality Review Committee Establishment Temporary Act of 2001 (<cite doc="D.C. Law 14-20">D.C. Law 14-20</cite>, September 6, 2001, law notification  48 DCR 9090).</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Emergency Legislation</heading>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 day) addition of section, see § 2913 of the Fiscal Year 2001 Budget Support Congressional Review Emergency Act of 2000 (D.C. Act 13-438, October 20, 2000,  47 DCR 8740).</annotation>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 day) amendment of section, see § 19(c) of Child Fatality Review Committee Establishment Emergency Act of 2001 (D.C. Act 14-40, April 25, 2001,  48 DCR 5917).</annotation>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 day) amendment of section, see § 19(c) of Child Fatality Review Committee Establishment Legislative Review Emergency Act of 2001 (D.C. Act 14-82, July 9, 2001,  48 DCR 6355).</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Delegation of Authority</heading>
        <annotation>Delegation of Authority Pursuant to Title XXIX of <cite doc="D.C. Law 13-172">D.C. Law 13-172</cite>, the “Fiscal Year 2001 Budget Support Act of 2000” Creating the Office of the Chief Medical Examiner, see Mayor’s Order 2001-04, January 5, 2001 ( 48 DCR 938).</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section from-code="true">
    <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" path="|5|14"/>
    <num codify:value="5-1413">2914</num>
    <heading>Records as evidence.</heading>
    <text>The records maintained pursuant to § <cite path="§5-1412">5-1412</cite>, or reproductions thereof certified by the CME, are admissible as evidence in any court in the District; except that, statements made by witnesses or other persons and conclusions upon nonmedical matters are not admissible.</text>
    <annotations>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>History</heading>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 13-172">Oct. 19, 2000, D.C. Law 13-172, § 2914, 47 DCR 6308</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Prior Codifications</heading>
        <annotation>1981 Ed., § 11-2310.</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Emergency Legislation</heading>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 day) addition of section, see § 2914 of the Fiscal Year 2001 Budget Support Congressional Review Emergency Act of 2000 (D.C. Act 13-438, October 20, 2000,  47 DCR 8740).</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section from-code="true">
    <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" path="|5|14"/>
    <num codify:value="5-1414">2915</num>
    <heading>Autopsies performed under court order.</heading>
    <text>In the case of unexplained, sudden, violent, or suspicious death, when the body is buried without investigation, or there has been an inadequate investigation, the United States Attorney, on his or her own motion, or on request of a medical examiner, or the Metropolitan Police Department, or other law enforcement agency, may petition the appropriate court for an order to conduct an inquiry. The court may order the body exhumed and an autopsy performed. In such cases, records and reports shall be filed as if the autopsy were performed prior to burial; except that, a copy of the report shall be furnished directly to the court.</text>
    <annotations>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>History</heading>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 13-172">Oct. 19, 2000, D.C. Law 13-172, § 2915, 47 DCR 6308</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Prior Codifications</heading>
        <annotation>1981 Ed., § 11-2311.</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Emergency Legislation</heading>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 day) addition of section, see § 2915 of the Fiscal Year 2001 Budget Support Congressional Review Emergency Act of 2000 (D.C. Act 13-438, October 20, 2000,  47 DCR 8740).</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section from-code="true">
    <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" path="|5|14"/>
    <reason>Repealed</reason>
    <num codify:value="5-1415">2916</num>
    <heading>Tissue transplants.</heading>
    <text>Repealed.</text>
    <annotations>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>History</heading>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 13-172">Oct. 19, 2000, D.C. Law 13-172, § 2916, 47 DCR 6308</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 17-145">Apr. 15, 2008, D.C. Law 17-145, § 30(b), 55 DCR 2532</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Prior Codifications</heading>
        <annotation>1981 Ed., § 11-2312.</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Emergency Legislation</heading>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 day) addition of section, see § 2916 of the Fiscal Year 2001 Budget Support Congressional Review Emergency Act of 2000 (D.C. Act 13-438, October 20, 2000,  47 DCR 8740).</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section from-code="true">
    <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" path="|5|14"/>
    <num codify:value="5-1416">2917</num>
    <heading>Personnel, records, functions, and authority transferred.</heading>
    <text>All positions, personnel, property, records, and unexpended balances of appropriations, allocations, and other funds available or to be available to the Office of the Chief Medical Examiner and all the functions assigned and authority delegated to the Office of the Chief Medical Examiner are hereby transferred to the Office of the Chief Medical Examiner established pursuant to § <cite path="§5-1402">5-1402</cite>:</text>
    <para>
      <num>(1)</num>
      <text>Commissioner’s Order 70-83, effective March 6, 1970, vesting the Director of the Department of Human Resources with authority over the Chief Medical Examiner and the operations of the Office of the Chief Medical Examiner under Public Law 91-358;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(2)</num>
      <text>Commissioner’s Order 71-16, effective January 26, 1971, establishing the Office of the Chief Medical Examiner, headed by the Chief Medical Examiner, in the Department of Human Resources with the functions set forth in Public Law 91-358;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(3)</num>
      <text>Part IV(B)(2) of Reorganization Plan No. 2 of 1979, effective February 21, 1980, vesting the Commissioner of Public Health, Department of Human Services, with administrative authority over the technical programs and services for medical investigation of all deaths, except clearly natural deaths under Public Law 91-358 and Commissioner’s Order 71-16, as amended;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(4)</num>
      <text>Part III(K) of Reorganization Plan No. 3 of 1986, effective January 3, 1987, vesting the Director of the Department of Human Services with responsibility for medically investigating and reporting on known or suspected homicides, suicides, medically unattended or accidental deaths and deaths which might threaten public health and safety;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(5)</num>
      <text>Mayor’s Order 89-62, Establishment of Commission on the Medical Examiner’s Office, effective March 28, 1989;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(6)</num>
      <text>Part IV(B)(2) of Reorganization Plan 4 of 1996, Establishment of the District of Columbia Department of Health, placing the Office of the Chief Medical Examiner under the supervision of the Director of the Department of Health; and</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(7)</num>
      <text>Department of Health Organization Order No. 15, Office of the Chief Medical Examiner, dated May 30, 1997, establishing the Office of the Chief Medical Examiner in the Department of Health.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>History</heading>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 13-172">Oct. 19, 2000, D.C. Law 13-172, § 2917, 47 DCR 6308</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Emergency Legislation</heading>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 day) addition section, see § 2917 of the Fiscal Year 2001 Budget Support Congressional Review Emergency Act of 2000 (D.C. Act 13-438, October 20, 2000,  47 DCR 8740).</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section from-code="true">
    <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" path="|5|14"/>
    <num codify:value="5-1417">2918</num>
    <heading>Regulations and fees.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>(a)</num>
      <text>The Mayor shall promulgate proposed regulations to implement the provisions of this chapter. The proposed regulations shall be submitted to the Council for a 45-day period of review, excluding Saturdays, Sundays, legal holidays, and days of Council recess. If the Council does not approve or disapprove the regulations, in whole or in part, by resolution within the 45-day review period, the proposed rules shall be deemed approved.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(b)</num>
      <text>The Mayor is authorized to establish fees and rates required by this chapter.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>History</heading>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 13-172">Oct. 19, 2000, D.C. Law 13-172, § 2918, 47 DCR 6308</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Section References</heading>
        <annotation>This section is referenced in § <cite path="§5-1412">5-1412</cite>.</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Emergency Legislation</heading>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 day) addition of section, see § 2918 of the Fiscal Year 2001 Budget Support Congressional Review Emergency Act of 2000 (D.C. Act 13-438, October 20, 2000,  47 DCR 8740).</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Delegation of Authority</heading>
        <annotation>Delegation of Authority Pursuant to Title XXIX of <cite doc="D.C. Law 13-172">D.C. Law 13-172</cite>, the “Fiscal Year 2001 Budget Support Act of 2000” Creating the Office of the Chief Medical Examiner, see Mayor’s Order 2001-04, January 5, 2001 ( 48 DCR 938).</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section from-code="true">
    <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" path="|5|14"/>
    <num codify:value="5-1418">2918a</num>
    <heading>Office of the Chief Medical Examiner Management Fund.</heading>
    <text>Repealed.</text>
    <annotations>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>History</heading>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 13-172">Oct. 19, 2000, D.C. Law 13-172, § 2918a</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 16-33">as added Oct. 20, 2005, D.C. Law 16-33, § 3002, 52 DCR 7503</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 19-21">Sept. 14, 2011, D.C. Law 19-21, § 9051, 58 DCR 6226</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Emergency Legislation</heading>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 day) addition, see § 3002 of Fiscal Year 2006 Budget Support Emergency Act of 2005 (D.C. Act 16-168, July 26, 2005,  52 DCR 7667).</annotation>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 day) addition of section, see § 202 of Comprehensive Impaired Driving and Alcohol Testing Program Emergency Amendment Act of 2012 (D.C. Act 19-429, July 30, 2012,  59 DCR 9387).</annotation>
        <annotation>For temporary addition of <cite doc="D.C. Law 13-172">D.C. Law 13-172</cite>, § 2918b, concerning blood and urine testing for the District’s impaired driving program, see § 202 of the Comprehensive Impaired Driving and Alcohol Testing Program Congressional Review Emergency Amendment Act of 2012 (D.C Act 19-508, October 26, 2012,  59 DCR 13325).</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Short Title</heading>
        <annotation>Short title of subtitle A of title III of Law 16-33: Section 3001 of <cite doc="D.C. Law 16-33">D.C. Law 16-33</cite> provided that subtitle A of title III of the act may be cited as the Office of the Chief Medical Examiner Management Fund Amendment Act of 2005.</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section from-code="true">
    <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" path="|5|14"/>
    <num codify:value="5-1419">2918b</num>
    <heading>Impaired driving program; chemical testing.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>(a)</num>
      <text>The CME shall be responsible for ensuring the accuracy of blood and urine testing for the District’s impaired driving program. The CME may test or authorize the testing of specimens, as defined by § <cite path="§50-1901">50-1901</cite>(18), for the purposes of determining if specimens contain alcohol or a drug.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(b)</num>
      <text>Until October 1, 2012, and after October 1, 2012 if authorized under § <cite path="§5-1501.07">5-1501.07</cite>(d), the CME shall be responsible for testing and certifying the accuracy of any District instrument utilized by District law enforcement personnel to test the alcohol content of breath. A District breath-test instrument shall only be used by District law enforcement personnel if it has been certified by the CME to be accurate. Certification of the accuracy of each breath test instrument must occur at least once every 180 days.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(c)</num>
      <text>In addition to the requirements under subsection (a) of this section, the CME shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Develop a program for District law enforcement personnel to become trained and certified as a breath test instrument operator;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Develop policies and procedures for the operation and maintenance of all breath test instruments utilized by District law enforcement personnel; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Develop policies and procedures for the maintenance of records demonstrating that the breath test instruments utilized by District law enforcement personnel are in proper operating condition.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>History</heading>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 13-172">Oct. 19, 2000, D.C. Law 13-172, § 2918b</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 19-266">as added Apr. 27, 2013, D.C. Law 19-266, § 202, 59 DCR 12957</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 19-260">Apr. 20, 2013, D.C. Law 19-260, § 2, 60 DCR 1292</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Effect of Amendments</heading>
        <annotation>The 2013 amendment by <cite doc="D.C. Law 19-260">D.C. Law 19-260</cite> substituted “180 days” for “3 months” in (b).</annotation>
        <annotation>The 2013 amendment by <cite doc="D.C. Law 19-266">D.C. Law 19-266</cite> added this section.</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Emergency Legislation</heading>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 days) addition of this section, see § 202 of the Comprehensive Impaired Driving and Alcohol Testing Program Congressional Review Emergency Act of 2013 (D.C. Act 20-3, January 29, 2013,  60 DCR 2762, 20 DCSTAT 410).</annotation>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 days) addition of this section, see § 202 of the Comprehensive Impaired Driving and Alcohol Testing Program Second Congressional Review Emergency Act of 2013 (D.C. Act 20-51, April 17, 2013,  60 DCR 6344, 20 DCSTAT 1360).</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Editor's Notes</heading>
        <annotation>Section 5 of <cite doc="D.C. Law 19-260">D.C. Law 19-260</cite> provided that the Act shall apply as of the effective date of the Comprehensive Impaired Driving and Alcohol Breath Testing Program Amendment Act of 2012, signed by the Mayor on October 24, 2012 (D.C. Act 19-489;  59 DCR 12957), which became <cite doc="D.C. Law 19-266">D.C. Law 19-266</cite>, effective April 27, 2013.</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section from-code="true">
    <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" path="|8|21|I"/>
    <num codify:value="8-2101.01">902</num>
    <heading>Establishment of Bureau of Rodent Control.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>(a)</num>
      <text>There is established within the Department of Health a Bureau of Rodent Control (“Bureau”).</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(b)</num>
      <text>The Bureau shall be responsible for the control and elimination of rodents in the District that serve as vectors for disease, including but not limited to:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The treatment and baiting of public spaces for rodents;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The conducting of surveys of locations; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The coordination of public outreach, education and enforcement efforts relating to cleanliness and rodent control.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>History</heading>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 13-172">Oct. 19, 2000, D.C. Law 13-172, § 902, 47 DCR 6308</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Emergency Legislation</heading>
        <annotation>For temporary (90-day) addition of §§ 6-1051.1 to 6-1051.7 1981 Ed., see §§ 902 to 908 of the Fiscal Year 2001 Budget Support Emergency Act of 2000 (D.C. Act 13-376, July 24, 2000,  47 DCR 6574).</annotation>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 day) amendment of section, see §§ 902 to 908 of the Fiscal Year 2001 Budget Support Congressional Review Emergency Act of 2000 (D.C. Act 13-438, October 20, 2000,  47 DCR 8740).</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Delegation of Authority</heading>
        <annotation>Delegation of Authority Pursuant to DC Law 6-100, the “Litter Control Administration Act of 1985;” DC Law 6-42, the “Department of Consumer and Regulatory Affairs Civil Infractions Act of 1985;” DC Law 5-165, the “DC Air Pollution Control Act of 1984;” DC Law 13-172, the “Rodent Control Act of 2000;” and DC Law 6-126, the “Construction Codes Approval and Amendments Act of 1986”, see Mayor’s Order 2002-5, February 1, 2002 ( 49 DCR 911).</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section from-code="true">
    <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" path="|8|21|I"/>
    <num codify:value="8-2101.02">903</num>
    <heading>Transfer of functions and duties from the Department of Public Works.</heading>
    <text>All the functions, duties, property, records, and personnel associated with the control and elimination of rodents now under the authority of the Department of Public Works are transferred to the Bureau.</text>
    <annotations>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>History</heading>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 13-172">Oct. 19, 2000, D.C. Law 13-172, § 903, 47 DCR 6308</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Emergency Legislation</heading>
        <annotation>For temporary (90-day) addition of section, see notes following § <cite path="§8-2101.01">8-2101.01</cite>.</annotation>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 day) amendment of section, see §§ 902 to 908 of the Fiscal Year 2001 Budget Support Congressional Review Emergency Act of 2000 (D.C. Act 13-438, October 20, 2000,  47 DCR 8740).</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section from-code="true">
    <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" path="|8|21|II"/>
    <num codify:value="8-2103.01">904</num>
    <heading>Definitions.</heading>
    <text>For the purposes of this subchapter, the term:</text>
    <para>
      <num>(1)</num>
      <text>“Abate” means removing rodent infestations by eliminating or rodent-proofing rodent food sources, eliminating rodent nesting areas, rodent-proofing building entry ways, and poisoning or trapping existing rodent  populations.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(2)</num>
      <text>“Debris” means any of the following:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(A)</num>
        <text>Construction or demolition waste that is not stored in a rodent-proof   container and not removed after 14 days or longer;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(B)</num>
        <text>Yard waste and branches that are not bundled and set out for waste collection, but not yard waste placed in a properly maintained compost pile; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(C)</num>
        <text>Fire wood that is stored next to a building or left in loose piles on   the ground, but not fire wood that is stored away from buildings and at least   18 inches above the ground or in a rodent-proof building.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(3)</num>
      <text>“Grease” means used cooking oil, vegetable oil, shortening, margarine or  any other used fat or oil used for cooking, frying or baking intended for  recycling or disposal.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(4)</num>
      <text>“Harborage” means rodent infestation or providing food or nesting areas for rodents, which may be identified by the presence of burrows, droppings, tracks, runways, gnawings, urine stains, odor, live or dead rodents, nests, and rodent gnawed food.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(5)</num>
      <text>“Hardware cloth” means galvanized metal cloth or netting with small  diameter holes used to prevent rodents from entering buildings.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(6)</num>
      <text>“Rodent-proof” or “rodent-proofing” includes:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(A)</num>
        <text>Heavy duty plastic or metal containers with tightly-fitting lids  fastened to the container; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(B)</num>
        <text>Using hardware cloth to seal building openings.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>History</heading>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 13-172">Oct. 19, 2000, D.C. Law 13-172, § 904, 47 DCR 6308</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Emergency Legislation</heading>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 day) amendment of section, see §§ 902 to 908 of the Fiscal Year 2001 Budget Support Congressional Review Emergency Act of 2000 (D.C. Act 13-438, October 20, 2000,  47 DCR 8740).</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section from-code="true">
    <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" path="|8|21|II"/>
    <reason>Expired</reason>
    <num codify:value="8-2103.02">905</num>
    <heading>Rodent Control Fund.</heading>
    <text>Expired.</text>
    <annotations>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>History</heading>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 13-172">Oct. 19, 2000, D.C. Law 13-172, § 905, 47 DCR 6308</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Emergency Legislation</heading>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 day) amendment of section, see §§ 902 to 908 of the Fiscal Year 2001 Budget Support Congressional Review Emergency Act of 2000 (D.C. Act 13-438, October 20, 2000,  47 DCR 8740).</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Editor's Notes</heading>
        <annotation>Pursuant to subsection (d) of this section, this section expired on September 30, 2002.</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section from-code="true">
    <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" path="|8|21|II"/>
    <reason>Expired</reason>
    <num codify:value="8-2103.03">906</num>
    <heading>Disbursements from the Fund.</heading>
    <text>Expired.</text>
    <annotations>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>History</heading>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 13-172">Oct. 19, 2000, D.C. Law 13-172, § 906, 47 DCR 6308</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Emergency Legislation</heading>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 day) amendment of section, see §§ 902 to 908 of the Fiscal Year 2001 Budget Support Congressional Review Emergency Act of 2000 (D.C. Act 13-438, October 20, 2000,  47 DCR 8740).</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Editor's Notes</heading>
        <annotation>Pursuant to subsection (f) of this section, this section expired on September 30, 2002.</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section from-code="true">
    <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" path="|8|21|II"/>
    <num codify:value="8-2103.04">907</num>
    <heading>Corrective actions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>(a)</num>
      <text>Subject to the availability of appropriations, the Bureau may undertake actions to correct certain health hazards that have resulted from the harborage of rodents, including cleanup, abatement, and preventive measures, if the following conditions exist:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The District needs to take an action in order to protect human health;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>One or more of the following conditions exist:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(A)</num>
          <text>The action is required to protect public space;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(B)</num>
          <text>No person can be found who is the owner of the property in question, and   is capable of proper implementation of the required corrective action within   30 days of the posting of notice on the property in question that violation   of this subtitle has occurred, or shorter period if so determined by the   Mayor as may be necessary to protect human health;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(C)</num>
          <text>A situation exists that requires immediate action by the Mayor to   protect human health; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(D)</num>
          <text>The responsible party has failed or refused to comply within 30 days of   a mayoral order for compliance.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(b)</num>
      <text>If the District incurs costs for undertaking any corrective or enforcement action to abate rodent infestation, rodent harborage, or rodent food sources, all parties found to be liable by the Mayor shall be jointly and severally liable to the District government for the costs incurred by the District. In addition to any other enforcement action, the Mayor may assess any reasonable costs for correcting the condition and any related expenses as a tax against the property, carry the tax on the regular tax rolls, and collect the tax in the same manner as real estate taxes are collected.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>History</heading>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 13-172">Oct. 19, 2000, D.C. Law 13-172, § 907, 47 DCR 6308</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Emergency Legislation</heading>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 day) amendment of section, see §§ 902 to 908 of the Fiscal Year 2001 Budget Support Congressional Review Emergency Act of 2000 (D.C. Act 13-438, October 20, 2000,  47 DCR 8740).</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section from-code="true">
    <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" path="|8|21|II"/>
    <num codify:value="8-2103.05">908</num>
    <heading>Rodent harborage prohibited.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>(a)</num>
      <text>It shall be unlawful for any person to cause or permit the accumulation of debris on public or private property or cause or permit weeds or grass to grow to a height of 8 inches or more on private property which they own.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(b)</num>
      <text>Upon the transfer or change in occupancy of any real property, the owner of the property shall inspect the property for signs of rodent harborage. If signs of past rodent harborage are found, all rodent entryways shall be sealed with hardware cloth or another appropriate material to prevent re-infestation. If an active infestation is found, all rodent entryways shall be sealed with hardware cloth or other appropriate material, and the infestation shall be abated.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(c)</num>
      <text>Any person violating subsections (a) and (b) of this section shall abate the condition causing rodent harborage within 14 days of notification of the violation from the Mayor. Any abatement of existing rodent populations shall be performed by a licensed and certified pest controller. Any person who fails to abate the condition causing rodent harborage shall be liable to arrest and upon conviction shall be deemed guilty of a misdemeanor and shall be subject to a fine for each offense not to exceed $10,000, or shall be imprisoned for a period not to exceed 90 days, or both, in the discretion of the court.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(d)</num>
      <text>Civil fines, penalties and fees may be imposed as alternative sanctions for any infraction of this subtitle, or any rules or regulations issued under the authority of this subchapter, pursuant to Chapter 18 of Title 2. Adjudication of any infractions shall be pursuant to Chapter 18 of Title 2.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>History</heading>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 13-172">Oct. 19, 2000, D.C. Law 13-172, § 908, 47 DCR 6308</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Emergency Legislation</heading>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 day) amendment of section, see §§ 902 to 908 of the Fiscal Year 2001 Budget Support Congressional Review Emergency Act of 2000 (D.C. Act 13-438, October 20, 2000,  47 DCR 8740).</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Delegation of Authority</heading>
        <annotation>Delegation of Authority Pursuant to Title IX of <cite doc="D.C. Law 13-172">D.C. Law 13-172</cite>, the “Rodent Control Act of 2000”, see Mayor’s Order 2001-21, February 2, 2001 ( 48 DCR 1362).</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section from-code="true">
    <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" path="|34|18"/>
    <num codify:value="34-1801">602</num>
    <heading>Definitions.</heading>
    <text>For the purposes of this chapter, the term:</text>
    <para>
      <num>(1)</num>
      <text>Repealed.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(2)</num>
      <text>“Commission” means the Public Service Commission of the District of  Columbia.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(2A)</num>
      <text>“Consumer” means an individual who purchases prepaid wireless telecommunications service in a retail transaction for any purpose other than resale.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(3)</num>
      <text>“Fund” means the Emergency and Non-Emergency Number Telephone Calling Systems Fund established under § <cite path="§34-1802">34-1802</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(4)</num>
      <text>“Local exchange carrier” means a person that is engaged in the provision  of local exchange service or exchange access.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(5)</num>
      <text>“Local exchange service” means a telecommunications service provided  within an exchange area.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(6)</num>
      <text>“Person” means an individual, corporation, company, association, joint-stock company, association, firm, partnership, or other entity.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(6A)</num>
      <text>“Prepaid wireless E911 charge” means the charge that is required to be collected by a seller from a consumer in the amount established under § <cite path="§34-1803.02">34-1803.02</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(6B)</num>
      <text>“Prepaid wireless telecommunications service” means a commercial mobile radio service, as defined by § 20.3 of Title 47 of the Code of Federal Regulations, that allows a caller to dial 911 to access the 911 system, which service must be paid for in advance and is sold in predetermined units or dollars of which the number declines with use in a known amount.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(6C)</num>
      <text>“Provider” means a person that provides prepaid wireless telecommunications service pursuant to a license issued by the Federal Communications Commission.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(7)</num>
      <text>“Public safety answering point” means an answering location for 911 and  311 calls originating in a given area.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(7A)</num>
      <text>“Retail transaction” means the purchase of prepaid wireless telecommunications service from a seller for any purpose other than resale.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(8)</num>
      <text>“Reverse 911 system” means a capability that allows the Metropolitan  Police Department to forward a pre-recorded message to residents and  businesses within a designated geographical area.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(8A)</num>
      <text>“Seller” means a person who sells prepaid wireless telecommunications service to another person.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(9)</num>
      <text>Repealed.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(10)</num>
      <text>“911 system” means:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(A)</num>
        <text>Equipment for connecting and out-switching a 911 call originating within   a local exchange carrier’s local exchange service;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(B)</num>
        <text>Trunking facilities from a local exchange carrier to a public safety answering point;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(C)</num>
        <text>Equipment necessary for routing a 911 call to a public safety answering point;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(D)</num>
        <text>Facilities and staff needed to operate a call answering center;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(E)</num>
        <text>A 311 system; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(F)</num>
        <text>A reverse 911 system.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(11)</num>
      <text>“311 system” means a telephone system that is used to reduce emergency  telephone call congestion by diverting non-emergency calls from the emergency  telephone lines.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>History</heading>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 13-172">Oct. 19, 2000, D.C. Law 13-172, § 602, 47 DCR 6308</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 15-39">Nov. 13, 2003, D.C. Law 15-39, § 502(a), 50 DCR 5668</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 18-223">Sept. 24, 2010, D.C. Law 18-223, § 3002(a), 57 DCR 6242</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Section References</heading>
        <annotation>This section is referenced in § <cite path="§1-327.53">1-327.53</cite>.</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Effect of Amendments</heading>
        <annotation>Section 607 of <cite doc="D.C. Law 13-172">D.C. Law 13-172</cite> provided: “Except for section 606, this title shall apply as of October 1, 2000.”</annotation>
        <annotation><cite doc="D.C. Law 15-39">D.C. Law 15-39</cite> repealed pars. (1) and (9).</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Emergency Legislation</heading>
        <annotation>For temporary (90-day) addition of section, see § 602 of the Fiscal Year 2001 Budget Support Emergency Act of 2000 (D.C. Act 13-376, July 24, 2000,  47 DCR 6574).</annotation>
        <annotation>For temporary (90-day) authorization of applicability of section, see § 609 of the Fiscal Year 2001 Budget Support Emergency Act of 2000 (D.C. Act 13-376, July 24, 2000,  47 DCR 6574).</annotation>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 day) amendment of section, see §§ 602 to 605, 607, of the Fiscal Year 2001 Budget Support Congressional Review Emergency Act of 2000 (D.C. Act 13-438, October 20, 2000,  47 DCR 8740).</annotation>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 day) amendment of section, see § 502(a) of Fiscal Year 2004 Budget Support Emergency Act of 2003 (D.C. Act 15-105, June 20, 2003,  50 DCR 5613).</annotation>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 day) amendment of section, see § 502(a) of Fiscal Year 2004 Budget Support Congressional Review Emergency Act of 2003 (D.C. Act 15-149, September 22, 2003,  50 DCR 8360).</annotation>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 day) amendment of section, see § 3002(a) of Fiscal Year 2011 Budget Support Emergency Act of 2010 (D.C. Act 18-463, July 2, 2010,  57 DCR 6542).</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Short Title</heading>
        <text>Short title of title V of Law 15-39: Section 501 of <cite doc="D.C. Law 15-39">D.C. Law 15-39</cite> provided that title V of the act may be cited as the Emergency and Non-Emergency Number Telephone Calling Systems Fund Amendment Act of 2003.</text>
        <text>Short title: Section 3001 of <cite doc="D.C. Law 18-223">D.C. Law 18-223</cite> provided that subtitle A of title III of the act may be cited as the “Prepaid Wireless E911 Charge Amendment Act of 2010”.</text>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Delegation of Authority</heading>
        <annotation>Delegation of Mayor’s Authority under Title VI of <cite doc="D.C. Law 13-172">D.C. Law 13-172</cite>, the “Emergency and Non-Emergency Number Telephone Calling Systems Fund Act of 2000”, see Mayor’s Order 2004-165, September 24, 2004 ( 51 DCR 9750).</annotation>
        <annotation>Delegation of Authority pursuant to the Emergency and Non-Emergency Number Telephone Calling Systems Fund Act of 2000 and Section 3208 of the Office of Unified Communications Establishment Act of 2004, see Mayor’s Order 2009-85, May 27, 2009 ( 56 DCR 6826).</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Editor's Notes</heading>
        <text>Applicability: Section 504 of <cite doc="D.C. Law 15-39">D.C. Law 15-39</cite> provided: Section 502 shall apply as of October 1, 2003.”</text>
        <text>Section 3003 of <cite doc="D.C. Law 18-223">D.C. Law 18-223</cite> provided: “Sec. 3003. Applicability. This subtitle shall apply as of October 1, 2010.”</text>
      </annoGroup>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section from-code="true">
    <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" path="|34|18"/>
    <num codify:value="34-1802">603</num>
    <heading>Emergency and Non-Emergency Number Telephone Calling Systems Fund.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>(a)</num>
      <text>There is established a fund designated as the Emergency and Non-Emergency Number Telephone Calling Systems Fund, which shall be separate from the General Fund of the District of Columbia and shall be used solely for the purposes set forth in subsection (b) of this section. The Fund shall be funded by a tax imposed under §§ <cite path="§34-1803">34-1803</cite> and <cite path="§34-1803.02">34-1803.02</cite> and from sources identified in § <cite path="§34-1803.03">34-1803.03</cite>. All monies collected under § <cite path="§34-1803">34-1803</cite>, § <cite path="§34-1803.02">34-1803.02</cite>, and 34-§ 1803.03 and all interest earned on those monies, shall be deposited into the Fund without regard to fiscal year limitation pursuant to an act of Congress. All monies deposited into the Fund shall not revert to, or be transferred to, the General Fund of the District of Columbia at the end of any fiscal year or at any other time, but shall be continually available for the uses and purposes set forth in subsection (b) of this section, subject to authorization by Congress in an appropriations act.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(a-1)</num>
      <text>All authority and operations of the Fund shall be administered by the Office of Unified Communications.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(b)</num>
      <text>The Fund shall be used solely to defray personnel and nonpersonnel costs incurred by the District of Columbia and its agencies and instrumentalities in providing a 911 system, and direct costs incurred by wireless carriers in providing wireless E-911 service. For purposes of this subsection, the term  “costs” shall include obligations incurred both before and after October 19, 2000. The Fund shall not be used for any other purpose.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(b-1)</num>
      <text>After October 1, 2008, no monies in the Fund shall be used to defray personnel costs.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(b-2)</num>
      <text>After October 1, 2010, no monies in the Fund shall be used to defray nonpersonal costs related to overhead, including energy, rentals, janitorial services, security, or occupancy costs. The Fund shall be used solely to defray technology and equipment costs directly incurred by the District of Columbia and its agencies and instrumentalities in providing a 911 system and direct costs incurred by wireless carriers in providing wireless E-911 service. The Fund shall not be used for any other purpose.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(b-3)</num>
      <text>Notwithstanding subsection (b-2) of this section, monies in the Fund may be used to defray security costs during fiscal year 2011 and fiscal year 2012.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(c)</num>
      <text>The Mayor shall submit to the Council, as a part of the annual budget, a requested appropriation for expenditures from the Fund. Any monies received but not expended in a given fiscal year shall be retained by the Fund.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(d)</num>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>All income and expenses of the Fund shall be audited annually by the Chief Financial Officer, who shall transmit the audit report to the Mayor and the Council.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(A)</num>
          <text>The expenses of the annual audit shall be defrayed by the Fund.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(B)</num>
          <text>The annual audit shall include the following:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>The assets, liabilities, fund balance, revenue, and expenditures of the Fund;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>A detailed accounting of the Fund’s expenditures;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Recommendations to improve the financial management processes of the Fund;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iv)</num>
            <text>Identification of any Fund expenditures that are not permitted under law;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(v)</num>
            <text>Recommendations to improve the language of the Fund’s enabling statute to reflect best practices; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(vi)</num>
            <text>Any other information deemed important by the Chief Financial Officer.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The Chief Financial Officer shall also transmit to the Mayor and Council quarterly reports summarizing the income and expenditures of the Fund.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(e)</num>
      <text>During fiscal year 2003, the Mayor shall allocate at least $500,000 of any revenue the Fund earns due to the enactment of the Emergency and Non-Emergency Number Telephone Calling Systems Fund Amendment Act of 2002 (title VII of <cite doc="D.C. Law 14-307">D.C. Law 14-307</cite>), in excess of the Fund revenue projection included in the District of Columbia’s budget submission to Congress, to increase the number of emergency call-taking staff who are working during hours when call volume is above average. The Mayor may increase the number of emergency call-taking staff through such measures that he considers appropriate, including hiring new staff, authorizing overtime, employing light-duty sworn police officers or firefighters, or offering a shift differential, in accordance with Chapter 6 of Title 1 and any applicable collective bargaining agreements.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>History</heading>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 13-172">Oct. 19, 2000, D.C. Law 13-172, § 603, 47 DCR 6308</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 14-307">June 5, 2003, D.C. Law 14-307, § 702(a), 49 DCR 11664</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 15-39">Nov. 13, 2003, D.C. Law 15-39, § 502(b), 50 DCR 5668</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 15-205">Dec. 7, 2004, D.C. Law 15-205, § 3222, 51 DCR 8441</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 17-20">Sept. 18, 2007, D.C. Law 17-20, § 3022(a), 54 DCR 7052</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 17-219">Aug. 16, 2008, D.C. Law 17-219, § 3002(a), 55 DCR 7598</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 18-111">Mar. 3, 2010, D.C. Law 18-111, § 3011(a), 57 DCR 181</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 18-223">Sept. 24, 2010, D.C. Law 18-223, §§ 3002(b), 3052, 57 DCR 6242</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 19-21">Sept. 14, 2011, D.C. Law 19-21, §§ 3052, 9052(a)(1), 58 DCR 6226</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 19-168">Sept. 20, 2012, D.C. Law 19-168, § 3042(a), 59 DCR 8025</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Section References</heading>
        <annotation>This section is referenced in § <cite path="§34-1801">34-1801</cite>.</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Effect of Amendments</heading>
        <annotation><cite doc="D.C. Law 14-307">D.C. Law 14-307</cite> rewrote subsec. (d) and added subsec. (e). Prior to amendment, subsec. (d) had read as follows: “(d) All income and expenses of the Fund shall be audited annually by the Mayor. The audit report shall be provided to the Council. The expenses of each audit shall be defrayed by the Fund.”</annotation>
        <annotation><cite doc="D.C. Law 15-39">D.C. Law 15-39</cite> rewrote subsec. (a) which had read as follows: “(a) There is established a fund designated as the Emergency and Non-Emergency Number Telephone Calling Systems Fund, which shall be separate from the General Fund of the District of Columbia and shall be used solely for the purposes set forth in subsection (b) of this section. The Fund shall be funded by user fees imposed under § <cite path="§34-1803">34-1803</cite>. All fees collected under § <cite path="§34-1803">34-1803</cite>, and all interest earned on those fees, shall be deposited into the Fund without regard to fiscal year limitation pursuant to an act of Congress. All fees deposited into the Fund shall not revert to the General Fund of the District of Columbia at the end of any fiscal year or at any other time, but shall be continually available for the uses and purposes set forth in subsection (b) of this section, subject to authorization by Congress in an appropriations act”.</annotation>
        <annotation><cite doc="D.C. Law 15-205">D.C. Law 15-205</cite> added subsec. (a-1).</annotation>
        <annotation><cite doc="D.C. Law 17-20">D.C. Law 17-20</cite>, in subsec. (a), substituted “The Fund shall be funded by a tax imposed under § <cite path="§34-1803">34-1803</cite> and from sources identified in § <cite path="§34-1803.01">34-1803.01</cite>” for “The Fund shall be funded by a tax imposed under § <cite path="§34-1803">34-1803</cite>”; and added subsec. (b-1).</annotation>
        <annotation><cite doc="D.C. Law 17-219">D.C. Law 17-219</cite> rewrote subsec. (b-1), which had read as follows: “(b-1) As of October 1, 2009, no more than 10 full-time equivalent employees shall be funded by the Fund. Beginning with the proposed budget for fiscal year 2009, the Mayor shall begin the transition of full-time equivalent employees funded by the Fund so that no more than 10 remain as of October 1, 2009.”</annotation>
        <annotation><cite doc="D.C. Law 18-111">D.C. Law 18-111</cite> added subsec. (b-2).</annotation>
        <annotation><cite doc="D.C. Law 18-223">D.C. Law 18-223</cite>, in subsec. (a), substituted “§ <cite path="§34-1803">34-1803</cite> and § <cite path="§34-1803.02">34-1803.02</cite>” for “§ <cite path="§34-1803">34-1803</cite>” in two places; and rewrote subsec. (d), which had read as follows: “(d) All income and expenses of the Fund shall be audited annually by the Chief Financial Officer, who shall transmit the audit report to the Mayor and Council. The expenses of the annual audit shall be defrayed by the Fund. The Chief Financial Officer shall also transmit to the Mayor and Council quarterly reports summarizing the income and expenditures of the Fund.”</annotation>
        <annotation><cite doc="D.C. Law 19-21">D.C. Law 19-21</cite>, in subsec. (a), deleted “and from sources identified in § <cite path="§34-1803.01">34-1803.01</cite>” following “§ <cite path="§34-1803.02">34-1803.02</cite>”; and added subsec. (b-3).</annotation>
        <annotation>The 2012 amendment by <cite doc="D.C. Law 19-168">D.C. Law 19-168</cite>, in (a), added “and from sources identified in § <cite path="§34-1803.03">34-1803.03</cite>” in the second sentence, substituted “§ <cite path="§34-1803">34-1803</cite>, 34-1803.02, and 34-1803.03” for “§ <cite path="§34-1803">34-1803</cite> and 34-1803.02” in the third sentence, and added “or be transferred to” in the last sentence.</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Emergency Legislation</heading>
        <annotation>For temporary (90-day) addition of section, see § 603 of the Fiscal Year 2001 Budget Support Emergency Act of 2000 (D.C. Act 13-376, July 24, 2000,  47 DCR 6574).</annotation>
        <annotation>For temporary (90-day) authorization of applicability of section, see § 609 of the Fiscal Year 2001 Budget Support Emergency Act of 2000 (D.C. Act 13-376, July 24, 2000,  47 DCR 6574).</annotation>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 day) amendment of section, see § 702(a) of Fiscal Year 2003 Budget Support Amendment Emergency Act of 2002 (D.C. Act 14-544, December 4, 2002,  49 DCR 11700).</annotation>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 day) amendment of section, see § 702(a) of the Fiscal Year 2003 Budget Support Amendment Congressional Review Emergency Act of 2003 (D.C. Act 15-27, February 24, 2003,  50 DCR 2151).</annotation>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 day) amendment of section, see § 702(a) of Fiscal Year 2003 Budget Support Amendment Second Congressional Review Emergency Act of 2003 (D.C. Act 15-103, June 20, 2003,  50 DCR 5499).</annotation>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 day) amendment of section, see § 502(b) of Fiscal Year 2004 Budget Support Emergency Act of 2003 (D.C. Act 15-105, June 20, 2003,  50 DCR 5613).</annotation>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 day) hiring freeze exemption provisions, see § 503 of Fiscal Year 2004 Budget Support Emergency Act of 2003 (D.C. Act 15-105, June 20, 2003,  50 DCR 5613).</annotation>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 day) amendment of section, see § 502(b) and 503 of Fiscal Year 2004 Budget Support Congressional Review Emergency Act of 2003 (D.C. Act 15-149, September 22, 2003,  50 DCR 8360).</annotation>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 day) amendment of section, see § 3222 of Fiscal Year 2005 Budget Support Emergency Act of 2004 (D.C. Act 15-486, August 2, 2004,  51 DCR 8236).</annotation>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 day) amendment of section, see § 3222 of Fiscal Year 2005 Budget Support Congressional Review Emergency Act of 2004 (D.C. Act 15-594, October 26, 2004,  51 DCR 11725).</annotation>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 day) amendment of section, see § 3022(a) of Fiscal Year 2008 Budget Support Emergency Act of 2007 (D.C. Act 17-74, July 25, 2007,  54 DCR 7549).</annotation>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 day) amendment of section, see § 3011(a) of Fiscal Year 2010 Budget Support Second Emergency Act of 2009 (D.C. Act 18-207, October 15, 2009,  56 DCR 8234).</annotation>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 day) amendment of section, see § 3011(a) of Fiscal Year Budget Support Congressional Review Emergency Amendment Act of 2009 (D.C. Act 18-260, January 4, 2010,  57 DCR 345).</annotation>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 day) amendment of section, see §§ 3002(b), 3052 of Fiscal Year 2011 Budget Support Emergency Act of 2010 (D.C. Act 18-463, July 2, 2010,  57 DCR 6542).</annotation>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 day) amendment of section, see § 3002 of Fiscal Year 2012 Budget Support Emergency Act of 2011 (D.C. Act 19-93, June 29, 2011,  58 DCR 5599).</annotation>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 day) amendment of section, see § 3042(a) of Fiscal Year 2013 Budget Support Emergency Act of 2012 (D.C. Act 19-383, June 19, 2012,  59 DCR 7764).</annotation>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 day) amendment of section, see § 3042(a) of Fiscal Year 2013 Budget Support Congressional Review Emergency Act of 2012 (D.C. Act 19-413, July 25, 2012,  59 DCR 9290).</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Short Title</heading>
        <text>Short title: Section 3021 of <cite doc="D.C. Law 17-20">D.C. Law 17-20</cite> provided that subtitle C of title III of the act may be cited as the “Critical Emergency Communications Amendment Act of 2007”.</text>
        <text>Short title: Section 3001 of <cite doc="D.C. Law 17-219">D.C. Law 17-219</cite> provided that subtitle A of title III of the act may be cited as the “Emergency Communications Funding Amendment Act of 2008”.</text>
        <text>Short title: Section 3010 of <cite doc="D.C. Law 18-111">D.C. Law 18-111</cite> provided that subtitle B of title III of the act may be cited as the “E-911 and Consumer Protection Fund Amendment Act of 2009”.</text>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Delegation of Authority</heading>
        <annotation>Delegation of Authority Under Title VI of DC Law 13-172, the “Emergency and Non-Emergency Number Telephone Calling Systems Fund Act of 2000”, see Mayor’s Order 2001-40, March 22, 2001 ( 48 DCR 3440).</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Editor's Notes</heading>
        <text>Section 3003 of <cite doc="D.C. Law 18-223">D.C. Law 18-223</cite> provided: “Sec. 3003. Applicability. This subtitle shall apply as of October 1, 2010.”</text>
        <text>Hiring freeze exemption: Section 503 of <cite doc="D.C. Law 15-39">D.C. Law 15-39</cite> provided: “The positions identified in the Fiscal Year 2004 Spending Plan for the Fund, dated April 16, 2003, shall not be subject to a hiring freeze during Fiscal Year 2004.”</text>
        <text>Applicability: Section 504 of <cite doc="D.C. Law 15-39">D.C. Law 15-39</cite> provided: “Section 502 shall apply as of October 1, 2003.”</text>
        <text>Section 3044 of <cite doc="D.C. Law 19-168">D.C. Law 19-168</cite> provided that Section 3042(a)(3) of the act shall apply as of October 1, 2011. Section 3042(a)(3) of <cite doc="D.C. Law 19-168">D.C. Law 19-168</cite> amended subsection (a) of this section by striking the phrase “All monies deposited into the Fund shall not revert to the General Fund of the District of Columbia” and inserting the phrase “All monies deposited into the Fund shall not revert to, or be transferred to, the General Fund of the District of Columbia” in its place.</text>
      </annoGroup>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section from-code="true">
    <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" path="|34|18"/>
    <num codify:value="34-1803">604</num>
    <heading>Assessments.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>(a)</num>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>There is imposed upon all local exchange carriers, including wireline and wireless carriers and interconnected Voice Over Internet Protocol (“VoIP”) service providers, as defined by 47 C.F.R. § 9.3, that connect users who dial or enter the digits 9-1-1 to the District’s public safety answering points, a monthly tax calculated on the basis of each individual telephone line sold or leased in the District as follows:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(A)</num>
          <text>For wireline local exchange service:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>$0.76 per exchange access line in the District of Columbia;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>$0.62 per Centrex line in the District of Columbia; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>$0.62 per private branch exchange station in the District of Columbia;</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(B)</num>
          <text>For wireless telephone exchange service, $0.76 for each telephone number that has a District of Columbia billing address; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(C)</num>
          <text>For interconnected VoIP service, as defined by 47 C.F.R. § 9.3, $0.76 for each line, trunk, or path that can access to, connect with, or interface with 911 service based on primary place of use.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The PBX tax per station shall be converted into a per-trunk tax based on a ratio of 8 PBX stations to one PBX trunk.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(b)</num>
      <text>Each local exchange carrier shall submit the tax imposed under subsection (a) of this section to the Mayor on a quarterly basis.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(c)</num>
      <text>As part of the annual request for appropriations from the Fund, the Mayor shall provide a report to the Council addressing whether the tax imposed under this section should be adjusted.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(d)</num>
      <text>Each local exchange carrier is authorized to state on the invoice to customers a separate line item stating the amount of tax levied pursuant to this section.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(e)</num>
      <text>The provisions of this section do not apply to prepaid wireless telecommunications service, which shall be subject to the provisions of § <cite path="§34-1803.02">34-1803.02</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>History</heading>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 13-172">Oct. 19, 2000, D.C. Law 13-172, § 604, 47 DCR 6308</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 14-307">June 5, 2003, D.C. Law 14-307, § 702(b), 49 DCR 11664</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 15-39">Nov. 13, 2003, D.C. Law 15-39, § 502(c), 50 DCR 5668</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 17-219">Aug. 16, 2008, D.C. Law 17-219, § 3002(b), 55 DCR 7598</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 18-223">Sept. 24, 2010, D.C. Law 18-223, § 3002(c), 57 DCR 6242</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Section References</heading>
        <annotation>This section is referenced in § <cite path="§34-1802">34-1802</cite> and § <cite path="§34-1805">34-1805</cite>.</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Effect of Amendments</heading>
        <annotation><cite doc="D.C. Law 15-39">D.C. Law 15-39</cite> rewrote the section.</annotation>
        <annotation><cite doc="D.C. Law 14-307">D.C. Law 14-307</cite> rewrote subsec. (a)(2).</annotation>
        <annotation><cite doc="D.C. Law 17-219">D.C. Law 17-219</cite> rewrote subsec. (a)(1).</annotation>
        <annotation><cite doc="D.C. Law 18-223">D.C. Law 18-223</cite> added subsec. (e).</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Emergency Legislation</heading>
        <annotation>For temporary (90-day) addition of section, see § 604 of the Fiscal Year 2001 Budget Support Emergency Act of 2000 (D.C. Act 13-376, July 24, 2000,  47 DCR 6574).</annotation>
        <annotation>For temporary (90-day) authorization of applicability of section, see § 609 of the Fiscal Year 2001 Budget Support Emergency Act of 2000 (D.C. Act 13-376, July 24, 2000,  47 DCR 6574).</annotation>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 day) amendment of section, see § 702(b) of Fiscal Year 2003 Budget Support Amendment Emergency Act of 2002 (D.C. Act 14-544, December 4, 2002,  49 DCR 11700).</annotation>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 day) amendment of section, see § 702(b) of the Fiscal Year 2003 Budget Support Amendment Congressional Review Emergency Act of 2003 (D.C. Act 15-27, February 24, 2003,  50 DCR 2151).</annotation>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 day) amendment of section, see § 702(b) of Fiscal Year 2003 Budget Support Amendment Second Congressional Review Emergency Act of 2003 (D.C. Act 15-103, June 20, 2003,  50 DCR 5499).</annotation>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 day) amendment of section, see § 502(c) of Fiscal Year 2004 Budget Support Emergency Act of 2003 (D.C. Act 15-105, June 20, 2003,  50 DCR 5613).</annotation>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 day) amendment of section, see § 502(c) of Fiscal Year 2004 Budget Support Congressional Review Emergency Act of 2003 (D.C. Act 15-149, September 22, 2003,  50 DCR 8360).</annotation>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 day) amendment of section, see § 3002(c) of Fiscal Year 2011 Budget Support Emergency Act of 2010 (D.C. Act 18-463, July 2, 2010,  57 DCR 6542).</annotation>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 day) addition of section, see § 3042(b) of Fiscal Year 2013 Budget Support Emergency Act of 2012 (D.C. Act 19-383, June 19, 2012,  59 DCR 7764).</annotation>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 day) addition of section, see § 3042(b) of Fiscal Year 2013 Budget Support Congressional Review Emergency Act of 2012 (D.C. Act 19-413, July 25, 2012,  59 DCR 9290).</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Editor's Notes</heading>
        <annotation>Section 3003 of <cite doc="D.C. Law 18-223">D.C. Law 18-223</cite> provided: “Sec. 3003. Applicability. This subtitle shall apply as of October 1, 2010.”</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section from-code="true">
    <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" path="|34|18"/>
    <reason>Repealed</reason>
    <num codify:value="34-1803.01">604a</num>
    <heading>Additional revenues.</heading>
    <text>Repealed.</text>
    <annotations>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>History</heading>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 13-172">Oct. 19, 2000, D.C. Law 13-172, § 604a</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 17-20">as added Sept. 18, 2007, D.C. Law 17-20, § 3022(b), 54 DCR 7052</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 18-111">Mar. 3, 2010, D.C. Law 18-111, § 3011(b), 57 DCR 181</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 19-21">Sept. 14, 2011, D.C. Law 19-21, § 9052(a)(2), 58 DCR 6226</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Emergency Legislation</heading>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 day) addition, see § 3022(b) of Fiscal Year 2008 Budget Support Emergency Act of 2007 (D.C. Act 17-74, July 25, 2007,  54 DCR 7549).</annotation>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 day) amendment of section, see § 3011(b) of Fiscal Year 2010 Budget Support Second Emergency Act of 2009 (D.C. Act 18-207, October 15, 2009,  56 DCR 8234).</annotation>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 day) amendment of section, see § 3011(b) of Fiscal Year Budget Support Congressional Review Emergency Amendment Act of 2009 (D.C. Act 18-260, January 4, 2010,  57 DCR 345).</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section from-code="true">
    <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" path="|34|18"/>
    <num codify:value="34-1803.02">604b</num>
    <heading>Collection and remittance of prepaid wireless E911 charge.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>(a)</num>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A prepaid wireless E911 charge of 2.0% of the sales price per retail transaction occurring in the District shall be collected by the seller from the consumer, and remitted to the District. The amount of the prepaid wireless E911 charge shall be separately stated on an invoice, receipt, or other similar document that is provided to the consumer by the seller.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>For the purposes of paragraph (1) of this subsection, a retail transaction that is effected in person by a consumer at a business location of the seller shall be treated as occurring in the District if that business location is in the District and any other retail transaction shall be treated as occurring in the District if the retail transaction is a sale at retail as described in § <cite path="§47-2001">47-2001</cite>(n)(1)(T) that is subject to tax pursuant to § <cite path="§47-2002">47-2002</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(b)</num>
      <text>The prepaid wireless E911 charge is the liability of the consumer and not of the seller or of any provider, except that the seller shall be liable to remit all prepaid wireless E911 charges that the seller collects from consumers, except for deductions pursuant to subsection (f) of this section, including all such charges that the seller is deemed to collect where the amount of the charge has not been separately stated on an invoice, receipt, or other similar document provided to the consumer by the seller.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(c)</num>
      <text>If the amount of the prepaid wireless E911 charge that is collected by a seller from a consumer is separately stated on an invoice, receipt, or other similar document provided to the consumer by the seller, the amount shall not be included in the base for measuring any tax, fee, surcharge, or other charge that is imposed by the District.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(d)</num>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Except as provided in paragraph (2) of this subsection, when prepaid wireless telecommunications service is sold with one or more other products or services for a single, non-itemized price, then the percentage specified in subsection (a) of this section shall apply to the entire non-itemized price unless the seller elects to apply the percentage to:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(A)</num>
          <text>The amount of the prepaid wireless telecommunications service disclosed to the consumer as a dollar amount; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(B)</num>
          <text>The portion of the price identified by the seller that is attributable to the prepaid wireless telecommunications service by reasonable and verifiable standards from the seller’s books and records that are kept in the regular course of business for other purposes, including non-tax purposes.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>If a minimal amount of prepaid wireless telecommunications service is sold with a prepaid wireless device for a single, non-itemized price, then the seller may elect not to apply the percentage specified in paragraph (1) of this subsection to the transaction. For the purposes of this paragraph, an amount of service denominated as 10 minutes or less, or $5 or less, is minimal.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(e)</num>
      <text>The Office of Tax and Revenue shall establish regulations governing collection, remittance, and other administrative provisions that are consistent with existing provisions governing the collection, remittance, and administration of the tax imposed by § <cite path="§47-2002">47-2002</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(f)</num>
      <text>A seller shall be permitted to deduct and retain 3% of prepaid wireless E911 charges that are collected by the seller from consumers.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>History</heading>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 13-172">Oct. 19, 2000, D.C. Law 13-172, § 604b</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 18-223">as added Sept. 24, 2010, D.C. Law 18-223, § 3002(d), 57 DCR 6242</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Section References</heading>
        <annotation>This section is referenced in § <cite path="§34-1801">34-1801</cite>, § <cite path="§34-1802">34-1802</cite>, and § <cite path="§34-1803">34-1803</cite>.</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Emergency Legislation</heading>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 day) addition of section, see § 3002(d) of Fiscal Year 2011 Budget Support Emergency Act of 2010 (D.C. Act 18-463, July 2, 2010,  57 DCR 6542).</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Editor's Notes</heading>
        <annotation>Section 3003 of <cite doc="D.C. Law 18-223">D.C. Law 18-223</cite> provided: “Sec. 3003. Applicability. This subtitle shall apply as of October 1, 2010.”</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section from-code="true">
    <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" path="|34|18"/>
    <num codify:value="34-1803.03">604c</num>
    <heading>Additional revenues.</heading>
    <text>All revenues from the following sources shall be deposited into the Fund:</text>
    <para>
      <num>(1)</num>
      <text>Steam (including arrearage payments) for the Correctional Treatment Facility received by the District since October 1, 2007; and</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(2)</num>
      <text>From fines paid due to automated photo enforcement in any one fiscal year:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(A)</num>
        <text>Aggregate revenues in excess of $105,791,000 in fiscal year 2013;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(B)</num>
        <text>Aggregate revenues in excess of $141,348,000 in fiscal year 2014;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(C)</num>
        <text>Aggregate revenues in excess of $155,812,000 in fiscal year 2015;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(D)</num>
        <text>Aggregate revenues in excess of $148,020,000 in fiscal year 2016; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(E)</num>
        <text>Aggregate revenues in excess of $140,618,000 in fiscal year 2017 and in each fiscal year thereafter.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>History</heading>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 13-172">Oct. 19, 2000, D.C. Law 13-172, § 604c</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 19-168">as added Sept. 20, 2012, D.C. Law 19-168, § 3042(b), 59 DCR 8025</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 20-61">Dec. 24, 2013, D.C. Law 20-61, § 3022, 60 DCR 12472</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Section References</heading>
        <annotation>This section is referenced in § <cite path="§34-1802">34-1802</cite>.</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Effect of Amendments</heading>
        <annotation>The 2012 amendment by <cite doc="D.C. Law 19-168">D.C. Law 19-168</cite> added this section.</annotation>
        <annotation>The 2013 amendment by <cite doc="D.C. Law 20-61">D.C. Law 20-61</cite> rewrote (2).</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Emergency Legislation</heading>
        <annotation>For temporary addition of section, see § 3042(b) of the Fiscal Year 2013 Budget Support Congressional Review Emergency Act of 2012 (D.C. Act 19-413, July 25, 2012,  59 DCR 9290).</annotation>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 days) amendment of this section, see § 3022 of the Fiscal Year 2014 Budget Support Emergency Act of 2013 (D.C. Act 20-130, July 30, 2013,  60 DCR 11384, 20 DCSTAT 1827).</annotation>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 days) amendment of this section, see § 3022 of the Fiscal Year 2014 Budget Support Congressional Review Emergency Act of 2013 (D.C. Act 20-204, October 17, 2013,  60 DCR 15341, 20 DCSTAT 2311).</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Short Title</heading>
        <annotation>Section 3021 of <cite doc="D.C. Law 20-61">D.C. Law 20-61</cite> provided that Subtitle C of Title III of the act may be cited as the “Automated Traffic Enforcement Enhancement Amendment Act of 2013”.</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Editor's Notes</heading>
        <annotation>Applicability of <cite doc="D.C. Law 20-61">D.C. Law 20-61</cite>: Section 11001 of <cite doc="D.C. Law 20-61">D.C. Law 20-61</cite> provided that, except as otherwise provided, the act shall apply as of October 1, 2013.</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section from-code="true">
    <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" path="|34|18"/>
    <reason>Repealed</reason>
    <num codify:value="34-1804">605</num>
    <heading>Removal of 911 system costs from base rates.</heading>
    <text>Repealed.</text>
    <annotations>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>History</heading>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 13-172">Oct. 19, 2000, D.C. Law 13-172, § 605, 47 DCR 6308</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 15-39">Nov. 13, 2003, D.C. Law 15-39, § 502(d), 50 DCR 5668</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Emergency Legislation</heading>
        <annotation>For temporary (90-day) addition of section, see § 605 of the Fiscal Year 2001 Budget Support Emergency Act of 2000 (D.C. Act 13-376, July 24, 2000,  47 DCR 6574).</annotation>
        <annotation>For temporary (90-day) authorization of applicability of section, see § 609 of the Fiscal Year 2001 Budget Support Emergency Act of 2000 (D.C. Act 13-376, July 24, 2000,  47 DCR 6574).</annotation>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 day) repeal of section, see § 502(d) of Fiscal Year 2004 Budget Support Emergency Act of 2003 (D.C. Act 15-105, June 20, 2003,  50 DCR 5613).</annotation>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 day) repeal of section, see § 502(d) of Fiscal Year 2004 Budget Support Congressional Review Emergency Act of 2003 (D.C. Act 15-149, September 22, 2003,  50 DCR 8360).</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section from-code="true">
    <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" path="|34|18"/>
    <num codify:value="34-1805">605a</num>
    <heading>Report to the Council.</heading>
    <text>Not later than September 15, 2003, the Mayor shall submit to the Council an analysis of the expenses of the Fund, which analysis shall include a recommendation as to whether the tax imposed under § <cite path="§34-1803">34-1803</cite> should be adjusted. In preparing this analysis:</text>
    <para>
      <num>(1)</num>
      <text>It shall be assumed that funding for call center operating personnel will be shifted from the Fund to the General Fund of the District of Columbia; and</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(2)</num>
      <text>A replacement reserve schedule for all technology equipment and software shall be used.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>History</heading>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 13-172">Oct. 19, 2000, D.C. Law 13-172, § 605a</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 15-39">as added Nov. 13, 2003, D.C. Law 15-39, § 502(c), 50 DCR 5668</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Emergency Legislation</heading>
        <annotation>For temporary (90-day) addition, see § 502(e) of Fiscal Year 2004 Budget Support Emergency Act of 2003 (D.C. Act 15-105, June 20 2003,  50 DCR 5613).</annotation>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 day) addition, see § 502(e) of Fiscal Year 2004 Budget Support Congressional Review Emergency Act of 2003 (D.C. Act 15-149, September 22, 2003,  50 DCR 8360).</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section from-code="true">
    <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" path="|34|18"/>
    <num codify:value="34-1806">605b</num>
    <heading>Replacement of equipment.</heading>
    <text>No later than October 1, 2007, the Office of Unified Communications shall establish a schedule for the replacement of equipment for the 911 system. The schedule shall be updated on February 1 of each subsequent year.</text>
    <annotations>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>History</heading>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 13-172">Oct. 19, 2000, D.C. Law 13-172, § 605b</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 17-20">as added Sept. 18, 2007, D.C. Law 17-20, § 3022(c), 54 DCR 7052</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Emergency Legislation</heading>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 day) addition, see § 3022(c) of Fiscal Year 2008 Budget Support Emergency Act of 2007 (D.C. Act 17-74, July 25, 2007,  54 DCR 7549).</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section from-code="true">
    <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" path="|4|3|III"/>
    <num codify:value="4-341">3802</num>
    <heading>Legislative findings.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>(a)</num>
      <text>The long term needs of District of Columbia children who are in foster care are not being served. Although the Adoption and Safe Families Amendment Act of 2000 shortens the time in which children may remain in foster care, many of these children require additional assistance in order to be adopted.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(b)</num>
      <text>The financial costs associated with maintaining the 3,000 foster children are high. In addition to the monthly payments to foster parents, the Child and Family Services Agency must supervise and staff each case, the Superior Court of the District of Columbia must pay attorneys and judges to review each case, and the Office of Corporation Counsel must staff and review each case.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(c)</num>
      <text>Even more critical are the tragic human costs associated with allowing children to languish in foster care. The most recent study on the fate of foster children who “age out” of the child welfare system without finding a permanent home found that 12 to 18 months after they left foster care, just half were employed, one-third were receiving public assistance, one-fifth of the girls had given birth, and more than one-quarter of the boys had been incarcerated.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(d)</num>
      <text>Many of the children in foster care have foster parents desirous of adopting them but are unable to do so because of the costs associated with adoption.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(e)</num>
      <text>Providing these foster parents with a one-time financial assistance package in the form of vouchers would facilitate adoptions. Financial assistance would consist of vouchers to cover the costs of the necessary homestudies, compilation of information on the foster children’s backgrounds and special needs, and attorneys’ fees.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(f)</num>
      <text>The Congress has appropriated, in the District of Columbia Appropriations Act, 2000, approved November 29, 1999 (Pub. L. No. 106-113; 113 Stat. 1501), a $5 million payment, to remain available until September 30, 2001, to the District of Columbia to create incentives to promote the adoption of children in the District’s foster care system.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>History</heading>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 13-172">Oct. 19, 2000, D.C. Law 13-172, § 3802, 47 DCR 6308</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Emergency Legislation</heading>
        <annotation>For temporary (90-day) addition of section, see § 3802 of the Fiscal Year 2001 Budget Support Emergency Act of 2000 (D.C. Act 13-376, July 24, 2000,  47 DCR 6574).</annotation>
        <annotation>For temporary (90-day) addition of section, see § 3802 of the Fiscal Year 2001 Budget Support Emergency Act of 2000 (D.C. Act 13-376, July 24, 2000,  47 DCR 6574).</annotation>
        <annotation>For temporary (90-day) addition of section, see § 3802 of the Fiscal Year 2001 Budget Support Emergency Act of 2000 (D.C. Act 13-376, July 24, 2000,  47 DCR 6574).</annotation>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 day) amendment of section, see §§ 3802 to 3807 of the Fiscal Year 2001 Budget Support Congressional Review Emergency Act of 2000 (D.C. Act 13-438, October 20, 2000,  47 DCR 8740).</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section from-code="true">
    <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" path="|4|3|III"/>
    <num codify:value="4-342">3803</num>
    <heading>Definitions.</heading>
    <text>For the purpose of this subchapter, the term:</text>
    <para>
      <num>(1)</num>
      <text>“Attorneys’ fees” means the legal costs and expenses which are directly  related to the adoption of a foster child or foster children.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(2)</num>
      <text>“Foster care” means 24 hour substitute care for children placed away from  their parents or guardians for whom the Child and Family Services Agency has  placement care and responsibility.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(3)</num>
      <text>“Foster child” and “foster children” mean a child, or children, who comes  under the jurisdiction of the Superior Court of the District of Columbia  pursuant to § <cite path="§16-2320">16-2320</cite> or whose parents’ rights have been relinquished pursuant  to § <cite path="§4-1406">4-1406</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(4)</num>
      <text>“Foster parent” means an individual with whom a foster child is legally  placed.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(5)</num>
      <text>“Homestudy” means the “investigation, report and recommendation” required  by § <cite path="§16-307">16-307</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(6)</num>
      <text>“Related sibling group” means a group of siblings with at least one  parent in common, residing together in the home of a foster parent.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>History</heading>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 13-172">Oct. 19, 2000, D.C. Law 13-172, § 3803, 47 DCR 6308</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Section References</heading>
        <annotation>This section is referenced in § <cite path="§1-608.01">1-608.01</cite> and § <cite path="§4-1303.03">4-1303.03</cite>.</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Emergency Legislation</heading>
        <annotation>For temporary (90-day) addition of section, see § 3803 of the Fiscal Year 2001 Budget Support Emergency Act of 2000 (D.C. Act 13-376, July 24, 2000,  47 DCR 6574).</annotation>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 day) amendment of section, see §§ 3802 to 3807 of the Fiscal Year 2001 Budget Support Congressional Review Emergency Act of 2000 (D.C. Act 13-438, October 20, 2000,  47 DCR 8740).</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section from-code="true">
    <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" path="|4|3|III"/>
    <num codify:value="4-343">3804</num>
    <heading>Establishment of the Adoption Incentive Program; purpose.</heading>
    <text>There is established the Adoption Incentive Program (“Program”). The purpose of the Program is to provide foster parents with access to a one-time financial assistance package to assist them with the expenses associated with attorneys’ fees and the homestudy relating to the adoption of a foster child, subject to the availability of funds in the Adoption Voucher Fund.</text>
    <annotations>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>History</heading>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 13-172">Oct. 19, 2000, D.C. Law 13-172, § 3804, 47 DCR 6308</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Emergency Legislation</heading>
        <annotation>For temporary (90-day) addition of section, see § 3804 of the Fiscal Year 2001 Budget Support Emergency Act of 2000 (D.C. Act 13-376, July 24, 2000,  47 DCR 6574).</annotation>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 day) amendment of section, see §§ 3802 to 3807 of the Fiscal Year 2001 Budget Support Congressional Review Emergency Act of 2000 (D.C. Act 13-438, October 20, 2000,  47 DCR 8740).</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section from-code="true">
    <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" path="|4|3|III"/>
    <num codify:value="4-344">3805</num>
    <heading>Establishment of the Adoption Voucher Fund.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>(a)</num>
      <text>There is established the Adoption Voucher Fund (“Fund”). The Fund shall be comprised of $2 million of the $5 million appropriated in the District of Columbia Appropriations Act, 2000, approved November 29, 1999 (Pub. L. No. 106-113; 113 Stat. 1501), and additional funds in their entirety which Congress may appropriate from time to time for the purpose of providing incentives for foster parents to adopt District children.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(b)</num>
      <text>Monies in the Fund shall be used only for the payment of homestudies and attorneys’ fees, as well as any administrative costs directly associated with the implementation of this subchapter. The Fund shall be the sole source of payments under the Program.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(c)</num>
      <text>Funds deposited in the Fund shall not revert to the General Fund of the District of Columbia at the end of the fiscal year or at any other time, but shall remain available until expended for the purposes set forth in subsection (b) of this section, subject to authorization by Congress in an appropriations act.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>History</heading>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 13-172">Oct. 19, 2000, D.C. Law 13-172, § 3805, 47 DCR 6308</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 15-205">Dec. 7, 2004, D.C. Law 15-205, § 5302, 51 DCR 8441</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Effect of Amendments</heading>
        <annotation><cite doc="D.C. Law 15-205">D.C. Law 15-205</cite> added subsec. (c).</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Emergency Legislation</heading>
        <annotation>For temporary (90-day) addition of section, see § 3805 of the Fiscal Year 2001 Budget Support Emergency Act of 2000 (D.C. Act 13-376, July 24, 2000,  47 DCR 6574).</annotation>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 day) amendment of section, see §§ 3802 to 3807 of the Fiscal Year 2001 Budget Support Congressional Review Emergency Act of 2000 (D.C. Act 13-438, October 20, 2000,  47 DCR 8740).</annotation>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 day) amendment of section, see § 5302 of Fiscal Year 2005 Budget Support Emergency Act of 2004 (D.C. Act 15-486, August 2, 2004,  51 DCR 8236).</annotation>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 day) amendment of section, see § 5302 of Fiscal Year 2005 Budget Support Congressional Review Emergency Act of 2004 (D.C. Act 15-594, October 26, 2004,  51 DCR 11725).</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Short Title</heading>
        <annotation>Short title of subtitle C of title V of Law 15-205: Section 5301 of <cite doc="D.C. Law 15-205">D.C. Law 15-205</cite> provided that subtitle C of title V of the act may be cited as the Adoption Voucher Fund Amendment Act of 2004.</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section from-code="true">
    <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" path="|4|3|III"/>
    <num codify:value="4-344.01">3805a</num>
    <heading>Establishment of the Adoption Support Fund.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>(a)</num>
      <text>There is established the Adoption Support Fund (“Support Fund”). The Support Fund shall be comprised of $3 million of the $5 million appropriated in the District of Columbia Appropriations Act, 2000, approved November 29, 1999 (Pub. L. No. 106-113; 113 Stat. 1501), and additional funds in their entirety which Congress may appropriate from time to time for the purpose of providing support incentives for foster parents who adopt District of Columbia children and enhancing recruitment and support of prospective adoptive families.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(b)</num>
      <text>Monies in the Support Fund shall be used only for the following purposes:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>$1 million to establish a scholarship fund to support postsecondary education and training for adopted children;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>$1 million to create an Adoption Resource Center with post-adoption service capacity; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>$1 million to enhance recruitment and support of prospective adoptive families.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(c)</num>
      <text>The Child and Family Services Agency shall administer the Support Fund.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>History</heading>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 13-172">Oct. 19, 2000, D.C. Law 13-172, § 3805a</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 14-28">as added Oct. 3, 2001, D.C. Law 14-28, § 2202, 48 DCR 6981</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Emergency Legislation</heading>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 day) addition of section, see § 2002 of Fiscal Year 2002 Budget Support Emergency Act of 2001 (D.C. Act 14-124, August 3, 2001,  48 DCR 7861).</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section from-code="true">
    <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" path="|4|3|III"/>
    <num codify:value="4-345">3806</num>
    <heading>Benefits.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>(a)</num>
      <text>A foster parent may receive the following:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A voucher for the payment of $1,500 for a homestudy for each foster child  or related sibling group; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A voucher for the payment of $5,000 for attorneys’ fees for each foster  child or related sibling group; provided that, the voucher may only be applied  to attorney’s fees charged at an hourly rate of not more than $125 per hour  and related expenses billed at actual cost.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(b)</num>
      <text>Nothing in this subchapter shall be construed to create an entitlement to financial assistance for the adoption of a foster child, or foster children, if no funds remain available in the Adoption Voucher Fund.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(c)</num>
      <text>Vouchers issued pursuant to this section shall be in addition to, and may not limit the amount of, money available to a foster parent under § <cite path="§4-301">4-301</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>History</heading>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 13-172">Oct. 19, 2000, D.C. Law 13-172, § 3806, 47 DCR 6308</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Emergency Legislation</heading>
        <annotation>For temporary (90-day) addition of section, see § 3806 of the Fiscal Year 2001 Budget Support Emergency Act of 2000 (D.C. Act 13-376, July 24, 2000,  47 DCR 6574).</annotation>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 day) amendment of section, see §§ 3802 to 3807 of the Fiscal Year 2001 Budget Support Congressional Review Emergency Act of 2000 (D.C. Act 13-438, October 20, 2000,  47 DCR 8740).</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section from-code="true">
    <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" path="|4|3|III"/>
    <num codify:value="4-346">3807</num>
    <heading>Administration of the Adoption Incentive Program and the Adoption Voucher Fund.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>(a)</num>
      <text>The Child and Family Services Agency (“CFSA”) shall administer the Program and the Fund. CFSA shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Within 180 days of October 19, 2000, identify children whose permanency  plans are adoption, for as long as funds are available from the Fund;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Obtain a document signed by the foster parents stating their intent to  adopt within 180 days of identifying the children pursuant to paragraph (1) of  this subsection; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Upon obtaining the signed document required by paragraph (2) of this subsection, immediately provide a voucher for attorneys’ fees and a voucher  for the homestudy to the foster parent.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(b)</num>
      <text>Vouchers issued pursuant to this section shall contain a statement describing the benefits to the adopting foster parents under the program, as well as the terms and conditions for the use of the vouchers.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(c)</num>
      <text>Adopting foster parents shall present the vouchers to their attorney and licensed agency hired to perform the homestudy.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(d)</num>
      <text>An attorney hired by a foster parent shall submit a voucher for attorneys’ fees with his or her first bill to CFSA, which shall set up an account with a  $5,000 balance. Thereafter, the attorney shall submit his or her bills quarterly to CFSA. CFSA shall pay the attorney within 30 days with funds from the account.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(e)</num>
      <text>The licensed agency hired to perform the homestudy shall submit its bill and the voucher for the homestudy to CFSA after the homestudy is complete for payment within 30 days.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>History</heading>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 13-172">Oct. 19, 2000, D.C. Law 13-172, § 3807, 47 DCR 6308</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Emergency Legislation</heading>
        <annotation>For temporary (90-day) addition of section, see § 3807 of the Fiscal Year 2001 Budget Support Emergency Act of 2000 (D.C. Act 13-376, July 24, 2000,  47 DCR 6574).</annotation>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 day) amendment of section, see §§ 3802 to 3807 of the Fiscal Year 2001 Budget Support Congressional Review Emergency Act of 2000 (D.C. Act 13-438, October 20, 2000,  47 DCR 8740).</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section from-code="true">
    <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" path="|50|2|I"/>
    <num codify:value="50-203">3402</num>
    <heading>EPA Miles Per Gallon requirement; restrictions on use of sport utility vehicles.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>(a)</num>
      <text>Except for security, emergency, rescue, or armored vehicles, all passenger automobiles, as defined in the Automobile Fuel Efficiency Act of 1980, approved October 10, 1980 (94 Stat. 1824; 15 U.S.C. § 2001(2)), purchased or leased by the District government shall have an Environmental Protection Agency estimated miles per gallon average of not less than 22 miles per gallon, and shall not be a sports utility vehicle.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(b)</num>
      <text>The District of Columbia government shall not purchase sport utility vehicles for government use; provided that this section shall not apply to security, emergency rescue, snow removal or armored vehicles.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>History</heading>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 13-172">Oct. 19, 2000, D.C. Law 13-172, § 3402, 47 DCR 6308</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 14-231">Mar. 25, 2003, D.C. Law 14-231, § 2, 49 DCR 9762</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 14-310">June 12, 2003, D.C. Law 14-310, § 17, 50 DCR 1092</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 15-105">Mar. 13, 2004, D.C. Law 15-105, § 3, 51 DCR 881</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Effect of Amendments</heading>
        <annotation><cite doc="D.C. Law 14-231">D.C. Law 14-231</cite> rewrote the section heading which formerly read: “EPA Miles Per Gallon Requirement”; redesignated the text as subsection (a); in the newly designated subsec. (a), inserted “, and shall not be a sports utility vehicle” before the period; and added subsec. (b).</annotation>
        <annotation><cite doc="D.C. Law 14-310">D.C. Law 14-310</cite> made no changes in the text, but made the amendments by <cite doc="D.C. Law 14-231">D.C. Law 14-231</cite> applicable prospectively to October 1, 2004.</annotation>
        <annotation><cite doc="D.C. Law 15-105">D.C. Law 15-105</cite>, substituted “emergency, rescue” for “emergency rescue”.</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Emergency Legislation</heading>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 day) amendment of section, see § 3402 of the Fiscal Year 2001 Budget Support Congressional Review Emergency Act of 2000 (D.C. Act 13-438, October 20, 2000,  47 DCR 8740).</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Editor's Notes</heading>
        <text>Section 17 of <cite doc="D.C. Law 14-310">D.C. Law 14-310</cite> added section 2a to <cite doc="D.C. Law 14-231">D.C. Law 14-231</cite> to read as follows:</text>
        <text>“Sec. 2a. This act [<cite doc="D.C. Law 14-231">D.C. Law 14-231</cite>] shall apply as of October 1, 2004.”</text>
      </annoGroup>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section from-code="true">
    <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" path="|50|2|I"/>
    <num codify:value="50-204">3602</num>
    <heading>Restrictions on the use of official vehicles.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>(a)</num>
      <text>Except as otherwise provided in this section, no officer or employee of the District may be provided with an official vehicle unless the officer or employee uses the vehicle only in the performance of the officer’s or employee’s official duties. For purposes of this subsection, the term “official duties” shall not include travel between the officer’s or employee’s residence and workplace; except in the case of (1) an officer or employee of the Metropolitan Police Department who resides in the District or is otherwise designated by the Chief of the Department; (2) at the discretion of the Fire Chief, an officer or employee of the D.C. Fire and Emergency Medical Services Department who resides in the District and is on call 24 hours a day; (3) the Mayor; (4) the Chairman of the Council; (5) at the discretion of the Chief Medical Examiner, an employee of the Office of the Chief Medical Examiner who resides in the District and is on call 24 hours a day; (6) at the discretion of the Director of the Homeland Security and Emergency Management Agency, an officer or employee of the Homeland Security and Emergency Management Agency who resides in the District and is on call 24 hours a day; and (7) at the discretion of the Director of the Department of Corrections, an officer or employee of the District of Columbia Department of Corrections who resides in the District and is on call 24 hours a day.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(b)</num>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>No officer or employee of the executive branch of the District government, except the Mayor, shall utilize the services of any District government employee for use as a chauffeur from residence to work or vice versa, unless such use is authorized first, in writing, by the Mayor. All such authorizations and the cost thereof shall be reported to the Council on a quarterly basis and made available on the Department of Public Works’ website.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>No officer or employee of the executive branch of the District government, except the Mayor, shall utilize the services of any District  government employee for use as a chauffeur during the work day unless such use  is authorized in writing, by the appropriate agency head. All such  authorizations and the cost thereof, shall be reported to the Council on a quarterly basis and made available to the public on the Department of Public Works’ website.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>No District employee shall offer or accept, as a perquisite of employment in hiring or contract negotiation, an assigned chauffeur.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(c)</num>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The Director shall make available on the Department of Public Works’ website an inventory of vehicles owned, leased, or otherwise controlled by the District government, or any of its entities, excluding vehicles falling under the guidelines of paragraph (4) of this subsection, as of the end of the fiscal year. The inventory shall be distributed to the Council and made available to the public on the Department of Public Works’ website by December 15 of each year. The inventory shall be completed annually for each fiscal year ending on September 30 and shall be distributed to the Council and made available to the public on the Department of Public Works’ website by December 15 of the next fiscal year.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The inventory shall include the following for each vehicle:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(A)</num>
          <text>The agency to which it is assigned;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(B)</num>
          <text>Its year, make, and vehicle tag number;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(C)</num>
          <text>Its acquisition date and cost;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(D)</num>
          <text>Its general condition;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(E)</num>
          <text>Its annual operating and maintenance costs;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(F)</num>
          <text>Its approximate current mileage; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(G)</num>
          <text>Whether it is allowed to be taken home by a District officer or employee and if so, the officer or employee’s title and state of residence, and a written justification explaining the public interest served by allowing the employee to take a vehicle to the employee’s residence.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The Director shall update the inventory on a quarterly basis to reflect any changes in fleet composition resulting from vehicle acquisition through purchase, lease, or transfer or disposed of through sale, demolition, disposal, or transfer.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The Metropolitan Police Department may submit, under separate seal, the total number and acquisition cost of vehicles used for undercover operations directly to the Chairman of the Council, the chair of the Council committee with oversight of the Metropolitan Police Department, and the chair of the Council committee with oversight of the Department of Public Works.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(d)</num>
      <text>[Not funded].</text>
    </para>
    <annotations>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>History</heading>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 13-172">Oct. 19, 2000, D.C. Law 13-172, § 3602, 47 DCR 6308</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 19-223">Mar. 5, 2013, D.C. Law 19-223, § 201, 59 DCR 13537</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Effect of Amendments</heading>
        <annotation>The 2013 amendment by <cite doc="D.C. Law 19-223">D.C. Law 19-223</cite> rewrote the section.</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Emergency Legislation</heading>
        <annotation>For temporary (90-day) addition of § 40-931 1981 Ed., see § 3402 of the Fiscal Year 2001 Budget Support Emergency Act of 2000 (D.C. Act 13-376, July 24, 2000,  47 DCR 6574).</annotation>
        <annotation>For temporary (90-day) addition of § 40-951 1981 Ed., see § 3602 of the Fiscal Year 2001 Budget Support Emergency Act of 2000 (D.C. Act 13-376, July 24, 2000,  47 DCR 6574).</annotation>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 day) amendment of section, see § 3602 of the Fiscal Year 2001 Budget Support Congressional Review Emergency Act of 2000 (D.C. Act 13-438, October 20, 2000,  47 DCR 8740).</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Editor's Notes</heading>
        <text>Section 120 of Pub. L. 107-96 provided:</text>
        <text>“(a) RESTRICTIONS ON USE OF OFFICIAL VEHICLES.—Except as otherwise provided in this section, none of the funds made available by this Act or by any other Act may be used to provide any officer or employee of the District of Columbia with an official vehicle unless the officer or employee uses the vehicle only in the performance of the officer’s or employee’s official duties. For purposes of this paragraph, the term ‘official duties’ does not include travel between the officer’s or employee’s residence and workplace (except: (1) in the case of an officer or employee of the Metropolitan Police Department who resides in the District of Columbia or is otherwise designated by the Chief of the Department; (2) at the discretion of the Fire Chief, an officer or employee of the District of Columbia Fire and Emergency Medical Services Department who resides in the District of Columbia and is on call 24 hours a day; (3) the Mayor of the District of Columbia; and (4) the Chairman of the Council of the District of Columbia).</text>
        <text>“(b) INVENTORY OF VEHICLES.—The Chief Financial Officer of the District of Columbia shall submit, by November 15, 2001, an inventory, as of September 30, 2001, of all vehicles owned, leased or operated by the District of Columbia government. The inventory shall include, but not be limited to, the department to which the vehicle is assigned; the year and make of the vehicle; the acquisition date and cost; the general condition of the vehicle; annual operating and maintenance costs; current mileage; and whether the vehicle is allowed to be taken home by a District officer or employee and if so, the officer or employee’s title and resident location.</text>
        <text>“(c) No officer or employee of the District of Columbia government (including any independent agency of the District but excluding the Office of the Chief Technology Officer, the Chief Financial Officer of the District of Columbia, and the Metropolitan Police Department) may enter into an agreement in excess of $2,500 for the procurement of goods or services on behalf of any entity of the District government until the officer or employee has conducted an analysis of how the procurement of the goods and services involved under the applicable regulations and procedures of the District government would differ from the procurement of the goods and services involved under the Federal supply schedule and other applicable regulations and procedures of the General Services Administration, including an analysis of any differences in the costs to be incurred and the time required to obtain the goods or services.”</text>
        <text>Section 401 of <cite doc="D.C. Law 19-223">D.C. Law 19-223</cite> provided that §§ 103, 105(c), and 201(d) of the act shall apply upon the inclusion of their fiscal effect in an approved budget and financial plan.</text>
        <text>Section 401 of <cite doc="D.C. Law 19-223">D.C. Law 19-223</cite> provided that §§ 101, 102, 104, 105(a), 105(b), 106, 107, 201(a), 201(b), 201(c), 202, 203, and 301 of the act shall apply as of Mar. 5, 2013.</text>
      </annoGroup>
    </annotations>
  </section>
</document>
