<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<document xmlns:codify="http://code.dccouncil.us/schemas/codify" id="D.C. Law 13-280">
  <num type="law">13-280</num>
  <heading type="short">Fair Phone Charges For Prisoners Act of 2000</heading>
  <meta>
    <effective>2001-04-27</effective>
    <cites>
      <law lawId="280" period="13" url="./docs/13-280.pdf"/>
      <register page="1885" vol="48"/>
    </cites>
    <history url="http://lims.dccouncil.us/Legislation/B13-0632">
      <narrative>Law 13-280, the “Fair Phone Charges For Prisoners Act of 2000”, was introduced in Council and assigned Bill No. 13-632, which was referred to the Committee on Consumer and Regulatory Affairs. The Bill was adopted on first and second readings on December 5, 2000, and December 19, 2000, respectively. Signed by the Mayor on January 22, 2001, it was assigned Act No. 13-577 and transmitted to both Houses of Congress for its review. D.C. Law 13-280 became effective on April 27, 2001.</narrative>
    </history>
  </meta>
  <section from-code="true">
    <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" path="|24|2|VII-A"/>
    <num codify:value="24-263.01">2</num>
    <heading>Telephone charges in penal or correctional institutions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>(a)</num>
      <text>Notwithstanding any other District of Columbia law, no telephone service provider shall charge a customer a rate for operator-assisted calls made from a penal or correctional institution in the District of Columbia in excess of the maximum rate determined by the Public Service Commission of the District of Columbia.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(b)</num>
      <text>No penal or correctional institution in the District of Columbia shall charge a surcharge, commission, or other financial imposition that is in addition to legally established rates for local or long-distance telephone service.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>History</heading>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 13-280">Apr. 27, 2001, D.C. Law 13-280, § 2, 48 DCR 1885</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section from-code="true">
    <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" path="|24|2|VII-A"/>
    <num codify:value="24-263.02">3</num>
    <heading>Prohibited charges in government contracts.</heading>
    <text>In any contract to which the District of Columbia is a party that is for the holding or incarceration of persons charged or convicted in the Superior Court of the District of Columbia, such contract shall prohibit surcharges, commissions, or other financial impositions that are in addition to the legally established rates for calls made by any inmate subject to the contract. The District of Columbia government shall seek to obtain quality service for the least cost to the individual party paying for the telephone call by an inmate subject to the contract.</text>
    <annotations>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>History</heading>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 13-280">Apr. 27, 2001, D.C. Law 13-280, § 3, 48 DCR 1885</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section from-code="true">
    <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" path="|24|2|VII-A"/>
    <num codify:value="24-263.03">4</num>
    <heading>Department of Corrections report.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>(a)</num>
      <text>The Department of Corrections (“Department”) shall survey the communications plans used by the Federal Bureau of Prisons, and all state prison systems. The Department shall explore additional alternative communication plans with telecommunications companies. The explored alternatives shall include prison commissary phone accounts, restricted calling cards, presenting calling cards, and debit calling cards.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(b)</num>
      <text>No later than 180 days after April 27, 2001, the Department shall report to the Council and the Mayor the results of the survey and the exploration of alternatives. The report shall include the merits and disadvantages of each communication plan examined, including consideration of the security needs of the Department, the financial burden to the families and other individuals telephoned, the availability of telecommunications to the inmates, the feasibility of waiving the gross receipts tax, and other incentives to control the cost of inmate phone service. The report shall include a recommendation for an inmate telephone service.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>History</heading>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 13-280">Apr. 27, 2001, D.C. Law 13-280, § 4, 48 DCR 1885</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section from-code="true">
    <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" path="|24|2|VII-A"/>
    <num codify:value="24-263.04">5</num>
    <heading>Operator-assisted calls.</heading>
    <text>The Public Service Commission shall determine the maximum rate for operator-assisted calls made from phones utilized by inmates of a penal or correctional institution in the District of Columbia.</text>
    <annotations>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>History</heading>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 13-280">Apr. 27, 2001, D.C. Law 13-280, § 5, 48 DCR 1885</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
    </annotations>
  </section>
</document>
