<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<document xmlns:codify="http://code.dccouncil.us/schemas/codify" id="D.C. Law 13-301">
  <num type="law">13-301</num>
  <heading type="short">Senior Protection Amendment Act of 2000</heading>
  <meta>
    <effective>2001-06-08</effective>
    <cites>
      <law lawId="301" period="13" url="./docs/13-301.pdf"/>
      <register page="7039" vol="47"/>
    </cites>
    <history url="http://lims.dccouncil.us/Legislation/B13-0297">
      <narrative>Law 13-301, the “Senior Protection Amendment Act of 2000”, was introduced in Council and assigned Bill No. 13-297, which was referred to the Committee on the Judiciary. The Bill was adopted on first and second readings on June 26, 2000, and July 11, 2000, respectively. Signed by the Mayor on August 2, 2000, it was assigned Act No. 13-396 and transmitted to both Houses of Congress for its review. D.C. Law 13-301 became effective on June 8, 2001.</narrative>
    </history>
  </meta>
  <section from-code="true">
    <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" path="|22|9A"/>
    <num codify:value="22-931">201</num>
    <heading>Short title.</heading>
    <text>This chapter may be cited as the “Criminal Abuse and Neglect of Vulnerable Adults Act of 2000”.</text>
    <annotations>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>History</heading>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 13-301">June 8, 2001, D.C. Law 13-301, § 201, 47 DCR 7039</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section from-code="true">
    <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" path="|22|9A"/>
    <num codify:value="22-932">202</num>
    <heading>Definitions.</heading>
    <text>For the purpose of this chapter “vulnerable adult” means a person 18 years of age or older who has a physical or mental condition which substantially impairs the person from adequately providing for his or her own care or protection.</text>
    <annotations>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>History</heading>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 13-301">June 8, 2001, D.C. Law 13-301, § 202, 47 DCR 7039</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section from-code="true">
    <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" path="|22|9A"/>
    <num codify:value="22-933">203</num>
    <heading>Criminal abuse of a vulnerable adult.</heading>
    <text>A person is guilty of criminal abuse of a vulnerable adult if that person intentionally or knowingly:</text>
    <para>
      <num>(1)</num>
      <text>Inflicts or threatens to inflict physical pain or injury by hitting, slapping, kicking, pinching, biting, pulling hair or other corporal means;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(2)</num>
      <text>Uses repeated or malicious oral or written statements that would be considered by a reasonable person to be harassing or threatening; or</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(3)</num>
      <text>Imposes unreasonable confinement or involuntary seclusion, including but not limited to, the forced separation from other persons against his or her will or the directions of any legal representative.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>History</heading>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 13-301">June 8, 2001, D.C. Law 13-301, § 203, 47 DCR 7039</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section from-code="true">
    <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" path="|22|9A"/>
    <num codify:value="22-934">204</num>
    <heading>Criminal negligence.</heading>
    <text>A person who knowingly, willfully or through a wanton, reckless or willful indifference fails to discharge a duty to provide care and services necessary to maintain the physical and mental health of a vulnerable adult, including but not limited to providing adequate food, clothing, medicine, shelter, supervision and medical services, that a reasonable person would deem essential for the well-being of the vulnerable adult is guilty of criminal negligence.</text>
    <annotations>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>History</heading>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 13-301">June 8, 2001, D.C. Law 13-301, § 204, 47 DCR 7039</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section from-code="true">
    <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" path="|22|9A"/>
    <num codify:value="22-935">205</num>
    <heading>Exception.</heading>
    <text>A person shall not be considered to commit an offense of abuse or neglect under this chapter for the sole reason that he provides or permits to be provided treatment by spiritual means through prayer alone in accordance with a religious method of healing, in lieu of medical treatment, to the vulnerable adult to whom he has a duty of care with the express consent or in accordance with the practice of the vulnerable adult.</text>
    <annotations>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>History</heading>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 13-301">June 8, 2001, D.C. Law 13-301, § 205, 47 DCR 7039</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section from-code="true">
    <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" path="|22|9A"/>
    <num codify:value="22-936">206</num>
    <heading>Penalties.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>(a)</num>
      <text>A person who commits the offense of criminal abuse or criminal neglect of a vulnerable person shall be subject to a fine of not more than the amount set forth in § <cite path="§22-3571.01">22-3571.01</cite>, imprisoned for not more than 180 days, or both.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(b)</num>
      <text>A person who commits the offense of criminal abuse or criminal neglect of a vulnerable adult which causes serious bodily injury or severe mental distress shall be subject to a fine of not more than the amount set forth in § <cite path="§22-3571.01">22-3571.01</cite>, imprisoned up to 10 years, or both.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(c)</num>
      <text>A person who commits the offense of criminal abuse or criminal neglect of a vulnerable adult which causes permanent bodily harm or death shall be subject to a fine of not more than the amount set forth in § <cite path="§22-3571.01">22-3571.01</cite>, imprisoned up to 20 years, or both.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>History</heading>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 13-301">June 8, 2001, D.C. Law 13-301, § 206, 47 DCR 7039</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 19-317">June 11, 2013, D.C. Law 19-317, § 208, 60 DCR 2064</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Section References</heading>
        <annotation>This section is referenced in § <cite path="§16-801">16-801</cite> and § <cite path="§22-951">22-951</cite>.</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Effect of Amendments</heading>
        <annotation>The 2013 amendment by <cite doc="D.C. Law 19-317">D.C. Law 19-317</cite> substituted “not more than the amount set forth in § <cite path="§22-3571.01">22-3571.01</cite>” for “up to $1,000” in (a), for “up to $100,000” in (b), and for “up to $250,000” in (c).</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Emergency Legislation</heading>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 days) amendment of this section, see § 208 of the Criminal Fine Proportionality Emergency Act of 2013 (D.C. Act 20-45, April 1, 2013,  60 DCR 5400, 20 DCSTAT 1300).</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Editor's Notes</heading>
        <annotation>Applicability of <cite doc="D.C. Law 19-317">D.C. Law 19-317</cite>: Section 401 of <cite doc="D.C. Law 19-317">D.C. Law 19-317</cite> provided that the act shall apply only to offenses committed on or after June 11, 2013.</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
    </annotations>
  </section>
</document>
