<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<document xmlns:codify="http://code.dccouncil.us/schemas/codify" id="D.C. Law 21-20">
  <num type="law">21-20</num>
  <heading type="short">Healthy Hearts of Babies Act of 2015</heading>
  <meta>
    <effective>2015-09-17</effective>
    <cites>
      <law lawId="20" period="21" url="http://lims.dccouncil.us/Download/33199/B21-0006-SignedAct.pdf"/>
      <register page="8845" vol="62"/>
    </cites>
    <history url="http://lims.dccouncil.us/Legislation/B21-0006">
      <narrative>Law 21-20, the “Healthy Hearts of Babies Act of 2015,” was introduced in Council and assigned Bill No. 21-6. The Bill was adopted on first and second readings on May 5, 2015, and June 2, 2015, respectively. Signed by the Mayor on June 17, 2015, it was assigned Act No. 21-90 and transmitted to Congress for its review. D.C. Law 21-20 became effective September 17, 2015.</narrative>
    </history>
  </meta>
  <section from-code="true">
    <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" path="|7|8B-i"/>
    <num codify:value="7-857.01">2</num>
    <heading>Definitions.</heading>
    <text>For the purposes of this chapter, the term:</text>
    <para>
      <num>(1)</num>
      <text>“Critical congenital heart disease” means a group of heart defects that cause serious, life-threatening symptoms and require intervention within the first days or first year of life.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(2)</num>
      <text>“Health benefit plan” shall have the same meaning as provided in § <cite path="§31-3301.01">31-3301.01</cite>(20).</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(3)</num>
      <text>“Health insurer” shall have the same meaning as provided in § <cite path="§31-3301.01">31-3301.01</cite>(22).</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(4)</num>
      <text>“Hospital” shall have the same meaning as provided in § <cite path="§44-501">44-501</cite>(a)(1).</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(5)</num>
      <text>“Maternity center” shall have the same meaning as provided in § <cite path="§44-501">44-501</cite>(a)(2).</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(6)</num>
      <text>“Nurse-midwife” means a registered nurse certified pursuant to 17 DCMR § 5800 et seq.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(7)</num>
      <text>“Pulse oximetry” means the non-invasive procedure used to measure oxygen levels in the blood.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>History</heading>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 21-20">Sept. 17, 2015, D.C. Law 21-20, § 2, 62 DCR 8845</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section from-code="true">
    <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" path="|7|8B-i"/>
    <num codify:value="7-857.02">3</num>
    <heading>Critical congenital heart disease screening.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>(a)</num>
      <text>Every newborn delivered in a hospital, maternity center, or home shall be screened for critical congenital heart disease using pulse oximetry until an alternative test for critical congenital heart disease is adopted by the American Academy of Pediatrics.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(b)</num>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Each hospital, maternity center, and nurse-midwife shall:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(A)</num>
          <text>Inform and educate the parent of the purpose and availability of critical congenital heart disease screening (“screening”);</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(B)</num>
          <text>Perform the screening unless the procedure is refused based on the parent’s religious or personal beliefs;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(C)</num>
          <text>Document the screening results or the parent’s refusal to allow the screening;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(D)</num>
          <text>Provide the screening results to the parent of the newborn and, if known, the newborn’s primary care provider;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(E)</num>
          <text>When a newborn tests positive for critical congenital heart disease, provide recommendations for follow-up testing and treatment to the parent of the newborn and, if known, the newborn’s primary care provider; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(F)</num>
          <text>On a quarterly basis, notify the Department of Health of the number of infants screened for critical congenital heart disease, the results of those screenings, and any documented parental refusal based on religious or personal beliefs.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Screening results shall include, at minimum, the age of the infant at the time of screening, actual screening values, and the final interpretation of the results.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(c)</num>
      <text>The screening required by subsection (a) of this section shall be performed in a manner consistent with the standards of the American Academy of Pediatrics for critical congenital heart disease.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>History</heading>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 21-20">Sept. 17, 2015, D.C. Law 21-20, § 3, 62 DCR 8845</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section from-code="true">
    <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" path="|7|8B-i"/>
    <num codify:value="7-857.03">4</num>
    <heading>Health benefit plan reimbursement.</heading>
    <text>All health insurer health benefit plans shall reimburse for screenings conducted under this chapter.</text>
    <annotations>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>History</heading>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 21-20">Sept. 17, 2015, D.C. Law 21-20, § 4, 62 DCR 8845</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section from-code="true">
    <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" path="|7|8B-i"/>
    <num codify:value="7-857.04">5</num>
    <heading>Rules.</heading>
    <text>The Mayor, pursuant to subchapter I of Chapter 5 of Title 2 [§ <cite path="§2-501">2-501</cite> et seq.], shall issue rules to implement the provisions of this chapter.</text>
    <annotations>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>History</heading>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 21-20">Sept. 17, 2015, D.C. Law 21-20, § 5, 62 DCR 8845</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
    </annotations>
  </section>
</document>
