<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<document xmlns:codify="http://code.dccouncil.us/schemas/codify" id="D.C. Law 21-36">
  <num type="law">21-36</num>
  <heading type="short">Fiscal Year 2016 Budget Support Act of 2015</heading>
  <meta>
    <effective>2015-10-22</effective>
    <cites>
      <law lawId="36" period="21" url="http://lims.dccouncil.us/Download/33645/B21-0158-SignedAct.pdf"/>
      <register page="10905" vol="62"/>
    </cites>
    <history url="http://lims.dccouncil.us/Legislation/B21-0158">
      <narrative>Law 21-36, the “Fiscal Year 2016 Budget Support Act of 2015,” was introduced in Council and assigned Bill No. 21-158. The Bill was adopted on first and second readings on May 27, 2015, and June 30, 2015, respectively. Signed by the Mayor on August 11, 2015, it was assigned Act No. 21-148 and transmitted to Congress for its review. D.C. Law 21-36 became effective October 22, 2015.</narrative>
    </history>
  </meta>
  <section from-code="true">
    <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" path="|44|6C"/>
    <num codify:value="44-661.01">5062</num>
    <heading>Definitions.</heading>
    <text>For the purposes of this chapter, the term:</text>
    <para>
      <num>(1)</num>
      <text>“Department” means the Department of Health Care Finance.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(2)</num>
      <text>“Hospital” shall have the same meaning as provided in § <cite path="§44-501">44-501</cite>(a)(1), but excludes any hospital operated by the federal government.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(3)</num>
      <text>“Hospital system” means any group of hospitals licensed separately, but operated, owned, or maintained by a common entity.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(4)</num>
      <text>“Medicaid” means the medical assistance programs authorized by Title XIX of the Social Security Act, approved July 30, 1965 (79 Stat. 343; 42 U.S.C. § 1396 et seq.), and by § <cite path="§1-307.02">1-307.02</cite>, and administered by the Department.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(5)</num>
      <text>“Outpatient gross patient revenue” means the amount calculated in accordance with generally accepted accounting principles for hospitals that is reported as the sum of Lines 18 and 19; Column 2; Worksheet G-2 of the Hospital and Hospital Health Care Complex Cost Report (Form CMS 2552-10), filed for the period ending between October 1, 2012, and June 30, 2013.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>History</heading>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 21-36">Oct. 22, 2015, D.C. Law 21-36, § 5062, 62 DCR 10905</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Emergency Legislation</heading>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 days) addition of this chapter, see §§ 50<cite path="§62-5070">62-5070</cite> of the Fiscal Year 2016 Budget Support Emergency Act of 2015 (D.C. Act 21-127, July 27, 2015,  62 DCR 10201).</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section from-code="true">
    <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" path="|44|6C"/>
    <num codify:value="44-661.02">5063</num>
    <heading>Hospital Provider Fee Fund.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>(a)</num>
      <text>There is established as a special fund the Hospital Provider Fee Fund (“Fund”), which shall be administered by the Department in accordance with subsections (c) and (d) of this section.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(b)</num>
      <text>Revenue from the following sources shall be deposited in the Fund:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Fees collected under this chapter; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Interest and penalties collected under this chapter.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(c)</num>
      <text>Money in the Fund may only be used for the following purposes:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Making Medicaid outpatient hospital access payments to hospitals as required under § <cite path="§44-661.05">44-661.05</cite>;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Payment of administrative expenses incurred by the Department or its agent in performing the activities authorized by this chapter in an amount not to exceed $150,000 annually; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Providing refunds to hospitals pursuant to § <cite path="§44-661.04">44-661.04</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(d)</num>
      <text>Money in the Fund may not be used to replace money appropriated to the Medicaid program.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(e)</num>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The money deposited into the Fund, and interest earned, shall not revert to the unrestricted fund balance of the General Fund of the District of Columbia at the end of a fiscal year, or at any other time.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Subject to authorization in an approved budget and financial plan, any funds appropriated in the Fund shall be continually available without regard to fiscal year limitation.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>History</heading>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 21-36">Oct. 22, 2015, D.C. Law 21-36, § 5063, 62 DCR 10905</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section from-code="true">
    <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" path="|44|6C"/>
    <num codify:value="44-661.03">5064</num>
    <heading>Hospital provider fee.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>(a)</num>
      <text>Beginning October 1, 2015, and subject to § <cite path="§44-661.04">44-661.04</cite>, the District may charge each hospital a fee based on its outpatient gross patient revenue. The fee shall be charged at a uniform rate necessary to generate the following:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>An amount equal to the non-federal share of the total available spending room under the Medicaid upper payment limit for private hospitals applicable to District Fiscal Year (“DFY”) 2016 consistent with the federal approval of the authorizing Medicaid State Plan amendment; plus</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>An amount equal to the lesser of the non-federal share of the total available spending room under the Medicaid upper payment limit for District operated hospitals applicable to DFY 2016 consistent with the federal approval of the authorizing Medicaid State Plan amendment or United Medical Center’s Medicaid disproportionate share hospital limit as adjusted by the District in accordance with the federally approved Medicaid State Plan; plus</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>An amount equal to the Department’s administrative expenses as described in § <cite path="§44-661.02">44-661.02</cite>(c)(2).</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(b)</num>
      <text>A psychiatric hospital that is an agency or a unit of the District government is exempt from the fee imposed under subsection (a) of this section, unless the exemption is adjudged to be unconstitutional or otherwise invalid, in which case a psychiatric hospital that is an agency or a unit of the District government shall pay the fee imposed by subsection (a) of this section.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>History</heading>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 21-36">Oct. 22, 2015, D.C. Law 21-36, § 5064, 62 DCR 10905</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section from-code="true">
    <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" path="|44|6C"/>
    <num codify:value="44-661.04">5065</num>
    <heading>Applicability of fees.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>(a)</num>
      <text>The fee imposed by § <cite path="§44-661.03">44-661.03</cite> shall not be due and payable until such time that the federal Centers for Medicare and Medicaid Services approves the Medicaid State Plan amendment authorizing the Medicaid payments described in § <cite path="§44-661.05">44-661.05</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(b)</num>
      <text>The fee imposed by § <cite path="§44-661.03">44-661.03</cite> shall cease to be imposed, and any moneys remaining in the Fund shall be refunded to hospitals in proportion to the amounts paid by them, if:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The Department makes changes in its rules that reduce the hospital inpatient or outpatient Medicaid payment rates, including adjustment to payment rates that are in effect on October 1, 2014; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The payments to hospitals required under § <cite path="§44-661.05">44-661.05</cite> are modified in any way other than to secure federal approval of such payments as described in § <cite path="§44-661.05">44-661.05</cite> or are not eligible for federal matching funds under section 1903(w) of the Social Security Act, approved July 30, 1965 (70 Stat. 349; 42 U.S.C. §1396b(w)) (“Social Security Act”).</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(c)</num>
      <text>The fee imposed by § <cite path="§44-661.03">44-661.03</cite> shall not take effect or shall cease to be imposed if the fee is determined to be an impermissible tax under section 1903(w)(3)(B) of the Social Security Act by the Centers for Medicare and Medicaid Services.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(d)</num>
      <text>Should the fee imposed by § <cite path="§44-661.03">44-661.03</cite> not take effect or cease to be imposed, moneys in the Fund derived from the imposed fee shall be disbursed in accordance with § <cite path="§44-661.05">44-661.05</cite> to the extent federal matching is available. If federal matching is not available due to a determination by the Centers for Medicare and Medicaid Services that the fee is impermissible, any remaining moneys shall be refunded to hospitals in proportion to the amounts paid by them.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>History</heading>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 21-36">Oct. 22, 2015, D.C. Law 21-36, § 5065, 62 DCR 10905</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section from-code="true">
    <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" path="|44|6C"/>
    <num codify:value="44-661.05">5066</num>
    <heading>Medicaid outpatient hospital access payments.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>(a)</num>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>For visits and services beginning October 1, 2015, quarterly Medicaid outpatient hospital access payments shall be made to each private hospital.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Each payment will be equal to the hospital’s DFY 2013 outpatient Medicaid payments divided by the total in District private hospital DFY 2013 outpatient Medicaid payments multiplied by 1/4 of the total outpatient private hospital access payment pool.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The total outpatient private hospital access payment pool is equal to the total available spending room under the private hospital outpatient Medicaid upper payment limit for DFY 2016.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(b)</num>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A private hospital that is also a Disproportionate Share Hospital (“DSH”) will receive no more in Medicaid outpatient hospital access payments than the available room under its District-adjusted, hospital-specific DSH limit.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Any Medicaid outpatient hospital access payments that would otherwise exceed a private DSH’s adjusted DSH limit shall be distributed to the remaining private hospitals consistent with each private hospital’s relative share of DFY 2013 outpatient Medicaid payments.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(c)</num>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>For visits and services beginning October 1, 2015, outpatient hospital access payments shall be made to the United Medical Center.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Each payment will be equal to one quarter of the total outpatient public hospital access payment pool.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The total outpatient public hospital access payment pool is equal to the lesser of the total available spending room under the District­operated hospital outpatient Medicaid upper payment limit for DFY 2016, and the United Medical Center District-adjusted Medicaid DSH limit.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(d)</num>
      <text>The quarterly Medicaid outpatient hospital access payments shall be made within 15 business days after the end of each DFY quarter for the Medicaid visits and services rendered during that quarter.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(e)</num>
      <text>No payments shall be made under this section until such time that the federal Centers for Medicare and Medicaid Services approves the Medicaid State Plan amendment authorizing the Medicaid payments described in this chapter.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(f)</num>
      <text>The Medicaid payment methodologies authorized under this chapter shall not be altered in any way unless such alteration is necessary to gain federal approval from the Centers for Medicare and Medicaid Services.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>History</heading>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 21-36">Oct. 22, 2015, D.C. Law 21-36, § 5066, 62 DCR 10905</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section from-code="true">
    <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" path="|44|6C"/>
    <num codify:value="44-661.06">5067</num>
    <heading>Quarterly notice and collection.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>(a)</num>
      <text>The fee imposed under § <cite path="§44-661.03">44-661.03</cite>, which shall be calculated, due, and payable on a quarterly basis, shall be due and payable by the 15th of the last month of each DFY quarter; provided, that the fee shall not be due and payable until:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The District issues written notice that the payment methodologies for payments to hospitals required under § <cite path="§44-661.05">44-661.05</cite> have been approved by the federal Centers for Medicare and Medicaid Services; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The District issues written notice to the hospital informing the hospital of its fee rate, outpatient gross patient revenue subject to the fee, and the fee amount owed on a quarterly basis, including, in the initial written notice from the District to the hospital, all fee amounts owed beginning with the period commencing on October 1, 2015, to ensure all applicable fee obligations have been identified.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(b)</num>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>If a hospital fails to pay the full amount of the fee in accordance with this chapter, the unpaid balance shall accrue interest at the rate of 1.5% per month or any fraction thereof, which shall be added to the unpaid balance.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The Chief Financial Officer may arrange a payment plan for the amount of the fee and interest in arrears.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(c)</num>
      <text>The payment by the hospital of the fee created in this chapter shall be reported as an allowable cost for purposes of Medicaid hospital reimbursement.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>History</heading>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 21-36">Oct. 22, 2015, D.C. Law 21-36, § 5067, 62 DCR 10905</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section from-code="true">
    <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" path="|44|6C"/>
    <num codify:value="44-661.07">5068</num>
    <heading>Multi-hospital systems, closure, merger, and new hospitals.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>(a)</num>
      <text>If a hospital system conducts, operates, or maintains more than one hospital licensed by the Department of Health, the hospital system shall pay the fee for each hospital separately.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(b)</num>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Notwithstanding any other provision in this chapter, if a hospital system or person ceases to conduct, operate, or maintain a hospital that is subject to a fee under § <cite path="§44-661.03">44-661.03</cite>, as evidenced by the transfer or surrender of the hospital license, the fee for the DFY in which the cessation occurs shall be adjusted by multiplying the fee computed under § <cite path="§44-661.03">44-661.03</cite> by a fraction, the numerator of which is the number of days in the year during which the hospital system or person conducted, operated, or maintained the hospital, and the denominator of which is 365.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Immediately upon ceasing to conduct, operate, or maintain a hospital, the hospital system or person shall pay the fee for the year as so adjusted, to the extent not previously paid.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(c)</num>
      <text>Notwithstanding any other provision in this chapter, a hospital system or person who conducts, operates, or maintains a hospital, upon notice by the Department, shall pay the fee computed under § <cite path="§44-661.03">44-661.03</cite> and subsection (a) of this section in installments on the due date stated in the notice and on the regular installment due dates for the DFY occurring after the due dates of the initial notice.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>History</heading>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 21-36">Oct. 22, 2015, D.C. Law 21-36, § 5068, 62 DCR 10905</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section from-code="true">
    <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" path="|44|6C"/>
    <num codify:value="44-661.08">5069</num>
    <heading>Rules.</heading>
    <text>The Mayor, pursuant to subchapter I of Chapter 5 of Title 2 [§ <cite path="§2-501">2-501</cite> et seq.], may issue rules to implement the provisions of this chapter.</text>
    <annotations>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>History</heading>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 21-36">Oct. 22, 2015, D.C. Law 21-36, § 5069, 62 DCR 10905</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section from-code="true">
    <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" path="|44|6C"/>
    <num codify:value="44-661.09">5070</num>
    <heading>Sunset.</heading>
    <text>This chapter shall expire on September 30, 2016.</text>
    <annotations>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>History</heading>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 21-36">Oct. 22, 2015, D.C. Law 21-36, § 5070, 62 DCR 10905</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section from-code="true">
    <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" path="|44|6D"/>
    <num codify:value="44-662.01">5072</num>
    <heading>Definitions.</heading>
    <text>For the purposes of this chapter, the term:</text>
    <para>
      <num>(1)</num>
      <text>“Department” means the Department of Health Care Finance.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(2)</num>
      <text>“Hospital” shall have the same meaning as provided in § <cite path="§44-501">44-501</cite>(a)(1) but excludes any hospital operated by the federal government and any specialty hospital, as defined by the District of Columbia’s Medicaid State Plan (“State Plan”), or a hospital that is reimbursed under a specialty hospital reimbursement methodology under the State Plan.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(3)</num>
      <text>“Hospital system” means any group of hospitals licensed separately but operated, owned, or maintained by a common entity.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(4)</num>
      <text>“Inpatient net patient revenue” means the amount calculated in accordance with generally accepted accounting principles for hospitals as derived from each hospital’s filed Hospital and Hospital Health Care Complex Cost Report (Form CMS-2552-10), filed for the period ending between October 1, 2012, and June 30, 2013, using the references below:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(A)</num>
        <text>The sum of: Worksheet G-2; Column 1; Lines 1, 2, 3, 4, 16 and 18.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(B)</num>
        <text>Minus: The ratio of the sum of Worksheet G-2; Column 1; Lines 5, 6, and 7 divided by Worksheet G-2; Column 1; Line 17 multiplied by Worksheet G-2; Column 1; Line 18.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(C)</num>
        <text>Divided by: Worksheet G-2; Column 3; Line 28</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(D)</num>
        <text>Multiplied by: Worksheet G-2; Column 1; Line 3</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(5)</num>
      <text>“Medicaid” means the medical assistance programs authorized by Title XIX of the Social Security Act, approved July 30, 1965 (79 Stat. 343; 42 U.S.C. § 1396 et seq.) (“Social Security Act”), and by § <cite path="§1-307.02">1-307.02</cite>, and administered by the Department.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>History</heading>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 21-36">Oct. 22, 2015, D.C. Law 21-36, § 5072, 62 DCR 10905</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Emergency Legislation</heading>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 days) addition of this chapter, see §§ 50<cite path="§72-5079">72-5079</cite> of the Fiscal Year 2016 Budget Support Emergency Act of 2015 (D.C. Act 21-127, July 27, 2015,  62 DCR 10201).</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section from-code="true">
    <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" path="|44|6D"/>
    <num codify:value="44-662.02">5073</num>
    <heading>Hospital Fund.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>(a)</num>
      <text>There is established as a special fund the Hospital Fund (“Fund”), which shall be administered by the Department in accordance with subsection (c) of this section.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(b)</num>
      <text>Revenue from the following sources shall be deposited in the Fund:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Fees collected under this chapter;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Interest and penalties collected under this chapter; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Other amounts collected under this chapter.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(c)</num>
      <text>Money in the Fund shall be used solely as set forth in § <cite path="§44-662.03">44-662.03</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(d)</num>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The money deposited in the Fund, and interest earned, shall not revert to the unrestricted fund balance of the General Fund of the District of Columbia at the end of a fiscal year, or at any other time.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Subject to authorization in an approved budget and financial plan, any funds appropriated in the Fund shall be continually available without regard to fiscal year limitation; provided, that any remaining money in the Fund at the end of each fiscal year shall be refunded to hospitals in proportion to the amounts paid by them.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>History</heading>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 21-36">Oct. 22, 2015, D.C. Law 21-36, § 5073, 62 DCR 10905</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section from-code="true">
    <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" path="|44|6D"/>
    <num codify:value="44-662.03">5074</num>
    <heading>Hospital provider fee.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>(a)</num>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Beginning October 1, 2015, and except as provided in subsection (b) of this section and § <cite path="§44-662.06">44-662.06</cite>, the District, through the Office of Tax and Revenue, may charge each hospital a fee based on its inpatient net patient revenue.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The fee shall be charged at a uniform rate necessary to generate no more than $10.4 million. Of this amount, $1.4 million may be used to support the Medicaid Managed Care Organization rates for inpatient hospitalization. The remaining amount shall be used to support the maintenance of inpatient Medicaid Fee-for-Service rates at the District Fiscal Year (“DFY”) 2015 level of 98% of cost to non-specialty hospitals.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The fee collected pursuant to this section shall be deposited in the Hospital Fund, established by § <cite path="§44-662.02">44-662.02</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(b)</num>
      <text>A psychiatric hospital that is an agency or a unit of the District government is exempt from the fee imposed under subsection (a) of this section, unless the exemption is adjudged to be unconstitutional or otherwise invalid, in which case a psychiatric hospital that is an agency or a unit of the District government shall pay the fee imposed by subsection (a) of this section.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(c)</num>
      <text>By August 1, 2015, the Department shall submit a provider tax waiver application to the Center for Medicare and Medicaid Services to ensure the provisions of this chapter qualify as a broad-based health care related tax, as that term is defined in section 1903(w)(3)(B) of the Social Security Act.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>History</heading>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 21-36">Oct. 22, 2015, D.C. Law 21-36, § 5074, 62 DCR 10905</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section from-code="true">
    <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" path="|44|6D"/>
    <num codify:value="44-662.04">5075</num>
    <heading>Quarterly notice and collection.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>(a)</num>
      <text>The fee imposed under § <cite path="§44-662.03">44-662.03</cite> shall be due and payable by the 15th of the last month of each DFY quarter.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(b)</num>
      <text>The fee imposed under § <cite path="§44-662.03">44-662.03</cite> shall be calculated, due, and payable on a quarterly basis, but shall not be due and payable until the District issues written notice to each hospital informing the hospital of its fee rate, inpatient net patient revenue subject to the fee, and the fee amount owed on a quarterly basis, including, in the initial written notice from the District to the hospital, all fee amounts owed beginning with the period October 1, 2015, to ensure all applicable fee obligations have been identified.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(c)</num>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>If a hospital fails to pay the full amount of its fee by the date required, the unpaid balance shall accrue interest at the rate of 1.5% per month or any fraction thereof, which shall be added to the unpaid balance.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The Chief Financial Officer may arrange a payment plan for the amount of the fee and interest in arrears.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(d)</num>
      <text>The payment by the hospital of the fee created in this chapter shall be reported as an allowable cost for purposes of Medicaid hospital reimbursement.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>History</heading>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 21-36">Oct. 22, 2015, D.C. Law 21-36, § 5075, 62 DCR 10905</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section from-code="true">
    <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" path="|44|6D"/>
    <num codify:value="44-662.05">5076</num>
    <heading>Multi-hospital systems, closure, merger, and new hospitals.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>(a)</num>
      <text>If a hospital system conducts, operates, or maintains more than one hospital licensed by the Department of Health, the hospital system shall pay the fee for each hospital separately.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(b)</num>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Notwithstanding § <cite path="§44-662.03">44-662.03</cite>, if a hospital system or person that is subject to a fee under § <cite path="§44-662.03">44-662.03</cite> ceases to conduct, operate, or maintain a hospital, as evidenced by the transfer or surrender of a hospital license, the fee for the DFY in which the cessation occurs shall be adjusted by multiplying the fee computed under § <cite path="§44-662.03">44-662.03</cite> by a fraction, the numerator of which is the number of days in the year during which the hospital system or person conducts, operates, or maintains the hospital and the denominator of which is 365.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Immediately upon ceasing to conduct, operate, or maintain a hospital, the hospital system or person shall pay the fee for the year as so adjusted, to the extent not previously paid.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(c)</num>
      <text>Notwithstanding any other provision of this chapter, a hospital system or person who conducts, operates, or maintains a hospital, upon notice by the Department, shall pay the fee required under §  44-662.03 in accordance with subsection (a) of this section on the due date stated in the notice and on the regular installment due dates for the DFY occurring after the due date of the initial notice.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>History</heading>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 21-36">Oct. 22, 2015, D.C. Law 21-36, § 5076, 62 DCR 10905</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section from-code="true">
    <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" path="|44|6D"/>
    <num codify:value="44-662.06">5077</num>
    <heading>Federal determinations; suspension and termination of assessment.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>(a)</num>
      <text>If the Centers for Medicare and Medicaid Services determines that an assessment imposed on a hospital pursuant to this chapter does not satisfy the requirements for federal financial participation set forth in section 1903(w) of the Social Security Act that determination shall not affect the validity, amount, applicable rate, or any other terms of an assessment on other hospitals imposed by this chapter.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(b)</num>
      <text>If the Centers for Medicare and Medicaid Services determines that an exclusion for specialty hospitals under this chapter would prevent an assessment imposed by this chapter from qualifying as a broad-based health care related tax, as that term is defined in section 1903(w)(3)(B) of the Social Security Act, the exclusion of specialty hospitals shall not be made.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>History</heading>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 21-36">Oct. 22, 2015, D.C. Law 21-36, § 5077, 62 DCR 10905</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section from-code="true">
    <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" path="|44|6D"/>
    <num codify:value="44-662.07">5078</num>
    <heading>Rules.</heading>
    <text>The Mayor, pursuant to subchapter I of Chapter 2 of Title 5 [§  2-501 et seq.], may issue rules to implement the provisions of this chapter.</text>
    <annotations>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>History</heading>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 21-36">Oct. 22, 2015, D.C. Law 21-36, § 5078, 62 DCR 10905</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section from-code="true">
    <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" path="|44|6D"/>
    <num codify:value="44-662.08">5079</num>
    <heading>Sunset.</heading>
    <text>This chapter shall expire on September 30, 2016.</text>
    <annotations>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>History</heading>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 21-36">Oct. 22, 2015, D.C. Law 21-36, § 5079, 62 DCR 10905</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section from-code="true">
    <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" path="|1|3|XI|D"/>
    <num codify:value="1-325.35">4032</num>
    <heading>At-Risk Supplemental Allocation Preservation Fund.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>(a)</num>
      <text>There is established as a special fund the At-Risk Supplemental Allocation Preservation Fund (“Fund”), which shall be administered by the Chancellor of the District of Columbia Public Schools in accordance with subsection (c) of this section.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(b)</num>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Subject to the limitations set forth in paragraph (2) of this subsection, at the end of each fiscal year, all unspent local funds in the District of Columbia Public Schools budget that are based on the at-risk add-on established by § <cite path="§38-2905">38-2905</cite>(c) shall be deposited in the Fund.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Each year’s deposit pursuant to paragraph (1) of this subsection shall not exceed 5% of the lower of the District of Columbia Public Schools budget associated with the at-risk add-on for:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(A)</num>
          <text>The fiscal year in which the funds would be deposited; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(B)</num>
          <text>The fiscal year after the year in which the funds would be deposited.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(c)</num>
      <text>The Fund shall be used solely to fund services and materials designed to assist at-risk students as defined in § <cite path="§38-2901">38-2901</cite>(2A).</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(d)</num>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The money deposited into the Fund, and interest earned, shall not revert to the unrestricted fund balance of the General Fund of the District of Columbia at the end of a fiscal year, or at any other time.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Subject to authorization in an approved budget and financial plan, any funds appropriated in the Fund shall be continually available without regard to fiscal year limitation.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>History</heading>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 21-36">Oct. 22, 2015, D.C. Law 21-36, §  4032, 62 DCR 10905</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Emergency Legislation</heading>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 days) addition of this section, see § 4032 of the Fiscal Year 2016 Budget Support Emergency Act of 2015 (D.C. Act 21-127, July 27, 2015,  62 DCR 10201).</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section from-code="true">
    <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" path="|1|3|XI|II"/>
    <num codify:value="1-325.341">6082</num>
    <heading>BID Parking Abatement Fund</heading>
    <para>
      <num>(a)</num>
      <text>There is established as a special fund the BID Parking Abatement Fund (“Fund”), which shall be administered by the Mayor in accordance with subsection (c) of this section.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(b)</num>
      <text>An allocation in the amount of $120,000 from the Fiscal Year 2016 approved budget and financial plan shall be deposited in the Fund.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(c)</num>
      <text>Money in the Fund shall be used to abate parking fees for a Business Improvement District (“BID”), as that term is defined in § <cite path="§2-1215.02">2-1215.02</cite>(7), that applies and is approved to reserve a public parking space within the BID for use by pedestrians; provided, that no more than 70% of the money available in a fiscal year shall be distributed to a single BID.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(d)</num>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The money deposited into the Fund, and interest earned, shall not revert to the unrestricted fund balance of the General Fund of the District of Columbia at the end of a fiscal year, or at any other time.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Subject to authorization in an approved budget and fiscal plan, any funds appropriated in the Fund shall be continually available without regard to fiscal year limitation.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>History</heading>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 21-36">Oct. 22, 2015, D.C. Law 21-36, § 6082, 62 DCR 10905</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Emergency Legislation</heading>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 days) addition of this section, see § 6082 of the Fiscal Year 2016 Budget Support Emergency Act of 2015 (D.C. Act 21-127, July 27, 2015,  62 DCR 10201).</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section from-code="true">
    <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" path="|2|12|IX|B|6"/>
    <num codify:value="2-1217.36a">7192</num>
    <heading>Definitions.</heading>
    <text>For the purposes of this subpart, the term:</text>
    <para>
      <num>(1)</num>
      <text>“Development costs” shall have the same meaning as provided in § <cite path="§2-1217.01">2-1217.01</cite>(13).</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(2)</num>
      <text>“Development Sponsor” means Edens, or an affiliate thereof approved by the Mayor.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(3)</num>
      <text>“Eligible project” shall have the same meaning as provided in § <cite path="§2-1217.01">2-1217.01</cite>(18).</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(4)</num>
      <text>“Home Rule Act” means Chapter 2 of Title 1 [§  1-201.01 et seq.].</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(5)</num>
      <text>“Project” means the financing, refinancing, or reimbursing of certain tax increment qualified costs incurred for the development of projects, including retail, residential, and office space on parcels, lots, and squares, within and abutting the boundary of the Florida Avenue Market as set forth in the Florida Avenue Market Small Area Plan, dated 2009, approved by the Florida Avenue Market Small Area Plan Approval Resolution of 2009, effective October 6, 2009 (Res. 18-257; 56 DCR 8401).</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(6)</num>
      <text>“Tax increment” shall have the same meaning as provided in § <cite path="§1-204.90">1-204.90</cite>(n)(6).</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(7)</num>
      <text>“TIF Act” means part A of this chapter [§  2-1217.01 et seq.].</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(8)</num>
      <text>“TIF Bonds” means bonds, notes, or other obligations issued pursuant to the TIF Act.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>History</heading>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 21-36">Oct. 22, 2015, D.C. Law 21-36, § 7192, 62 DCR 10905</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Emergency Legislation</heading>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 days) addition of this section, see § 7162 of the Fiscal Year 2016 Budget Support Emergency Act of 2015 (D.C. Act 21-127, July 27, 2015,  62 DCR 10201).</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section from-code="true">
    <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" path="|2|12|IX|B|6"/>
    <num codify:value="2-1217.36b">7193</num>
    <heading>Findings.</heading>
    <text>The Council finds that:</text>
    <para>
      <num>(1)</num>
      <text>Pursuant to § <cite path="§1-204.90">1-204.90</cite>, the TIF Act provides for the issuance of TIF Bonds to finance certain public infrastructure costs of eligible projects to the extent the debt service on the TIF Bonds can be paid from tax revenues generated by those eligible projects and does not violate District law with regard to the limitations on the issue of debt.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(2)</num>
      <text>The Development Sponsor has requested that the District consider the issuance of TIF Bonds, in one or more taxable or tax-exempt issues, for the purpose of financing or reimbursing the Development Sponsor for development costs of the Project in the net amount of $90 million.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(3)</num>
      <text>The Project is desirable and in the public interest.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>History</heading>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 21-36">Oct. 22, 2015, D.C. Law 21-36, § 7193, 62 DCR 10905</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Emergency Legislation</heading>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 days) addition of this section, see § 7163 of the Fiscal Year 2016 Budget Support Emergency Act of 2015 (D.C. Act 21-127, July 27, 2015,  62 DCR 10201).</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section from-code="true">
    <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" path="|2|12|IX|B|6"/>
    <num codify:value="2-1217.36c">7194</num>
    <heading>Declaration of intent.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>(a)</num>
      <text>The Council supports the Project and, to the extent feasible, legal, and prudent under the District’s debt limitations, and in compliance with law, supports efforts to issue TIF Bonds to finance eligible development costs of the Project.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(b)</num>
      <text>The maximum principal amount of the TIF Bonds to be issued to finance the Project shall be determined by agreement of the Development Sponsor, the Chief Financial Officer, and the Mayor.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(c)</num>
      <text>The issuance of the TIF Bonds shall be dependent on the execution of a mutually agreed upon development agreement and other agreements between the District and the Development Sponsor and certification of the Project by the Chief Financial Officer pursuant to the TIF Act.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>History</heading>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 21-36">Oct. 22, 2015, D.C. Law 21-36, § 7194, 62 DCR 10905</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Emergency Legislation</heading>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 days) addition of this section, see § 7164 of the Fiscal Year 2016 Budget Support Emergency Act of 2015 (D.C. Act 21-127, July 27, 2015,  62 DCR 10201).</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section from-code="true">
    <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" path="|2|12|IX|B|6"/>
    <num codify:value="2-1217.36d">7195</num>
    <heading>Future legal requirements.</heading>
    <text>The issuance of TIF Bonds to finance the Project and the terms of the resolution approving the issuance of the TIF Bonds are subject to approval by the Council as set forth in the TIF Act. Enactment of this subpart in no way guarantees that the District will authorize the issue of TIF Bonds in any amount, that the TIF Bonds will be approved by the District, or that the TIF Bonds will actually be issued.</text>
    <annotations>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>History</heading>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 21-36">Oct. 22, 2015, D.C. Law 21-36, § 7195, 62 DCR 10905</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Emergency Legislation</heading>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 days) addition of this section, see § 7165 of the Fiscal Year 2016 Budget Support Emergency Act of 2015 (D.C. Act 21-127, July 27, 2015,  62 DCR 10201).</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section from-code="true">
    <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" path="|39|2A"/>
    <num codify:value="39-231">1072</num>
    <heading>Creation of a cultural plan.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>(a)</num>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>On or before December 15, 2016, the Director of the Office of Planning (“Office”) shall submit to the Mayor and the Council and post on the Office’s website a comprehensive cultural plan (“Plan”). Before that date, the Office shall oversee the solicitation, through a request for proposals, of a private cultural-planning firm to develop the Plan.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The request for proposals to develop the Plan shall propose compensation for the firm developing the Plan that does not exceed $200,000. The Office may accept contributions from private foundations to defray additional costs, if any, of compensating the firm that develops the Plan.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>At a minimum, the Plan shall include:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(A)</num>
          <text>Recommended means by which the District may increase participation in cultural activities throughout the District and address the desires of residents of each of the 8 wards with respect to art and culture policy in their neighborhoods;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(B)</num>
          <text>An outline of the city’s cultural policies and the means of implementing those policies and a study of the economic benefits and the impacts on quality of life, community development, and cultural literacy of those policies;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(C)</num>
          <text>A proposed process for community decision-making regarding cultural activities that focuses on neighborhoods, engages and encourages community input, and supports access to the arts and cultural programming in neighborhoods;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(D)</num>
          <text>An analysis of whether some neighborhoods are better served than others with respect to cultural activities and proposals to remedy the disparities;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(E)</num>
          <text>An analysis of the needs of artists and other members of the creative economy and recommendations regarding steps that may be taken to retain and otherwise support such individuals in the District’s current real-estate environment, including recommendations with regard to the creation of both long-term and temporary affordable studio and rehearsal space, including space that otherwise would remain vacant, as well as affordable housing for artists and other members of the creative economy;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(F)</num>
          <text>An analysis of the current state of arts education in District of Columbia Public Schools and District public charter schools and recommendations regarding the improvement of arts education in the District;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(G)</num>
          <text>An analysis of the means by which District agencies can incorporate the arts to enhance their missions while better serving the cultural needs of the District. On or before November 1, 2015, each District agency shall submit its own analysis of those means that shall be incorporated in the Plan;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(H)</num>
          <text>An examination of means by which the arts can be incorporated into community and economic development planning processes and policies;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(I)</num>
          <text>Recommendations as to means by which the District can create a more arts-friendly regulatory structure, specifically with regard to facilitating performances and exhibitions that seek to engage the public in a public setting; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(J)</num>
          <text>Any existing data sets regarding the distribution of cultural resources throughout the city, as well as any other existing data sets relevant to the Plan.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>All recommendations, initiatives, and priorities included in the Plan shall be indicated as being proposed to occur in a short-, medium-, or long-term timeframe and categorized by the following budget ranges: under $50,000; $50,000 to $250,000; $250,000 to $1 million; and over $1 million;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>The development of the Plan shall occur in a transparent and accessible fashion. Whenever feasible, the Office shall utilize appropriate technology to enhance outreach and communication with the public during the development of the Plan.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>The Office shall consult with the Commission on the Arts and Humanities in the development of the Plan.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>To the extent feasible, any agency implicated by the conclusions and recommendations of the Plan shall incorporate those conclusions and recommendations into its budget and programming.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(b)</num>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A Cultural Planning Steering Committee (“Committee”) shall be formed to assist in the implementation of the Plan. The Committee shall consist of at least 3 members of the arts and creative economy community with relevant arts and creative economy expertise and each of the following individuals, or his or her appointee:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(A)</num>
          <text>Deputy Mayor for Planning and Economic Development;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(B)</num>
          <text>The Director of the Office of Planning;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(C)</num>
          <text>The Executive Director of the Commission on the Arts and Humanities;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(D)</num>
          <text>The Chairperson of the Commission on the Arts and Humanities;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(E)</num>
          <text>The Chairman of the Council’s designee;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(F)</num>
          <text>The Chairman of the Council’s Committee on Finance and Revenue’s designee; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(G)</num>
          <text>The DC BID Council Executive Director.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The Committee shall meet with the Office and representatives of other affected agencies on a quarterly basis to track the progress of the recommendations in the Plan, beginning with the first quarter after submission of the Plan to the Mayor and the Council.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>History</heading>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 21-36">Oct. 22, 2015, D.C. Law 21-36, § 1072, 62 DCR 10905</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Emergency Legislation</heading>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 days) addition of this section, see § 1072 of the Fiscal Year 2016 Budget Support Emergency Act of 2015 (D.C. Act 21-127, July 27, 2015,  62 DCR 10201).</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section from-code="true">
    <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" path="|5|1|VIII-B|A"/>
    <num codify:value="5-116.31">3002</num>
    <heading>Body-Worn Camera Program; generally.</heading>
    <text>The Body-Worn Camera Program in the Metropolitan Police Department in Fiscal Year 2016 shall not be implemented until certification by the Chief Financial Officer that the cost of public access to body-worn camera recordings, if any, is funded in the Fiscal Year 2016 budget and 4-year financial plan.</text>
    <annotations>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>History</heading>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 21-36">Oct. 22, 2015, D.C. Law 21-36, § 3002, 62 DCR 10905</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Emergency Legislation</heading>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 days) addition of this section, see § 3002 of the Fiscal Year 2016 Budget Support Emergency Act of 2015 (D.C. Act 21-127, July 27, 2015,  62 DCR 10201).</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section from-code="true">
    <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" path="|5|1|VIII-B|A"/>
    <num codify:value="5-116.32">3003</num>
    <heading>Body-Worn Camera Program; rulemaking requirement.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>(a)</num>
      <text>The Mayor, pursuant to subchapter I of Chapter 5 of Title 2 [§ <cite path="§2-501">2-501</cite> et seq.], and in accordance with this section, shall issue rules regarding the Metropolitan Police Department’s Body-Worn Camera Program. The rules, at a minimum, shall provide:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Standards for public access to body-worn camera recordings;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Policies for retaining body-worn camera recordings;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Procedures for auditing the Body-Worn Camera Program;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Policies for protecting the security and integrity of body-worn camera data; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Mechanisms for cost recovery of Freedom of Information Act requests.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(b)</num>
      <text>The Mayor shall establish and consult with an advisory group to provide recommendations for the proposed rules required by subsection (c) of this section. The advisory group shall consist of one representative from each of the following agencies and organizations:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The Committee on the Judiciary of the Council of the District of Columbia;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The Office of Police Complaints;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The Office of Open Government of the Board of Ethics and Government Accountability;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The Fraternal Order of Police, D.C. Police Union;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>The Electronic Privacy and Information Center;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>The D.C. Coalition Against Domestic Violence;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>The American Civil Liberties Union of the National Capital Area;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>The Reporters Committee for Freedom of the Press;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>The D.C. Open Government Coalition;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(10)</num>
        <text>The Office of the Attorney General;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(11)</num>
        <text>The United States Attorney’s Office for the District of Columbia; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(12)</num>
        <text>The Public Defender Service for the District of Columbia.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(c)</num>
      <text>The Mayor shall submit the proposed rules required by this section to the Council by October 1, 2015, for a 45-day period of review, excluding Saturdays, Sundays, legal holidays, and days of Council recess. If the Council does not approve or disapprove the proposed rules, in whole or in part, by resolution, within this 45-day period of review, the proposed rules shall be deemed disapproved.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>History</heading>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 21-36">Oct. 22, 2015, D.C. Law 21-36, § 3003, 62 DCR 10905</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Temporary Legislation</heading>
        <annotation>For temporary (225 days) restriction on the use of body-worn cameras, see § 6 of the Fiscal Year 2015 and Fiscal Year 2016 Revised Budget Request Adjustment Temporary Act of 2015 (<cite doc="D.C. Law 21-48">D.C. Law 21-48</cite>, Jan. 9, 2016,  62 DCR 13979).</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Emergency Legislation</heading>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 days) addition of this section, see § 3003 of the Fiscal Year 2016 Budget Support Emergency Act of 2015 (D.C. Act 21-127, July 27, 2015,  62 DCR 10201).</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section from-code="true">
    <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" path="|5|1|VIII-B|A"/>
    <num codify:value="5-116.33">3004</num>
    <heading>Body-Worn Camera Program; reporting requirements.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>(a)</num>
      <text>By October 1, 2015, and every 6 months thereafter, the Mayor shall collect, and make available in a publicly accessible format, data on the Metropolitan Police Department’s Body-Worn Camera Program, including:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>How many hours of body-worn camera recordings were collected;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>How many times body-worn cameras failed while officers were on shift and the reasons for the failures;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>How many times internal investigations were opened for a failure to turn on body-worn cameras during interactions;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>How many times body-worn camera recordings were used by the Metropolitan Police Department in internal affairs investigations;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>How many times body-worn camera recordings were used by the Metropolitan Police Department to investigate complaints made by an individual or group;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>How many body-worn cameras are assigned to each police district and police unit for the reporting period;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>How many Freedom of Information Act requests the Metropolitan Police Department received for body-worn camera recordings during the reporting period, the outcome of each request, including any reasons for denial, and the cost to the department for complying with each request, including redaction; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>How many recordings were assigned to each body-worn camera recording category.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(b)</num>
      <text>The Metropolitan Police Department shall provide the Office of Police Complaints with direct access to body-worn camera recordings.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>History</heading>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 21-36">Oct. 22, 2015, D.C. Law 21-36, § 3004, 62 DCR 10905</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 21-83">Mar. 9, 2016, D.C. Law 21-83, § 3, 63 DCR 774</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Effect of Amendments</heading>
        <annotation>The 2016 amendment by <cite doc="D.C. Law 21-83">D.C. Law 21-83</cite> rewrote (a)(7); and added (a)(8) and made a related change.</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Emergency Legislation</heading>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 days) addition of this section, see § 3004 of the Fiscal Year 2016 Budget Support Emergency Act of 2015 (D.C. Act 21-127, July 27, 2015,  62 DCR 10201).</annotation>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 days) amendment of this section, see § 3 of the Body-Worn Camera Program Emergency Amendment Act of 2015 (D.C. Act 21-253, Dec. 30, 2015,  63 DCR 271).</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section from-code="true">
    <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" path="|5|5|II-A"/>
    <num codify:value="5-525.01">7092</num>
    <heading>Fire and Emergency Medical Services Overtime Settlement Fund.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>(a)</num>
      <text>There is established as a special fund the Fire and Emergency Medical Services Overtime Settlement Fund (“Fund”), which shall be administered by the Office of the City Administrator in accordance with subsection (c) of this section.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(b)</num>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Subject to paragraph (2) of this subsection, there shall be deposited into the Fund:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(A)</num>
          <text>Excess Fiscal Year 2015 revenues certified by the Chief Financial Officer in the June 2015 quarterly revenue estimate; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(B)</num>
          <text>Immediately upon completion of the fiscal year-end close, the undesignated and unreserved end-of-the-year fund balance of the General Fund of the District of Columbia.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The Chief Financial Officer shall deposit into the Fund only the amount necessary to fully satisfy the District’s obligations referenced in subsection (c) of this section. Any excess above that amount shall be deposited into the unrestricted fund balance of the General Fund of the District of Columbia, subject to any allocation required by § <cite path="§47-392.02">47-392.02</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(c)</num>
      <text>The Fund shall be used to pay the District’s obligations arising from the decision of the District of Columbia Court of Appeals in District of Columbia Fire and Emergency Medical Services Department v. District of Columbia Public Employee Relations Board, et al., 105 A.3d 992 (D.C. 2014).</text>
      <text>
        <em>District of Columbia Fire and Emergency Medical Services Department v. District of Columbia Public Employee Relations Board, et al.</em>
      </text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(d)</num>
      <text>The money deposited into the Fund, and interest earned, shall not revert to the unrestricted fund balance of the General Fund of the District of Columbia at the end of a fiscal year, or at any other time.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>History</heading>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 21-36">Oct. 22, 2015, D.C. Law 21-36, § 7092, 62 DCR 10905</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Emergency Legislation</heading>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 days) addition of this section, see § 7062 of the Fiscal Year 2016 Budget Support Emergency Act of 2015 (D.C. Act 21-127, July 27, 2015,  62 DCR 10201).</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section from-code="true">
    <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" path="|5|5|II-A"/>
    <num codify:value="5-525.02">7093</num>
    <heading>Applicability.</heading>
    <text>If funds deposited under § <cite path="§5-525.01">5-525.01</cite>(b) are sufficient to fully satisfy the District’s obligations arising from the decision of the District of Columbia Court of Appeals in<em>District of Columbia Fire and Emergency Medical Services Department v. District of Columbia Public Employee Relations Board, et al.</em>, 105 A.3d 992 (D.C. 2014)  , as certified by the Chief Financial Officer, § <cite path="§5-525.01">5-525.01</cite> shall not apply.</text>
    <annotations>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>History</heading>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 21-36">Oct. 22, 2015, D.C. Law 21-36, § 7093, 62 DCR 10905</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Emergency Legislation</heading>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 days) addition of this section, see § 7063 of the Fiscal Year 2016 Budget Support Emergency Act of 2015 (D.C. Act 21-127, July 27, 2015,  62 DCR 10201).</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section from-code="true">
    <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" path="|50|26|III"/>
    <num codify:value="50-2636">6004</num>
    <heading>Enforcement of parking meters in Premium Demand Parking Meter Rate Zones.</heading>
    <text>As of October 1, 2015, the District Department of Transportation shall provide for enforcement of parking meters in Premium Demand Parking Meter Rate Zones from 7:00 a.m. until midnight.</text>
    <annotations>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>History</heading>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 21-36">Oct. 22, 2015, D.C. Law 21-36, § 6004, 62 DCR 10905</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Temporary Legislation</heading>
        <annotation>For temporary (225 days) repeal of this section, see § 2(a) of the Fiscal Year 2016 Budget Support Clarification Temporary Amendment Act of 2015 (<cite doc="D.C. Law 21-76">D.C. Law 21-76</cite>, Feb. 27, 2016,  63 DCR 264).</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Emergency Legislation</heading>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 days) addition of this section, see §  6004 of the Fiscal Year 2016 Budget Support Emergency Act of 2015 (D.C. Act 21-127, July 27, 2015, 62 DCR 10201).</annotation>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 days) repeal of section, see § 2 of the Fiscal Year 2016 Second Budget Support Clarification Emergency Amendment Act of 2015 (D.C. Act 21-202, Nov. 23, 2015,  62 DCR 15276).</annotation>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 days) repeal of this section, see § 2 of the Fiscal Year 2016 Budget Support Clarification Congressional Review Emergency Amendment Act of 2016 (D.C. Act 21-307, Feb. 18, 2016,  63 DCR 2182).</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section from-code="true">
    <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" path="|50|26|III"/>
    <num codify:value="50-2637">6012</num>
    <heading>Unlawfully parked vehicles.</heading>
    <text>It shall be a violation of Chapter 23 of this title [§  50-2301.01 et seq.] for a person to park, leave unattended, or store a vehicle in violation of posted parking restrictions at a parking facility, as that term is defined in § <cite path="§50-2602">50-2602</cite>(4), owned by the Washington Metropolitan Area Transit Authority.</text>
    <annotations>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>History</heading>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 21-36">Oct. 22, 2015, D.C. Law 21-36, § 6012, 62 DCR 10905</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Temporary Legislation</heading>
        <annotation>For temporary (225 days) amendment of this section, see § 18 of the Fiscal Year 2016 Budget Support Clarification Temporary Amendment Act of 2015 (<cite doc="D.C. Law 21-76">D.C. Law 21-76</cite>, Feb. 27, 2016,  63 DCR 264).</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Emergency Legislation</heading>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 days) addition of this section, see §  6012 of the Fiscal Year 2016 Budget Support Emergency Act of 2015 (D.C. Act 21-127, July 27, 2015, 62 DCR 10201).</annotation>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 days) amendment of section, see § 9 of the Fiscal Year 2016 Second Budget Support Clarification Emergency Amendment Act of 2015 (D.C. Act 21-202, Nov. 23, 2015,  62 DCR 15276).</annotation>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 days) amendment of this section, see § 9 of the Fiscal Year 2016 Budget Support Clarification Congressional Review Emergency Amendment Act of 2016 (D.C. Act 21-307, Feb. 18, 2016,  63 DCR 2182).</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
    </annotations>
  </section>
</document>
