<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<document xmlns:codify="http://code.dccouncil.us/schemas/codify" id="D.C. Law 18-354">
  <num type="law">18-354</num>
  <heading type="short">H Street, N.E., Retail Priority Area Incentive Act of 2010</heading>
  <meta>
    <effective>2011-04-08</effective>
    <cites>
      <law lawId="354" period="18" url="./docs/18-354.pdf"/>
      <register page="754" vol="58"/>
    </cites>
    <history url="http://lims.dccouncil.us/Legislation/B18-0970">
      <narrative>Law 18-354, the “H Street, N.E., Retail Priority Area Incentive Act of 2010”, was introduced in Council and assigned Bill No. 18-970, which was referred to the Committee on Finance and Revenue. The Bill was adopted on first and second readings on December 7, 2010, and December 21, 2010, respectively. Signed by the Mayor on January 19, 2011, it was assigned Act No. 18-704 and transmitted to both Houses of Congress for its review. D.C. Law 18-354 became effective on April 8, 2011.</narrative>
    </history>
  </meta>
  <section from-code="true">
    <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" path="|1|3|XI|R"/>
    <num codify:value="1-325.171">2</num>
    <heading>Definitions.</heading>
    <text>For the purposes of this part, the term:</text>
    <para>
      <num>(1)</num>
      <text>“Chief Financial Officer” means the Chief Financial Officer established by § <cite path="§1-204.24">1-204.24</cite>(a).</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(2)</num>
      <text>“DMPED” means the Office of the Deputy Mayor for Planning and Economic Development established by Mayor’s Order 99-62 (April 9, 1999).</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(3)</num>
      <text>“Developer Sponsor” shall have the same meaning as provided in § <cite path="§47-4634">47-4634</cite>(1).</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(4)</num>
      <text>“H Street Real Property Tax Increment Revenue” means the portion of the real property tax imposed by Chapter 8 of Title 47 on real property in the H Street, N.E., Retail Priority Area in any fiscal year that exceeds the amount of the real property tax imposed on the real property in the H Street, N.E., Retail Priority Area in the fiscal year ended September 30, 2007.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(5)</num>
      <text>“H Street, N.E., Retail Priority Area” means the H Street, N.E., Retail Priority Area as defined in section 2(2) of the Great Streets Neighborhood Retail Priority Areas Approval Resolution of 2007, effective July 10, 2007(Res. 17-257; 54 DCR 7194).</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(6)</num>
      <text>“H Street Retail Developer” means a person or corporation that proposes to, or provides technical assistance to, engage in the business of sale of personal property or services for use or consumption by the purchasers at locations in the H Street, N.E., Retail Priority Area.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(7)</num>
      <text>“H Street Sales Tax Increment Revenue” means the portion of the sales tax imposed by Chapter 20 of Title 47 on goods and services sold in the H Street, N.E., Retail Priority Area in any fiscal year that exceeds the amount of the sales tax imposed in the H Street, N.E., Retail Priority Area in the fiscal year ended September 30, 2007.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>History</heading>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 18-354">Apr. 8, 2011, D.C. Law 18-354, § 2, 58 DCR 754</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 19-168">Sept. 20, 2012, D.C. Law 19-168, § 2162(a), 59 DCR 8025</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 20-155">Feb. 26, 2015, D.C. Law 20-155, § 2092, 61 DCR 9990</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 21-36">Oct. 22, 2015, D.C. Law 21-36, § 2022(a), 62 DCR 10905</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Effect of Amendments</heading>
        <annotation>The 2012 amendment by <cite doc="D.C. Law 19-168">D.C. Law 19-168</cite> added “or services” in (6).</annotation>
        <annotation>The 2015 amendment by <cite doc="D.C. Law 20-155">D.C. Law 20-155</cite> added “and, after October 1, 2014, the Bladensburg Road, N.E., Retail Priority Area, as defined in § <cite path="§2-1217.73">2-1217.73</cite>” at the end of (5).</annotation>
        <annotation>The 2015 amendment by <cite doc="D.C. Law 21-36">D.C. Law 21-36</cite> rewrote (5).</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Emergency Legislation</heading>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 day) amendment of section, see § 2162(a) of Fiscal Year 2013 Budget Support Emergency Act of 2012 (D.C. Act 19-383, June 19, 2012,  59 DCR 7764).</annotation>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 day) amendment of section, see § 2162(a) of Fiscal Year 2013 Budget Support Congressional Review Emergency Act of 2012 (D.C. Act 19-413, July 25, 2012,  59 DCR 9290).</annotation>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 days) amendment of this section, see §  2092 of the Fiscal Year 2015 Budget Support Emergency Act of 2014 (D.C. Act 20-377, July 14, 2014, 61 DCR 7598, 20 STAT 3696).</annotation>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 days) amendment of this section, see §  2092 of the Fiscal Year 2015 Budget Support Congressional Review Emergency Act of 2014 (D.C. Act 20-449, October 10, 2014, 61 DCR 10915, 20 STAT 4188).</annotation>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 days) amendment of this section, see §  2092 of the Fiscal Year 2015 Budget Support Second Congressional Review Emergency Act of 2014 (D.C. Act 20-566, January 9, 2015, 62 DCR 884, 21 STAT 541).</annotation>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 days) amendment of this section, see § 2022(a) of the Fiscal Year 2016 Budget Support Emergency Act of 2015 (D.C. Act 21-127, July 27, 2015,  62 DCR 10201).</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section from-code="true">
    <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" path="|1|3|XI|R"/>
    <num codify:value="1-325.172">3</num>
    <heading>Establishment of the H Street Retail Priority Area Grant Fund.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>(a)</num>
      <text>There is established as a nonlapsing fund outside the General Fund of the District of Columbia a fund designated as the H Street Retail Priority Area Grant Fund. The Chief Financial Officer shall pay upon April 8, 2011, an amount not to exceed $5 million annually, but not to exceed $25 million in the aggregate, of the H Street Real Property Tax Increment Revenue and the H Street Sales Tax Increment Revenue into the H Street Retail Priority Area Grant Fund.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(b)</num>
      <text>All funds deposited into the H Street Retail Priority Area Grant Fund, and any interest earned on those funds, shall not revert to the unrestricted fund balance of the General Fund of the District of Columbia at the end of a fiscal year, or at any other time, but shall be continually available for the uses and purposes set forth in subsection (c) of this section without regard to fiscal year limitation, subject to authorization by Congress.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(c)</num>
      <text>DMPED shall use a portion of each of the $5 million annual allocations into the H Street Retail Priority Area Grant Fund as follows:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <para>
          <num>(A)</num>
          <text>Repay the General Fund of the District of Columbia annually for all tax abatements to the Developer Sponsor;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(B)</num>
          <text>The value of the tax abatements to the Developer Sponsor shall not exceed $5 million in the aggregate;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Make grants to H Street Retail Developers in accordance with § <cite path="§1-325.173">1-325.173</cite>;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Beginning October 1, 2015, and ending September 30, 2016, make grants to support revitalization programs pursuant to § <cite path="§2-1217.73b">2-1217.73b</cite>. Grants may be awarded for revitalization programs within any of the Retail Priority Areas established by or pursuant to § <cite path="§2-1217.73">2-1217.73</cite>. The total amount of funds that may be granted pursuant to this paragraph shall not exceed $4 million; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <para>
          <num>(A)</num>
          <text>In Fiscal Year 2016, the Deputy Mayor for Planning and Economic Development may use monies credited to the Fund to award up to $2 million in grants to one or more Qualified High Technology Companies (“QHTCs”), as defined by § <cite path="§47-1817.01">47-1817.01</cite>(5), for the purpose of assisting the recipients in making improvements to building space that is rented, or to be rented, and occupied exclusively, or to be occupied exclusively, by those QHTCs.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(B)</num>
          <text>The total amount of grants to a single recipient shall not exceed $1 million.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(d)</num>
      <text>The Mayor shall prepare and deliver an annual report to the Council each year on January 1st. The annual report shall contain a listing and description of each grant issued from the H Street Retail Priority Area Grant Fund pursuant to this part. Each listing shall contain specific information about the nature of the grant, the grantee, the use of the grant funds, the projected number of new jobs created for District residents, the projected economic benefit to the District, and any other information the Council may request regarding each grant.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>History</heading>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 18-354">Apr. 8, 2011, D.C. Law 18-354, § 3, 58 DCR 754</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 21-36">Oct. 22, 2015, D.C. Law 21-36, §§  2022(b), 2174, 62 DCR 10905</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Effect of Amendments</heading>
        <annotation>The 2015 amendment by <cite doc="D.C. Law 21-36">D.C. Law 21-36</cite> added (c)(3) and (c)(4); and made related changes.</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Emergency Legislation</heading>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 days) amendment of this section, see §§  2022(b) and 2174 of the Fiscal Year 2016 Budget Support Emergency Act of 2015 (D.C. Act 21-127, July 27, 2015,  62 DCR 10201).</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section from-code="true">
    <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" path="|1|3|XI|R"/>
    <num codify:value="1-325.173">4</num>
    <heading>H Street, N.E., Retail Priority Area business development.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>(a)</num>
      <text>The Mayor shall publish no later than 120 days after April 8, 2011, and no less than annually after that date, a notice of funding availability to make grants to assist retail development projects which generate new jobs in new or improved existing retail space in the H Street, N.E., Retail Priority Area.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(b)</num>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Eligible development projects shall include businesses engaged in the sale of home furnishings, apparel, books, art, groceries, and general merchandise to specialized customers or service-oriented businesses providing a direct service to specialized customers or artistic endeavors, such as art galleries, theaters, or performing arts centers. Special consideration shall be given to businesses that include entrepreneurial and innovative retail elements.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Eligible retail development projects shall not include liquor stores, restaurants whose annual alcohol sales exceed 20%, nightclubs, phone stores, or businesses with 20 or more locations in the United States.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(c)</num>
      <text>Eligibility for retail development projects shall include:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Site control of the property either through fee simple ownership of the site or through an executed contract or lease with the property owner;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Direct frontage on the H Street, N.E., corridor from 3rd Street, N.E., to 15th Street, N.E.;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Repealed;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Execution of a First Source Agreement with the District’s Department of Employment Services; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Adherence to design, construction, and rehabilitation requirements as defined by DMPED.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>History</heading>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 18-354">Apr. 8, 2011, D.C. Law 18-354, § 4, 58 DCR 754</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 19-168">Sept. 20, 2012, D.C. Law 19-168, § 2162(b), 59 DCR 8025</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 20-262">May 2, 2015, D.C. Law 20-262, § 4, 62 DCR 15116</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Section References</heading>
        <annotation>This section is referenced in § <cite path="§1-325.172">1-325.172</cite>.</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Effect of Amendments</heading>
        <annotation>The 2012 amendment by <cite doc="D.C. Law 19-168">D.C. Law 19-168</cite> rewrote (b); and repealed (c)(3), which read: “Total retail space which is not less than 1,200 square feet.”</annotation>
        <annotation>The 2015 amendment by <cite doc="D.C. Law 20-262">D.C. Law 20-262</cite> added “whose annual alcohol sales exceed 20%” in (b).</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Temporary Legislation</heading>
        <annotation>For temporary (225 days) amendment of this section, see § 2 of the H Street, N.E., Retail Priority Area Incentive Temporary Amendment Act of 2014 (<cite doc="D.C. Law 20-170">D.C. Law 20-170</cite>, March 7, 2015, 61 DCR 12121).</annotation>
        <annotation>For temporary (225 days) amendment of this section, see §§ 4 and 5 of the H Street, N.E., Retail Priority Area Clarification Temporary Amendment Act of 2015 (<cite doc="D.C. Law 21-1">D.C. Law 21-1</cite>, June 4, 2015,  62 DCR 4550).</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Emergency Legislation</heading>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 day) amendment of section, see § 2162(b) of Fiscal Year 2013 Budget Support Emergency Act of 2012 (D.C. Act 19-383, June 19, 2012,  59 DCR 7764).</annotation>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 day) amendment of section, see § 2162(b) of Fiscal Year 2013 Budget Support Congressional Review Emergency Act of 2012 (D.C. Act 19-413, July 25, 2012,  59 DCR 9290).</annotation>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 days) amendment of this section, see § 2 of the H Street, N.E., Retail Priority Area Incentive Emergency Amendment Act of 2014 (D.C. Act 20-460, Oct. 24, 2014, 61 DCR 11377, 20 STAT 4367).</annotation>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 days) amendment of this section, see §§ 4 and 5 of the H Street, N.E., Retail Priority Area Clarification Emergency Amendment Act of 2015 (D.C. Act 21-6, Feb. 23, 2015,  62 DCR 2474, 21 STAT 805).</annotation>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 days) amendment of this section, see § 3 of the H Street, N.E., Retail Priority Area Clarification Congressional Review Emergency Amendment Act of 2015 (D.C. Act 21-65, May 22, 2015,  62 DCR 6865, 21 DCSTAT 1444).</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
    </annotations>
  </section>
</document>
