<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<document xmlns:codify="http://code.dccouncil.us/schemas/codify" id="D.C. Law 18-335">
  <num type="law">18-335</num>
  <heading type="short">Prohibition on Government Employee Engagement in Political Activity Act of 2010, </heading>
  <meta>
    <effective>2011-03-31</effective>
    <cites>
      <law lawId="335" period="18" url="./docs/18-335.pdf"/>
      <register page="599" vol="58"/>
    </cites>
    <history url="http://lims.dccouncil.us/Legislation/B18-0460">
      <narrative>Law 18-335, the “Prohibition on Government Employee Engagement in Political Activity Act of 2010, ” was introduced in Council and assigned Bill No. 18-460. The Bill was adopted on first and second readings on Nov. 23, 2010, and Dec. 21, 2010, respectively. Signed by the Mayor on Jan. 12, 2011, it was assigned Act No. 18-679 and transmitted to Congress for its review. D.C. Law 18-335 became effective on Mar. 31, 2011.</narrative>
    </history>
  </meta>
  <section from-code="true">
    <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" path="|1|11B"/>
    <num codify:value="1-1171.01">2</num>
    <heading>Definitions.</heading>
    <text>For the purposes of this chapter, the term:</text>
    <para>
      <num>(1)</num>
      <text>“Board” means the District of Columbia Board of Ethics and Government Accountability established by § <cite path="§1-1162.02">1-1162.02</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(2)</num>
      <text>“Candidate” means an individual who seeks nomination or election to any elective office in the District whether or not the person is elected. An individual is deemed to be a candidate if the individual has received political contributions or made expenditures or has consented to another person receiving contributions or making expenditures with a view to bringing about the individual’s nomination or election.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(3)</num>
      <text>“Employee” means:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(A)</num>
        <text>Any individual paid by the District government from grant or appropriated funds for his or her services or holding office in the District of Columbia, other than the following (if not otherwise employed by the District):</text>
        <para>
          <num>(i)</num>
          <text>Employees of the courts of the District of Columbia;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(ii)</num>
          <text>The Mayor;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(iii)</num>
          <text>The Attorney General, after January 1, 2018;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(iv)</num>
          <text>The members of the Council;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(v)</num>
          <text>Advisory Neighborhood Commissioners;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(vi)</num>
          <text>Members of the State Board of Education; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(vii)</num>
          <text>Members of the District of Columbia Statehood Delegation;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(B)</num>
        <text>A member of a board or commission who is nominated for a position pursuant to § <cite path="§1-523.01">1-523.01</cite>(e); and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(C)</num>
        <text>A member of a board or commission who is nominated for a position pursuant to § <cite path="§1-523.01">1-523.01</cite>(f), when the member is engaged in political activity that relates to the subject matter that the member’s board or commission regulates.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(4)</num>
      <text>“On duty” means the time period when an employee is:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(A)</num>
        <text>In a pay status other than paid leave, compensatory time off, credit hours, time off as an incentive award, or excused or authorized absence (including leave without pay); or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(B)</num>
        <text>Representing any agency or instrumentality of the District government in an official capacity.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(5)</num>
      <text>“Partisan” when used as an adjective means related to a political party.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(6)</num>
      <text>“Partisan political group” means any committee, club, or other organization that is regulated by the District and that is affiliated with a political party or candidate for public office in a partisan election, or organized for a partisan purpose, or which engages in partisan political activity.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(7)</num>
      <text>“Partisan political office” means any office in the District government for which any candidate is nominated or elected as representing a party any of whose candidates for Presidential elector received votes in the last preceding election at which Presidential electors were selected, but shall exclude any office or position within a political party or affiliated organization.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(8)</num>
      <para>
        <num>(A)</num>
        <text>“Political activity” means any activity that is regulated by the District directed toward the success or failure of a political party, candidate for partisan political office, partisan political group, ballot initiative, or referendum. For the purposes of § <cite path="§1-1171.03">1-1171.03</cite>, political activity is not limited to activities regulated by the District.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(B)</num>
        <para>
          <num>(i)</num>
          <text>The Board may, by rule, define certain basic activities as nonpolitical activities.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(ii)</num>
          <text>The term “nonpolitical activities” shall include:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(I)</num>
            <text>Media inquiries;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(II)</num>
            <text>Answering questionnaires; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(III)</num>
            <text>Scheduling.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(9)</num>
      <para>
        <num>(A)</num>
        <text>“Political contribution” means:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(i)</num>
          <text>A gift, subscription, loan, advance, or deposit of money, or anything of value, made for any political purpose;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(ii)</num>
          <text>A contract, promise, or agreement, express or implied, whether or not legally enforceable, to make a contribution for any political purpose;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(iii)</num>
          <text>A payment by any person, other than a candidate or a political party or affiliated organization, of compensation for the personal services of another person which are rendered to any candidate or political party or affiliated organization without charge for any political purpose; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(iv)</num>
          <text>The provision of personal services, paid or unpaid, for any political purpose.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(B)</num>
        <text>The term “political contribution” shall not include the value of services provided without compensation by any individual on behalf of any candidate, campaign, political party, or partisan political group.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(10)</num>
      <text>“Political party” means a national political party, a State political party, or an affiliated organization that is regulated by the District.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(11)</num>
      <text>“Political purpose” means an objective of promoting or opposing a political party, candidate for partisan political office, or partisan political group that is regulated by the District.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>History</heading>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 18-335">Mar. 31, 2011, D.C. Law 18-335, § 2, 58 DCR 599</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 20-80">Feb. 22, 2014, D.C. Law 20-80, § 2(a), 61 DCR 169</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Cross References</heading>
        <annotation>Hatch Act retention, § <cite path="§1-625.01">1-625.01</cite>.</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Effect of Amendments</heading>
        <annotation>The 2014 amendment by <cite doc="D.C. Law 20-80">D.C. Law 20-80</cite> rewrote this section.</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Temporary Legislation</heading>
        <annotation>For temporary (225 days) amendment of this section, see § 2(a) of the Prohibition on Government Employee Engagement in Political Activity Temporary Amendment Act of 2013 (<cite doc="D.C. Law 20-4">D.C. Law 20-4</cite>, May 18, 2013,  60 DCR 4624, 20 DCSTAT 1268).</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Emergency Legislation</heading>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 days) amendment of this section, see § 2(a) of the Prohibition on Government Employee Engagement in Political Activity Emergency Amendment Act of 2013 (D.C. Act 20-25, March 7, 2013,  60 DCR 3986, 20 DCSTAT 485).</annotation>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 days) amendment of this section, see § 2(a) of the Prohibition on Government Employee Engagement in Political Activity Congressional Review Emergency Amendment Act of 2013 (D.C. Act 20-231, December 20, 2013,  61 DCR 3, 20 DCSTAT 2633).</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section from-code="true">
    <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" path="|1|11B"/>
    <num codify:value="1-1171.02">3</num>
    <heading>Political activity authorized; prohibitions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>(a)</num>
      <text>An employee may take an active part in political management or in political campaigns; provided, that an employee shall not:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Use his official authority or influence for the purpose of interfering with or affecting the result of an election;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Knowingly solicit, accept, or receive a political contribution from any person, except if the employee has filed as a candidate for political office;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>File as a candidate for election to a partisan political office; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Knowingly direct, or authorize anyone else to direct, that any subordinate employee participate in an election campaign or request a subordinate to make a political contribution.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(b)</num>
      <text>The Mayor and each member of the Council may designate one employee while on leave to perform any of the functions described in subsection (a)(2) of this section; provided, that:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The employee shall not perform the activities while the employee is on duty or in any room or building occupied in the discharge of official duties in the District government, including any agency or instrumentality thereof;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Any designation pursuant to this subsection shall be made in writing to the Secretary of the District of Columbia or the Secretary to the Council;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Any designated employee shall file a report within 15 days of being designated and as otherwise required pursuant to  § <cite path="§1-1162.24">1-1162.24</cite>; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The Mayor and the Council shall issue standards of conduct implementing this subsection.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(c)</num>
      <text>Repealed.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>History</heading>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 18-335">Mar. 31, 2011, D.C. Law 18-335, § 3, 58 DCR 599</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 20-80">Feb. 22, 2014, D.C. Law 20-80, § 2(b), 61 DCR 169</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Effect of Amendments</heading>
        <annotation>The 2014 amendment by <cite doc="D.C. Law 20-80">D.C. Law 20-80</cite>, substituted “§ <cite path="§1-1162.24">1-1162.24</cite>” for “§ <cite path="§1-1106.02">1-1106.02</cite>” in (b)(3); and repealed (c).</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Temporary Legislation</heading>
        <annotation>For temporary (225 days) amendment of this section, see § 2(b) of the Prohibition on Government Employee Engagement in Political Activity Temporary Amendment Act of 2013 (<cite doc="D.C. Law 20-4">D.C. Law 20-4</cite>, May 18, 2013,  60 DCR 4624, 20 DCSTAT 1268).</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Emergency Legislation</heading>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 days) amendment of this section, see § 2(b) of the Prohibition on Government Employee Engagement in Political Activity Emergency Amendment Act of 2013 (D.C. Act 20-25, March 7, 2013,  60 DCR 3986, 20 DCSTAT 485).</annotation>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 days) amendment of this section, see § 2(b) of the Prohibition on Government Employee Engagement in Political Activity Congressional Review Emergency Amendment Act of 2013 (D.C. Act 20-231, December 20, 2013,  61 DCR 3, 20 DCSTAT 2633).</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section from-code="true">
    <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" path="|1|11B"/>
    <num codify:value="1-1171.03">4</num>
    <heading>Political activities on duty; prohibition.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>(a)</num>
      <text>An employee shall not engage in political activity:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>While the employee is on duty;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>In any room or building occupied in the discharge of official duties in the District government, including any agency or instrumentality thereof;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>While wearing a uniform or official insignia identifying the office or position of the employee; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Using any vehicle owned or leased by the District of Columbia, including any agency or instrumentality thereof.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(b)</num>
      <text>An employee may not coerce, explicitly or implicitly, any subordinate employee to engage in political activity.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(c)</num>
      <text>For the purposes of this section, the term “political activity” is not limited to activities regulated by the District and includes soliciting, accepting, receiving, or making political contributions or other political activities.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>History</heading>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 18-335">Mar. 31, 2011, D.C. Law 18-335, § 4, 58 DCR 599</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 20-80">Feb. 22, 2014, D.C. Law 20-80, § 2(c), 61 DCR 169</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Section References</heading>
        <annotation>This section is referenced in § <cite path="§1-1171.01">1-1171.01</cite>.</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Effect of Amendments</heading>
        <annotation>The 2014 amendment by <cite doc="D.C. Law 20-80">D.C. Law 20-80</cite> designated the existing text as (a); and added (b) and (c).</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Temporary Legislation</heading>
        <annotation>For temporary (225 days) amendment of this section, see § 2(c) of the Prohibition on Government Employee Engagement in Political Activity Temporary Amendment Act of 2013 (<cite doc="D.C. Law 20-4">D.C. Law 20-4</cite>, May 18, 2013,  60 DCR 4624, 20 DCSTAT 1268).</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Emergency Legislation</heading>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 days) amendment of this section, see § 2(c) of the Prohibition on Government Employee Engagement in Political Activity Emergency Amendment Act of 2013 (D.C. Act 20-25, March 7, 2013,  60 DCR 3986, 20 DCSTAT 485).</annotation>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 days) amendment of this section, see § 2(c) of the Prohibition on Government Employee Engagement in Political Activity Congressional Review Emergency Amendment Act of 2013 (D.C. Act 20-231, December 20, 2013,  61 DCR 3, 20 DCSTAT 2633).</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section from-code="true">
    <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" path="|1|11B"/>
    <num codify:value="1-1171.04">5</num>
    <heading>Enforcement.</heading>
    <text>A violation of this chapter shall constitute a violation of the Code of Conduct as defined in § <cite path="§1-1161.01">1-1161.01</cite>(7), and shall be enforceable by the Board in accordance with Chapter 11A of this title [§ <cite path="§1-1161.01">1-1161.01</cite> et seq.].</text>
    <annotations>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>History</heading>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 18-335">Mar. 31, 2011, D.C. Law 18-335, § 5, 58 DCR 599</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 20-80">Feb. 22, 2014, D.C. Law 20-80, § 2(d), 61 DCR 169</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Effect of Amendments</heading>
        <annotation>The 2014 amendment by <cite doc="D.C. Law 20-80">D.C. Law 20-80</cite> rewrote this section.</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Temporary Legislation</heading>
        <annotation>For temporary (225 days) amendment of this section, see § 2(d) of the Prohibition on Government Employee Engagement in Political Activity Temporary Amendment Act of 2013 (<cite doc="D.C. Law 20-4">D.C. Law 20-4</cite>, May 18, 2013,  60 DCR 4624, 20 DCSTAT 1268).</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Emergency Legislation</heading>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 days) amendment of this section, see § 2(d) of the Prohibition on Government Employee Engagement in Political Activity Emergency Amendment Act of 2013 (D.C. Act 20-25, March 7, 2013,  60 DCR 3986, 20 DCSTAT 485).</annotation>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 days) amendment of this section, see § 2(d) of the Prohibition on Government Employee Engagement in Political Activity Congressional Review Emergency Amendment Act of 2013 (D.C. Act 20-231, December 20, 2013,  61 DCR 3, 20 DCSTAT 2633).</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section from-code="true">
    <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" path="|1|11B"/>
    <reason>Repealed</reason>
    <num codify:value="1-1171.05">6</num>
    <heading>Criminal penalties.</heading>
    <text>Repealed.</text>
    <annotations>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>History</heading>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 18-335">Mar. 31, 2011, D.C. Law 18-335, § 6, 58 DCR 599</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 20-80">Feb. 22, 2014, D.C. Law 20-80, § 2(e), 61 DCR 169</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Temporary Legislation</heading>
        <annotation>For temporary (225 days) repeal of this section, see § 2(e) of the Prohibition on Government Employee Engagement in Political Activity Temporary Amendment Act of 2013 (<cite doc="D.C. Law 20-4">D.C. Law 20-4</cite>, May 18, 2013,  60 DCR 4624, 20 DCSTAT 1268).</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Emergency Legislation</heading>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 days) repeal of this section, see § 2(e) of the Prohibition on Government Employee Engagement in Political Activity Emergency Amendment Act of 2013 (D.C. Act 20-25, March 7, 2013,  60 DCR 3986, 20 DCSTAT 485).</annotation>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 days) repeal of this section, see § 2(e) of the Prohibition on Government Employee Engagement in Political Activity Congressional Review Emergency Amendment Act of 2013 (D.C. Act 20-231, December 20, 2013,  61 DCR 3, 20 DCSTAT 2633).</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section from-code="true">
    <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" path="|1|11B"/>
    <num codify:value="1-1171.06">7</num>
    <heading>Rules.</heading>
    <text>The Board, pursuant to subchapter I of Chapter 5 of Title 2 [§ <cite path="§2-501">2-501</cite> et seq.], may issue rules to implement the provisions of this chapter.</text>
    <annotations>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>History</heading>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 18-335">Mar. 31, 2011, D.C. Law 18-335, § 7, 58 DCR 599</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 20-80">Feb. 22, 2014, D.C. Law 20-80, § 2(f), 61 DCR 169</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Effect of Amendments</heading>
        <annotation>The 2014 amendment by <cite doc="D.C. Law 20-80">D.C. Law 20-80</cite> substituted “Board” for “Board of Elections and Ethics”.</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Temporary Legislation</heading>
        <annotation>For temporary (225 days) amendment of this section, see § 2(f) of the Prohibition on Government Employee Engagement in Political Activity Temporary Amendment Act of 2013 (<cite doc="D.C. Law 20-4">D.C. Law 20-4</cite>, May 18, 2013,  60 DCR 4624, 20 DCSTAT 1268).</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Emergency Legislation</heading>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 days) amendment of this section, see § 2(f) of the Prohibition on Government Employee Engagement in Political Activity Emergency Amendment Act of 2013 (D.C. Act 20-25, March 7, 2013,  60 DCR 3986, 20 DCSTAT 485).</annotation>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 days) amendment of this section, see § 2(f) of the Prohibition on Government Employee Engagement in Political Activity Congressional Review Emergency Amendment Act of 2013 (D.C. Act 20-231, December 20, 2013,  61 DCR 3, 20 DCSTAT 2633).</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section from-code="true">
    <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" path="|1|11B"/>
    <reason>Omitted</reason>
    <num codify:value="1-1171.06a">7a</num>
    <heading>Conforming amendment.</heading>
    <text>Omitted.</text>
    <annotations>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>History</heading>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 18-335">Mar. 31, 2011, D.C. Law 18-335, § 7a</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 20-80">as added Feb. 22, 2014, D.C. Law 20-80, § 2(g), 61 DCR 169</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Temporary Legislation</heading>
        <annotation>For temporary (225 days) addition of <cite doc="D.C. Law 18-335">D.C. Law 18-335</cite>, § 7a, see § 2(g) of the Prohibition on Government Employee Engagement in Political Activity Temporary Amendment Act of 2013 (<cite doc="D.C. Law 20-4">D.C. Law 20-4</cite>, May 18, 2013,  60 DCR 4624, 20 DCSTAT 1268).</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Emergency Legislation</heading>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 days) addition of <cite doc="D.C. Law 18-335">D.C. Law 18-335</cite>, § 7a, amending subdivision (7) of this section, see § 2(g) of the Prohibition on Government Employee Engagement in Political Activity Emergency Amendment Act of 2013 (D.C. Act 20-25, March 7, 2013,  60 DCR 3986, 20 DCSTAT 485).</annotation>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 days) addition of <cite doc="D.C. Law 18-335">D.C. Law 18-335</cite>, § 7a, amending subdivision (7) of this section, see § 2(g) of the Prohibition on Government Employee Engagement in Political Activity Congressional Review Emergency Amendment Act of 2013 (D.C. Act 20-231, December 20, 2013,  61 DCR 3, 20 DCSTAT 2633).</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Editor's Notes</heading>
        <annotation><cite doc="D.C. Law 18-335">D.C. Law 18-335</cite>, § 7a, as added by <cite doc="D.C. Law 20-80">D.C. Law 20-80</cite>, § 2(g), is codified as § <cite path="§1-1161.01">1-1161.01</cite>(7)(E-i).</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section from-code="true">
    <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" path="|1|11B"/>
    <num codify:value="1-1171.07">8</num>
    <heading>Applicability.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>(a)</num>
      <text>This chapter shall apply as of January 29, 2013.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(b)</num>
      <text>For an offense committed between January 29, 2013, and March 7, 2013, this chapter shall not be construed to prohibit any conduct that was proscribed under the federal Hatch Act, 5 U.S.C. § 7321 et seq., or this chapter, or authorize any penalties that were not available before March 7, 2013.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>History</heading>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 18-335">Mar. 31, 2011, D.C. Law 18-335, § 8, 58 DCR 599</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 20-80">Feb. 22, 2014, D.C. Law 20-80, § 2(h), 61 DCR 169</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Cross References</heading>
        <annotation>Hatch Act retention, § <cite path="§1-625.01">1-625.01</cite>.</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Effect of Amendments</heading>
        <annotation>The 2014 amendment by <cite doc="D.C. Law 20-80">D.C. Law 20-80</cite> rewrote (a), which formerly read “This chapter shall apply upon enactment by the Congress of an act excluding the District of Columbia from the coverage of  5 U.S.C. §§ 7321 through  7326 (Hatch Act)”; and rewrote (b), which formerly read “This chapter shall apply upon inclusion of its fiscal effect in an approved budget and financial plan”.</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Temporary Legislation</heading>
        <annotation>For temporary (225 days) amendment of this section, see § 2(h) of the Prohibition on Government Employee Engagement in Political Activity Temporary Amendment Act of 2013 (<cite doc="D.C. Law 20-4">D.C. Law 20-4</cite>, May 18, 2013,  60 DCR 4624, 20 DCSTAT 1268).</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Emergency Legislation</heading>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 days) amendment of this section, see § 2(h) of the Prohibition on Government Employee Engagement in Political Activity Emergency Amendment Act of 2013 (D.C. Act 20-25, March 7, 2013,  60 DCR 3986, 20 DCSTAT 485).</annotation>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 days) amendment of this section, see § 2(h) of the Prohibition on Government Employee Engagement in Political Activity Congressional Review Emergency Amendment Act of 2013 (D.C. Act 20-231, December 20, 2013,  61 DCR 3, 20 DCSTAT 2633).</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Editor's Notes</heading>
        <text>Congress enacted and the President signed Public Law 112-230 on December 28, 2012, excluding the District of Columbia from the coverage of  5 U.S.C. §§ 7321 through  7326 (Hatch Act).</text>
        <text>Public Law 112-230 was approved December 28, 2012, satisfying the applicability requirement of subsection (a) of this section.</text>
        <text>The Budget Director of the Council of the District of Columbia has determined that the fiscal effect of <cite doc="D.C. Law 18-335">D.C. Law 18-335</cite> has been included in an approved budget and financial plan.</text>
      </annoGroup>
    </annotations>
  </section>
</document>
