<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<document xmlns:codify="http://code.dccouncil.us/schemas/codify" id="D.C. Law 1-85">
  <num type="law">1-85</num>
  <meta>
    <effective>1976-09-24</effective>
    <cites>
      <law lawId="85" period="1" url="./docs/1-85.pdf"/>
      <register page="2464" vol="23"/>
    </cites>
    <history>
      <narrative>Law 1-85, the ‘Firearms Control Regulations Act of 1975,’ was introduced in Council and assigned Bill No. 1-164, which was referred to the Committee on the Judiciary and the Committee on Criminal Law. The Bill was adopted on first, amended first, and second readings, and reconsideration of second reading, on May 3, 1976, May 18, 1976, June 15, 1976, and June 29, 1976, respectively. Signed by the Mayor on July 23, 1976, it was assigned Act No. 1-142 and transmitted to both Houses of Congress for review</narrative>
    </history>
  </meta>
  <container>
    <prefix>Title</prefix>
    <num>I</num>
    <section from-code="true">
      <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" path="|7|25|I"/>
      <num codify:value="7-2501.01">101</num>
      <heading>Definitions.</heading>
      <text>As used in this unit the term:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>“Acts of Congress” means:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(A)</num>
          <text>Chapter 45 of Title 22;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(B)</num>
          <text>Omnibus Crime Control and Safe Streets Act of 1968, as amended (title VII, Unlawful Possession or Receipt of Firearms (82 Stat. 1236; 18 U.S.C. Appendix)); and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(C)</num>
          <text>An Act to Amend Title 18, United States Code, To Provide for Better Control of the Interstate Traffic in Firearms Act of 1968 (82 Stat. 1213; 18 U.S.C. § 921 et seq.).</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>“Ammunition” means cartridge cases, shells, projectiles (including shot), primers, bullets (including restricted pistol bullets), propellant powder, or other devices or materials designed, redesigned, or intended for use in a firearm or destructive device.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>“Antique firearm” means:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(A)</num>
          <text>Any firearm (including any firearm with a matchlock, flintlock, percussion cap, or similar type of ignition system) manufactured in or before 1898; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(B)</num>
          <text>Any replica of any firearm described in subparagraph (A) if such replica:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Is not designed or redesigned for using rim-fire or conventional center-fire fixed ammunition; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Uses rim-fire or conventional ammunition which is no longer manufactured in the United States and which is not readily available in the ordinary channels of commercial trade.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3A)</num>
        <para>
          <num>(A)</num>
          <text>“Assault weapon” means:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>The following semiautomatic firearms:</text>
            <para>
              <num>(I)</num>
              <text>All of the following specified rifles:</text>
              <para>
                <num>(aa)</num>
                <text>All AK series including, but not limited to, the models identified as follows:</text>
                <para>
                  <num>(1)</num>
                  <text>Made in China AK, AKM, AKS, AK47, AK47S, 56, 56S, 84S, and 86S;</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(2)</num>
                  <text>Norinco (all models);</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(3)</num>
                  <text>Poly Technologies (all models);</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(4)</num>
                  <text>MAADI AK47 and ARM; and</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(5)</num>
                  <text>Mitchell (all models).</text>
                </para>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(bb)</num>
                <text>UZI and Galil;</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(cc)</num>
                <text>Beretta AR-70;</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(dd)</num>
                <text>CETME Sporter;</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(ee)</num>
                <text>Colt AR-15 series;</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(ff)</num>
                <text>Daewoo K-1, K-2, Max 1, Max 2, AR 100, and AR110 C;</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(gg)</num>
                <text>Fabrique Nationale FAL, LAR, FNC, 308 Match, and Sporter;</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(hh)</num>
                <text>MAS 223.</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(ii)</num>
                <text>HK-91, HK-93, HK-94, and HK-PSG-1;</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(jj)</num>
                <text>The following MAC types:</text>
                <para>
                  <num>(1)</num>
                  <text>RPB Industries Inc. sM10 and sM11; and</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(2)</num>
                  <text>SWD Incorporated M11;</text>
                </para>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(kk)</num>
                <text>SKS with detachable magazine;</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(ll)</num>
                <text>SIG AMT, PE-57, SG 550, and SG 551;</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(mm)</num>
                <text>Springfield Armory BM59 and SAR-48;</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(nn)</num>
                <text>Sterling MK-6;</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(oo)</num>
                <text>Steyer AUG, Steyr AUG;</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(pp)</num>
                <text>Valmet M62S, M71S, and M78S;</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(qq)</num>
                <text>Armalite AR-180;</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(rr)</num>
                <text>Bushmaster Assault Rifle;</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(ss)</num>
                <text>Calico —900;</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(tt)</num>
                <text>J&amp;R ENG —68; and</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(uu)</num>
                <text>Weaver Arms Nighthawk.</text>
              </para>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(II)</num>
              <text>All of the following specified pistols:</text>
              <para>
                <num>(aa)</num>
                <text>UZI;</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(bb)</num>
                <text>Encom MP-9 and MP-45;</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(cc)</num>
                <text>The following MAC types:</text>
                <para>
                  <num>(1)</num>
                  <text>RPB Industries Inc. sM10 and sM11;</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(2)</num>
                  <text>SWD Incorporated -11;</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(3)</num>
                  <text>Advance Armament Inc. —11; and</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(4)</num>
                  <text>Military Armament Corp. Ingram M-11;</text>
                </para>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(dd)</num>
                <text>Intratec TEC-9 and TEC-DC9;</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(ee)</num>
                <text>Sites Spectre;</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(ff)</num>
                <text>Sterling MK-7;</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(gg)</num>
                <text>Calico M-950; and</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(hh)</num>
                <text>Bushmaster Pistol.</text>
              </para>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(III)</num>
              <text>All of the following specified shotguns:</text>
              <para>
                <num>(aa)</num>
                <text>Franchi SPAS 12 and LAW 12; and</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(bb)</num>
                <text>Striker 12. The Streetsweeper type S/S Inc. SS/12;</text>
              </para>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(IV)</num>
              <text>A semiautomatic, rifle that has the capacity to accept a detachable magazine and any one of the following:</text>
              <para>
                <num>(aa)</num>
                <text>A pistol grip that protrudes conspicuously beneath the action of the weapon;</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(bb)</num>
                <text>A thumbhole stock;</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(cc)</num>
                <text>A folding or telescoping stock;</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(dd)</num>
                <text>A grenade launcher or flare launcher;</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(ee)</num>
                <text>A flash suppressor; or</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(ff)</num>
                <text>A forward pistol grip;</text>
              </para>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(V)</num>
              <text>A semiautomatic pistol that has the capacity to accept a detachable magazine and any one of the following:</text>
              <para>
                <num>(aa)</num>
                <text>A threaded barrel, capable of accepting a flash suppressor, forward handgrip, or silencer;</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(bb)</num>
                <text>A second handgrip;</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(cc)</num>
                <text>A shroud that is attached to, or partially or completely encircles, the barrel that allows the bearer to fire the weapon without burning his or her hand, except a slide that encloses the barrel; or</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(dd)</num>
                <text>The capacity to accept a detachable magazine at some location outside of the pistol grip;</text>
              </para>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(VI)</num>
              <text>A semiautomatic shotgun that has one or more of the following:</text>
              <para>
                <num>(aa)</num>
                <text>A folding or telescoping stock;</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(bb)</num>
                <text>A pistol grip that protrudes conspicuously beneath the action of the weapon;</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(cc)</num>
                <text>A thumbhole stock; or</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(dd)</num>
                <text>A vertical handgrip; and</text>
              </para>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(VII)</num>
              <text>A semiautomatic shotgun that has the ability to accept a detachable magazine; and</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(VIII)</num>
              <text>All other models within a series that are variations, with minor differences, of those models listed in subparagraph (A) of this paragraph, regardless of the manufacturer;</text>
            </para>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Any shotgun with a revolving cylinder; provided, that this sub-subparagraph shall not apply to a weapon with an attached tubular device designed to accept, and capable of operating only with, .22 caliber rimfire ammunition; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Any firearm that the Chief may designate as an assault weapon by rule, based on a determination that the firearm would reasonably pose the same or similar danger to the health, safety, and security of the residents of the District as those weapons enumerated in this paragraph.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(B)</num>
          <text>The term “assault weapon” shall not include:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Any antique firearm; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Any of the following pistols, which are designed expressly for use in Olympic target shooting events, sanctioned by the International Olympic Committee and by USA Shooting, the national governing body for international shooting competition in the United States, and used for Olympic target shooting purposes:</text>
          </para>
          <afterText>
            <table>
              <tr>
                <th>MANUFACTURER</th>
                <th>MODEL</th>
                <th>CALIBER</th>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td>BENELLI</td>
                <td>MP90</td>
                <td>.22LR</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td>BENELLI</td>
                <td>MP90</td>
                <td>.32 S&amp;W LONG</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td>BENELLI</td>
                <td>MP95</td>
                <td>.22LR</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td>BENELLI</td>
                <td>MP95</td>
                <td>.32 S&amp;W LONG</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td>HAMMERLI</td>
                <td>280</td>
                <td>.22LR</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td>HAMMERLI</td>
                <td>280</td>
                <td>.32 S&amp;W LONG</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td>HAMMERLI</td>
                <td>SP20</td>
                <td>.22LR</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td>HAMMERLI</td>
                <td>SP20</td>
                <td>.32 S&amp;W LONG</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td>PARDINI</td>
                <td>GPO</td>
                <td>.22 SHORT</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td>PARDINI</td>
                <td>GP-SCHUMANN</td>
                <td>.22 SHORT</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td>PARDINI</td>
                <td>HP</td>
                <td>.32 S&amp;W LONG</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td>PARDINI</td>
                <td>MP</td>
                <td>.32 S&amp;W LONG</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td>PARDINI</td>
                <td>SP</td>
                <td>.22LR</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td>PARDINI</td>
                <td>SPE</td>
                <td>.22LR</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td>WALTHER</td>
                <td>GSP</td>
                <td>.22LR</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td>WALTHER</td>
                <td>GSP</td>
                <td>.32 S&amp;W LONG</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td>WALTHER</td>
                <td>OSP</td>
                <td>.22 SHORT</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td>WALTHER</td>
                <td>OSP-2000</td>
                <td>.22 SHORT</td>
              </tr>
            </table>
          </afterText>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(C)</num>
          <text>The Chief may exempt, by rule, new models of competitive pistols that would otherwise fall within the definition of “assault weapon” pursuant to this section from being classified as an assault weapon. The exemption of competitive pistols shall be based either on recommendations by USA Shooting consistent with the regulations contained in the USA Shooting Official Rules or on the recommendation or rules of any other organization that the Chief considers relevant.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>“Chief” means the Chief of Police of the Metropolitan Police Department of the District of Columbia or his designated agent.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>“Crime of violence” shall have the same meaning as provided in D.C. Official Code § <cite path="§23-1331">23-1331</cite>(4).</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>“Dealer’s license” means a license to buy or sell, repair, trade, or otherwise deal in firearms, destructive devices, or ammunition as provided for in subchapter IV of this unit.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>“Destructive device” means:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(A)</num>
          <text>An explosive, incendiary, or poison gas bomb, grenade, rocket, missile, mine, or similar device;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(B)</num>
          <text>Any device by whatever name known which will, or is designed or redesigned, or may be readily converted or restored to expel a projectile by the action of an explosive or other propellant through a smooth bore barrel, except a shotgun;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(C)</num>
          <text>Any device containing tear gas or a chemically similar lacrimator or sternutator by whatever name known;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(D)</num>
          <text>Any device designed or redesigned, made or remade, or readily converted or restored, and intended to stun or disable a person by means of electric shock;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(E)</num>
          <text>Any combination of parts designed or intended for use in converting any device into any destructive device; or from which a destructive device may be readily assembled; provided, that the term shall not include:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Any pneumatic, spring, or B-B gun which expels a single projectile not exceeding .18 inch in diameter;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Any device which is neither designed nor redesigned for use as a weapon;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Any device originally a weapon which has been redesigned for use as a signaling, line throwing, or safety device; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iv)</num>
            <text>Any device which the Chief finds is not likely to be used as a weapon.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>“District” means District of Columbia.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8A)</num>
        <text>“.50 BMG rifle” means:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(A)</num>
          <text>A rifle capable of firing a center-fire cartridge in .50 BMG caliber, including a 12.7 mm equivalent of .50 BMG and any other metric equivalent; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(B)</num>
          <text>A copy or duplicate of any rifle described in subparagraph (A) of this paragraph, or any other rifle developed and manufactured after January 6, 2009, regardless of caliber, if such rifle is capable of firing a projectile that attains a muzzle energy of 12,000 foot-pounds or greater in any combination of bullet, propellant, case, or primer.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>“Firearm” means any weapon, regardless of operability, which will, or is designed or redesigned, made or remade, readily converted, restored, or repaired, or is intended to, expel a projectile or projectiles by the action of an explosive; the frame or receiver of any such device; or any firearm muffler or silencer; provided, that such term shall not include:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(A)</num>
          <text>Antique firearms; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(B)</num>
          <text>Destructive devices;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(C)</num>
          <text>Any device used exclusively for line throwing, signaling, or safety, and required or recommended by the Coast Guard or Interstate Commerce Commission; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(D)</num>
          <text>Any device used exclusively for firing explosive rivets, stud cartridges, or similar industrial ammunition and incapable for use as a weapon.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9A)</num>
        <text>“Firearms instructor” means an individual who is certified by the Chief to be qualified to teach firearms training and safety courses.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9B)</num>
        <text>“Intrafamily offense” shall have the same meaning as provided in § <cite path="§16-1001">16-1001</cite>(8).</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(10)</num>
        <text>“Machine gun” means any firearm which shoots, is designed to shoot, or can be readily restored to shoot, automatically more than one shot, without manual reloading, by a single function of the trigger. The term “machine gun” shall also include the frame or receiver of any such firearm, any part designed and intended solely and exclusively, or combination of parts designed and intended, for use in converting a firearm into a machine gun, and any combination of parts from which a machine gun can be assembled if such parts are in the possession or under the control of a person.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(11)</num>
        <text>“Organization” means any partnership, company, corporation, or other business entity, or any group or association of 2 or more persons united for a common purpose.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(12)</num>
        <text>“Pistol” means any firearm originally designed to be fired by use of a single hand or with a barrel less than 12 inches in length.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(12A)</num>
        <text>“Place of business” means a business that is located in an immovable structure at a fixed location and that is operated and owned entirely, or in substantial part, by the firearm registrant.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(13)</num>
        <text>“Registration certificate” means a certificate validly issued pursuant to this unit evincing the registration of a firearm pursuant to this unit.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(13A)</num>
        <para>
          <num>(A)</num>
          <text>“Restricted pistol bullet” means:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>A projectile or projectile core which may be used in a pistol and which is constructed entirely (excluding the presence of traces of other substances) from one or a combination of tungsten alloys, steel, iron, brass, bronze, beryllium copper, or depleted uranium;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>A full jacketed projectile larger than .22 caliber designed and intended for use in a pistol and whose jacket has a weight of more than 25% of the total weight of the projectile; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>Ammunition for a .50 BMG rifle.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(B)</num>
          <text>The term “restricted pistol bullet” does not include:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Shotgun shot required by federal or state environmental or game regulations for hunting purposes;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>A frangible projectile designed for target shooting;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>A projectile which the Attorney General of the United States finds is primarily intended to be used for sporting purposes; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iv)</num>
            <text>Any other projectile or projectile core which the Attorney General of the United States finds is intended to be used for industrial purposes, including a charge used in an oil and gas well perforating device.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(14)</num>
        <text>“Rifle” means a grooved bore firearm using a fixed metallic cartridge with a single projectile and designed or redesigned, made or remade, and intended to be fired from the shoulder.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(15)</num>
        <text>“Sawed-off shotgun” means a shotgun having a barrel of less than 18 inches in length; or a firearm made from a shotgun if such firearm as modified has an overall length of less than 26 inches or any barrel of less than 18 inches in length.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(16)</num>
        <text>“Shotgun” means a smooth bore firearm using a fixed shotgun shell with either a number of ball shot or a single projectile, and designed or redesigned, made or remade, and intended to be fired from the shoulder.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(17)</num>
        <text>“Short barreled rifle” means a rifle having any barrel less than 16 inches in length, or a firearm made from a rifle if such firearm as modified has an overall length of less than 26 inches or any barrel of less than 16 inches.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(18)</num>
        <text>“Weapons offense” means any violation in any jurisdiction of any law which involves the sale, purchase, transfer in any manner, receipt, acquisition, possession, having under control, use, repair, manufacture, carrying, or transportation of any firearm, ammunition, or destructive device.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annoGroup>
          <heading>History</heading>
          <annotation doc="D.C. Law 1-85">Sept. 24, 1976, D.C. Law 1-85, title I, § 101, 23 DCR 2464</annotation>
          <annotation doc="D.C. Law 2-62">Mar. 16, 1978, D.C. Law 2-62, § 2, 24 DCR 5780</annotation>
          <annotation doc="D.C. Law 5-19">Aug. 2, 1983, D.C. Law 5-19, § 2, 30 DCR 3328</annotation>
          <annotation doc="D.C. Law 17-372">Mar. 31, 2009, D.C. Law 17-372, § 3(a), 56 DCR 1365</annotation>
          <annotation doc="D.C. Law 19-170">Sept. 29, 2012, D.C. Law 19-170, § 2(a), 59 DCR 5691</annotation>
          <annotation doc="D.C. Law 19-295">Apr. 27, 2013, D.C. Law 19-295, § 2(a), 60 DCR 2623</annotation>
        </annoGroup>
        <annoGroup>
          <heading>Section References</heading>
          <annotation>This section is referenced in § <cite path="§7-2502.13">7-2502.13</cite>, § <cite path="§7-2507.06a">7-2507.06a</cite>, § <cite path="§7-2531.01">7-2531.01</cite>, § <cite path="§7-2551.01">7-2551.01</cite>, § <cite path="§16-2301">16-2301</cite>, § <cite path="§16-2333">16-2333</cite>, § <cite path="§22-4501">22-4501</cite>, § <cite path="§42-3101">42-3101</cite>, and § <cite path="§48-1203">48-1203</cite>.</annotation>
        </annoGroup>
        <annoGroup>
          <heading>Prior Codifications</heading>
          <annotation>1981 Ed., § 6-2302.</annotation>
          <annotation>1973 Ed., § 6-1802.</annotation>
        </annoGroup>
        <annoGroup>
          <heading>Effect of Amendments</heading>
          <annotation><cite doc="D.C. Law 17-372">D.C. Law 17-372</cite> added pars. (3A), (8A), (9A), and (12A); in par. (9), substituted “any weapon, regardless of operability, which will, or is designed or redesigned, made or remade, readily converted, restored, or repaired, or is intended to,” for “any weapon which will, or is designed or redesigned, made or remade, readily converted or restored, and intended to,”; rewrote par. (10); in par. (12), substituted “hand or with a barrel less than 12 inches in length” for “hand”; and, in par. (15), substituted “18 inches in length” for “20 inches in length” in two places. Prior to amendment, par. (10) read as follows: “(10) ‘Machine gun’ means any firearm which shoots, is designed to shoot, or can be readily converted or restored to shoot: (A) Automatically, more than 1 shot by a single function of the trigger; (B) Semiautomatically, more than 12 shots without manual reloading.”</annotation>
          <annotation>The 2012 amendment by <cite doc="D.C. Law 19-170">D.C. Law 19-170</cite> rewrote (5); added (9A); redesignated former (9A) and (13a) as (9B) and (13A); and made a stylistic change.</annotation>
          <annotation>The 2013 amendment by <cite doc="D.C. Law 19-295">D.C. Law 19-295</cite> rewrote (13A).</annotation>
        </annoGroup>
        <annoGroup>
          <heading>Emergency Legislation</heading>
          <annotation>For temporary (90 day) amendment of section, see § 2(a) of Second Firearms Control Emergency Amendment Act of 2008 (D.C. Act 17-502, September 16, 2008,  55 DCR 9904).</annotation>
          <annotation>For temporary (90 day) amendment of section, see § 2(a) of Second Firearms Control Congressional Review Emergency Amendment Act of 2008 (D.C. Act 17-601, December 12, 2008,  56 DCR 9).</annotation>
          <annotation>For temporary (90 day) amendment of section, see § 3(a) of Firearms Registration Emergency Amendment Act of 2008 (D.C. Act 17-651, January 6, 2009,  56 DCR 911).</annotation>
          <annotation>For temporary (90 day) amendment of section, see § 2(a) of Firearms Emergency Amendment Act of 2012 (D.C. Act 19-352, May 11, 2012,  59 DCR 5116).</annotation>
          <annotation>For temporary (90 day) amendment of section, see § 2(a) of the Firearms Amendments Congressional Review Emergency Amendment Act of 2012 (D.C. Act 19-394, July 18, 2012,  59 DCR 8694).</annotation>
          <annotation>For temporary amendment of (5), (9A) and (13a), see § 2(a) of the Firearms Second Congressional Review Emergency Amendment Act of 2012 (D.C. Act 19-510, October 26, 2012,  59 DCR 12808).</annotation>
        </annoGroup>
        <annoGroup>
          <heading>References in Text</heading>
          <annotation>“An Act to Amend Title 18, United States Code, to Provide for Better Control of the Interstate Traffic in Firearms Act of 1968,” referred to in subparagraph (C) of paragraph (1), is the Gun Control Act of 1968, Pub. L. 90-618.</annotation>
        </annoGroup>
      </annotations>
    </section>
  </container>
  <container>
    <prefix>Title</prefix>
    <num>II</num>
    <section from-code="true">
      <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" path="|7|25|II"/>
      <num codify:value="7-2502.01">201</num>
      <heading>Registration requirements.</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>Except as otherwise provided in this unit, no person or organization in the District of Columbia (“District”) shall receive, possess, control, transfer, offer for sale, sell, give, or deliver any destructive device, and no person or organization in the District shall possess or control any firearm, unless the person or organization holds a valid registration certificate for the firearm. A registration certificate may be issued:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>To an organization if:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(A)</num>
            <text>The organization employs at least 1 commissioned special police officer or employee licensed to carry a firearm whom the organization arms during the employee’s duty hours; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(B)</num>
            <text>The registration is issued in the name of the organization and in the name of the president or chief executive officer of the organization;</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>In the discretion of the Chief of Police, to a police officer who has retired from the Metropolitan Police Department;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(3)</num>
          <text>In the discretion of the Chief of Police, to the Fire Marshal and any member of the Fire and Arson Investigation Unit of the Fire Prevention Bureau of the Fire Department of the District of Columbia, who is designated in writing by the Fire Chief, for the purpose of enforcing the arson and fire safety laws of the District of Columbia;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(4)</num>
          <text>To a firearms instructor, or to an organization that employs a firearms instructor, for the purpose of conducting firearms training; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(5)</num>
          <text>To a person who complies with, and meets the requirements of, this unit.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>Subsection (a) of this section shall not apply to:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>Any law enforcement officer or agent of the District or the United States, or any law enforcement officer or agent of the government of any state or subdivision thereof, or any member of the armed forces of the United States, the National Guard or organized reserves, when such officer, agent, or member is authorized to possess such a firearm or device while on duty in the performance of official authorized functions;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>Any person holding a dealer’s license; provided, that the firearm or destructive device is:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(A)</num>
            <text>Acquired by such person in the normal conduct of business;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(B)</num>
            <text>Kept at the place described in the dealer’s license; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(C)</num>
            <text>Not kept for such person’s private use or protection, or for the protection of his business;</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(3)</num>
          <text>With respect to firearms, any nonresident of the District participating in any lawful recreational firearm-related activity in the District, or on his way to or from such activity in another jurisdiction; provided, that such person, whenever in possession of a firearm, shall upon demand of any member of the Metropolitan Police Department, or other bona fide law enforcement officer, exhibit proof that he is on his way to or from such activity, and that his possession or control of such firearm is lawful in the jurisdiction in which he resides; provided further, that such weapon shall be transported in accordance with § <cite path="§22-4504.02">22-4504.02</cite>;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(4)</num>
          <text>Any person who temporarily possesses a firearm registered to another person while in the home or place of business of the registrant; provided, that the person is not otherwise prohibited from possessing firearms and the person reasonably believes that possession of the firearm is necessary to prevent imminent death or great bodily harm to himself or herself; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(5)</num>
          <text>Any person who temporarily possesses a firearm while participating in a firearms training and safety class conducted by a firearms instructor.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(c)</num>
        <text>For the purposes of subsection (b)(3) of this section, the term “recreational firearm-related activity” includes a firearms training and safety class.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annoGroup>
          <heading>History</heading>
          <annotation doc="D.C. Law 1-85">Sept. 24, 1976, D.C. Law 1-85, title II, § 201, 23 DCR 2464</annotation>
          <annotation doc="D.C. Law 9-266">May 7, 1993, D.C. Law 9-266, § 2(a), 39 DCR 5676</annotation>
          <annotation doc="D.C. Law 12-176">Mar. 26, 1999, D.C. Law 12-176,§ 5, 45 DCR 5662</annotation>
          <annotation doc="D.C. Law 12-264">Apr. 20, 1999, D.C. Law 12-264, § 19, 46 DCR 2118</annotation>
          <annotation doc="D.C. Law 17-372">Mar. 31, 2009, D.C. Law 17-372, § 3(b), 56 DCR 1365</annotation>
          <annotation doc="D.C. Law 19-170">Sept. 29, 2012, D.C. Law 19-170, § 2(b), 59 DCR 5691</annotation>
          <annotation doc="D.C. Law 20-279">June 16, 2015, D.C. Law 20-279, § 2(a), 62 DCR 1944</annotation>
        </annoGroup>
        <annoGroup>
          <heading>Section References</heading>
          <annotation>This section is referenced in § <cite path="§7-2504.01">7-2504.01</cite>, § <cite path="§7-2507.06">7-2507.06</cite>, and § <cite path="§7-2508.01">7-2508.01</cite>.</annotation>
        </annoGroup>
        <annoGroup>
          <heading>Prior Codifications</heading>
          <annotation>1981 Ed., § 6-2311.</annotation>
          <annotation>1973 Ed., § 6-1811.</annotation>
        </annoGroup>
        <annoGroup>
          <heading>Effect of Amendments</heading>
          <annotation><cite doc="D.C. Law 17-372">D.C. Law 17-372</cite>, in subsec. (b)(3), substituted “that such weapon shall be transported in accordance with § <cite path="§22-4504.02">22-4504.02</cite>; or” for “that such weapon shall be unloaded, securely wrapped, and carried in open view”; and added subsec. (b)(4).</annotation>
          <annotation>The 2012 amendment by <cite doc="D.C. Law 19-170">D.C. Law 19-170</cite> added (a)(4), (a)(5), (b)(5), and (c); and made related changes.</annotation>
          <annotation>The 2015 amendment by <cite doc="D.C. Law 20-279">D.C. Law 20-279</cite> added “or place of business” in (b)(4).</annotation>
        </annoGroup>
        <annoGroup>
          <heading>Temporary Legislation</heading>
          <annotation>For temporary (225 days) amendment of this section, see § 2(a) of the License to Carry a Pistol Temporary Amendment Act of 2014 (<cite doc="D.C. Law 20-169">D.C. Law 20-169</cite>, May 5, 2015, 61 DCR 11814).</annotation>
        </annoGroup>
        <annoGroup>
          <heading>Emergency Legislation</heading>
          <annotation>For temporary authorization for seizure and forfeiture of firearms under certain circumstances, see § 2(b) of the Zero Tolerance for Guns Emergency Amendment Act of 1996 (D.C. Act 11-390, August 26, 1996,  43 DCR 4986).</annotation>
          <annotation>For temporary amendment of section, see § 5 of the Arson Investigators Emergency Amendment Act of 1998 (D.C. Act 12-406, July 13, 1998,  45 DCR 4833),§ 5 of the Arson Investigators Congressional Review Emergency Amendment Act of 1998 (D.C. Act 12-466, October 28, 1998,  45 DCR 7838), and § 5 of the Arson Investigators Second Congressional Review Emergency Amendment Act of 1998 (D.C. Act 12-539, December 24, 1998,  45 DCR 297).</annotation>
          <annotation>For temporary (90 day) amendment of section, see § 3(b) of Firearms Registration Emergency Amendment Act of 2008 (D.C. Act 17-651, January 6, 2009,  56 DCR 911).</annotation>
          <annotation>For temporary (90 day) amendment of section, see § 2(b) of Firearms Emergency Amendment Act of 2012 (D.C. Act 19-352, May 11, 2012,  59 DCR 5116).</annotation>
          <annotation>For temporary (90 day) amendment of section, see § 2(b) of the Firearms Amendments Congressional Review Emergency Amendment Act of 2012 (D.C. Act 19-394, July 18, 2012,  59 DCR 8694).</annotation>
          <annotation>For temporary amendment of (a) and (b), and addition of (c), see § 2(b) of the Firearms Second Congressional Review Emergency Amendment Act of 2012 (D.C. Act 19-510, October 26, 2012,  59 DCR 12808).</annotation>
          <annotation>For temporary (90 days) amendment of this section, see § 2(a) of the License to Carry a Pistol Emergency Amendment Act of 2014 (D.C. Act 20-447, Oct. 7, 2014, 61 DCR 10765, 20 STAT 4175).</annotation>
          <annotation>For temporary (90 days) repeal of emergency D.C. Act 20-447, § 4, the act’s applicability clause, see § 2 of the License to Carry a Pistol Clarification Emergency Amendment Act of 2014 (D.C. Act 20-448, Oct. 7, 2014,  61 DCR 10777, 20 STAT 4187).</annotation>
          <annotation>For temporary (90 days) amendment of this section, see § 2(a) of the License to Carry a Pistol Second Emergency Amendment Act of 2014 (D.C. Act 20-564, Jan. 6, 2015, 62 DCR 866, 21 STAT 527).</annotation>
          <annotation>For temporary (90 days) repeal of emergency D.C. Act 20-447, see § 4(b) of the License to Carry a Pistol Second Emergency Amendment Act of 2014 (D.C. Act 20-564, Jan. 6, 2015,  62 DCR 866, 21 STAT 527).</annotation>
          <annotation>For temporary (90 days) repeal of temporary D.C. Act 20-169, see § 4(c) of the License to Carry a Pistol Second Emergency Amendment Act of 2014 (D.C. Act 20-564, Jan. 6, 2015,  62 DCR 866, 21 STAT 527).</annotation>
          <annotation>For temporary (90 days) amendment of this section, see § 2(a) of the License to Carry a Pistol Congressional Review Emergency Amendment Act of 2015 (D.C. Act 21-74, June 4, 2015,  62 DCR 8242, 21 DCSTAT 1451).</annotation>
        </annoGroup>
        <annoGroup>
          <heading>Editor's Notes</heading>
          <text>Employees of United States Department of Agriculture authorized to carry firearms: Public Law 97-312 provided that any employee of the United States Department of Agriculture designated by the Secretary of Agriculture and the Attorney General of the United States may carry a firearm and use a firearm when necessary for self-protection, in accordance with rules and regulations issued by the Secretary of Agriculture and the Attorney General of the United States, while such employee is engaged in the performance of the employee’s official duties to (1) carry out any law or regulation related to the control, eradication, or prevention of the introduction or dissemination of communicable disease of livestock or poultry into the United States or (2) perform any duty related to such disease control, eradication, or prevention, subject to the direction of the Secretary.</text>
          <text>Seizure and forfeiture of conveyances used in firearms offenses: Section 2(b) of <cite doc="D.C. Law 11-273">D.C. Law 11-273</cite> provided for the forfeiture and seizure of any conveyance, including vehicles and vessels in which any person or persons transport, possess, or conceal any firearm as defined in § <cite path="§7-2501.01">7-2501.01</cite>, or in any manner use to facilitate a violation of §§ <cite path="§22-4503">22-4503</cite> and <cite path="§22-4504">22-4504</cite>. <cite doc="D.C. Law 11-273">D.C. Law 11-273</cite> became effective on June 3, 1997.</text>
        </annoGroup>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section from-code="true">
      <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" path="|7|25|II"/>
      <num codify:value="7-2502.02">202</num>
      <heading>Registration of certain firearms prohibited.</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>A registration certificate shall not be issued for a:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>Sawed-off shotgun;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>Machine gun;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(3)</num>
          <text>Short-barreled rifle;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(4)</num>
          <text>Pistol not validly registered to the current registrant in the District prior to September 24, 1976, except that the prohibition on registering a pistol shall not apply to:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(A)</num>
            <text>Any organization that employs at least one commissioned special police officer or other employee licensed to carry a firearm and that arms the employee with a firearm during the employee’s duty hours;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(B)</num>
            <text>A police officer who has retired from the Metropolitan Police Department;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(C)</num>
            <text>Any person who seeks to register a pistol:</text>
            <para>
              <num>(i)</num>
              <text>For use in self-defense within that person’s home or place of business; or</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(ii)</num>
              <text>As part of the application process for a license to carry a concealed pistol pursuant to § <cite path="§7-2509.02">7-2509.02</cite>; or</text>
            </para>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(D)</num>
            <text>A firearms instructor, or an organization that employs a firearms instructor, for the purpose of conducting firearms training.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(5)</num>
          <text>An unsafe firearm prohibited under § <cite path="§7-2505.04">7-2505.04</cite>;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(6)</num>
          <text>An assault weapon; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(7)</num>
          <text>A .50 BMG rifle.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>Repealed.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annoGroup>
          <heading>History</heading>
          <annotation doc="D.C. Law 1-85">Sept. 24, 1976, D.C. Law 1-85, title II, § 202, 23 DCR 2464</annotation>
          <annotation doc="D.C. Law 2-62">Mar. 16, 1978, D.C. Law 2-62, § 2, 24 DCR 5780</annotation>
          <annotation doc="D.C. Law 9-266">May 7, 1993, D.C. Law 9-266, § 2(b), 39 DCR 5676</annotation>
          <annotation doc="D.C. Law 17-372">Mar. 31, 2009, D.C. Law 17-372, § 3(c), 56 DCR 1365</annotation>
          <annotation doc="D.C. Law 19-170">Sept. 29, 2012, D.C. Law 19-170, § 2(c), 59 DCR 5691</annotation>
          <annotation doc="D.C. Law 20-279">June 16, 2015, D.C. Law 20-279, § 2(b), 62 DCR 1944</annotation>
        </annoGroup>
        <annoGroup>
          <heading>Section References</heading>
          <annotation>This section is referenced in § <cite path="§7-2502.09">7-2502.09</cite>, § <cite path="§7-2504.01">7-2504.01</cite>, § <cite path="§7-2505.02">7-2505.02</cite>, and § <cite path="§7-2507.06a">7-2507.06a</cite>.</annotation>
        </annoGroup>
        <annoGroup>
          <heading>Prior Codifications</heading>
          <annotation>1981 Ed., § 6-2312.</annotation>
          <annotation>1973 Ed., § 6-1812.</annotation>
        </annoGroup>
        <annoGroup>
          <heading>Effect of Amendments</heading>
          <annotation><cite doc="D.C. Law 17-372">D.C. Law 17-372</cite>, in subsec. (a), deleted “or” from the end of par. (3), rewrote par. (4), and added pars. (5), (6), and (7); and repealed subsec. (b).</annotation>
          <annotation>The 2012 amendment by <cite doc="D.C. Law 19-170">D.C. Law 19-170</cite> added (a)(4)(D); and made related changes.</annotation>
          <annotation>The 2015 amendment by <cite doc="D.C. Law 20-279">D.C. Law 20-279</cite> rewrote (a)(4)(C).</annotation>
        </annoGroup>
        <annoGroup>
          <heading>Temporary Legislation</heading>
          <annotation>For temporary (225 days) amendment of this section, see § 2(b) of the License to Carry a Pistol Temporary Amendment Act of 2014 (<cite doc="D.C. Law 20-169">D.C. Law 20-169</cite>, May 5, 2015, 61 DCR 11814).</annotation>
        </annoGroup>
        <annoGroup>
          <heading>Emergency Legislation</heading>
          <annotation>For temporary (90 day) amendment, see § 2(a) of Firearms Control Emergency Amendment Act of 2008 (D.C. Act 17-422, July 16, 2008,</annotation>
          <annotation>For temporary amendment of (a)(4), see § 2(c) of the Firearms Second Congressional Review Emergency Amendment Act of 2012 (D.C. Act 19-510, October 26, 2012,  59 DCR 12808).</annotation>
          <annotation>For temporary (90 day) amendment of section, see § 2(b) of Second Firearms Control Emergency Amendment Act of 2008 (D.C. Act 17-502, September 16, 2008,  55 DCR 9904).</annotation>
          <annotation>For temporary (90 day) repeal of D.C. Act 17-422, see § 5 of Second Firearms Control Emergency Amendment Act of 2008 (D.C. Act 17-502, September 16, 2008,  55 DCR 9904).</annotation>
          <annotation>For temporary (90 day) amendment of section, see §§ 2(b) and 4 of Second Firearms Control Congressional Review Emergency Amendment Act of 2008 (D.C. Act 17-601, December 12, 2008,  56 DCR 9).</annotation>
          <annotation>For temporary (90 day) amendment of section, see § 3(c) of Firearms Registration Emergency Amendment Act of 2008 (D.C. Act 17-651, January 6, 2009,  56 DCR 911).</annotation>
          <annotation>For temporary (90 day) amendment of section, see § 2(c) of Firearms Emergency Amendment Act of 2012 (D.C. Act 19-352, May 11, 2012,  59 DCR 5116).</annotation>
          <annotation>For temporary (90 day) amendment of section, see § 2(c) of the Firearms Amendments Congressional Review Emergency Amendment Act of 2012 (D.C. Act 19-394, July 18, 2012,  59 DCR 8694).</annotation>
          <annotation>For temporary (90 days) amendment of this section, see § 2(b) of the License to Carry a Pistol Emergency Amendment Act of 2014 (D.C. Act 20-447, Oct. 7, 2014,  61 DCR 10765, 20 STAT 4175).</annotation>
          <annotation>For temporary (90 days) repeal of emergency D.C. Act 20-447, § 4, the act’s applicability clause, see § 2 of the License to Carry a Pistol Clarification Emergency Amendment Act of 2014 (D.C. Act 20-448, Oct. 7, 2014,  61 DCR 10777, 20 STAT 4187).</annotation>
          <annotation>For temporary (90 days) amendment of this section, see § 2(b) of the License to Carry a Pistol Second Emergency Amendment Act of 2014 (D.C. Act 20-564, Jan. 6, 2015, 62 DCR 866, 21 STAT 527).</annotation>
          <annotation>For temporary  (90 days) repeal of emergency D.C. Act 20-447, see § 4(b) of  the  License to Carry a Pistol Second Emergency Amendment  Act of 2014 (D.C. Act 20-564, Jan. 6, 2015, 62 DCR 866, 21 STAT 527).</annotation>
          <annotation>For temporary (90 days) repeal of temporary D.C. Act 20-169, see § 4(c) of the License to Carry a Pistol Second Emergency Amendment Act of 2014 (D.C. Act 20-564, Jan. 6, 2015,  62 DCR 866, 21 STAT 527).</annotation>
          <annotation>For temporary (90 days) amendment of this section, see § 2(b) of the License to Carry a Pistol Congressional Review Emergency Amendment Act of 2015 (D.C. Act 21-74, June 4, 2015,  62 DCR 8242, 21 DCSTAT 1451).</annotation>
        </annoGroup>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section from-code="true">
      <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" path="|7|25|II"/>
      <num codify:value="7-2502.03">203</num>
      <heading>Qualifications for registration; information required for registration.</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>No registration certificate shall be issued to any person (and in the case of a person between the ages of 18 and 21, to the person and his signatory parent or guardian) or organization unless the Chief determines that such person (or the president or chief executive in the case of an organization):</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>Is 21 years of age or older; provided, that the Chief may issue to an applicant between the ages of 18 and 21 years old, and who is otherwise qualified, a registration certificate if the application is accompanied by a notarized statement of the applicant’s parent or guardian:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(A)</num>
            <text>That the applicant has the permission of his parent or guardian to own and use the firearm to be registered; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(B)</num>
            <text>The parent or guardian assumes civil liability for all damages resulting from the actions of such applicant in the use of the firearm to be registered; provided further, that such registration certificate shall expire on such person’s 21st birthday;</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>Has not been convicted of a weapons offense (but not an infraction or misdemeanor violation under § <cite path="§7-2502.08">7-2502.08</cite>, § <cite path="§7-2507.02">7-2507.02</cite>, § <cite path="§7-2507.06">7-2507.06</cite>, or § <cite path="§7-2508.07">7-2508.07</cite>) or a felony in this or any other jurisdiction (including a crime punishable by imprisonment for a term exceeding one year);</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(3)</num>
          <text>Is not under indictment for a crime of violence or a weapons offense;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(4)</num>
          <text>Has not been convicted within 5 years prior to the application of any:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(A)</num>
            <text>Violation in any jurisdiction of any law restricting the use, possession, or sale of any narcotic or dangerous drug;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(B)</num>
            <text>A violation of D.C. Official Code § <cite path="§22-404">22-404</cite>, regarding assaults and threats, or D.C. Official Code § <cite path="§22-407">22-407</cite>, regarding threats to do bodily harm, or a violation of any similar provision of the law of another jurisdiction;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(C)</num>
            <text>Two or more violations of D.C. Official Code § <cite path="§50-2201.05">50-2201.05</cite>(b), or, in this or any other jurisdiction, any law restricting driving under the influence of alcohol or drugs;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(D)</num>
            <text>Intrafamily offense punishable as a misdemeanor, including any similar provision in the law of another jurisdiction;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(E)</num>
            <text>Misdemeanor violation pursuant to § <cite path="§7-2507.02">7-2507.02</cite> or § <cite path="§7-2507.06">7-2507.06</cite>; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(F)</num>
            <text>Violation of § <cite path="§22-3133">22-3133</cite>;</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(5)</num>
          <text>Within the 5-year period immediately preceding the application, has not been acquitted of any criminal charge by reason of insanity or has not been adjudicated a chronic alcoholic by any court; provided, that this paragraph shall not apply if such person shall present to the Chief, with the application, a medical certification indicating that the applicant has recovered from such insanity or alcoholic condition and is capable of safe and responsible possession of a firearm;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(6)</num>
          <text>Within the 5 years immediately preceding the application, has not been voluntarily or involuntarily committed to any mental hospital or institution; provided, that this paragraph shall not apply, if such person shall present to the Chief, with the application, a medical certification that the applicant has recovered from whatever malady prompted such commitment;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(6A)</num>
          <text>Within the 5 years immediately preceding the application, has not had a history of violent behavior.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(7)</num>
          <text>Does not appear to suffer from a physical defect which would tend to indicate that the applicant would not be able to possess and use a firearm safely and responsibly;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(8)</num>
          <text>Has not been adjudicated negligent in a firearm mishap causing death or serious injury to another human being;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(9)</num>
          <text>Is not otherwise ineligible to possess a firearm under § <cite path="§22-4503">22-4503</cite>;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(10)</num>
          <text>Has not failed to demonstrate satisfactorily, in accordance with a test prescribed by the Chief, a knowledge of the laws of the District of Columbia pertaining to firearms and, in particular, the requirements of this unit, the responsibilities regarding storage, and the requirements for transport; provided, that once this determination is made with respect to a given applicant for a particular firearm, it need not be made again for the same applicant with respect to a subsequent application for a firearm or for the renewal of a registration certificate pursuant to § <cite path="§7-2502.07a">7-2502.07a</cite>;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(11)</num>
          <text>Is not blind, as defined in D.C. Official Code § <cite path="§7-1009">7-1009</cite>(1);</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(12)</num>
          <para>
            <num>(A)</num>
            <text>Has not been the respondent in an intrafamily proceeding in which a civil protection order was issued against the applicant pursuant to § <cite path="§16-1005">16-1005</cite>; provided, that an applicant who has been the subject of such an order shall be eligible for registration if the applicant has submitted to the Chief a certified court record establishing that the order has expired or has been rescinded for a period of 5 years or more; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(B)</num>
            <text>Has not been the respondent in a proceeding in which a foreign protection order, as that term is defined in § <cite path="§16-1041">16-1041</cite>, was issued against the applicant; provided, that an applicant who has been the subject of such an order shall be eligible for registration if the applicant has submitted to the Chief a certified court record establishing that the order has expired or has been rescinded for a period of 5 years;</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(13)</num>
          <para>
            <num>(A)</num>
            <text>Has completed a firearms training and safety class provided free of charge by the Chief; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(B)</num>
            <text>Has submitted evidence of any of the following:</text>
            <para>
              <num>(i)</num>
              <text>That the applicant has received firearms training in the United States military;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(ii)</num>
              <text>A license from another state for which firearms training is required, where the training, as determined by the Chief, is equal to or greater than that provided under subparagraph (A) of this paragraph; or</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(iii)</num>
              <text>That the applicant has otherwise completed a firearms training or safety course conducted by a firearms instructor that, as determined by the Chief, is equal to or greater than that conducted under subparagraph (A) of this paragraph; and</text>
            </para>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(14)</num>
          <text>Has not been prohibited from possessing or registering a firearm pursuant to § <cite path="§7-2502.08">7-2502.08</cite>.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>Every person applying for a registration certificate shall provide on a form prescribed by the Chief:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>The full name or any other name by which the applicant is known;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>The present address and each home address where the applicant has resided during the 5-year period immediately preceding the application;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(3)</num>
          <text>The present business or occupation of the applicant and the address and phone number of the employer;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(4)</num>
          <text>The date and place of birth of the applicant;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(5)</num>
          <text>The sex of the applicant;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(6)</num>
          <text>Whether (and if so, the reasons) the District, the United States or the government of any state or subdivision of any state has denied or revoked the applicant’s license, registration certificate, or permit pertaining to any firearm;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(7)</num>
          <text>A description of the applicant’s role in any mishap involving a firearm, including the date, place, time, circumstances, and the names of the persons injured or killed;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(8)</num>
          <text>Repealed.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(9)</num>
          <text>The caliber, make, model, manufacturer’s identification number, serial number, and any other identifying marks on the firearm;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(10)</num>
          <text>The name and address of the person or organization from whom the firearm was obtained, and in the case of a dealer, his dealer’s license number;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(11)</num>
          <text>Where the firearm will generally be kept;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(12)</num>
          <text>Whether the applicant has applied for other registration certificates issued and outstanding;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(13)</num>
          <text>Such other information as the Chief determines is necessary to carry out the provisions of this unit.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(c)</num>
        <text>Every organization applying for a registration certificate shall:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>With respect to the president or chief executive of such organization, comply with the requirements of subsection (b) of this section; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>Provide such other information as the Chief determines is necessary to carry out the provisions of this unit.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(d)</num>
        <text>Repealed.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(e)</num>
        <text>The Chief shall register no more than one pistol per registrant during any 30-day period; provided, that the Chief may permit a person first becoming a District resident to register more than one pistol if those pistols were lawfully owned in another jurisdiction for a period of 6 months prior to the date of the application.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annoGroup>
          <heading>History</heading>
          <annotation doc="D.C. Law 1-85">Sept. 24, 1976, D.C. Law 1-85, title II, § 203, 23 DCR 2464</annotation>
          <annotation doc="D.C. Law 2-62">Mar. 16, 1978, D.C. Law 2-62, § 2, 24 DCR 5780</annotation>
          <annotation doc="D.C. Law 17-372">Mar. 31, 2009, D.C. Law 17-372, § 3(d), 56 DCR 1365</annotation>
          <annotation doc="D.C. Law 18-377">June 3, 2011, D.C. Law 18-377, § 2(a), 58 DCR 1174</annotation>
          <annotation doc="D.C. Law 19-170">Sept. 29, 2012, D.C. Law 19-170, § 2(d), 59 DCR 5691</annotation>
          <annotation doc="D.C. Law 20-279">June 16, 2015, D.C. Law 20-279, § 2(c), 62 DCR 1944</annotation>
        </annoGroup>
        <annoGroup>
          <heading>Section References</heading>
          <annotation>This section is referenced in § <cite path="§7-2502.04">7-2502.04</cite>, § <cite path="§7-2502.05">7-2502.05</cite>, § <cite path="§7-2502.07a">7-2502.07a</cite>, § <cite path="§7-2502.09">7-2502.09</cite>, and § <cite path="§7-2504.02">7-2504.02</cite>.</annotation>
        </annoGroup>
        <annoGroup>
          <heading>Prior Codifications</heading>
          <annotation>1981 Ed., § 6-2313.</annotation>
          <annotation>1973 Ed., § 6-1813.</annotation>
        </annoGroup>
        <annoGroup>
          <heading>Effect of Amendments</heading>
          <annotation><cite doc="D.C. Law 17-372">D.C. Law 17-372</cite>, in subsec. (a)(4), deleted “or” from the end of par. (A) and added pars. (C) and (D); added subsec. (a)(6A); in subsec. (a)(10), substituted “and, in particular, the safe and responsible use, handling, and storage of the same in accordance with training, tests, and standards” for “and the safe and responsible use of the same in accordance with tests and standards” and deleted “and” from the end; in subsec. (a)(11), substituted a semicolon for a period; added subsecs. (a)(12), (13), and (14); and added subsecs. (d) and (e).</annotation>
          <annotation><cite doc="D.C. Law 18-377">D.C. Law 18-377</cite> rewrote subsec. (a)(4)(D); in subsec. (a)(9), substituted “firearm” for “pistol”; in subsec. (a)(14), substituted “§ <cite path="§7-2502.08">7-2502.08</cite>” for “§ <cite path="§7-2502.09">7-2502.09</cite>”; rewrote subsec. (b)(3); and repealed subsec. (b)(8).</annotation>
          <annotation>The 2012 amendment by <cite doc="D.C. Law 19-170">D.C. Law 19-170</cite> rewrote (a)(2); rewrote (a)(4)(B) through (a)(4)(D); added (a)(4)(E); rewrote (a)(10) and (a)(11); rewrote (a)(13)(A) and (a)(13)(B); and repealed (d), which formerly read: “The Chief shall require any registered pistol to be submitted for a ballistics identification procedure and shall establish a reasonable fee for the procedure.”</annotation>
          <annotation>The 2015 amendment by <cite doc="D.C. Law 20-279">D.C. Law 20-279</cite> added (a)(4)(F) and made related changes.</annotation>
        </annoGroup>
        <annoGroup>
          <heading>Emergency Legislation</heading>
          <annotation>For temporary (90 day) amendment, see § 2(b) of Firearms Control Emergency Amendment Act of 2008 (D.C. Act 17-422, July 16, 2008,  55 DCR 8237).</annotation>
          <annotation>For temporary (90 day) amendment of section, see § 2(c) of Second Firearms Control Emergency Amendment Act of 2008 (D.C. Act 17-502, September 16, 2008,  55 DCR 9904).</annotation>
          <annotation>For temporary (90 day) repeal of D.C. Act 17-422, see § 5 of Second Firearms Control Emergency Amendment Act of 2008 (D.C. Act 17-502, September 16, 2008,  55 DCR 9904).</annotation>
          <annotation>For temporary (90 day) amendment of section, see §§ 2(c) and 4 of Second Firearms Control Congressional Review Emergency Amendment Act of 2008 (D.C. Act 17-601, December 12, 2008,  56 DCR 9).</annotation>
          <annotation>For temporary (90 day) amendment of section, see § 3(d) of Firearms Registration Emergency Amendment Act of 2008 (D.C. Act 17-651, January 6, 2009,  56 DCR 911).</annotation>
          <annotation>For temporary (90 day) amendment of section, see § 502(a) of Public Safety Legislation Sixty-Day Layover Emergency Amendment Act of 2010 (D.C. Act 18-693, January 18, 2011,  58 DCR 640).</annotation>
          <annotation>For temporary (90 day) amendment of section, see § 502(a) of Public Safety Legislation Sixty-Day Layover Congressional Review Emergency Amendment Act of 2011 (D.C. Act 19-45, April 20, 2011,  58 DCR 3701).</annotation>
          <annotation>For temporary (90 day) amendment of section, see § 2(d) of Firearms Emergency Amendment Act of 2012 (D.C. Act 19-352, May 11, 2012,  59 DCR 5116).</annotation>
          <annotation>For temporary (90 day) amendment of section, see § 2(d) of the Firearms Amendments Congressional Review Emergency Amendment Act of 2012 (D.C. Act 19-394, July 18, 2012,  59 DCR 8694).</annotation>
          <annotation>For temporary amendment of (a) and repeal of (d), see § 2(d) of the Firearms Second Congressional Review Emergency Amendment Act of 2012 (D.C. Act 19-510, October 26, 2012,  59 DCR 12808).</annotation>
          <annotation>For temporary (90 days) amendment of this section, see § 2(c) of the License to Carry a Pistol Second Emergency Amendment Act of 2014 (D.C. Act 20-564, Jan. 6, 2015, 62 DCR 866, 21 STAT 527).</annotation>
          <annotation>For temporary (90 days) amendment of this section, see § 2(c) of the License to Carry a Pistol Congressional Review Emergency Amendment Act of 2015 (D.C. Act 21-74, June 4, 2015,  62 DCR 8242, 21 DCSTAT 1451).</annotation>
        </annoGroup>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section from-code="true">
      <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" path="|7|25|II"/>
      <num codify:value="7-2502.04">204</num>
      <heading>Fingerprints and photographs of applicants; application in person required.</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>The Chief shall require any person applying for a registration certificate to be fingerprinted in order to conduct an efficient and adequate investigation into the matters described in § <cite path="§7-2502.03">7-2502.03</cite> and to effectuate the purposes of this unit. The Chief shall maintain a record of the fingerprints of sufficient quality to enable periodic investigation to ensure compliance with § <cite path="§7-2502.03">7-2502.03</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>The Chief shall take a digitalized, full-face photograph of each applicant, other than an organization, to be included as part of a person’s firearms registration application. The photo shall be taken simultaneously with the filing of the application.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(c)</num>
        <text>Every applicant (or in the case of an organization, the president or chief executive, or a person authorized in writing by him), shall appear in person at a time and place prescribed by the Chief, and may be required to bring with him the firearm for which a registration certificate is sought, which shall be transported in accordance with § <cite path="§22-4504.02">22-4504.02</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annoGroup>
          <heading>History</heading>
          <annotation doc="D.C. Law 1-85">Sept. 24, 1976, D.C. Law 1-85, title II, § 204, 23 DCR 2464</annotation>
          <annotation doc="D.C. Law 2-62">Mar. 16, 1978, D.C. Law 2-62, § 2, 24 DCR 5780</annotation>
          <annotation doc="D.C. Law 17-372">Mar. 31, 2009, D.C. Law 17-372, § 3(e), 56 DCR 1365</annotation>
          <annotation doc="D.C. Law 19-170">Sept. 29, 2012, D.C. Law 19-170, § 2(e), 59 DCR 5691</annotation>
        </annoGroup>
        <annoGroup>
          <heading>Prior Codifications</heading>
          <annotation>1981 Ed., § 6-2314.</annotation>
          <annotation>1973 Ed., § 6-1814.</annotation>
        </annoGroup>
        <annoGroup>
          <heading>Effect of Amendments</heading>
          <annotation><cite doc="D.C. Law 17-372">D.C. Law 17-372</cite>, in subsec. (a), substituted “6 years” for “5 years”; and, in subsec. (c), substituted “shall be transported in accordance with § <cite path="§22-4504.02">22-4504.02</cite>” for “shall be unloaded and securely wrapped, and carried in open view”.</annotation>
          <annotation>The 2012 amendment by <cite doc="D.C. Law 19-170">D.C. Law 19-170</cite> rewrote (a) and (b).</annotation>
        </annoGroup>
        <annoGroup>
          <heading>Emergency Legislation</heading>
          <annotation>For temporary (90 day) amendment of section, see § 3(e) of Firearms Registration Emergency Amendment Act of 2008 (D.C. Act 17-651, January 6, 2009,  56 DCR 911).</annotation>
          <annotation>For temporary (90 day) amendment of section, see § 2(e) of Firearms Emergency Amendment Act of 2012 (D.C. Act 19-352, May 11, 2012,  59 DCR 5116).</annotation>
          <annotation>For temporary (90 day) amendment of section, see § 2(e) of the Firearms Amendments Congressional Review Emergency Amendment Act of 2012 (D.C. Act 19-394, July 18, 2012,  59 DCR 8694).</annotation>
          <annotation>For temporary amendment of (a) and (b), see § 2(e) of the Firearms Second Congressional Review Emergency Amendment Act of 2012 (D.C. Act 19-510, October 26, 2012,  59 DCR 12808).</annotation>
        </annoGroup>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section from-code="true">
      <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" path="|7|25|II"/>
      <num codify:value="7-2502.05">205</num>
      <heading>Application signed under oath; fees.</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>Each applicant (the president or chief executive in the case of an organization) shall sign an oath or affirmation attesting to the truth of all the information required by § <cite path="§7-2502.03">7-2502.03</cite> or § <cite path="§7-2502.07a">7-2502.07a</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>Each application required by this subchapter shall be accompanied by a nonrefundable fee to be established by the Mayor; provided, that such fee shall, in the judgment of the Mayor, reimburse the District for the cost of services provided under this subchapter.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(c)</num>
        <text>Any declaration, certificate, verification, or statement made for purposes of firearm registration under this title shall be made under penalty of perjury pursuant to D.C. Official Code § <cite path="§22-2402">22-2402</cite>. Except as required in § <cite path="§7-2502.03">7-2502.03</cite>(a)(1), no document shall be required to be notarized.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annoGroup>
          <heading>History</heading>
          <annotation doc="D.C. Law 1-85">Sept. 24, 1976, D.C. Law 1-85, title II, § 205, 23 DCR 2464</annotation>
          <annotation doc="D.C. Law 17-372">Mar. 31, 2009, D.C. Law 17-372, § 3(f), 56 DCR 1365</annotation>
          <annotation doc="D.C. Law 19-170">Sept. 29, 2012, D.C. Law 19-170, § 2(f), 59 DCR 5691</annotation>
        </annoGroup>
        <annoGroup>
          <heading>Section References</heading>
          <annotation>This section is referenced in § <cite path="§7-2507.06">7-2507.06</cite>.</annotation>
        </annoGroup>
        <annoGroup>
          <heading>Prior Codifications</heading>
          <annotation>1981 Ed., § 6-2315.</annotation>
          <annotation>1973 Ed., § 6-1815.</annotation>
        </annoGroup>
        <annoGroup>
          <heading>Effect of Amendments</heading>
          <annotation><cite doc="D.C. Law 17-372">D.C. Law 17-372</cite>, in subsec. (a), substituted “§§ <cite path="§7-2502.03">7-2502.03</cite> or § <cite path="§7-2502.07a">7-2502.07a</cite>” for “§ <cite path="§7-2502.03">7-2502.03</cite>”.</annotation>
          <annotation>The 2012 amendment by <cite doc="D.C. Law 19-170">D.C. Law 19-170</cite> added (c).</annotation>
        </annoGroup>
        <annoGroup>
          <heading>Emergency Legislation</heading>
          <annotation>For temporary (90 day) amendment of section, see § 3(f) of Firearms Registration Emergency Amendment Act of 2008 (D.C. Act 17-651, January 6, 2009,  56 DCR 911).</annotation>
          <annotation>For temporary (90 day) amendment of section, see § 2(f) of Firearms Emergency Amendment Act of 2012 (D.C. Act 19-352, May 11, 2012,  59 DCR 5116).</annotation>
          <annotation>For temporary (90 day) amendment of section, see § 2(f) of the Firearms Amendments Congressional Review Emergency Amendment Act of 2012 (D.C. Act 19-394, July 18, 2012,  59 DCR 8694).</annotation>
          <annotation>For temporary addition of (c), see § 2(f) of the Firearms Second Congressional Review Emergency Amendment Act of 2012 (D.C. Act 19-510, October 26, 2012,  59 DCR 12808).</annotation>
        </annoGroup>
        <annoGroup>
          <heading>Delegation of Authority</heading>
          <annotation>Delegation of Authority pursuant to <cite doc="D.C. Law 1-85">D.C. Law 1-85</cite>, the Firearms Control Regulation Act of 1975</annotation>
        </annoGroup>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section from-code="true">
      <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" path="|7|25|II"/>
      <num codify:value="7-2502.06">206</num>
      <heading>Time for filing registration applications.</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>An application for a registration certificate shall be filed (and a registration certificate issued) prior to taking possession of a firearm from a licensed dealer or from any person or organization holding a registration certificate therefor. In all other cases, an application for registration shall be filed immediately after a firearm is brought into the District. It shall be deemed compliance with the preceding sentence if such person personally communicates with the Metropolitan Police Department (as determined by the Chief to be sufficient) and provides such information as may be demanded; provided, that such person files an application for a registration certificate within 48 hours after such communication.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>Repealed.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annoGroup>
          <heading>History</heading>
          <annotation doc="D.C. Law 1-85">Sept. 24, 1976, D.C. Law 1-85, title II, § 206, 23 DCR 2464</annotation>
          <annotation doc="D.C. Law 2-62">Mar. 16, 1978, D.C. Law 2-62, § 2, 24 DCR 5780</annotation>
          <annotation doc="D.C. Law 19-170">Sept. 29, 2012, D.C. Law 19-170, § 2(g), 59 DCR 5691</annotation>
        </annoGroup>
        <annoGroup>
          <heading>Prior Codifications</heading>
          <annotation>1981 Ed., § 6-2316.</annotation>
          <annotation>1973 Ed., § 6-1816.</annotation>
        </annoGroup>
        <annoGroup>
          <heading>Effect of Amendments</heading>
          <annotation>The 2012 amendment by <cite doc="D.C. Law 19-170">D.C. Law 19-170</cite> repealed (b), which formerly read: “Any firearm validly registered under prior regulations must be registered pursuant to this unit in accordance with procedures to be promulgated by the Chief. An application to register such firearm shall be filed pursuant to this unit within 60 days of September 24, 1976.”</annotation>
        </annoGroup>
        <annoGroup>
          <heading>Emergency Legislation</heading>
          <annotation>For temporary (90 day) repeal of section, see § 2(g) of Firearms Emergency Amendment Act of 2012 (D.C. Act 19-352, May 11, 2012,  59 DCR 5116).</annotation>
          <annotation>For temporary (90 day) repeal of section, see § 2(g) of the Firearms Amendments Congressional Review Emergency Amendment Act of 2012 (D.C. Act 19-394, July 18, 2012,  59 DCR 8694).</annotation>
          <annotation>For temporary repeal of (b), see § 2(g) of the Firearms Second Congressional Review Emergency Amendment Act of 2012 (D.C. Act 19-510, October 26, 2012,  59 DCR 12808).</annotation>
        </annoGroup>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section from-code="true">
      <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" path="|7|25|II"/>
      <num codify:value="7-2502.07">207</num>
      <heading>Issuance of registration certificate; time period; corrections.</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>Upon receipt of a properly executed application for registration certificate, the Chief, upon determining through inquiry, investigation, or otherwise, that the applicant is entitled and qualified under the provisions of this unit, thereto, shall issue a registration certificate. Each registration certificate shall be in duplicate and bear a unique registration certificate number and such other information as the Chief determines is necessary to identify the applicant and the firearm registered. The duplicate of the registration certificate shall be delivered to the applicant and the Chief shall retain the original.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>The Chief shall approve or deny an application for a registration certificate within a 60-day period beginning on the date the Chief receives the application, unless good cause is shown, including nonreceipt of information from sources outside the District government; provided, that in the case of an application to register a firearm validly registered under prior regulations, the Chief shall have 365 days after the receipt of such application to approve or deny such application. The Chief may hold in abeyance an application where there is a revocation proceeding pending against such person or organization.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(c)</num>
        <text>Upon receipt of a registration certificate, each applicant shall examine same to ensure that the information thereon is correct. If the registration certificate is incorrect in any respect, the person or organization named thereon shall return it to the Chief with a signed statement showing the nature of the error. The Chief shall correct the error, if it occurred through administrative error. In the event the error resulted from information contained in the application, the applicant shall be required to file an amended application setting forth the correct information, and a statement explaining the error in the original application. Each amended application shall be accompanied by a fee equal to that required for the original application.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(d)</num>
        <text>In the event the Chief learns of an error in a registration certificate other than as provided in subsection (c) of this section, he may require the holder to return the registration certificate for correction. If the error resulted from information contained in the application, the person or organization named therein shall be required to file an amended application as provided in subsection (c) of this section.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(e)</num>
        <text>Each registration certificate issued by the Chief shall be accompanied by a statement setting forth the registrant’s duties under this unit.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(f)</num>
        <text>In the discretion of the Chief of Police, a registration certificate may be issued to a retired police officer who is a resident of the District of Columbia for a pistol and ammunition which conforms to the Metropolitan Police Department General Orders and policies.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(g)</num>
        <text>When the retired police officer ceases to be a resident of the District of Columbia the registration certificate expires.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(h)</num>
        <text>Nothing in this unit shall create an entitlement to a registration certificate for a retired police officer. If the Chief of Police denies a retired police officer’s registration certificate application, the Chief of Police shall state the reasons for the denial in writing.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(i)</num>
        <text>The District of Columbia shall not incur any liability by reason of the issuance or denial of a certificate, nor for any use made of the registered firearm.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annoGroup>
          <heading>History</heading>
          <annotation doc="D.C. Law 1-85">Sept. 24, 1976, D.C. Law 1-85, title II, § 207, 23 DCR 2464</annotation>
          <annotation doc="D.C. Law 2-62">Mar. 16, 1978, D.C. Law 2-62, § 2, 24 DCR 5780</annotation>
          <annotation doc="D.C. Law 9-266">May 7, 1993, D.C. Law 9-266, § 2(c), 39 DCR 5676</annotation>
        </annoGroup>
        <annoGroup>
          <heading>Prior Codifications</heading>
          <annotation>1981 Ed., § 6-2317.</annotation>
          <annotation>1973 Ed., § 6-1817.</annotation>
        </annoGroup>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section from-code="true">
      <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" path="|7|25|II"/>
      <num codify:value="7-2502.07a">207a</num>
      <heading>Expiration and renewal of registration certificate.</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>Registration certificates shall expire 3 years after the date of issuance unless renewed in accordance with this section for subsequent 3-year periods.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>A registrant shall be eligible for renewal of registration of a firearm if the registrant continues to meet all of the initial registration requirements set forth in § <cite path="§7-2502.03">7-2502.03</cite>(a) and follows any procedures the Chief may establish by rule.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(c)</num>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>For each renewal, a registrant shall submit a statement to the Metropolitan Police Department attesting to:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(A)</num>
            <text>Possession of the registered firearm;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(B)</num>
            <text>The registrant’s address; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(C)</num>
            <text>The registrant’s continued compliance with all registration requirements set forth in § <cite path="§7-2502.03">7-2502.03</cite>(a).</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>The statement submitted pursuant to paragraph (1) of this subsection shall be on a form provided by the Chief that can be submitted online via the Metropolitan Police Department website, by mail, or in person.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(d)</num>
        <text>Repealed.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(e)</num>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>The Metropolitan Police Department shall mail a renewal notice to each registrant at least 90 days prior to the expiration of the registration certificate.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>A renewal application shall be received by the Metropolitan Police Department at least 60 days prior to the expiration of the current registration certificate to ensure timely renewal.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(3)</num>
          <text>It is the duty of the registrant to timely renew a registration before its expiration date and a failure of the Metropolitan Police Department to mail or the registrant to receive the notice required under paragraph (1) of this subsection shall not prevent a registration from expiring as of that date.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(f)</num>
        <text>Repealed.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(g)</num>
        <text>The Chief shall establish, by rule, a method for conducting the renewal of registration certificates for all firearms registered before January 1, 2011. This method shall be established before January 1, 2014.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(h)</num>
        <text>Notwithstanding subsection (a) of this section, no registration certificate shall expire and no renewal of a registration certificate shall be required earlier than provided in the rule established pursuant to subsection (g) of this section.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annoGroup>
          <heading>History</heading>
          <annotation doc="D.C. Law 1-85">Sept. 24, 1976, D.C. Law 1-85, title II, § 207a</annotation>
          <annotation doc="D.C. Law 17-372">as added Mar. 31, 2009, D.C. Law 17-372, § 3(g), 56 DCR 1365</annotation>
          <annotation doc="D.C. Law 18-377">June 3, 2011, D.C. Law 18-377, § 2(b), 58 DCR 1174</annotation>
          <annotation doc="D.C. Law 19-170">Sept. 29, 2012, D.C. Law 19-170, § 2(h), 59 DCR 5691</annotation>
        </annoGroup>
        <annoGroup>
          <heading>Section References</heading>
          <annotation>This section is referenced in § <cite path="§7-2502.05">7-2502.05</cite>.</annotation>
        </annoGroup>
        <annoGroup>
          <heading>Effect of Amendments</heading>
          <annotation><cite doc="D.C. Law 18-377">D.C. Law 18-377</cite> substituted “§ <cite path="§7-2502.03">7-2502.03</cite>(a)” for “§ <cite path="§7-2502.03">7-2502.03</cite>”.</annotation>
          <annotation>The 2012 amendment by <cite doc="D.C. Law 19-170">D.C. Law 19-170</cite> added the (c)(1) designation; redesignated former (c)(1) through (c)(3) as (c)(1)(A) through (c)(1)(C); added (c)(2); repealed (d), which formerly read: “A registrant shall submit to a background check once every 6 years to confirm that the registrant continues to qualify for registration under § <cite path="§7-2502.03">7-2502.03</cite>(a)”; repealed (f), which formerly read: “An applicant for the renewal of a registration certificate may be charged a reasonable fee to cover the administrative costs incurred by the Metropolitan Police Department in connection with the renewal”; in (g), in the first sentence, substituted “registration certificates” for “registrations” and “before January 1, 2011” for “prior to March 31, 2009” and rewrote the second sentence; and added (h).</annotation>
        </annoGroup>
        <annoGroup>
          <heading>Emergency Legislation</heading>
          <annotation>For temporary (90 day) addition, see § 3(g) of Firearms Registration Emergency Amendment Act of 2008 (D.C. Act 17-651, January 6, 2009,  56 DCR 911).</annotation>
          <annotation>For temporary (90 day) amendment of section, see § 502(b) of Public Safety Legislation Sixty-Day Layover Emergency Amendment Act of 2010 (D.C. Act 18-693, January 18, 2011,  58 DCR 640).</annotation>
          <annotation>For temporary (90 day) amendment of section, see § 502(b) of Public Safety Legislation Sixty-Day Layover Congressional Review Emergency Amendment Act of 2011 (D.C. Act 19-45, April 20, 2011,  58 DCR 3701).</annotation>
          <annotation>For temporary (90 day) amendment of section, see § 2 of Firearms Registration Renewal Emergency Amendment Act of 2012 (D.C. Act 19-324, March 18, 2012,  59 DCR 2258).</annotation>
          <annotation>For temporary (90 day) amendment of section, see § 2(h) of Firearms Emergency Amendment Act of 2012 (D.C. Act 19-352, May 11, 2012,  59 DCR 5116).</annotation>
          <annotation>For temporary (90 day) amendment of section, see § 2(h) of the Firearms Amendments Congressional Review Emergency Amendment Act of 2012 (D.C. Act 19-394, July 18, 2012,  59 DCR 8694).</annotation>
          <annotation>For temporary amendment of (c) and (g), repeal of (d) and (f), and addition of (h), see § 2(h) of the Firearms Second Congressional Review Emergency Amendment Act of 2012 (D.C. Act 19-510, October 26, 2012,  59 DCR 12808).</annotation>
        </annoGroup>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section from-code="true">
      <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" path="|7|25|II"/>
      <num codify:value="7-2502.08">208</num>
      <heading>Duties of registrants.</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>Each person or organization holding a registration certificate (for purposes of this section, “registrant”) shall:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>Notify the Chief in writing of the loss, theft, or destruction of the registration certificate or of a registered firearm (including the circumstances, if known) immediately upon discovery of such loss, theft, or destruction;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>Notify the Chief in writing within 30 days of a change in the registrant’s name or address as it appears on the registration certificate;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(3)</num>
          <text>Notify the Chief in writing of the sale, transfer, or other disposition of the firearm within 2 business days of such sale, transfer, or other disposition. The notification shall include:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(A)</num>
            <text>The identification of the registrant, the firearm, and the serial number of the registration certificate;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(B)</num>
            <text>The name, address, and date of birth of the person to whom the firearm has been sold or transferred; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(C)</num>
            <text>Whether the firearm was sold or how it was otherwise transferred or disposed of.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>Each registrant shall return to the Chief the registration certificate for any firearm which is lost, stolen, destroyed, sold, or otherwise transferred or disposed of, at the time the registrant notifies the Chief of such loss, theft, destruction, sale, transfer, or other disposition.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(c)</num>
        <text>Each registrant shall have in the registrant’s possession, whenever in possession of a firearm, the registration certificate, or exact photocopy thereof, for such firearm, and exhibit the same upon the demand of a member of the Metropolitan Police Department, or other law enforcement officer.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(d)</num>
        <text>The duties set forth in subsections (a) through (c) of this section are in addition to any other requirements imposed by this unit or other applicable law.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(e)</num>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>A registrant shall be subject to a civil fine of $100 for the first violation or omission of the duties and requirements imposed by this section.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>A registrant shall be subject to a civil fine of $500 for the second violation or omission of the duties and requirements imposed by this section, a registrant’s registration certificates shall be revoked, and the registrant shall be prohibited from possessing or registering any firearm for a period of 5 years.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(3)</num>
          <text>A registrant shall be subject to a civil fine of $1,000 for the third violation or omission of the duties and requirements imposed by this section, a registrant’s registration certificates shall be revoked, and the registrant shall be prohibited from possessing or registering any firearm.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(4)</num>
          <text>For the purposes of this subsection, “a violation or omission” that applies to multiple firearms shall constitute a single violation or omission if the violation or omission pertaining to each firearm arose from the same occurrence.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(5)</num>
          <text>The penalties prescribed in § <cite path="§7-2507.06">7-2507.06</cite> shall not apply to a violation or omission of the duties and requirements imposed by this section.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annoGroup>
          <heading>History</heading>
          <annotation doc="D.C. Law 1-85">Sept. 24, 1976, D.C. Law 1-85, title II, § 208, 23 DCR 2464</annotation>
          <annotation doc="D.C. Law 18-377">June 3, 2011, D.C. Law 18-377, § 2(c), 58 DCR 1174</annotation>
          <annotation doc="D.C. Law 19-170">Sept. 29, 2012, D.C. Law 19-170, § 2(i), 59 DCR 5691</annotation>
        </annoGroup>
        <annoGroup>
          <heading>Cross References</heading>
          <annotation>Applicability to private operator, see § <cite path="§24-261.02a">24-261.02a</cite>.</annotation>
        </annoGroup>
        <annoGroup>
          <heading>Section References</heading>
          <annotation>This section is referenced in § <cite path="§7-2502.03">7-2502.03</cite>, § <cite path="§7-2507.06">7-2507.06</cite>, and § <cite path="§24-261.02a">24-261.02a</cite>.</annotation>
        </annoGroup>
        <annoGroup>
          <heading>Prior Codifications</heading>
          <annotation>1981 Ed., § 6-2318.</annotation>
          <annotation>1973 Ed., § 6-1818.</annotation>
        </annoGroup>
        <annoGroup>
          <heading>Effect of Amendments</heading>
          <annotation><cite doc="D.C. Law 18-377">D.C. Law 18-377</cite> rewrote the section, which formerly read:</annotation>
          <annotation>“Each person and organization holding a registration certificate, in addition to any other requirements imposed by this unit, or the acts of Congress, shall:</annotation>
          <annotation>“(1) Notify the Chief in writing of:</annotation>
          <annotation>“(A) The loss, theft, or destruction of the registration certificate or of a registered firearm (including the circumstances, if known) immediately upon discovery of such loss, theft, or destruction;</annotation>
          <annotation>“(B) A change in any of the information appearing on the registration certificate or required by § <cite path="§7-2502.03">7-2502.03</cite>;</annotation>
          <annotation>“(C) The sale, transfer or other disposition of the firearm not less than 48 hours prior to delivery, pursuant to such sale, transfer or other disposition, including:</annotation>
          <annotation>“(i) Identification of the registrant, the firearm and the serial number of the registration certificate;</annotation>
          <annotation>“(ii) The name, residence, and business address and date of birth of the person to whom the firearm has been sold or transferred; and</annotation>
          <annotation>“(iii) Whether the firearm was sold or how it was otherwise transferred or disposed of.</annotation>
          <annotation>“(2) Return to the Chief, the registration certificate for any firearm which is lost, stolen, destroyed, or otherwise transferred or disposed of, at the time he notifies the Chief of such loss, theft, destruction, sale, transfer, or other disposition.</annotation>
          <annotation>“(3) Have in his possession, whenever in possession of a firearm, the registration certificate for such firearm, and exhibit the same upon the demand of a member of the Metropolitan Police Department, or other law enforcement officer.”</annotation>
          <annotation>The 2012 amendment by <cite doc="D.C. Law 19-170">D.C. Law 19-170</cite> added “penalties” in the section heading.</annotation>
        </annoGroup>
        <annoGroup>
          <heading>Emergency Legislation</heading>
          <annotation>For temporary (90 day) amendment of section, see § 502(c) of Public Safety Legislation Sixty-Day Layover Emergency Amendment Act of 2010 (D.C. Act 18-693, January 18, 2011,  58 DCR 640).</annotation>
          <annotation>For temporary (90 day) amendment of section, see § 502(c) of Public Safety Legislation Sixty-Day Layover Congressional Review Emergency Amendment Act of 2011 (D.C. Act 19-45, April 20, 2011,  58 DCR 3701).</annotation>
          <annotation>For temporary (90 day) amendment of section heading, see § 2(i) of Firearms Emergency Amendment Act of 2012 (D.C. Act 19-352, May 11, 2012,  59 DCR 5116).</annotation>
          <annotation>For temporary (90 day) amendment of section heading, see § 2(i) of the Firearms Amendments Congressional Review Emergency Amendment Act of 2012 (D.C. Act 19-394, July 18, 2012,  59 DCR 8694).</annotation>
          <annotation>For temporary amendment of the section heading, see § 2(i) of the Firearms Second Congressional Review Emergency Amendment Act of 2012 (D.C. Act 19-510, October 26, 2012,  59 DCR 12808).</annotation>
        </annoGroup>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section from-code="true">
      <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" path="|7|25|II"/>
      <num codify:value="7-2502.09">209</num>
      <heading>Revocation of registration certificate.</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>A registration certificate shall be revoked if:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>Any of the criteria in § <cite path="§7-2502.03">7-2502.03</cite>(a) are not currently met;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>The registered firearm has become an unregisterable firearm under the terms of § <cite path="§7-2502.02">7-2502.02</cite>, or a destructive device; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(3)</num>
          <text>The information furnished to the Chief on the application for a registration certificate proves to be intentionally false.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(4)</num>
          <text>Repealed.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>Repealed.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annoGroup>
          <heading>History</heading>
          <annotation doc="D.C. Law 1-85">Sept. 24, 1976, D.C. Law 1-85, title II, § 209, 23 DCR 2464</annotation>
          <annotation doc="D.C. Law 17-372">Mar. 31, 2009, D.C. Law 17-372, § 3(h), 56 DCR 1365</annotation>
          <annotation doc="D.C. Law 18-377">June 3, 2011, D.C. Law 18-377,§ 2(d), 58 DCR 1174</annotation>
        </annoGroup>
        <annoGroup>
          <heading>Cross References</heading>
          <annotation>Applicability to private operator, see § <cite path="§24-261.02a">24-261.02a</cite>.</annotation>
        </annoGroup>
        <annoGroup>
          <heading>Section References</heading>
          <annotation>This section is referenced in § <cite path="§2-1831.03">2-1831.03</cite> and § <cite path="§24-261.02a">24-261.02a</cite>.</annotation>
        </annoGroup>
        <annoGroup>
          <heading>Prior Codifications</heading>
          <annotation>1981 Ed., § 6-2319.</annotation>
          <annotation>1973 Ed., § 6-1819.</annotation>
        </annoGroup>
        <annoGroup>
          <heading>Effect of Amendments</heading>
          <annotation><cite doc="D.C. Law 17-372">D.C. Law 17-372</cite> designated subsec. (a); in subsec. (a), inserted “or” at the end of par. (2), substituted a period for “; and” at the end of par. (3), and repealed par. (4); and added subsec. (b). Prior to repeal, par. (4) of subsec. (a) read as follows: “(4) There is a violation or omission of the duties, obligations or requirements imposed by § <cite path="§7-2502.08">7-2502.08</cite>.”</annotation>
          <annotation><cite doc="D.C. Law 18-377">D.C. Law 18-377</cite>, in subsec. (a)(1), substituted “§ <cite path="§7-2502.03">7-2502.03</cite>(a)” for “§ <cite path="§7-2502.03">7-2502.03</cite>”; and rewrote subsec. (b).</annotation>
        </annoGroup>
        <annoGroup>
          <heading>Emergency Legislation</heading>
          <annotation>For temporary (90 day) amendment of section, see § 3(h) of Firearms Registration Emergency Amendment Act of 2008 (D.C. Act 17-651, January 6, 2009,  56 DCR 911).</annotation>
          <annotation>For temporary (90 day) amendment of section, see § 502(d) of Public Safety Legislation Sixty-Day Layover Emergency Amendment Act of 2010 (D.C. Act 18-693, January 18, 2011,  58 DCR 640).</annotation>
          <annotation>For temporary (90 day) amendment of section, see § 502(d) of Public Safety Legislation Sixty-Day Layover Congressional Review Emergency Amendment Act of 2011 (D.C. Act 19-45, April 20, 2011,  58 DCR 3701).</annotation>
        </annoGroup>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section from-code="true">
      <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" path="|7|25|II"/>
      <num codify:value="7-2502.10">210</num>
      <heading>Procedure for denial and revocation of registration certificate.</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>If it appears to the Chief that an application for a registration certificate should be denied or that a registration certificate should be revoked, the Chief shall notify the applicant or registrant of the proposed denial or revocation, briefly stating the reason or reasons therefor. Service may be made by delivering a copy of the notice to the applicant or registrant personally, or by leaving a copy thereof at the place of residence identified on the application or registration with some person of suitable age and discretion then residing therein, or by mailing a copy of the notice first class mail, postage prepaid, to the residence address identified on the application or certificate. In the case of an organization, service may be made upon the president, chief executive, or other officer, managing agent or person authorized by appointment or law to receive such notice as described in the preceding sentence at the business address of the organization identified in the application or registration certificate. The person serving the notice shall make proof thereof by preparing an affidavit identifying the person served and stating the time, place, and manner of service. The applicant or registrant shall have 15 days from the date the notice is served in which to submit further evidence in support of the application or qualifications to continue to hold a registration certificate, as the case may be; provided, that if the applicant does not make such a submission within 15 days from the date of service, the applicant or registrant shall be deemed to have conceded the validity of the reason or reasons stated in the notice, and the denial or revocation shall become final.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>Within 10 days of the date upon which the Chief receives such a submission, he shall serve upon the applicant or registrant in the manner specified in subsection (a) of this section notice of his final decision. The Chief’s decision shall become effective at the expiration of the time within which to file a notice of appeal pursuant to the District of Columbia Administrative Procedure Act (§ <cite path="§2-501">2-501</cite> et seq.) or, if such a notice of appeal is filed, at the time the final order or judgment of the District of Columbia Court of Appeals becomes effective.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(c)</num>
        <text>Within 7 days of a decision unfavorable to the applicant or registrant becoming final, the applicant or registrant shall:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>Peaceably surrender to the Chief the firearm for which the registration certificate was revoked in the manner provided in § <cite path="§7-2507.05">7-2507.05</cite>; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>Lawfully remove such firearm from the District for so long as he has an interest in such firearm; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(3)</num>
          <text>Otherwise lawfully dispose of his interest in such firearm.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(d)</num>
        <text>If a firearm is in the possession of the Chief, the Chief may maintain possession of the firearm for which the registrant is temporarily or permanently prohibited from having lawful possession until final disposition of the matter.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annoGroup>
          <heading>History</heading>
          <annotation doc="D.C. Law 1-85">Sept. 24, 1976, D.C. Law 1-85, title II, § 210, 23 DCR 2464</annotation>
          <annotation doc="D.C. Law 2-62">Mar. 16, 1978, D.C. Law 2-62, § 2, 24 DCR 5780</annotation>
          <annotation doc="D.C. Law 17-372">Mar. 31, 2009, D.C. Law 17-372, § 3(i), 56 DCR 1365</annotation>
        </annoGroup>
        <annoGroup>
          <heading>Section References</heading>
          <annotation>This section is referenced in § <cite path="§2-1831.03">2-1831.03</cite>, § <cite path="§7-2504.06">7-2504.06</cite>, § <cite path="§7-2505.01">7-2505.01</cite>, and § <cite path="§7-2507.05">7-2507.05</cite>.</annotation>
        </annoGroup>
        <annoGroup>
          <heading>Prior Codifications</heading>
          <annotation>1981 Ed., § 6-2320.</annotation>
          <annotation>1973 Ed., § 6-1820.</annotation>
        </annoGroup>
        <annoGroup>
          <heading>Effect of Amendments</heading>
          <annotation><cite doc="D.C. Law 17-372">D.C. Law 17-372</cite> rewrote subsec. (a); and added subsec. (d).</annotation>
        </annoGroup>
        <annoGroup>
          <heading>Emergency Legislation</heading>
          <annotation>For temporary (90 day) amendment of section, see § 3(i) of Firearms Registration Emergency Amendment Act of 2008 (D.C. Act 17-651, January 6, 2009,  56 DCR 911).</annotation>
        </annoGroup>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section from-code="true">
      <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" path="|7|25|II"/>
      <num codify:value="7-2502.11">211</num>
      <heading>Information prohibited from use as evidence in criminal proceedings.</heading>
      <text>No information obtained from a person under this subchapter or retained by a person in order to comply with any section of this subchapter, shall be used as evidence against such person in any criminal proceeding with respect to a violation of this unit, occurring prior to or concurrently with the filing of the information required by this subchapter; provided, that this section shall not apply to any violation of § <cite path="§22-2402">22-2402</cite>, or § <cite path="§7-2507.04">7-2507.04</cite>.</text>
      <annotations>
        <annoGroup>
          <heading>History</heading>
          <annotation doc="D.C. Law 1-85">Sept. 24, 1976, D.C. Law 1-85, title II, § 211, 23 DCR 2464</annotation>
          <annotation doc="D.C. Law 2-62">Mar. 16, 1978, D.C. Law 2-62, § 2, 24 DCR 5780</annotation>
          <annotation doc="D.C. Law 5-24">Aug. 2, 1983, D.C. Law 5-24, § 13, 30 DCR 3341</annotation>
        </annoGroup>
        <annoGroup>
          <heading>Prior Codifications</heading>
          <annotation>1981 Ed., § 6-2321.</annotation>
          <annotation>1973 Ed., § 6-1821.</annotation>
        </annoGroup>
        <annoGroup>
          <heading>Temporary Legislation</heading>
          <annotation>For temporary (225 days) addition of <cite doc="D.C. Law 1-85">D.C. Law 1-85</cite>, § 211a, concerning a freedom of information exception, see § 2(c) of the  License to Carry a Pistol Temporary Amendment Act of 2014 (<cite doc="D.C. Law 20-169">D.C. Law 20-169</cite>, May 5, 2015, 61 DCR 11814).</annotation>
        </annoGroup>
        <annoGroup>
          <heading>Emergency Legislation</heading>
          <annotation>For temporary (90 days) addition of <cite doc="D.C. Law 1-85">D.C. Law 1-85</cite>, § 211a, concerning freedom of information exception, see § 2(c) of the  License to Carry a Pistol Emergency Amendment Act of 2014 (D.C. Act 20-447, Oct. 7, 2014, 61 DCR 10765, 20 STAT 4175).</annotation>
          <annotation>For temporary (90 days) repeal of emergency D.C. Act 20-447, § 4, the act’s applicability clause, see §  2 of the License to Carry a Pistol Clarification Emergency Amendment Act of 2014 (D.C. Act 20-448, Oct. 7, 2014, 61 DCR 10777, 20 STAT 4187).</annotation>
          <annotation>For temporary (90 days) addition of <cite doc="D.C. Law 1-85">D.C. Law 1-85</cite>, § 211a, concerning a freedom of information exception, see § 2(d) of the  License to Carry a Pistol Second Emergency Amendment Act of 2014 (D.C. Act 20-564, Jan. 6, 2015, 62 DCR 866, 21 STAT 527).</annotation>
          <annotation>For temporary  (90 days) repeal of emergency D.C. Act 20-447, see § 4(b) of  the  License to Carry a Pistol Second Emergency Amendment  Act of 2014 (D.C. Act 20-564, Jan. 6, 2015, 62 DCR 866, 21 STAT 527).</annotation>
          <annotation>For temporary (90 days) repeal of temporary D.C. Act 20-169, see § 4(c) of the  License to Carry a Pistol Second Emergency Amendment Act of 2014 (D.C. Act 20-564, Jan. 6, 2015, 62 DCR 866, 21 STAT 527).</annotation>
        </annoGroup>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section from-code="true">
      <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" path="|7|25|II"/>
      <num codify:value="7-2502.11a">211a</num>
      <heading>Freedom of information exception.</heading>
      <text>Any record regarding a person who has applied for, received, or had revoked any registration issued pursuant to this subchapter shall not be made available as a public record under § <cite path="§2-532">2-532</cite>.</text>
      <annotations>
        <annoGroup>
          <heading>History</heading>
          <annotation doc="D.C. Law 1-85">Sept. 24, 1976, D.C. Law 1-85, title II, § 211a</annotation>
          <annotation doc="D.C. Law 20-279">as added June 16, 2015, D.C. Law 20-279, § 2(d), 62 DCR 1944</annotation>
        </annoGroup>
        <annoGroup>
          <heading>Emergency Legislation</heading>
          <annotation>For temporary (90 days) addition of this section, see § 2(d) of the License to Carry a Pistol Congressional Review Emergency Amendment Act of 2015 (D.C. Act 21-74, June 4, 2015,  62 DCR 8242, 21 DCSTAT 1451).</annotation>
        </annoGroup>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section from-code="true">
      <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" path="|7|25|II"/>
      <num codify:value="7-2502.12">212</num>
      <heading>Definition of self-defense sprays.</heading>
      <text>For the purposes of §§ <cite path="§7-2502.12">7-2502.12</cite> through <cite path="§7-2502.14">7-2502.14</cite>, the term:</text>
      <text>“Self-defense spray” means a mixture of a lacrimator including chloroacetophenone, alphacloracetophenone, phenylchloromethylketone, orthochlorobenazalm-alononitrile or oleoresin capsicum.</text>
      <annotations>
        <annoGroup>
          <heading>History</heading>
          <annotation doc="D.C. Law 1-85">Sept. 24, 1976, D.C. Law 1-85, title II, § 212</annotation>
          <annotation doc="D.C. Law 9-244">as added Mar. 17, 1993, D.C. Law 9-244, § 2, 40 DCR 647</annotation>
          <annotation doc="D.C. Law 10-255">May 16, 1995, D.C. Law 10-255, § 10(a), 41 DCR 5193</annotation>
        </annoGroup>
        <annoGroup>
          <heading>Section References</heading>
          <annotation>This section is referenced in § <cite path="§7-2502.13">7-2502.13</cite>.</annotation>
        </annoGroup>
        <annoGroup>
          <heading>Prior Codifications</heading>
          <annotation>1981 Ed., § 6-2322.</annotation>
        </annoGroup>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section from-code="true">
      <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" path="|7|25|II"/>
      <num codify:value="7-2502.13">213</num>
      <heading>Possession of self-defense sprays.</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>Notwithstanding the provisions of § <cite path="§7-2501.01">7-2501.01</cite>(7)(C), a person 18 years of age or older may possess and use a self-defense spray in the exercise of reasonable force in defense of the person or the person’s property only if it is propelled from an aerosol container, labeled with or accompanied by clearly written instructions as to its use, and dated to indicate its anticipated useful life.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>No person shall possess a self-defense spray which is of a type other than that specified in §§ <cite path="§7-2502.12">7-2502.12</cite> to 7-2502.14.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annoGroup>
          <heading>History</heading>
          <annotation doc="D.C. Law 1-85">Sept. 24, 1976, D.C. Law 1-85, title II, § 213</annotation>
          <annotation doc="D.C. Law 9-244">as added Mar. 17, 1993, D.C. Law 9-244, § 2, 40 DCR 647</annotation>
          <annotation doc="D.C. Law 10-255">May 16, 1995, D.C. Law 10-255, § 10(b), 41 DCR 5193</annotation>
        </annoGroup>
        <annoGroup>
          <heading>Prior Codifications</heading>
          <annotation>1981 Ed., § 6-2323.</annotation>
        </annoGroup>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section from-code="true">
      <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" path="|7|25|II"/>
      <num codify:value="7-2502.14">214</num>
      <heading>Registration of self-defense sprays.</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>A person 18 years of age or older must register the self-defense spray at the time of purchase by completing a standard registration form.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>The vendor must forward the registration form to the Metropolitan Police Department.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annoGroup>
          <heading>History</heading>
          <annotation doc="D.C. Law 1-85">Sept. 24, 1976, D.C. Law 1-85, title II, § 214</annotation>
          <annotation doc="D.C. Law 9-244">as added Mar. 17, 1993, D.C. Law 9-244, § 2, 40 DCR 647</annotation>
        </annoGroup>
        <annoGroup>
          <heading>Prior Codifications</heading>
          <annotation>1981 Ed., § 6-2324.</annotation>
        </annoGroup>
      </annotations>
    </section>
  </container>
  <container>
    <prefix>Title</prefix>
    <num>III</num>
    <section from-code="true">
      <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" path="|7|25|III"/>
      <num codify:value="7-2503.01">301</num>
      <heading>Rights and responsibilities of executors and administrators.</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>The executor or administrator of an estate containing a firearm shall notify the Chief of the death of the decedent within 30 days of his appointment or qualification, whichever is earlier.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>Until the lawful distribution of such firearm to an heir or legatee or the lawful sale, transfer, or disposition of the firearm by the estate, the executor or administrator of such estate shall be charged with the duties and obligations which would have been imposed by this unit upon the decedent, if the decedent were still alive; provided, that such executor or administrator shall not be liable to the criminal penalties of § <cite path="§7-2507.06">7-2507.06</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annoGroup>
          <heading>History</heading>
          <annotation doc="D.C. Law 1-85">Sept. 24, 1976, D.C. Law 1-85, title III, § 301, 23 DCR 2464</annotation>
          <annotation doc="D.C. Law 2-62">Mar. 16, 1978, D.C. Law 2-62, § 2, 24 DCR 5780</annotation>
          <annotation doc="D.C. Law 5-19">Aug. 2, 1983, D.C. Law 5-19, § 3, 30 DCR 3328</annotation>
        </annoGroup>
        <annoGroup>
          <heading>Prior Codifications</heading>
          <annotation>1981 Ed., § 6-2331.</annotation>
          <annotation>1973 Ed., § 6-1831.</annotation>
        </annoGroup>
      </annotations>
    </section>
  </container>
  <container>
    <prefix>Title</prefix>
    <num>IV</num>
    <section from-code="true">
      <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" path="|7|25|IV"/>
      <num codify:value="7-2504.01">401</num>
      <heading>Manufacture of firearms, destructive devices or ammunition prohibited; requirement for dealer’s license.</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>No person or organization shall manufacture any firearm, destructive device or parts thereof, or ammunition, within the District; provided, that persons holding registration certificates may engage in hand loading, reloading, or custom loading ammunition for his registered firearms; provided further, that such person may not hand load, reload, or custom load ammunition for others.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>No person or organization shall engage in the business of selling, purchasing, or repairing any firearm, destructive device, parts therefor, or ammunition, without first obtaining a dealer’s license, and no licensee shall engage in the business of selling, purchasing, or repairing firearms which are unregisterable under § <cite path="§7-2502.02">7-2502.02</cite>, destructive devices, or parts therefor, except pursuant to a valid work or purchase order, for those persons specified in § <cite path="§7-2502.01">7-2502.01</cite>(b)(1).</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(c)</num>
        <text>Any license issued pursuant to this section shall be issued by the Metropolitan Police Department as a Public Safety endorsement to a basic business license under the basic business license system as set forth in subchapter I-A of Chapter 28 of Title 47.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annoGroup>
          <heading>History</heading>
          <annotation doc="D.C. Law 1-85">Sept. 24, 1976, D.C. Law 1-85, title IV, § 401, 23 DCR 2464</annotation>
          <annotation doc="D.C. Law 12-261">Apr. 20, 1999, D.C. Law 12-261, § 2003(k)(1), 46 DCR 3142</annotation>
          <annotation doc="D.C. Law 15-38">Oct. 28, 2003, D.C. Law 15-38, § 3(i)(1), 50 DCR 6913</annotation>
        </annoGroup>
        <annoGroup>
          <heading>Section References</heading>
          <annotation>This section is referenced in § <cite path="§7-2508.01">7-2508.01</cite>.</annotation>
        </annoGroup>
        <annoGroup>
          <heading>Prior Codifications</heading>
          <annotation>1981 Ed., § 6-2341.</annotation>
          <annotation>1973 Ed., § 6-1841.</annotation>
        </annoGroup>
        <annoGroup>
          <heading>Effect of Amendments</heading>
          <annotation><cite doc="D.C. Law 15-38">D.C. Law 15-38</cite>, in subsec. (c), substituted “Public Safety endorsement to a basic business license under the basic” for “Class A Public Safety endorsement to a master business license under the master”.</annotation>
        </annoGroup>
        <annoGroup>
          <heading>Emergency Legislation</heading>
          <annotation>For temporary (90 day) amendment of section, see § 3(i)(1) of Streamlining Regulation Emergency Act of 2003 (D.C. Act 15-145, August 11, 2003,  50 DCR 6896).</annotation>
        </annoGroup>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section from-code="true">
      <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" path="|7|25|IV"/>
      <num codify:value="7-2504.02">402</num>
      <heading>Qualifications for dealer’s license; application; fee.</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>Any person eligible to register a firearm under this unit and who, if a registrant, has not previously failed to perform any of the duties imposed by this unit; and, any person eligible under the acts of Congress to engage in such business, may obtain a dealer’s license, or a renewal thereof, which shall be valid for a period of not more than 1 year from the date of issuance. The license required by this unit, shall be in addition to any other license or licensing procedure required by law.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>Each application for a dealer’s license and each application for renewal thereof shall be made on a form prescribed by the Chief, shall be sworn to or affirmed by the applicant, and shall contain:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>The information required by § <cite path="§7-2502.03">7-2502.03</cite>(a);</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>The address where the applicant conducts or intends to conduct his business;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(3)</num>
          <text>Whether the applicant, prior to September 24, 1976, held a license to deal in deadly weapons in the District; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(4)</num>
          <text>Such other information as the Chief may require, including fingerprints and photographs of the applicant, to carry out the purposes of this unit.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(c)</num>
        <text>Each application for a dealer’s license, or renewal shall be accompanied by a fee established by the Mayor; provided, that such fee shall in the judgment of the Mayor, reimburse the District for the cost of services provided under this subchapter.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(d)</num>
        <text>Any license issued pursuant to this section shall be issued as a Public Safety endorsement to a basic business license under the basic business license system as set forth in subchapter I-A of Chapter 28 of Title 47.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annoGroup>
          <heading>History</heading>
          <annotation doc="D.C. Law 1-85">Sept. 24, 1976, D.C. Law 1-85, title IV, § 402, 23 DCR 2464</annotation>
          <annotation doc="D.C. Law 12-261">Apr. 20, 1999, D.C. Law 12-261, § 2003(k)(2), 46 DCR 3142</annotation>
          <annotation doc="D.C. Law 15-38">Oct. 28, 2003, D.C. Law 15-38, § 3(i)(2), 50 DCR 6913</annotation>
        </annoGroup>
        <annoGroup>
          <heading>Section References</heading>
          <annotation>This section is referenced in § <cite path="§7-2504.04">7-2504.04</cite>.</annotation>
        </annoGroup>
        <annoGroup>
          <heading>Prior Codifications</heading>
          <annotation>1981 Ed., § 6-2342.</annotation>
          <annotation>1973 Ed., § 6-1842.</annotation>
        </annoGroup>
        <annoGroup>
          <heading>Effect of Amendments</heading>
          <annotation><cite doc="D.C. Law 15-38">D.C. Law 15-38</cite>, in subsec. (c), substituted “Public Safety endorsement to a basic business license under the basic” for “Class A Public Safety endorsement to a master business license under the master”.</annotation>
        </annoGroup>
        <annoGroup>
          <heading>Emergency Legislation</heading>
          <annotation>For temporary (90 day) amendment of section, see § 3(i)(2) of Streamlining Regulation Emergency Act of 2003 (D.C. Act 15-145, August 11, 2003,  50 DCR 6896).</annotation>
        </annoGroup>
        <annoGroup>
          <heading>Delegation of Authority</heading>
          <annotation>Delegation of Authority pursuant to <cite doc="D.C. Law 1-85">D.C. Law 1-85</cite>, the Firearms Control Regulation Act of 1975</annotation>
        </annoGroup>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section from-code="true">
      <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" path="|7|25|IV"/>
      <num codify:value="7-2504.03">403</num>
      <heading>Issuance of dealer’s license; time period; corrections.</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>Upon receipt of a properly executed application for a dealer’s license, or renewal thereof, the Chief, upon determining through further inquiry, investigation, or otherwise, that the applicant is entitled and qualified under the provisions of this unit thereto, shall issue a dealer’s license. Each dealer’s license shall be in duplicate and bear a unique dealer’s license number, and such other information as the Chief determines is necessary to identify the applicant and premises. The duplicate of the dealer’s license shall be delivered to the applicant and the Chief shall retain the original.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>The Chief shall approve or deny an application for a registration certificate within a 60-day period beginning on the date the Chief receives the application, unless good cause is shown, including nonreceipt of information from sources outside the District government. The Chief may hold in abeyance an application where there is any firearms revocation proceeding pending against such person.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(c)</num>
        <text>Upon receipt of a dealer’s license, each applicant shall examine the same to ensure that the information thereon is correct. If the dealer’s license is incorrect in any respect, the person named thereon shall return the same to the Chief with a signed statement showing the nature of the error. The Chief shall correct the error, if it occurred through administrative error. In the event the error resulted from information contained in the application, the applicant shall be required to file an amended application explaining the error in the original application. Each amended application shall be accompanied by a fee equal to that required for the original application.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(d)</num>
        <text>In the event the Chief learns of an error in a dealer’s license, other than as provided in subsection (c) of this section, he may require the holder to return the dealer’s license for correction. If the error resulted from information contained in the application, the person named therein shall be required to file an amended application as provided in subsection (c) of this section.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(e)</num>
        <text>Each dealer’s license issued by the Chief shall be accompanied by a statement setting forth a dealer’s duties under this unit.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annoGroup>
          <heading>History</heading>
          <annotation doc="D.C. Law 1-85">Sept. 24, 1976, D.C. Law 1-85, title IV, § 403, 23 DCR 2464</annotation>
        </annoGroup>
        <annoGroup>
          <heading>Prior Codifications</heading>
          <annotation>1981 Ed., § 6-2343.</annotation>
          <annotation>1973 Ed., § 6-1843.</annotation>
        </annoGroup>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section from-code="true">
      <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" path="|7|25|IV"/>
      <num codify:value="7-2504.04">404</num>
      <heading>Duties of licensed dealers; records required.</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>Each person holding a dealer’s license, in addition to any other requirements imposed by this unit, the acts of Congress, and other law, shall:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>Display the dealer’s license in a conspicuous place on the premises;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>Notify the Chief in writing:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(A)</num>
            <text>Of the loss, theft, or destruction of the dealer’s license (including the circumstances, if known) immediately upon the discovery of such loss, theft, or destruction or of the loss, theft, or destruction of any firearms or ammunition in the dealer’s inventory;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(B)</num>
            <text>Of a change in any of the information appearing on the dealer’s license or required by § <cite path="§7-2504.02">7-2504.02</cite> immediately upon the occurrence of any such change;</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(3)</num>
          <text>Keep at the premises identified in the dealer’s license a true and current record in book form of:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(A)</num>
            <text>The name, address, home phone, and date of birth of each employee handling firearms, ammunition, or destructive devices;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(B)</num>
            <text>Each firearm or destructive device received into inventory or for repair including the:</text>
            <para>
              <num>(i)</num>
              <text>Serial number, caliber, make, model, manufacturer’s number (if any), dealer’s identification number (if any), registration certificate number (if any) of the firearm, and similar descriptive information for destructive devices;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(ii)</num>
              <text>Name, address, and dealer’s license number (if any) of the person or organization from whom the firearm or destructive device was purchased or otherwise received;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(iii)</num>
              <text>Consideration given for the firearm or destructive device, if any;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(iv)</num>
              <text>Date and time received by the licensee and in the case of repair, returned to the person holding the registration certificate; and</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(v)</num>
              <text>Nature of the repairs made;</text>
            </para>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(C)</num>
            <text>Each firearm or destructive device sold or transferred including the:</text>
            <para>
              <num>(i)</num>
              <text>Serial number, caliber, make, model, manufacturer’s number or dealer’s identification number, and registration certificate number (if any) of the firearm or similar information for destructive devices;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(ii)</num>
              <text>Name, address, registration certificate number or license number (if any) of the person or organization to whom transferred;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(iii)</num>
              <text>The consideration for transfer; and</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(iv)</num>
              <text>Time and date of delivery of the firearm or destructive device to the transferee;</text>
            </para>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(D)</num>
            <text>Ammunition received into inventory including the:</text>
            <para>
              <num>(i)</num>
              <text>Brand and number of rounds of each caliber or gauge;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(ii)</num>
              <text>Name, address, and dealer’s license or registration number (if any) of the person or organization from whom received;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(iii)</num>
              <text>Consideration given for the ammunition; and</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(iv)</num>
              <text>Date and time of the receipt of the ammunition;</text>
            </para>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(E)</num>
            <text>Ammunition sold or transferred including:</text>
            <para>
              <num>(i)</num>
              <text>Brand and number of rounds of each caliber or gauge;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(ii)</num>
              <text>Name, address and dealer’s license number (if any) of the person or organization to whom sold or transferred;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(iii)</num>
              <text>If the purchaser or transferee is not a licensee, the registration certificate number of the firearm for which the ammunition was sold or transferred;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(iv)</num>
              <text>The consideration for the sale and transfer; and</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(v)</num>
              <text>The date and time of sale or transfer.</text>
            </para>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>The records required by subsection (a) of this section shall upon demand be exhibited during normal business hours to any member of the Metropolitan Police Department. In addition, the records required by subsection (a) of this section shall be submitted upon demand with the dealer’s application for license renewal.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(c)</num>
        <text>Each person holding a dealer’s license shall, when required by the Chief in writing, submit on a form and for the periods of time specified, any record information required to be maintained by subsection (a) of this section, and any other information reasonably obtainable therefrom.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annoGroup>
          <heading>History</heading>
          <annotation doc="D.C. Law 1-85">Sept. 24, 1976, D.C. Law 1-85, title IV, § 404, 23 DCR 2464</annotation>
          <annotation doc="D.C. Law 17-372">Mar. 31, 2009, D.C. Law 17-372, § 3(j), 56 DCR 1365</annotation>
        </annoGroup>
        <annoGroup>
          <heading>Section References</heading>
          <annotation>This section is referenced in § <cite path="§7-2504.05">7-2504.05</cite>.</annotation>
        </annoGroup>
        <annoGroup>
          <heading>Prior Codifications</heading>
          <annotation>1981 Ed., § 6-2344.</annotation>
          <annotation>1973 Ed., § 6-1844.</annotation>
        </annoGroup>
        <annoGroup>
          <heading>Effect of Amendments</heading>
          <annotation><cite doc="D.C. Law 17-372">D.C. Law 17-372</cite>, in subsec. (a)(2)(A), substituted “destruction or of the loss, theft, or destruction of any firearms or ammunition in the dealer’s inventory;” for “destruction;”; and, in subsec. (b), added the second sentence.</annotation>
        </annoGroup>
        <annoGroup>
          <heading>Emergency Legislation</heading>
          <annotation>For temporary (90 day) amendment of section, see § 3(j) of Firearms Registration Emergency Amendment Act of 2008 (D.C. Act 17-651, January 6, 2009,  56 DCR 911).</annotation>
        </annoGroup>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section from-code="true">
      <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" path="|7|25|IV"/>
      <num codify:value="7-2504.05">405</num>
      <heading>Revocation of dealer’s license.</heading>
      <text>A dealer’s license shall be revoked if:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Any of the criteria in § <cite path="§7-2504.04">7-2504.04</cite> is not currently met;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The information furnished to the Chief on the application for a dealer’s license proves to be intentionally false;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>There is a violation or omission of the duties, obligations, or requirements imposed by § <cite path="§7-2504.04">7-2504.04</cite>; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>The license holder no longer meets any of the criteria required by this subchapter.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annoGroup>
          <heading>History</heading>
          <annotation doc="D.C. Law 1-85">Sept. 24, 1976, D.C. Law 1-85, title IV, § 405, 23 DCR 2464</annotation>
          <annotation doc="D.C. Law 17-372">Mar. 31, 2009, D.C. Law 17-372, § 3(k), 56 DCR 1365</annotation>
          <annotation doc="D.C. Law 19-170">Sept. 29, 2012, D.C. Law 19-170, § 2(j), 59 DCR 5691</annotation>
        </annoGroup>
        <annoGroup>
          <heading>Prior Codifications</heading>
          <annotation>1981 Ed., § 6-2345.</annotation>
          <annotation>1973 Ed., § 6-1845.</annotation>
        </annoGroup>
        <annoGroup>
          <heading>Effect of Amendments</heading>
          <annotation><cite doc="D.C. Law 17-372">D.C. Law 17-372</cite>, in pars. (1) and (2), deleted “or” at the end; in par. (3), substituted “; or” for a period; and added par. (4).</annotation>
          <annotation>The 2012 amendment by <cite doc="D.C. Law 19-170">D.C. Law 19-170</cite> substituted “subchapter” for “unit” in (4).</annotation>
        </annoGroup>
        <annoGroup>
          <heading>Emergency Legislation</heading>
          <annotation>For temporary (90 day) amendment of section, see § 3(k) of Firearms Registration Emergency Amendment Act of 2008 (D.C. Act 17-651, January 6, 2009,  56 DCR 911).</annotation>
          <annotation>For temporary (90 day) amendment of section, see § 2(j) of Firearms Emergency Amendment Act of 2012 (D.C. Act 19-352, May 11, 2012,  59 DCR 5116).</annotation>
          <annotation>For temporary (90 day) amendment of section, see § 2(j) of the Firearms Amendments Congressional Review Emergency Amendment Act of 2012 (D.C. Act 19-394, July 18, 2012,  59 DCR 8694).</annotation>
          <annotation>For temporary amendment of (4), see § 2(j) of the Firearms Second Congressional Review Emergency Amendment Act of 2012 (D.C. Act 19-510, October 26, 2012,  59 DCR 12808).</annotation>
        </annoGroup>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section from-code="true">
      <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" path="|7|25|IV"/>
      <num codify:value="7-2504.06">406</num>
      <heading>Procedure for denial and revocation of dealer’s license.</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>If it appears to the Chief that an application for a dealer’s license should be denied or that a dealer’s license should be revoked, the Chief shall notify the applicant or registrant of the proposed denial or revocation briefly stating the reason or reasons therefor. Service may be made as provided for in § <cite path="§7-2502.10">7-2502.10</cite>(a). The applicant or dealer shall have 15 days from the date of service in which to submit further evidence in support of the application or qualifications to continue to hold a dealer’s license, as the case may be; provided, that if the applicant or dealer does not make such a submission within 15 days from the date of service, the applicant or dealer shall be deemed to have conceded the validity of the reason or reasons stated in the notice, and the denial or revocation shall become final.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>Within 10 days of the date upon which the Chief receives such a submission, the Chief shall serve upon the applicant or registrant in the manner provided in § <cite path="§7-2502.10">7-2502.10</cite>(a) notice of his final decision. The Chief ’s decision shall become effective at the expiration of the time within which to file a notice of appeal pursuant to the District of Columbia Administrative Procedure Act (§ <cite path="§2-501">2-501</cite> et seq.) or, if such a notice of appeal is filed, at the time the final order or judgment of the District of Columbia Court of Appeals becomes effective.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(c)</num>
        <text>Within 45 days of a decision becoming effective, which is unfavorable to a licensee or to an applicant for a dealer’s license, the licensee or applicant shall:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>If he is eligible to register firearms pursuant to this unit, register such firearms in his inventory as are capable of registration pursuant to this unit;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>Peaceably surrender to the Chief any firearms in his inventory which he does not register, and all destructive devices in his inventory in the manner provided for in § <cite path="§7-2507.05">7-2507.05</cite>;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(3)</num>
          <text>Lawfully remove from the District any firearm in his inventory which he does not register and all destructive devices and ammunition in his inventory for so long as he has an interest in them; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(4)</num>
          <text>Otherwise lawfully dispose of any firearms in his inventory which he does not register and all destructive devices and ammunition in his inventory.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annoGroup>
          <heading>History</heading>
          <annotation doc="D.C. Law 1-85">Sept. 24, 1976, D.C. Law 1-85, title IV, § 406, 23 DCR 2464</annotation>
          <annotation doc="D.C. Law 2-62">Mar. 16, 1978, D.C. Law 2-62, § 2, 24 DCR 5780</annotation>
        </annoGroup>
        <annoGroup>
          <heading>Section References</heading>
          <annotation>This section is referenced in § <cite path="§2-1831.03">2-1831.03</cite>.</annotation>
        </annoGroup>
        <annoGroup>
          <heading>Prior Codifications</heading>
          <annotation>1981 Ed., § 6-2346.</annotation>
          <annotation>1973 Ed., § 6-1846.</annotation>
        </annoGroup>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section from-code="true">
      <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" path="|7|25|IV"/>
      <num codify:value="7-2504.07">407</num>
      <heading>Display of firearms or ammunition by dealers; security; employees of dealers.</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>No licensed dealer shall display any firearm or ammunition in windows visible from a street or sidewalk. All firearms, destructive devices, and ammunition shall be kept at all times in a securely locked place affixed to the premises except when being shown to a customer, being repaired, or otherwise being worked on.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>No licensee shall knowingly employ any person in his establishment if such person would not be eligible to register a firearm under this unit.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annoGroup>
          <heading>History</heading>
          <annotation doc="D.C. Law 1-85">Sept. 24, 1976, D.C. Law 1-85, title IV, § 407, 23 DCR 2464</annotation>
        </annoGroup>
        <annoGroup>
          <heading>Prior Codifications</heading>
          <annotation>1981 Ed., § 6-2347.</annotation>
          <annotation>1973 Ed., § 6-1847.</annotation>
        </annoGroup>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section from-code="true">
      <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" path="|7|25|IV"/>
      <num codify:value="7-2504.08">408</num>
      <heading>Identification number on firearm required before sale.</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>No licensee shall sell or offer for sale any firearm which does not have imbedded into the metal portion of such firearm a unique manufacturer’s identification number or serial number, unless the licensee shall have imbedded into the metal portion of such firearm a unique dealer’s identification number.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>Beginning on January 1, 2016, no licensee shall sell or offer for sale any semiautomatic pistol manufactured on or after January 1, 2016, that is not microstamp-ready as required by and in accordance with § <cite path="§7-2505.03">7-2505.03</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annoGroup>
          <heading>History</heading>
          <annotation doc="D.C. Law 1-85">Sept. 24, 1976, D.C. Law 1-85, title IV, § 408, 23 DCR 2464</annotation>
          <annotation doc="D.C. Law 17-372">Mar. 31, 2009, D.C. Law 17-372, § 3(l), 56 DCR 1365</annotation>
          <annotation doc="D.C. Law 18-377">June 3, 2011, D.C. Law 18-377,§ 2(e), 58 DCR 1174</annotation>
          <annotation doc="D.C. Law 19-170">Sept. 29, 2012, D.C. Law 19-170, § 2(k), 59 DCR 5691</annotation>
          <annotation doc="D.C. Law 20-155">Feb. 26, 2015, D.C. Law 20-155, § 3022(a), 61 DCR 9990</annotation>
        </annoGroup>
        <annoGroup>
          <heading>Prior Codifications</heading>
          <annotation>1981 Ed., § 6-2348.</annotation>
          <annotation>1973 Ed., § 6-1848.</annotation>
        </annoGroup>
        <annoGroup>
          <heading>Effect of Amendments</heading>
          <annotation><cite doc="D.C. Law 17-372">D.C. Law 17-372</cite> designated subsec. (a); and added subsec. (b).</annotation>
          <annotation><cite doc="D.C. Law 18-377">D.C. Law 18-377</cite>, in subsec. (b), substituted “January 1, 2013” for “January 1, 2011”.</annotation>
          <annotation>The 2012 amendment by <cite doc="D.C. Law 19-170">D.C. Law 19-170</cite> substituted “January 1, 2014” for “January 1, 2013” twice in (b).</annotation>
          <annotation>The 2015 amendment by <cite doc="D.C. Law 20-155">D.C. Law 20-155</cite> substituted “January 1, 2016” for “January 1, 2014” twice in (b).</annotation>
        </annoGroup>
        <annoGroup>
          <heading>Temporary Legislation</heading>
          <annotation>For temporary (225 days) amendment of this section, see § 2(a) of the Microstamping Implementation Temporary Amendment Act of 2014 (<cite doc="D.C. Law 20-93">D.C. Law 20-93</cite>, March 11, 2014,  61 DCR 783).</annotation>
          <annotation>For temporary (225 days) amendment of this section, see § 2(a) of the Microstamping Implementation Temporary Amendment Act of 2015 (<cite doc="D.C. Law 21-93">D.C. Law 21-93</cite>, Mar. 23, 2016,  63 DCR 993).</annotation>
        </annoGroup>
        <annoGroup>
          <heading>Emergency Legislation</heading>
          <annotation>For temporary (90 day) amendment of section, see § 3(l) of Firearms Registration Emergency Amendment Act of 2008 (D.C. Act 17-651, January 6, 2009,  56 DCR 911).</annotation>
          <annotation>For temporary (90 day) amendment of section, see § 502(e) of Public Safety Legislation Sixty-Day Layover Emergency Amendment Act of 2010 (D.C. Act 18-693, January 18, 2011,  58 DCR 640).</annotation>
          <annotation>For temporary (90 day) amendment of section, see § 502(e) of Public Safety Legislation Sixty-Day Layover Congressional Review Emergency Amendment Act of 2011 (D.C. Act 19-45, April 20, 2011,  58 DCR 3701).</annotation>
          <annotation>For temporary (90 day) amendment of section, see § 2(k) of Firearms Emergency Amendment Act of 2012 (D.C. Act 19-352, May 11, 2012,  59 DCR 5116).</annotation>
          <annotation>For temporary (90 day) amendment of section, see § 2(k) of the Firearms Amendments Congressional Review Emergency Amendment Act of 2012 (D.C. Act 19-394, July 18, 2012,  59 DCR 8694).</annotation>
          <annotation>For temporary amendment of (b), see § 2(k) of the Firearms Second Congressional Review Emergency Amendment Act of 2012 (D.C. Act 19-510, October 26, 2012,  59 DCR 12808).</annotation>
          <annotation>For temporary amendment of this section, see § 2(a) of the Microstamping Implementation Emergency Amendment Act of 2013 (D.C. Act 20-261, January 2, 2014,  61 DCR 324).</annotation>
          <annotation>For temporary (90 days) amendment of this section, see §  3022(a) of the Fiscal Year 2015 Budget Support Emergency Act of 2014 (D.C. Act 20-377, July 14, 2014, 61 DCR 7598, 20 STAT 3696).</annotation>
          <annotation>For temporary (90 days) amendment of this section, see §  3022(a) of the Fiscal Year 2015 Budget Support Congressional Review Emergency Act of 2014 (D.C. Act 20-449, October 10, 2014, 61 DCR 10915, 20 STAT 4188).</annotation>
          <annotation>For temporary (90 days) amendment of this section, see §  3022(a) of the Fiscal Year 2015 Budget Support Second Congressional Review Emergency Act of 2014 (D.C. Act 20-566, January 9, 2015, 62 DCR 884, 21 STAT 541).</annotation>
          <annotation>For temporary (90 days) amendment of this section, see § 2(a) of the Microstamping Implementation Emergency Amendment Act of 2015 (D.C. Act 21-258, Jan. 6, 2016,  63 DCR 530).</annotation>
          <annotation>For temporary (90 days) amendment of this section, see § 2(a) of the Microstamping Implementation Congressional Review Emergency Amendment Act of 2016 (D.C. Act 21-329, Mar. 16, 2016,  63 DCR 4298).</annotation>
        </annoGroup>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section from-code="true">
      <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" path="|7|25|IV"/>
      <num codify:value="7-2504.09">409</num>
      <heading>Certain information obtained from or retained by dealers not to be used as evidence in criminal proceedings.</heading>
      <text>No information obtained from or retained by a licensed dealer to comply with this unit shall be used as evidence against such licensed dealer in any criminal proceeding with respect to a violation of this unit occurring prior to or concurrently with the filing of such information; provided, that this section shall not apply to any violation of § <cite path="§22-2402">22-2402</cite>, or of § <cite path="§7-2507.04">7-2507.04</cite>.</text>
      <annotations>
        <annoGroup>
          <heading>History</heading>
          <annotation doc="D.C. Law 1-85">Sept. 24, 1976, D.C. Law 1-85, title IV, § 409, 23 DCR 2464</annotation>
          <annotation doc="D.C. Law 2-62">Mar. 16, 1978, D.C. Law 2-62, § 2, 24 DCR 5780</annotation>
          <annotation doc="D.C. Law 5-24">Aug. 2, 1983, D.C. Law 5-24, § 13, 30 DCR 3341</annotation>
        </annoGroup>
        <annoGroup>
          <heading>Prior Codifications</heading>
          <annotation>1981 Ed., § 6-2349.</annotation>
          <annotation>1973 Ed., § 6-1849.</annotation>
        </annoGroup>
        <annoGroup>
          <heading>Emergency Legislation</heading>
          <annotation>For temporary (90 day) addition of section, see § 2(l) of Firearms Emergency Amendment Act of 2012 (D.C. Act 19-352, May 11, 2012,  59 DCR 5116).</annotation>
          <annotation>For temporary (90 day) addition of section, see § 2(l) of the Firearms Amendments Congressional Review Emergency Amendment Act of 2012 (D.C. Act 19-394, July 18, 2012,  59 DCR 8694).</annotation>
        </annoGroup>
      </annotations>
    </section>
  </container>
  <container>
    <prefix>Title</prefix>
    <num>V</num>
    <section from-code="true">
      <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" path="|7|25|V"/>
      <num codify:value="7-2505.01">501</num>
      <heading>Sales and transfers prohibited.</heading>
      <text>No person or organization shall sell, transfer or otherwise dispose of any firearm, destructive device or ammunition in the District except as provided in § <cite path="§7-2502.10">7-2502.10</cite>(c), § <cite path="§7-2505.02">7-2505.02</cite>, or § <cite path="§7-2507.05">7-2507.05</cite>.</text>
      <annotations>
        <annoGroup>
          <heading>History</heading>
          <annotation doc="D.C. Law 1-85">Sept. 24, 1976, D.C. Law 1-85, title V, § 501, 23 DCR 2464</annotation>
          <annotation doc="D.C. Law 2-62">Mar. 16, 1978, D.C. Law 2-62, § 2, 24 DCR 5780</annotation>
        </annoGroup>
        <annoGroup>
          <heading>Section References</heading>
          <annotation>This section is referenced in § <cite path="§7-2508.01">7-2508.01</cite>.</annotation>
        </annoGroup>
        <annoGroup>
          <heading>Prior Codifications</heading>
          <annotation>1981 Ed., § 6-2351.</annotation>
          <annotation>1973 Ed., § 6-1851.</annotation>
        </annoGroup>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section from-code="true">
      <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" path="|7|25|V"/>
      <num codify:value="7-2505.02">502</num>
      <heading>Permissible sales and transfers.</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>Any person or organization eligible to register a firearm may sell or otherwise transfer ammunition or any firearm, except those which are unregisterable under § <cite path="§7-2502.02">7-2502.02</cite>, to a licensed dealer.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>Any licensed dealer may sell or otherwise transfer:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>Ammunition, excluding one or more restricted pistol bullets, and any firearm or destructive device which is lawfully a part of such licensee’s inventory, to any nonresident person or business licensed under the acts of Congress and the jurisdiction where such person resides or conducts such business;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>Ammunition, including one or more restricted pistol bullets, and any firearm or destructive device which is lawfully a part of such licensee’s inventory to:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(A)</num>
            <text>Any other licensed dealer;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(B)</num>
            <text>Any law enforcement officer or agent of the District or the United States of America when such officer or agent is on duty, and acting within the scope of his duties when acquiring such firearm, ammunition, or destructive device, if the officer or agent has in his possession a statement from the head of his agency stating that the item is to be used in such officer’s or agent’s official duties.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(c)</num>
        <text>Any licensed dealer may sell or otherwise transfer a firearm except those which are unregisterable under § <cite path="§7-2502.02">7-2502.02</cite>, to any person or organization possessing a registration certificate for such firearm; provided, that if the Chief denies a registration certificate, he shall so advise the licensee who shall thereupon: (1) withhold delivery until such time as a registration certificate is issued, or, at the option of the purchaser; (2) declare the contract null and void, in which case consideration paid to the licensee shall be returned to the purchaser; provided further, that this subsection shall not apply to persons covered by subsection (b) of this section.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(d)</num>
        <text>Except as provided in subsections (b) and (e) of this section, no licensed dealer shall sell or otherwise transfer ammunition unless:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>The sale or transfer is made in person; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>The purchaser exhibits, at the time of sale or other transfer, a valid registration certificate, or in the case of a nonresident, proof that the weapon is lawfully possessed in the jurisdiction where such person resides;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(3)</num>
          <text>The ammunition to be sold or transferred is of the same caliber or gauge as the firearm described in the registration certificate, or other proof in the case of nonresident; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(4)</num>
          <text>The purchaser signs a receipt for the ammunition which (in addition to the other records required under this unit) shall be maintained by the licensed dealer for a period of 1 year from the date of sale.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(e)</num>
        <text>Any licensed dealer may sell ammunition to any person holding an ammunition collector’s certificate on September 24, 1976; provided, that the collector’s certificate shall be exhibited to the licensed dealer whenever the collector purchases ammunition for his collection; provided further, that the collector shall sign a receipt for the ammunition, which shall be treated in the same manner as that required under paragraph (4) of subsection (d) of this section.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annoGroup>
          <heading>History</heading>
          <annotation doc="D.C. Law 1-85">Sept. 24, 1976, D.C. Law 1-85, title V, § 502, 23 DCR 2464</annotation>
          <annotation doc="D.C. Law 2-62">Mar. 16, 1978, D.C. Law 2-62, § 2, 24 DCR 5780</annotation>
          <annotation doc="D.C. Law 5-19">Aug. 2, 1983, D.C. Law 5-19, § 3, 30 DCR 3328</annotation>
          <annotation doc="D.C. Law 19-295">Apr. 27, 2013, D.C. Law 19-295, § 2(b), 60 DCR 2623</annotation>
        </annoGroup>
        <annoGroup>
          <heading>Section References</heading>
          <annotation>This section is referenced in § <cite path="§7-2505.01">7-2505.01</cite>.</annotation>
        </annoGroup>
        <annoGroup>
          <heading>Prior Codifications</heading>
          <annotation>1981 Ed., § 6-2352.</annotation>
          <annotation>1973 Ed., § 6-1852.</annotation>
        </annoGroup>
        <annoGroup>
          <heading>Effect of Amendments</heading>
          <annotation>The 2013 amendment by <cite doc="D.C. Law 19-295">D.C. Law 19-295</cite> substituted “one or more restricted pistol bullets” for “restricted pistol bullets” in (b)(1) and (b)(2).</annotation>
        </annoGroup>
        <annoGroup>
          <heading>Temporary Amendment of Section</heading>
          <annotation>For temporary (225 day) provisions prohibiting the transfer by the Metropolitan Police Department of ammunition feeding devices, see § 2 of Prohibition on the Transfer of Firearms Temporary Act of 1995 (<cite doc="D.C. Law 11-35">D.C. Law 11-35</cite>, September 8, 1995, law notification  42 DCR 5304).</annotation>
        </annoGroup>
        <annoGroup>
          <heading>Emergency Legislation</heading>
          <annotation>For temporary provisions prohibiting the transfer by the Metropolitan Police Department of ammunition feeding devices, see § 2 of the Prohibition on the Transfer of Firearms Emergency Act of 1995 (D.C. Act 11-58, May 18, 1995,  42 DCR 2574).</annotation>
        </annoGroup>
        <annoGroup>
          <heading>Editor's Notes</heading>
          <annotation>Prohibition on transfer of ammunition feeding devices: For provisions prohibiting the transfer by the Metropolitan Police Department of ammunition feeding devices, see § <cite path="§4-191">4-191</cite>.</annotation>
        </annoGroup>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section from-code="true">
      <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" path="|7|25|V"/>
      <num codify:value="7-2505.03">503</num>
      <heading>Microstamping.</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>For the purposes of the section, the term:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>“Firearms dealer” means a person or organization possessing a dealer’s license under authority of subchapter IV of this chapter.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>“Manufacturer” means any person in business to manufacture or assemble a firearm, for sale or distribution.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(3)</num>
          <text>“Microstamp-ready” means a semiautomatic pistol that is manufactured to produce a unique alpha-numeric or geometric code on at least 2 locations on each expended cartridge case that identifies the make, model, and serial number of the pistol.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(4)</num>
          <text>“Semiautomatic pistol” means a pistol capable of utilizing a portion of the energy of a firing cartridge to extract the fired cartridge case and automatically chamber the next round, and that requires a separate pull of the trigger to fire each successive round.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>Except as provided in subsection (c) of this section, beginning on January 1, 2016, a semiautomatic pistol shall be microstamp-ready if it is:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>Manufactured in the District of Columbia;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>Manufactured on or after January 1, 2016, and delivered or caused to be delivered by any manufacturer to a firearms dealer in the District of Columbia; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(3)</num>
          <text>Manufactured on or after January 1, 2016, and sold, offered for sale, loaned, given, or transferred by a firearms dealer in the District of Columbia.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(c)</num>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>A semiautomatic pistol manufactured after January 1, 2016, that is not microstamp-ready and that was acquired outside of the District by a person who was not a District resident at the time of acquisition but who subsequently moved to the District shall be registered if the requirements of this unit are met, and may be sold, transferred, or given away; provided, that the pistol shall be sold, transferred, or given away only through a firearms dealer.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>If a firearms dealer lawfully acquires a microstamp-ready semiautomatic pistol that was originally purchased by a non-dealer resident of the District of Columbia, the firearms dealer shall not sell, offer for sale, loan, give, or transfer that pistol if he or she knows or reasonably should have known that the unique alphanumeric or geometric code associated with that pistol has been changed, altered, removed, or obliterated, excepting for normal wear.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(d)</num>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>Except as provided in paragraph (2) of this subsection, and except for normal wear, no person shall change, alter, remove, or obliterate the unique alpha-numeric or geometric code associated with that pistol.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>Replacing a firing pin that has been damaged or worn and is in need of replacement for the safe use of the semiautomatic pistol or for a legitimate sporting purpose shall not alone be evidence that someone has violated this subsection.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(e)</num>
        <text>Beginning January 1, 2016, a manufacturer that delivers a semiautomatic pistol, or causes a semiautomatic pistol to be delivered, to a firearms dealer for sale in the District of Columbia shall certify whether the pistol was manufactured on or after January 1, 2016, and, if it was, that:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>The semiautomatic pistol will produce a unique alpha-numeric code or a geometric code on each cartridge case that identifies the make, model, and serial number of the semiautomatic pistol that expended the cartridge casing; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>The manufacturer will supply the Chief with the make, model, and serial number of the semiautomatic pistol that expended the cartridge case, when presented with an alpha-numeric or geometric code from a cartridge case; provided, that the cartridge case was recovered as part of a legitimate law enforcement investigation.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(f)</num>
        <text>The Chief, pursuant to subchapter I of Chapter 5 of Title 2 [§ <cite path="§2-501">2-501</cite> et seq.], shall issue rules to implement the provisions of this section.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annoGroup>
          <heading>History</heading>
          <annotation doc="D.C. Law 1-85">Sept. 24, 1976, D.C. Law 1-85, title V, § 503</annotation>
          <annotation doc="D.C. Law 17-372">as added Mar. 31, 2009, D.C. Law 17-372, § 3(m), 56 DCR 1365</annotation>
          <annotation doc="D.C. Law 18-377">June 3, 2011, D.C. Law 18-377, § 2(f), 58 DCR 1174</annotation>
          <annotation doc="D.C. Law 19-170">Sept. 29, 2012, D.C. Law 19-170, § 2(m), 59 DCR 5691</annotation>
          <annotation doc="D.C. Law 20-155">Feb. 26, 2015, D.C. Law 20-155, § 3022(b), 61 DCR 9990</annotation>
        </annoGroup>
        <annoGroup>
          <heading>Section References</heading>
          <annotation>This section is referenced in § <cite path="§7-2504.08">7-2504.08</cite>.</annotation>
        </annoGroup>
        <annoGroup>
          <heading>Effect of Amendments</heading>
          <annotation><cite doc="D.C. Law 18-377">D.C. Law 18-377</cite>, in subsec. (f), substituted “January 1, 2013” for “January 1, 2011”.</annotation>
          <annotation>The 2012 amendment by <cite doc="D.C. Law 19-170">D.C. Law 19-170</cite> substituted “January 1, 2014” for “January 1, 2013” wherever it appears in (b), (c)(1), and (e).</annotation>
          <annotation>The 2015 amendment by <cite doc="D.C. Law 20-155">D.C. Law 20-155</cite> substituted “January 1, 2016” for “January 1, 2014” throughout the section.</annotation>
        </annoGroup>
        <annoGroup>
          <heading>Temporary Legislation</heading>
          <annotation>For temporary (225 days) amendment of this section, see § 2(b) of the Microstamping Implementation Temporary Amendment Act of 2014 (<cite doc="D.C. Law 20-93">D.C. Law 20-93</cite>, March 11, 2014,  61 DCR 783).</annotation>
          <annotation>For temporary (225 days) amendment of this section, see § 2(b) of the Microstamping Implementation Temporary Amendment Act of 2016 (<cite doc="D.C. Law 21-93">D.C. Law 21-93</cite>, Mar. 23, 2015,  63 DCR 993).</annotation>
        </annoGroup>
        <annoGroup>
          <heading>Emergency Legislation</heading>
          <annotation>For temporary (90 day) addition, see § 3(m) of Firearms Registration Emergency Amendment Act of 2008 (D.C. Act 17-651, January 6, 2009,  56 DCR 911).</annotation>
          <annotation>For temporary (90 day) amendment of section, see § 502(f) of Public Safety Legislation Sixty-Day Layover Emergency Amendment Act of 2010 (D.C. Act 18-693, January 18, 2011,  58 DCR 640).</annotation>
          <annotation>For temporary (90 day) amendment of section, see § 502(f) of Public Safety Legislation Sixty-Day Layover Congressional Review Emergency Amendment Act of 2011 (D.C. Act 19-45, April 20, 2011,  58 DCR 3701).</annotation>
          <annotation>For temporary (90 day) amendment of section, see § 2(m) of Firearms Emergency Amendment Act of 2012 (D.C. Act 19-352, May 11, 2012,  59 DCR 5116).</annotation>
          <annotation>For temporary (90 day) amendment of section, see § 2(m) of the Firearms Amendments Congressional Review Emergency Amendment Act of 2012 (D.C. Act 19-394, July 18, 2012,  59 DCR 8694).</annotation>
          <annotation>For temporary amendment of (b), (c)(1) and (e), see § 2(m) of the Firearms Second Congressional Review Emergency Amendment Act of 2012 (D.C. Act 19-510, October 26, 2012,  59 DCR 12808).</annotation>
          <annotation>For temporary amendment of this section, see § 2(b) of the Microstamping Implementation Emergency Amendment Act of 2013 (D.C. Act 20-261, January 2, 2014,  61 DCR 324).</annotation>
          <annotation>For temporary (90 days) amendment of this section, see § 3022(b) of the  Fiscal Year 2015 Budget Support Emergency Act of 2014 (D.C. Act 20-377, July 14, 2014, 61 DCR 7598, 20 STAT 3696).</annotation>
          <annotation>For temporary (90 days) amendment of this section, see § 3022(b) of the  Fiscal Year 2015 Budget Support Congressional Review Emergency Act of 2014 (D.C. Act 20-449, October 10, 2014, 61 DCR 10915, 20 STAT 4188).</annotation>
          <annotation>For temporary (90 days) amendment of this section, see § 3022(b) of the  Fiscal Year 2015 Budget Support Second Congressional Review Emergency Act of 2014 (D.C. Act 20-566, January 9, 2015, 62 DCR 884, 21 STAT 541).</annotation>
          <annotation>For temporary (90 days) amendment of this section, see § 2(b) of the Microstamping Implementation Emergency Amendment Act of 2015 (D.C. Act 21-258, Jan. 6, 2016,  63 DCR 530).</annotation>
          <annotation>For temporary (90 days) amendment of this section, see § 2(b) of the Microstamping Implementation Congressional Review Emergency Amendment Act of 2016 (D.C. Act 21-329, Mar. 16, 2016,  63 DCR 4298).</annotation>
        </annoGroup>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section from-code="true">
      <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" path="|7|25|V"/>
      <num codify:value="7-2505.04">504</num>
      <heading>Prohibition on sale, transfer, ownership, or possession of designated unsafe pistol.</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>Except as provided in subsections (c), (d), or (e) of this section, beginning January 1, 2009, a pistol that is not on the California Roster of Handguns Certified for Sale, (also known as the California Roster of Handguns Determined Not to be Unsafe), pursuant to California Penal Code § 12131, as of January 1, 2009, may not be manufactured, sold, given, loaned, exposed for sale, transferred, or imported into the District of Columbia.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>Except as provided in subsection (e) of this section, beginning January 1, 2009, a pistol that is not on the California Roster of Handguns Certified for Sale as of January 1, 2009, may not be owned or possessed within the District of Columbia unless that pistol was lawfully owned and registered prior to January 1, 2009.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(c)</num>
        <text>Except as provided in subsection (e) of this section, a District of Columbia resident who is the owner of a pistol lawfully registered prior to January 1, 2009, that is not on the California Roster of Handguns Certified for Sale as of January 1, 2009, and who wishes to sell or transfer that pistol after January 1, 2009, may do so only by selling or transferring ownership of the handgun to a licensed firearm dealer.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(d)</num>
        <text>Except as provided in subsection (e) of this section, beginning January 1, 2009, a licensed firearm dealer who retains in the dealer’s inventory, or who otherwise lawfully acquires, any pistol not on the California Roster of Handguns Certified for Sale as of January 1, 2009, may sell, loan, give, trade, or otherwise transfer the firearm only to another licensed firearm dealer.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(e)</num>
        <text>This section shall not apply to:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>Firearms defined as curios or relics, as defined in 27 C.F.R. § 478.11;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>The purchase of any firearm by any law enforcement officer or agent of the District or the United States;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(3)</num>
          <text>Pistols that are designed expressly for use in Olympic target shooting events, as defined by rule;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(4)</num>
          <text>Certain single-action revolvers, as defined by rule;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(5)</num>
          <text>The sale, loan, or transfer of any firearm that is to be used solely as a prop during the course of a motion picture, television, or video production by an authorized participant in the course of making that production or event or by an authorized employee or agent of the entity producing that production or event;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(6)</num>
          <text>The temporary transfer of a lawfully owned and registered firearm for the purposes of cleaning, repair, or servicing of the firearm by a licensed firearm dealer; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(7)</num>
          <text>The possession of a firearm by a non-resident of the District of Columbia while temporarily traveling through the District; provided, that the firearm shall be transported in accordance with § <cite path="§22-4504.02">22-4504.02</cite>.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(f)</num>
        <text>The Chief shall review any additions or deletions to the California Roster of Handguns Certified for Sale at least annually. For purposes of District law, the Chief is authorized to revise, by rule, the roster of handguns determined not to be unsafe prescribed by subsection (a) of this section and to prescribe by rule the firearms permissible pursuant to subsection (e) of this section.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(g)</num>
        <text>The Chief shall provide to the licensed firearm dealers within the District information about how to obtain a copy of the California Roster of Handguns Certified for Sale and any revisions to it made the Chief.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annoGroup>
          <heading>History</heading>
          <annotation doc="D.C. Law 1-85">Sept. 24, 1976, D.C. Law 1-85, title V, § 504</annotation>
          <annotation doc="D.C. Law 17-372">as added Mar. 31, 2009, D.C. Law 17-372, § 3(m), 56 DCR 1365</annotation>
        </annoGroup>
        <annoGroup>
          <heading>Section References</heading>
          <annotation>This section is referenced in § <cite path="§7-2502.02">7-2502.02</cite>.</annotation>
        </annoGroup>
        <annoGroup>
          <heading>Emergency Legislation</heading>
          <annotation>For temporary (90 day) addition, see § 3(m) of Firearms Registration Emergency Amendment Act of 2008 (D.C. Act 17-651, January 6, 2009,  56 DCR 911).</annotation>
        </annoGroup>
      </annotations>
    </section>
  </container>
  <container>
    <prefix>Title</prefix>
    <num>VI</num>
    <section from-code="true">
      <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" path="|7|25|VI"/>
      <num codify:value="7-2506.01">601</num>
      <heading>Persons permitted to possess ammunition.</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>No person shall possess ammunition in the District of Columbia unless:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>He is a licensed dealer pursuant to subchapter IV of this unit;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>He is an officer, agent, or employee of the District of Columbia or the United States of America, on duty and acting within the scope of his duties when possessing such ammunition;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(3)</num>
          <text>He is the holder of a valid registration certificate for a firearm pursuant to subchapter II of this chapter; except, that no such person shall possess one or more restricted pistol bullets;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(4)</num>
          <text>He holds an ammunition collector’s certificate on September 24, 1976; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(5)</num>
          <text>He temporarily possesses ammunition while participating in a firearms training and safety class conducted by a firearms instructor.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>No person in the District shall possess, sell, or transfer any large capacity ammunition feeding device regardless of whether the device is attached to a firearm. For the purposes of this subsection, the term “large capacity ammunition feeding device” means a magazine, belt, drum, feed strip, or similar device that has a capacity of, or that can be readily restored or converted to accept, more than 10 rounds of ammunition. The term “large capacity ammunition feeding device” shall not include an attached tubular device designed to accept, and capable of operating only with, .22 caliber rimfire ammunition.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annoGroup>
          <heading>History</heading>
          <annotation doc="D.C. Law 1-85">Sept. 24, 1976, D.C. Law 1-85, title VI, § 601, 23 DCR 2464</annotation>
          <annotation doc="D.C. Law 2-62">Mar. 16, 1978, D.C. Law 2-62, § 2, 24 DCR 5780</annotation>
          <annotation doc="D.C. Law 5-19">Aug. 2, 1983, D.C. Law 5-19, § 4, 30 DCR 3328</annotation>
          <annotation doc="D.C. Law 17-372">Mar. 31, 2009, D.C. Law 17-372, § 3(n), 56 DCR 1365</annotation>
          <annotation doc="D.C. Law 19-170">Sept. 29, 2012, D.C. Law 19-170, § 2(n), 59 DCR 5691</annotation>
          <annotation doc="D.C. Law 19-295">Apr. 27, 2013, D.C. Law 19-295, § 2(c), 60 DCR 2623</annotation>
        </annoGroup>
        <annoGroup>
          <heading>Section References</heading>
          <annotation>This section is referenced in § <cite path="§7-2507.06">7-2507.06</cite> and § <cite path="§7-2508.01">7-2508.01</cite>.</annotation>
        </annoGroup>
        <annoGroup>
          <heading>Prior Codifications</heading>
          <annotation>1981 Ed., § 6-2361.</annotation>
          <annotation>1973 Ed., § 6-1861.</annotation>
        </annoGroup>
        <annoGroup>
          <heading>Effect of Amendments</heading>
          <annotation><cite doc="D.C. Law 17-372">D.C. Law 17-372</cite> designated subsec. (a); and added subsec. (b).</annotation>
          <annotation>The 2012 amendment by <cite doc="D.C. Law 19-170">D.C. Law 19-170</cite> substituted “pursuant to subchapter II of this chapter” for “of the same gauge or caliber as the ammunition he possesses” in (a)(3); added (a)(5); and made a related change.</annotation>
          <annotation>The 2013 amendment by <cite doc="D.C. Law 19-295">D.C. Law 19-295</cite> substituted “possess one or more restricted pistol bullets” for “possess restricted pistol bullets” in (a)(3).</annotation>
        </annoGroup>
        <annoGroup>
          <heading>Emergency Legislation</heading>
          <annotation>For temporary (90 day) amendment of section, see § 2(d) of Second Firearms Control Emergency Amendment Act of 2008 (D.C. Act 17-502, September 16, 2008,  55 DCR 9904).</annotation>
          <annotation>For temporary (90 day) amendment of section, see § 2(d) of Second Firearms Control Congressional Review Emergency Amendment Act of 2008 (D.C. Act 17-601, December 12, 2008,  56 DCR 9).</annotation>
          <annotation>For temporary (90 day) amendment of section, see § 3(n) of Firearms Registration Emergency Amendment Act of 2008 (D.C. Act 17-651, January 6, 2009,  56 DCR 911).</annotation>
          <annotation>For temporary (90 day) amendment of section, see § 2(n) of Firearms Emergency Amendment Act of 2012 (D.C. Act 19-352, May 11, 2012,  59 DCR 5116).</annotation>
          <annotation>For temporary (90 day) amendment of section, see § 2(n) of the Firearms Amendments Congressional Review Emergency Amendment Act of 2012 (D.C. Act 19-394, July 18, 2012,  59 DCR 8694).</annotation>
          <annotation>For temporary amendment of (a), see § 2(n) of the Firearms Second Congressional Review Emergency Amendment Act of 2012 (D.C. Act 19-510, October 26, 2012,  59 DCR 12808).</annotation>
        </annoGroup>
      </annotations>
    </section>
  </container>
  <container>
    <prefix>Title</prefix>
    <num>VII</num>
    <section from-code="true">
      <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" path="|7|25|VII"/>
      <num codify:value="7-2507.01">701</num>
      <heading>Security mortgages, deposits, or pawns with firearms, destructive devices, or ammunition prohibited; loan or rental of firearms, destructive devices, or ammunition prohibited.</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>No firearm, destructive device, or ammunition shall be security for, or be taken or received by way of any mortgage, deposit, pledge, or pawn.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>No person may loan, borrow, give, or rent to or from another person, any firearm, destructive device, or ammunition.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annoGroup>
          <heading>History</heading>
          <annotation doc="D.C. Law 1-85">Sept. 24, 1976, D.C. Law 1-85, title VII, § 701, 23 DCR 2464</annotation>
        </annoGroup>
        <annoGroup>
          <heading>Prior Codifications</heading>
          <annotation>1981 Ed., § 6-2371.</annotation>
          <annotation>1973 Ed., § 6-1871.</annotation>
        </annoGroup>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section from-code="true">
      <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" path="|7|25|VII"/>
      <num codify:value="7-2507.02">702</num>
      <heading>Responsibilities regarding storage of firearms.</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>It shall be the policy of the District of Columbia that each registrant should keep any firearm in his or her possession unloaded and either disassembled or secured by a trigger lock, gun safe, locked box, or other secure device.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>No person shall store or keep any firearm on any premises under his control if he knows or reasonably should know that a minor is likely to gain access to the firearm without the permission of the parent or guardian of the minor unless such person:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>Keeps the firearm in a securely locked box, secured container, or in a location which a reasonable person would believe to be secure; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>Carries the firearm on his person or within such close proximity that he can readily retrieve and use it as if he carried it on his person.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(c)</num>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>A person who violates subsection (b) of this section is guilty of criminally negligent storage of a firearm and, except as provided in paragraph (2) of this subsection, shall be fined not more than $1,000, imprisoned not more than 180 days, or both.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>A person who violates subsection (b) of this section and the minor causes injury or death to himself or another shall be fined not more than $5,000, imprisoned not more than 5 years, or both.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(3)</num>
          <text>The provisions of paragraphs (1) and (2) of this subsection shall not apply if the minor obtains the firearm as a result of an unlawful entry or burglary to any premises by any person.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(c-1)</num>
        <text>The provisions of § <cite path="§7-2507.06">7-2507.06</cite> shall not apply to this section.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(d)</num>
        <text>For the purposes of this section, the term “minor” shall mean a person under the age of 18 years.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annoGroup>
          <heading>History</heading>
          <annotation doc="D.C. Law 1-85">Sept. 24, 1976, D.C. Law 1-85, title VII, § 702, 23 DCR 2464</annotation>
          <annotation doc="D.C. Law 17-372">Mar. 31, 2009, D.C. Law 17-372, § 3(o), 56 DCR 1365</annotation>
          <annotation doc="D.C. Law 19-170">Sept. 29, 2012, D.C. Law 19-170, § 2(o), 59 DCR 5691</annotation>
        </annoGroup>
        <annoGroup>
          <heading>Section References</heading>
          <annotation>This section is referenced in § <cite path="§7-2502.03">7-2502.03</cite> and § <cite path="§7-2507.06">7-2507.06</cite>.</annotation>
        </annoGroup>
        <annoGroup>
          <heading>Prior Codifications</heading>
          <annotation>1981 Ed., § 6-2372.</annotation>
          <annotation>1973 Ed., § 6-1872.</annotation>
        </annoGroup>
        <annoGroup>
          <heading>Effect of Amendments</heading>
          <annotation><cite doc="D.C. Law 17-372">D.C. Law 17-372</cite> rewrote the section, which had read as follows: “Except for law enforcement personnel described in § <cite path="§7-2502.01">7-2502.01</cite>(b)(1), each registrant shall keep any firearm in his possession unloaded and disassembled or bound by a trigger lock or similar device unless such firearm is kept at his place of business, or while being used for lawful recreational purposes within the District of Columbia.”</annotation>
          <annotation>The 2012 amendment by <cite doc="D.C. Law 19-170">D.C. Law 19-170</cite> added “penalties” in the section heading; and added (c-1).</annotation>
        </annoGroup>
        <annoGroup>
          <heading>Emergency Legislation</heading>
          <annotation>For temporary (90 day) amendment, see § 2(c) of Firearms Control Emergency Amendment Act of 2008 (D.C. Act 17-422, July 16, 2008,  55 DCR 8237).</annotation>
          <annotation>For temporary (90 day) amendment of section, see § 2(e) of Second Firearms Control Emergency Amendment Act of 2008 (D.C. Act 17-502, September 16, 2008,  55 DCR 9904).</annotation>
          <annotation>For temporary (90 day) repeal of D.C. Act 17-422, see § 5 of Second Firearms Control Emergency Amendment Act of 2008 (D.C. Act 17-502, September 16, 2008,  55 DCR 9904).</annotation>
          <annotation>For temporary (90 day) amendment of section, see §§ 2(e) and 4 of Second Firearms Control Congressional Review Emergency Amendment Act of 2008 (D.C. Act 17-601, December 12, 2008,  56 DCR 9).</annotation>
          <annotation>For temporary (90 day) amendment of section, see § 3(o) of Firearms Registration Emergency Amendment Act of 2008 (D.C. Act 17-651, January 6, 2009,  56 DCR 911).</annotation>
          <annotation>For temporary (90 day) amendment of section, see § 2(o) of Firearms Emergency Amendment Act of 2012 (D.C. Act 19-352, May 11, 2012,  59 DCR 5116).</annotation>
          <annotation>For temporary (90 day) amendment of section, see § 2(o) of the Firearms Amendments Congressional Review Emergency Amendment Act of 2012 (D.C. Act 19-394, July 18, 2012,  59 DCR 8694).</annotation>
          <annotation>For temporary addition of (c-1) and amendment of section heading, see § 2(o) of the Firearms Second Congressional Review Emergency Amendment Act of 2012 (D.C. Act 19-510, October 26, 2012,  59 DCR 12808).</annotation>
        </annoGroup>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section from-code="true">
      <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" path="|7|25|VII"/>
      <num codify:value="7-2507.03">703</num>
      <heading>Firing ranges.</heading>
      <text>Any person operating a firing range in the District, shall in addition to any other requirement imposed by law, register with the Chief, on a form prescribed by him, which shall include the business name of the range, the location, the names and home addresses of the owners and principal officers, the types of weapons fired there, the number and types of weapons normally stored there, the days and hours of operation, and such other information as the Chief shall require.</text>
      <annotations>
        <annoGroup>
          <heading>History</heading>
          <annotation doc="D.C. Law 1-85">Sept. 24, 1976, D.C. Law 1-85, title VII, § 703, 23 DCR 2464</annotation>
        </annoGroup>
        <annoGroup>
          <heading>Prior Codifications</heading>
          <annotation>1981 Ed., § 6-2373.</annotation>
          <annotation>1973 Ed., § 6-1873.</annotation>
        </annoGroup>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section from-code="true">
      <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" path="|7|25|VII"/>
      <num codify:value="7-2507.04">704</num>
      <heading>False information; forgery or alteration.</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>It shall be unlawful for any person purchasing any firearm or ammunition, or applying for any registration certificate or dealer’s license under this unit, or in giving any information pursuant to the requirements of this unit, to knowingly give false information or offer false evidence of identity.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>It shall be unlawful for anyone to forge or alter any application, registration certificate, or dealer’s license submitted, retained or issued under this unit.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annoGroup>
          <heading>History</heading>
          <annotation doc="D.C. Law 1-85">Sept. 24, 1976, D.C. Law 1-85, title VII, § 704, 23 DCR 2464</annotation>
        </annoGroup>
        <annoGroup>
          <heading>Section References</heading>
          <annotation>This section is referenced in § <cite path="§7-2502.11">7-2502.11</cite> and § <cite path="§7-2504.09">7-2504.09</cite>.</annotation>
        </annoGroup>
        <annoGroup>
          <heading>Prior Codifications</heading>
          <annotation>1981 Ed., § 6-2374.</annotation>
          <annotation>1973 Ed., § 6-1874.</annotation>
        </annoGroup>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section from-code="true">
      <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" path="|7|25|VII"/>
      <num codify:value="7-2507.05">705</num>
      <heading>Voluntary surrender of firearms, destructive devices, or ammunition; immunity from prosecution; determination of evidentiary value of firearm.</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>If a person or organization within the District voluntarily and peaceably delivers and abandons to the Chief any firearm, destructive device or ammunition at any time, such delivery shall preclude the arrest and prosecution of such person on a charge of violating any provision of this unit with respect to the firearm, destructive device, or ammunition voluntarily delivered. Delivery under this section may be made at any police district, station, or central headquarters, or by summoning a police officer to the person’s residence or place of business. Every firearm and destructive device to be delivered and abandoned to the Chief under this section shall be transported in accordance with § <cite path="§22-4504.02">22-4504.02</cite> and, in the case of delivery to a police facility, the package shall be carried in open view. No person who delivers and abandons a firearm, destructive device, or ammunition under this section, shall be required to furnish identification, photographs, or fingerprints. No amount of money shall be paid for any firearm, destructive device, or ammunition delivered and abandoned under this section.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>Whenever any firearm, destructive device, or any ammunition is surrendered under this section or pursuant to § <cite path="§7-2502.10">7-2502.10</cite>(c)(1), the Chief shall inquire of the United States Attorney and the Corporation Counsel for the District whether such firearm is needed as evidence; provided, that if the same is not needed as evidence, it shall be destroyed.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annoGroup>
          <heading>History</heading>
          <annotation doc="D.C. Law 1-85">Sept. 24, 1976, D.C. Law 1-85, title VII, § 705, 23 DCR 2464</annotation>
          <annotation doc="D.C. Law 17-372">Mar. 31, 2009, D.C. Law 17-372, § 3(p), 56 DCR 1365</annotation>
        </annoGroup>
        <annoGroup>
          <heading>Cross References</heading>
          <annotation>Ammunition feeding devices transfers, prohibition, see § <cite path="§5-133.16">5-133.16</cite>.</annotation>
        </annoGroup>
        <annoGroup>
          <heading>Section References</heading>
          <annotation>This section is referenced in § <cite path="§5-133.16">5-133.16</cite>, § <cite path="§7-2502.10">7-2502.10</cite>, § <cite path="§7-2504.06">7-2504.06</cite>, and § <cite path="§7-2505.01">7-2505.01</cite>.</annotation>
        </annoGroup>
        <annoGroup>
          <heading>Prior Codifications</heading>
          <annotation>1981 Ed., § 6-2375.</annotation>
          <annotation>1973 Ed., § 6-1875.</annotation>
        </annoGroup>
        <annoGroup>
          <heading>Effect of Amendments</heading>
          <annotation><cite doc="D.C. Law 17-372">D.C. Law 17-372</cite>, in subsec. (a), substituted “shall be transported in accordance with § 4504.02,” for “shall be unloaded and securely wrapped in a package”.</annotation>
        </annoGroup>
        <annoGroup>
          <heading>Temporary Amendment of Section</heading>
          <annotation>For temporary (225 day) provisions prohibiting the transfer by the Metropolitan Police Department of ammunition feeding devices, see § 2 of Prohibition on the Transfer of Firearms Temporary Act of 1995 (<cite doc="D.C. Law 11-35">D.C. Law 11-35</cite>, September 8, 1995, law notification  42 DCR 5304).</annotation>
        </annoGroup>
        <annoGroup>
          <heading>Emergency Legislation</heading>
          <annotation>For temporary prohibition on the transfer by the Metropolitan Police Department of any ammunition feeding device, see § 2 of the Prohibition on the Transfer of Firearms Emergency Act of 1995 (D.C. Act 11-58, May 18, 1995,  42 DCR 2574).</annotation>
          <annotation>For temporary (90 day) amendment of section, see § 3(p) of Firearms Registration Emergency Amendment Act of 2008 (D.C. Act 17-651, January 6, 2009,  56 DCR 911).</annotation>
        </annoGroup>
        <annoGroup>
          <heading>Editor's Notes</heading>
          <annotation>Prohibition on transfer of ammunition feeding devices: For provisions prohibiting the transfer by the Metropolitan Police Department of ammunition feeding devices, see § <cite path="§4-191">4-191</cite>.</annotation>
        </annoGroup>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section from-code="true">
      <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" path="|7|25|VII"/>
      <num codify:value="7-2507.06">706</num>
      <heading>Penalties.</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>Except as provided in §§ <cite path="§7-2502.05">7-2502.05</cite>, <cite path="§7-2502.08">7-2502.08</cite>, <cite path="§7-2507.02">7-2507.02</cite>, <cite path="§7-2508.07">7-2508.07</cite>, and subchapter IX of this chapter [§ <cite path="§7-2509.01">7-2509.01</cite> et seq.], any person convicted of a violation of any provision of this unit shall be fined not more than the amount set forth in § <cite path="§22-3571.01">22-3571.01</cite> or imprisoned for not more than 1 year, or both; except that:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>A person who knowingly or intentionally sells, transfers, or distributes a firearm, destructive device, or ammunition to a person under 18 years of age shall be fined not more than the amount set forth in § <cite path="§22-3571.01">22-3571.01</cite> or imprisoned for not more than 10 years, or both.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <para>
            <num>(A)</num>
            <text>Except as provided in subparagraph (B) of this paragraph, any person who is convicted a second time for possessing an unregistered firearm shall be fined not more than the amount set forth in § <cite path="§22-3571.01">22-3571.01</cite> or imprisoned not more than 5 years, or both.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(B)</num>
            <text>A person who in the person’s dwelling place, place of business, or on other land possessed by the person, possesses a pistol, or firearm that could otherwise be registered, shall be fined not more than the amount set forth in § <cite path="§22-3571.01">22-3571.01</cite> or imprisoned not more than 1 year, or both.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(3)</num>
          <para>
            <num>(A)</num>
            <text>A person convicted of possessing more than one restricted pistol bullet in violation of § <cite path="§7-2506.01">7-2506.01</cite>(a)(3) may be sentenced to imprisonment for a term not to exceed 10 years and shall be sentenced to imprisonment for a mandatory-minimum term of not less than 1 year and shall not be released from prison or granted probation or suspension of sentence prior to serving the mandatory-minimum sentence, and, in addition, may be fined not more than the amount set forth in § <cite path="§22-3571.01">22-3571.01</cite>.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(B)</num>
            <text>A person convicted of possessing a single restricted pistol bullet in violation of § <cite path="§7-2506.01">7-2506.01</cite>(a)(3) shall be fined not more than the amount set forth in § <cite path="§22-3571.01">22-3571.01</cite> or imprisoned for not more than 1 year, or both.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>For the following violations of this unit, the prosecution may, in the operation of its discretion, offer an administrative disposition whereby a person may immediately resolve his or her case upon payment of a fine, in an amount set by the Board of Judges of the Superior Court of the District of Columbia; provided, that the person is not concurrently charged with another criminal offense arising from the same event, other than an offense pursuant to § <cite path="§7-2502.01">7-2502.01</cite> or § <cite path="§7-2506.01">7-2506.01</cite>:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(A)</num>
            <text>Possession of an unregistered firearm pursuant to § <cite path="§7-2502.01">7-2502.01</cite>;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(B)</num>
            <text>Unlawful possession of ammunition (but not possession of more than one restricted pistol bullet) pursuant to § <cite path="§7-2506.01">7-2506.01</cite>; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(C)</num>
            <text>Possession of a single restricted pistol bullet pursuant to § <cite path="§7-2507.06">7-2507.06</cite>(a)(3)(B); provided, that the person did not also possess a firearm at the time of arrest.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>In determining whether to offer an administrative disposition pursuant to this subsection, the prosecution, in the operation of its discretion, may consider, among other factors, whether at the time of his or her arrest, the person was a resident of the District of Columbia and whether the person had knowledge of § <cite path="§7-2502.01">7-2502.01</cite>, § <cite path="§7-2506.01">7-2506.01</cite>, or § <cite path="§7-2507.06">7-2507.06</cite>(a)(3)(B).</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(3)</num>
          <text>An administrative disposition pursuant to this subsection is not a conviction of a crime and shall not be equated to a criminal conviction. The fact that a person resolved a charge through an administrative disposition pursuant to this subsection may not be relied upon by any court of the District of Columbia or any agency of the District of Columbia in any subsequent criminal, civil, or administrative proceeding or administrative action to impose any sanction, penalty, enhanced sentence, or civil disability.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(4)</num>
          <text>At the time of the prosecution’s offer of an administrative disposition, the person may elect to proceed with the criminal case in lieu of an administrative disposition.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(5)</num>
          <text>The Mayor, pursuant to subchapter I of Chapter 5 of Title 2 [§ <cite path="§2-501">2-501</cite> et seq.], may issue rules to implement the provisions of this subsection. The rules may provide procedures and criteria to be used in determining when the prosecution, in the operation of its discretion, may offer the option of an administrative disposition pursuant to this subsection.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annoGroup>
          <heading>History</heading>
          <annotation doc="D.C. Law 1-85">Sept. 24, 1976, D.C. Law 1-85, title VII, § 706, 23 DCR 2464</annotation>
          <annotation doc="D.C. Law 3-147">Mar. 5, 1981, D.C. Law 3-147, § 2, 27 DCR 4882</annotation>
          <annotation doc="D.C. Law 10-151">Aug. 20, 1994, D.C. Law 10-151, § 301, 41 DCR 2608</annotation>
          <annotation doc="D.C. Law 16-306">Apr. 24, 2007, D.C. Law 16-306, § 205, 53 DCR 8610</annotation>
          <annotation doc="D.C. Law 19-170">Sept. 29, 2012, D.C. Law 19-170, § 2(p), 59 DCR 5691</annotation>
          <annotation doc="D.C. Law 19-295">Apr. 27, 2013, D.C. Law 19-295, § 2(d), 60 DCR 2623</annotation>
          <annotation doc="D.C. Law 20-279">June 16, 2015, D.C. Law 20-279, § 2(e), 62 DCR 1944</annotation>
        </annoGroup>
        <annoGroup>
          <heading>Section References</heading>
          <annotation>This section is referenced in § <cite path="§7-2502.03">7-2502.03</cite>, § <cite path="§7-2502.08">7-2502.08</cite>, § <cite path="§7-2503.01">7-2503.01</cite>, § <cite path="§7-2507.02">7-2507.02</cite>, and § <cite path="§7-2507.08">7-2507.08</cite>.</annotation>
        </annoGroup>
        <annoGroup>
          <heading>Prior Codifications</heading>
          <annotation>1981 Ed., § 6-2376.</annotation>
          <annotation>1973 Ed., § 6-1876.</annotation>
        </annoGroup>
        <annoGroup>
          <heading>Effect of Amendments</heading>
          <annotation><cite doc="D.C. Law 16-306">D.C. Law 16-306</cite> added par. (3).</annotation>
          <annotation>The 2012 amendment by <cite doc="D.C. Law 19-170">D.C. Law 19-170</cite> added “Except as provided in §§ <cite path="§7-2502.05">7-2502.05</cite>, <cite path="§7-2502.08">7-2502.08</cite>, <cite path="§7-2507.02">7-2507.02</cite>, and <cite path="§7-2508.07">7-2508.07</cite>,” in the introductory language.</annotation>
          <annotation>The 2013 amendment by <cite doc="D.C. Law 19-295">D.C. Law 19-295</cite> designated the existing provisions as (a); substituted “not more than the amount set forth in § <cite path="§22-3571.01">22-3571.01</cite>” for “not more than $1,000” in the introductory language of (a) and in (a)(2)(B); substituted “not more than the amount set forth in § <cite path="§22-3571.01">22-3571.01</cite>” for “not more than $10,000” in (a)(1); substituted “not more than the amount set forth in § <cite path="§22-3571.01">22-3571.01</cite>” for “not more than $5,000” in (a)(2)(A); rewrote (a)(3); and added (b).</annotation>
          <annotation>The 2015 amendment by <cite doc="D.C. Law 20-279">D.C. Law 20-279</cite> substituted “§§  <cite path="§7-2502.05">7-2502.05</cite>, <cite path="§7-2502.08">7-2502.08</cite>, <cite path="§7-2507.02">7-2507.02</cite>, <cite path="§7-2508.07">7-2508.07</cite>, and subchapter IX of this chapter” for “7-2502.05, 7-2502.08, 7-2507.02, and 7-2508.07” in the introductory paragraph of (a).</annotation>
        </annoGroup>
        <annoGroup>
          <heading>Temporary Legislation</heading>
          <annotation>For temporary (225 days) amendment of this section, see § 2(d) of the License to Carry a Pistol Temporary Amendment Act of 2014 (<cite doc="D.C. Law 20-169">D.C. Law 20-169</cite>, May 5, 2015, 61 DCR 11814).</annotation>
        </annoGroup>
        <annoGroup>
          <heading>Emergency Legislation</heading>
          <annotation>For temporary amendment of section, see § 301 of the Omnibus Criminal Justice Reform Emergency Amendment Act of 1994 (D.C. Act 10-255, June 22, 1994,  41 DCR 4286).</annotation>
          <annotation>For temporary (90 day) amendment of section, see § 205 of Omnibus Public Safety Emergency Amendment Act of 2006 (D.C. Act 16-445, July 19, 2006,  53 DCR 6443).</annotation>
          <annotation>For temporary (90 day) amendment of section, see § 205 of Omnibus Public Safety Congressional Review Emergency Amendment Act of 2006 (D.C. Act 16-490, October 18, 2006,  53 DCR 8686).</annotation>
          <annotation>For temporary (90 day) amendment of section, see § 205 of Omnibus Public Safety Congressional Review Emergency Amendment Act of 2007 (D.C. Act 17-10, January 16, 2007,  54 DCR 1479).</annotation>
          <annotation>For temporary (90 day) amendment of section, see § 205 of Omnibus Public Safety Second Congressional Review Emergency Amendment Act of 2007 (D.C. Act 17-25, April 19, 2007,  54 DCR 4036).</annotation>
          <annotation>For temporary (90 day) amendment of section, see § 2(p) of Firearms Emergency Amendment Act of 2012 (D.C. Act 19-352, May 11, 2012,  59 DCR 5116).</annotation>
          <annotation>For temporary (90 day) amendment of section, see § 2(o) of the Firearms Amendments Congressional Review Emergency Amendment Act of 2012 (D.C. Act 19-394, July 18, 2012,  59 DCR 8694).</annotation>
          <annotation>For temporary amendment of section, see § 2(p) of the Firearms Second Congressional Review Emergency Amendment Act of 2012 (D.C. Act 19-510, October 26, 2012,  59 DCR 12808).</annotation>
          <annotation>For temporary (90 days) amendment of this section, see §§ 410 and 501(b) of the Criminal Fine Proportionality Emergency Act of 2013 (D.C. Act 20-45, April 1, 2013,  60 DCR 5400, 20 DCSTAT 1300).</annotation>
          <annotation>For temporary (90 days) amendment of this section, see § 2(d) of the License to Carry a Pistol Emergency Amendment Act of 2014 (D.C. Act 20-447, Oct. 7, 2014, 61 DCR 10765, 20 STAT 4175).</annotation>
          <annotation>For temporary (90 days) repeal of emergency D.C. Act 20-447, § 4, the act’s applicability clause, see § 2 of the License to Carry a Pistol Clarification Emergency Amendment Act of 2014 (D.C. Act 20-448, Oct. 7, 2014,  61 DCR 10777, 20 STAT 4187).</annotation>
          <annotation>For temporary (90 days) amendment of this section, see § 2(e) of the License to Carry a Pistol Second Emergency Amendment Act of 2014 (D.C. Act 20-564, Jan. 6, 2015, 62 DCR 866, 21 STAT 527).</annotation>
          <annotation>For temporary (90 days) repeal of emergency D.C. Act 20-447, see § 4(b) of the License to Carry a Pistol Second Emergency Amendment Act of 2014 (D.C. Act 20-564, Jan. 6, 2015,  62 DCR 866, 21 STAT 527).</annotation>
          <annotation>For temporary (90 days) repeal of temporary D.C. Act 20-169, see § 4(c) of the License to Carry a Pistol Second Emergency Amendment Act of 2014 (D.C. Act 20-564, Jan. 6, 2015,  62 DCR 866, 21 STAT 527).</annotation>
          <annotation>For temporary (90 days) amendment of this section, see § 2(e) of the License to Carry a Pistol Congressional Review Emergency Amendment Act of 2015 (D.C. Act 21-74, June 4, 2015,  62 DCR 8242, 21 DCSTAT 1451).</annotation>
        </annoGroup>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section from-code="true">
      <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" path="|7|25|VII"/>
      <num codify:value="7-2507.06a">706a</num>
      <heading>Seizure and forfeiture of conveyances.</heading>
      <text>Any conveyance in which a person or persons transport, possess, or conceal any firearm, as that term is defined in § <cite path="§7-2501.01">7-2501.01</cite>, or in any manner use to facilitate a violation of § <cite path="§7-2502.02">7-2502.02</cite> or § <cite path="§22-4503">22-4503</cite> or § <cite path="§22-4504">22-4504</cite>, is subject to forfeiture pursuant to the standards and procedures set forth in <cite doc="D.C. Law 20-278">D.C. Law 20-278</cite>.</text>
      <annotations>
        <annoGroup>
          <heading>History</heading>
          <annotation doc="D.C. Law 1-85">Sept. 24, 1976, D.C. Law 1-85, title VII, § 706a</annotation>
          <annotation doc="D.C. Law 11-273">as added June 3, 1997, D.C. Law 11-273, § 2, 43 DCR 6168</annotation>
          <annotation doc="D.C. Law 11-274">June 3, 1997, D.C. Law 11-274, § 19(b), 44 DCR 1232</annotation>
          <annotation doc="D.C. Law 20-278">June 16, 2015, D.C. Law 20-278, § 302, 62 DCR 1920</annotation>
        </annoGroup>
        <annoGroup>
          <heading>Prior Codifications</heading>
          <annotation>1981 Ed., § 6-2376.1.</annotation>
        </annoGroup>
        <annoGroup>
          <heading>Effect of Amendments</heading>
          <annotation>The 2015 amendment by <cite doc="D.C. Law 20-278">D.C. Law 20-278</cite> rewrote the section.</annotation>
        </annoGroup>
        <annoGroup>
          <heading>Emergency Legislation</heading>
          <annotation>For temporary addition of section, see § 2 of the Zero Tolerance for Guns Emergency Amendment Act of 1996 (D.C. Act 11-390, August 26, 1996,  43 DCR 4986), § 2 of the Zero Tolerance for Guns Congressional Adjournment Emergency Amendment Act of 1996 (D.C. Act 11-436, December 4, 1996,  43 DCR 6651), and § 2 of the Zero Tolerance for Guns Congressional Review Emergency Amendment Act of 1997 (D.C. Act 12-35, March 11, 1997,  44 DCR 1928).</annotation>
        </annoGroup>
        <annoGroup>
          <heading>Editor's Notes</heading>
          <annotation><cite doc="D.C. Law 20-278">D.C. Law 20-278</cite>, referred to in this section, enacted Chapter 3 of Title 41 (§ <cite path="§41-301">41-301</cite> et seq.), made amendments to the criminal offenses in §§ <cite path="§48-901.02">48-901.02</cite> and <cite path="§48-905.02">48-905.02</cite>, and made conforming amendments to §§ <cite path="§7-2507.06a">7-2507.06a</cite>, <cite path="§8-905">8-905</cite>, <cite path="§22-902">22-902</cite>, <cite path="§22-1705">22-1705</cite>, <cite path="§22-2723">22-2723</cite>, <cite path="§32-1343">32-1343</cite>, <cite path="§48-905.03">48-905.03</cite>, and <cite path="§50-1501.04">50-1501.04</cite>.</annotation>
        </annoGroup>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section from-code="true">
      <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" path="|7|25|VII"/>
      <num codify:value="7-2507.07">707</num>
      <heading>Public education program.</heading>
      <text>The Chief shall carry on a suitable publicity program designed to inform the citizens of the District of the provisions of this unit and the rights and obligations created by it.</text>
      <annotations>
        <annoGroup>
          <heading>History</heading>
          <annotation doc="D.C. Law 1-85">Sept. 24, 1976, D.C. Law 1-85, title VII, § 707, 23 DCR 2464</annotation>
        </annoGroup>
        <annoGroup>
          <heading>Prior Codifications</heading>
          <annotation>1981 Ed., § 6-2377.</annotation>
          <annotation>1973 Ed., § 6-1877.</annotation>
        </annoGroup>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section from-code="true">
      <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" path="|7|25|VII"/>
      <num codify:value="7-2507.08">709</num>
      <heading>Construction of unit.</heading>
      <text>Nothing in this unit shall be construed, or applied to necessarily require, or excuse noncompliance with any provision of any federal law. This unit and the penalties prescribed in § <cite path="§7-2507.06">7-2507.06</cite>, for violations of this unit, shall not supersede but shall supplement all statutes of the District and the United States in which similar conduct is prohibited or regulated.</text>
      <annotations>
        <annoGroup>
          <heading>History</heading>
          <annotation doc="D.C. Law 1-85">Sept. 24, 1976, D.C. Law 1-85, title VII, § 709, 23 DCR 2464</annotation>
          <annotation doc="D.C. Law 2-62">Mar. 16, 1978, D.C. Law 2-62, § 2, 24 DCR 5780</annotation>
        </annoGroup>
        <annoGroup>
          <heading>Prior Codifications</heading>
          <annotation>1981 Ed., § 6-2378.</annotation>
          <annotation>1973 Ed., § 6-1878.</annotation>
        </annoGroup>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section from-code="true">
      <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" path="|7|25|VII"/>
      <num codify:value="7-2507.09">710</num>
      <heading>Applicability of District of Columbia Administrative Procedure Act.</heading>
      <text>The provisions of the District of Columbia Administrative Procedure Act (§ <cite path="§2-501">2-501</cite> et seq.) shall apply to each proceeding, decision, or other administrative action specified in this unit, unless otherwise specifically provided.</text>
      <annotations>
        <annoGroup>
          <heading>History</heading>
          <annotation doc="D.C. Law 1-85">Sept. 24, 1976, D.C. Law 1-85, title VII, § 710, 23 DCR 2464</annotation>
        </annoGroup>
        <annoGroup>
          <heading>Prior Codifications</heading>
          <annotation>1981 Ed., § 6-2379.</annotation>
          <annotation>1973 Ed., § 6-1879.</annotation>
        </annoGroup>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section from-code="true">
      <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" path="|7|25|VII"/>
      <num codify:value="7-2507.10">711</num>
      <heading>Severability.</heading>
      <text>If any provision of this unit or the application thereof to any person or circumstance is held invalid, the remainder of this unit and the application of such provision to other persons not similarly situated or to other circumstances shall not be affected thereby.</text>
      <annotations>
        <annoGroup>
          <heading>History</heading>
          <annotation doc="D.C. Law 1-85">Sept. 24, 1976, D.C. Law 1-85, title VII, § 711, 23 DCR 2464</annotation>
        </annoGroup>
        <annoGroup>
          <heading>Prior Codifications</heading>
          <annotation>1981 Ed., § 6-2380.</annotation>
          <annotation>1973 Ed., § 6-1880.</annotation>
        </annoGroup>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section from-code="true">
      <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" path="|7|25|VII"/>
      <num codify:value="7-2507.11">712</num>
      <heading>Rules.</heading>
      <text>The Chief, pursuant to subchapter I of Chapter 5 of Title 2 [§ <cite path="§2-501">2-501</cite> et seq.], may issue rules to implement the provisions of this unit.</text>
      <annotations>
        <annoGroup>
          <heading>History</heading>
          <annotation doc="D.C. Law 1-85">Sept. 24, 1976, D.C. Law 1-85, title VII, § 712</annotation>
          <annotation doc="D.C. Law 17-372">as added Mar. 31, 2009, D.C. Law 17-372, § 3(q), 56 DCR 1365</annotation>
          <annotation doc="D.C. Law 19-170">Sept. 29, 2012, D.C. Law 19-170, § 2(q), 59 DCR 5691</annotation>
        </annoGroup>
        <annoGroup>
          <heading>Effect of Amendments</heading>
          <annotation>The 2012 amendment by <cite doc="D.C. Law 19-170">D.C. Law 19-170</cite> made a technical correction which did not affect this section as codified.</annotation>
        </annoGroup>
        <annoGroup>
          <heading>Emergency Legislation</heading>
          <annotation>For temporary (90 day) addition, see § 3(q) of Firearms Registration Emergency Amendment Act of 2008 (D.C. Act 17-651, January 6, 2009,  56 DCR 911).</annotation>
          <annotation>For temporary (90 day) additions, see § 502 of Crime Bill Emergency Amendment Act of 2009 (D.C. Act 18-129, June 29, 2009,  56 DCR 5495).</annotation>
          <annotation>For temporary (90 day) additions, see § 205 of Omnibus Public Safety and Justice Emergency Amendment Act of 2009 (D.C. Act 18-181, August 6, 2009,  56 DCR 6903).</annotation>
          <annotation>For temporary (90 day) amendment of section, see § 2(q) of Firearms Emergency Amendment Act of 2012 (D.C. Act 19-352, May 11, 2012,  59 DCR 5116).</annotation>
          <annotation>For temporary (90 day) amendment of section, see § 2(q) of the Firearms Amendments Congressional Review Emergency Amendment Act of 2012 (D.C. Act 19-394, July 18, 2012,  59 DCR 8694).</annotation>
          <annotation>For temporary amendment of section, see § 2(q) of the Firearms Second Congressional Review Emergency Amendment Act of 2012 (D.C. Act 19-510, October 26, 2012,  59 DCR 12808).</annotation>
        </annoGroup>
      </annotations>
    </section>
  </container>
  <container>
    <prefix>Title</prefix>
    <num>VIII</num>
    <section from-code="true">
      <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" path="|7|25|VIII"/>
      <num codify:value="7-2508.01">801</num>
      <heading>Definitions.</heading>
      <text>For the purposes of this subchapter, the term:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>“Correctional facility” means any building or group of buildings and concomitant services operated as a single management unit by the Department of Corrections, or a similar federal, state, county, or local government agency, or a contractor to such an agency, for the purpose of housing and providing services to persons ordered confined pending trial or sentencing, or incarcerated following sentencing for a violation of law.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>“Gun offender” means a person:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(A)</num>
          <text>Convicted at any time of a gun offense in the District;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(B)</num>
          <text>Convicted at any time of a gun offense who resides in the District within the registration period established pursuant to § <cite path="§7-2508.02">7-2508.02</cite>;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(C)</num>
          <text>Who has as a mandatory condition of release a registration requirement in the District pursuant to § <cite path="§7-2508.04">7-2508.04</cite>(f).</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>“Gun offense” means:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(A)</num>
          <text>A conviction for the sale, purchase, transfer, receipt, acquisition, possession, use, manufacture, carrying, transportation, registration, or licensing of a firearm under Chapter 45 of Title 22 [§ <cite path="§22-4501">22-4501</cite> et seq.], or an attempt or conspiracy to commit any of the foregoing offenses;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(B)</num>
          <text>A conviction for violating § <cite path="§7-2502.01">7-2502.01</cite>, § <cite path="§7-2504.01">7-2504.01</cite>, § <cite path="§7-2505.01">7-2505.01</cite>, or § <cite path="§7-2506.01">7-2506.01</cite>, or an attempt or conspiracy to commit any of the foregoing offenses;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(B-i)</num>
          <text>A conviction for a firearms-related violation of the provisions § <cite path="§22-402">22-402</cite> (assault with a dangerous weapon), § <cite path="§22-2603.02">22-2603.02</cite> (unlawful possession of contraband), or § <cite path="§22-2803">22-2803</cite>(b) (carjacking); or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(C)</num>
          <text>Violations in other jurisdictions of any offense with an element that involves the violations listed in subparagraphs (A), (B), or (B-i) of this paragraph.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>“Resides” means to stay overnight in the District of Columbia for an aggregate period of time exceeding 30 days in any calendar year.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annoGroup>
          <heading>History</heading>
          <annotation doc="D.C. Law 1-85">Sept. 24, 1976, D.C. Law 1-85, title VIII, § 801</annotation>
          <annotation doc="D.C. Law 18-88">as added Dec. 10, 2009, D.C. Law 18-88, § 205, 56 DCR 7413</annotation>
          <annotation doc="D.C. Law 18-377">June 3, 2011, D.C. Law 18-377, § 2(g), 58 DCR 1174</annotation>
          <annotation doc="D.C. Law 19-170">Sept. 29, 2012, D.C. Law 19-170, § 2(r), 59 DCR 5691</annotation>
        </annoGroup>
        <annoGroup>
          <heading>Section References</heading>
          <annotation>This section is referenced in § <cite path="§23-1322">23-1322</cite>.</annotation>
        </annoGroup>
        <annoGroup>
          <heading>Effect of Amendments</heading>
          <annotation><cite doc="D.C. Law 18-377">D.C. Law 18-377</cite>, in pars. (2)(A) and (B), substituted “Convicted at any time” for “Convicted”; in pars. (3)(A) and (B), inserted “, or an attempt or conspiracy to commit any of the foregoing offenses”.</annotation>
          <annotation>The 2012 amendment by <cite doc="D.C. Law 19-170">D.C. Law 19-170</cite> added (3)(B-i); substituted “subparagraphs (A), (B), or (B-i)” for “subparagraph (A) or (B)” in (3)(C); and made a related change.</annotation>
          <annotation>The 2012 amendment by <cite doc="D.C. Law 19-170">D.C. Law 19-170</cite> added (3)(B-i); substituted “subparagraphs (A), (B), or (B-i)” for “subparagraph (A) or (B)” in (3)(C); and made a related change.</annotation>
        </annoGroup>
        <annoGroup>
          <heading>Temporary Amendment of Section</heading>
          <annotation>Section 2(a) of <cite doc="D.C. Law 18-255">D.C. Law 18-255</cite>, in pars. (2)(A) and (B), substituted “Convicted at any time” for “Convicted”.</annotation>
          <annotation>Section 4(b) of <cite doc="D.C. Law 18-255">D.C. Law 18-255</cite> provided that the act shall expire after 225 days of its having taken effect.</annotation>
        </annoGroup>
        <annoGroup>
          <heading>Emergency Legislation</heading>
          <annotation>For temporary (90 day) addition, see § 205 of Omnibus Public Safety and Justice Congressional Review Emergency Amendment Act of 2009 (D.C. Act 18-227, October 21, 2009,  56 DCR 8668).</annotation>
          <annotation>For temporary (90 day) amendment of section, see § 2(a) of Gun Offender Registration Emergency Amendment Act of 2010 (D.C. Act 18-464, July 2, 2010,  57 DCR 6908).</annotation>
          <annotation>For temporary (90 day) amendment of section, see § 2(a) of Gun Offender Registration Congressional Review Emergency Amendment Act of 2010 (D.C. Act 18-539, October 5, 2010,  57 DCR 9610).</annotation>
          <annotation>For temporary (90 day) amendment of section, see § 2(a) of Gun Offender Registration Second Congressional Review Emergency Amendment Act of 2010 (D.C. Act 18-672, December 28, 2010,  58 DCR 126).</annotation>
          <annotation>For temporary (90 day) amendment of section, see § 502(g) of Public Safety Legislation Sixty-Day Layover Emergency Amendment Act of 2010 (D.C. Act 18-693, January 18, 2011,  58 DCR 640).</annotation>
          <annotation>For temporary (90 day) amendment of section, see § 502(g) of Public Safety Legislation Sixty-Day Layover Congressional Review Emergency Amendment Act of 2011 (D.C. Act 19-45, April 20, 2011,  58 DCR 3701).</annotation>
          <annotation>For temporary (90 day) amendment of section, see § 2(r) of Firearms Emergency Amendment Act of 2012 (D.C. Act 19-352, May 11, 2012,  59 DCR 5116).</annotation>
          <annotation>For temporary (90 day) amendment of section, see § 2(r) of the Firearms Amendments Congressional Review Emergency Amendment Act of 2012 (D.C. Act 19-394, July 18, 2012,  59 DCR 8694).</annotation>
          <annotation>For temporary amendment of (3), see § 2(r) of the Firearms Second Congressional Review Emergency Amendment Act of 2012 (D.C. Act 19-510, October 26, 2012,  59 DCR 12808).</annotation>
        </annoGroup>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section from-code="true">
      <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" path="|7|25|VIII"/>
      <num codify:value="7-2508.02">802</num>
      <heading>Duty to register and to verify.</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>A gun offender shall register with the Chief for a period of 2 years, unless a longer period is required by § <cite path="§7-2508.03">7-2508.03</cite> or § <cite path="§7-2508.07">7-2508.07</cite>(b). The offender shall register:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>Within 48 hours (not including a Saturday, Sunday, legal holiday, or day on which the District of Columbia government is closed) of:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(A)</num>
            <text>Release, if the gun offender receives a sentence of imprisonment;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(B)</num>
            <text>The time sentence is imposed, if the sentence does not include imprisonment;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(C)</num>
            <text>Receipt of notice of the obligation to register, if at a time other than sentencing; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(D)</num>
            <text>Changing the place where he or she resides, works, or attends school in the District or elsewhere;</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>By personally appearing at an office designated by the Chief to sign a statement under oath, verified by whatever documentation may be required, that provides, to the extent it is available:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(A)</num>
            <text>The gun offender’s name, date of birth, sex, race, height, weight, and eye color;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(B)</num>
            <text>The address where the gun offender resides or expects to reside in the District;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(C)</num>
            <text>Any other legal names of the gun offender;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(D)</num>
            <text>Aliases of the gun offender;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(E)</num>
            <text>The jurisdiction and a description of the offense for which the gun offender was convicted and the date of conviction;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(F)</num>
            <text>Fingerprints of the gun offender;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(G)</num>
            <text>The identification number of the gun offender’s driver’s license or non-driver photo identification card;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(H)</num>
            <text>The name and address of any school the gun offender attends or expects to attend; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(I)</num>
            <text>Repealed.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>During the period in which a gun offender is required to register under this subchapter, the gun offender shall comply with the following:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>Except as specified in paragraphs (2) and (3) of this subsection, no later than 20 calendar days following the one-year anniversary of the gun offender’s initial registration date, the gun offender shall personally appear at such office as the Chief may direct for the purpose of verifying the information required under subsection (a) of this section.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>If a gun offender required to register under this subchapter is confined to any federal, state, or local correctional facility, residential treatment center, hospital, or institution throughout the 20-day period described in paragraph (1) of this subsection, the gun offender shall personally appear as required by paragraph (1) of this subsection within 48 hours of release.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(3)</num>
          <text>If a gun offender neither resides, works, nor attends school in the District of Columbia, the gun offender shall not be required to comply with paragraph (1) or (2) of this subsection.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(4)</num>
          <text>The Chief may photograph the gun offender and require the gun offender to provide such documentation as the Chief considers acceptable to verify the information provided in subsection (a)(2) of this section.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(c)</num>
        <text>The Chief shall have the authority to maintain and operate the gun offender registry for the District, including the authority to collect and maintain gun offender information obtained pursuant to subsection (b) of this section and enter the information into appropriate record systems and databases.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annoGroup>
          <heading>History</heading>
          <annotation doc="D.C. Law 1-85">Sept. 24, 1976, D.C. Law 1-85, title VIII, § 802</annotation>
          <annotation doc="D.C. Law 18-88">as added Dec. 10, 2009, D.C. Law 18-88, § 205, 56 DCR 7413</annotation>
          <annotation doc="D.C. Law 18-377">June 3, 2011, D.C. Law 18-377, § 2(h), 58 DCR 1174</annotation>
        </annoGroup>
        <annoGroup>
          <heading>Section References</heading>
          <annotation>This section is referenced in § <cite path="§7-2508.01">7-2508.01</cite> and § <cite path="§7-2508.03">7-2508.03</cite>.</annotation>
        </annoGroup>
        <annoGroup>
          <heading>Effect of Amendments</heading>
          <annotation><cite doc="D.C. Law 18-377">D.C. Law 18-377</cite>, in the lead-in language of subsec. (a)(1), substituted “48 hours (not including a Saturday, Sunday, legal holiday, or day on which the District of Columbia government is closed) of:” for “48 hours of:”; rewrote subsec. (a)(1)(C) and repealed subsec. (a)(2)(I), which formerly read:</annotation>
          <annotation>“(C) Remaining in the District to reside, work, or attend school after receipt of notice of the obligation to register; or”.</annotation>
          <annotation>“(I) The name and address of the gun offender’s expected place of work, including the name and phone number of a supervisor.”</annotation>
        </annoGroup>
        <annoGroup>
          <heading>Emergency Legislation</heading>
          <annotation>For temporary (90 day) addition, see § 205 of Omnibus Public Safety and Justice Congressional Review Emergency Amendment Act of 2009 (D.C. Act 18-227, October 21, 2009,  56 DCR 8668).</annotation>
          <annotation>For temporary (90 day) amendment of section, see § 502(h) of Public Safety Legislation Sixty-Day Layover Emergency Amendment Act of 2010 (D.C. Act 18-693, January 18, 2011,  58 DCR 640).</annotation>
          <annotation>For temporary (90 day) amendment of section, see § 502(h) of Public Safety Legislation Sixty-Day Layover Congressional Review Emergency Amendment Act of 2011 (D.C. Act 19-45, April 20, 2011,  58 DCR 3701).</annotation>
        </annoGroup>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section from-code="true">
      <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" path="|7|25|VIII"/>
      <num codify:value="7-2508.03">803</num>
      <heading>Registration period.</heading>
      <text>A gun offender shall comply with the registration and verification provisions required by § <cite path="§7-2508.02">7-2508.02</cite> for a period beginning when he or she is sentenced for a gun offense and continuing until 2 years after the expiration of any time being served on probation, parole, supervised release, or conditional release, or 2 years after the gun offender is unconditionally released from a correctional facility, prison, hospital, or other place of confinement, whichever is latest. The registration period is tolled for any time the gun offender fails to register or otherwise fails to comply with the requirements of this subchapter.</text>
      <annotations>
        <annoGroup>
          <heading>History</heading>
          <annotation doc="D.C. Law 1-85">Sept. 24, 1976, D.C. Law 1-85, title VIII, § 803</annotation>
          <annotation doc="D.C. Law 18-88">as added Dec. 10, 2009, D.C. Law 18-88, § 205, 56 DCR 7413</annotation>
        </annoGroup>
        <annoGroup>
          <heading>Section References</heading>
          <annotation>This section is referenced in § <cite path="§7-2508.02">7-2508.02</cite>.</annotation>
        </annoGroup>
        <annoGroup>
          <heading>Emergency Legislation</heading>
          <annotation>For temporary (90 day) addition, see § 205 of Omnibus Public Safety and Justice Congressional Review Emergency Amendment Act of 2009 (D.C. Act 18-227, October 21, 2009,  56 DCR 8668).</annotation>
        </annoGroup>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section from-code="true">
      <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" path="|7|25|VIII"/>
      <num codify:value="7-2508.04">804</num>
      <heading>Certification duties of the Superior Court of the District of Columbia.</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>Upon a defendant’s conviction for a gun offense, the Superior Court of the District of Columbia (“Court”) shall enter an order certifying that the defendant is a gun offender. The Court shall:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>Advise the gun offender of his or her duties under this subchapter;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>Order the gun offender to report to the Chief to register as required by this subchapter; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(3)</num>
          <text>Order the gun offender to comply with the requirements of this subchapter.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>The Court shall provide to the Chief, and to the Court Services and Offender Supervision Agency, a copy of the certification and order, and such other records and information in its possession that will assist in the registration of the gun offender.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(c)</num>
        <text>In any case where the Court orders the release of a gun offender into the community following a period of detention, incarceration, confinement, civil commitment, or hospitalization, the Court shall provide the gun offender with a copy of the order required under subsection (a) of this section and require the gun offender to read, or have read to him or her, and sign the copy of the order.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(d)</num>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>For a person who has not been required to comply with the requirements of this subchapter as set forth in subsections (a) and (c) of this section, but who nevertheless qualifies and is within the period for which registration is required by this subchapter, the Court may, upon motion of the government, enter an order certifying that a person convicted of a gun offense is a gun offender and issue an order requiring the gun offender to register and to comply with the provisions of this subchapter.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>The certification and order shall be personally served upon the person, at which time the requirements of this subchapter shall apply, unless that person moves the Court to rescind the certification and order and the Court grants the motion.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(e)</num>
        <text>Agencies in the District of Columbia to which the probation, parole, supervised release, or conditional release of a gun offender is transferred from another jurisdiction are authorized to inform the Chief of that transfer of supervision for purposes of implementing the provisions of subsection (d) of this section.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(f)</num>
        <text>Notwithstanding the court certification requirements of this subchapter, any person convicted of a gun offense in any jurisdiction other than the District of Columbia who is ordered by competent authority in that jurisdiction to register as a gun offender in the District of Columbia shall comply with the registration and other requirements of this subchapter.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annoGroup>
          <heading>History</heading>
          <annotation doc="D.C. Law 1-85">Sept. 24, 1976, D.C. Law 1-85, title VIII, § 804</annotation>
          <annotation doc="D.C. Law 18-88">as added Dec. 10, 2009, D.C. Law 18-88, § 205, 56 DCR 7413</annotation>
          <annotation doc="D.C. Law 18-377">June 3, 2011, D.C. Law 18-377, § 2(i), 58 DCR 1174</annotation>
        </annoGroup>
        <annoGroup>
          <heading>Section References</heading>
          <annotation>This section is referenced in § <cite path="§7-2508.01">7-2508.01</cite>.</annotation>
        </annoGroup>
        <annoGroup>
          <heading>Effect of Amendments</heading>
          <annotation><cite doc="D.C. Law 18-377">D.C. Law 18-377</cite> rewrote subsec. (d)(1), which formerly read:</annotation>
          <annotation>“(d)(1) For persons who have not been required to comply with the requirements of this subchapter as set forth in subsections (a) and (c) of this section, but nevertheless qualify, the Court may, upon motion of the government, enter an order certifying that a person convicted of a gun offense within the period for which registration is required by this subchapter is a gun offender and issue an order requiring the gun offender to register and to comply with the provisions of this subchapter.”</annotation>
          <annotation>Temporary Amendment of Section Section 2(b) of <cite doc="D.C. Law 18-255">D.C. Law 18-255</cite> rewrote subsec. (d)(1) to read as follows: “(d)(1) For a person who has not been required to comply with the requirements of this title as set forth in subsections (a) and (c) of this section, but who nevertheless qualifies and is within the period for which registration is required by this act, the Court may, upon motion of the government, enter an order certifying that a person convicted of a gun offense is a gun offender and issue an order requiring the gun offender to register and to comply with the provisions of this act.”.</annotation>
          <annotation>Section 4(b) of <cite doc="D.C. Law 18-255">D.C. Law 18-255</cite> provided that the act shall expire after 225 days of its having taken effect.</annotation>
        </annoGroup>
        <annoGroup>
          <heading>Emergency Legislation</heading>
          <annotation>For temporary (90 day) addition, see § 205 of Omnibus Public Safety and Justice Congressional Review Emergency Amendment Act of 2009 (D.C. Act 18-227, October 21, 2009,  56 DCR 8668).</annotation>
          <annotation>For temporary (90 day) amendment of section, see § 2(b) of Gun Offender Registration Emergency Amendment Act of 2010 (D.C. Act 18-464, July 2, 2010,  57 DCR 6908).</annotation>
          <annotation>For temporary (90 day) amendment of section, see § 2(b) of Gun Offender Registration Congressional Review Emergency Amendment Act of 2010 (D.C. Act 18-539, October 5, 2010,  57 DCR 9610).</annotation>
          <annotation>For temporary (90 day) amendment of section, see § 2(b) of Gun Offender Registration Second Congressional Review Emergency Amendment Act of 2010 (D.C. Act 18-672, December 28, 2010,  58 DCR 126).</annotation>
          <annotation>For temporary (90 day) amendment of section, see § 502(i) of Public Safety Legislation Sixty-Day Layover Emergency Amendment Act of 2010 (D.C. Act 18-693, January 18, 2011,  58 DCR 640).</annotation>
          <annotation>For temporary (90 day) amendment of section, see § 502(i) of Public Safety Legislation Sixty-Day Layover Congressional Review Emergency Amendment Act of 2011 (D.C. Act 19-45, April 20, 2011,  58 DCR 3701).</annotation>
        </annoGroup>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section from-code="true">
      <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" path="|7|25|VIII"/>
      <num codify:value="7-2508.05">805</num>
      <heading>Sharing of registration information; Freedom of Information Act exception.</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>Gun offender registration information shall not be made available except as authorized under subsection (b) of this section. No gun offender registration information shall be available as a public record under § <cite path="§2-532">2-532</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>The Chief is authorized to make gun offender registration information available to other local, state, or federal government agencies.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annoGroup>
          <heading>History</heading>
          <annotation doc="D.C. Law 1-85">Sept. 24, 1976, D.C. Law 1-85, title VIII, § 805</annotation>
          <annotation doc="D.C. Law 18-88">as added Dec. 10, 2009, D.C. Law 18-88, § 205, 56 DCR 7413</annotation>
        </annoGroup>
        <annoGroup>
          <heading>Emergency Legislation</heading>
          <annotation>For temporary (90 day) addition, see § 205 of Omnibus Public Safety and Justice Congressional Review Emergency Amendment Act of 2009 (D.C. Act 18-227, October 21, 2009,  56 DCR 8668).</annotation>
        </annoGroup>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section from-code="true">
      <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" path="|7|25|VIII"/>
      <num codify:value="7-2508.06">806</num>
      <heading>Rules.</heading>
      <text>The Chief, pursuant to subchapter I of Chapter 5 of Title 2 [§ <cite path="§2-501">2-501</cite> et seq.], may issue rules and establish such forms as are necessary to implement the provisions of this subchapter.</text>
      <annotations>
        <annoGroup>
          <heading>History</heading>
          <annotation doc="D.C. Law 1-85">Sept. 24, 1976, D.C. Law 1-85, title VIII, § 806</annotation>
          <annotation doc="D.C. Law 18-88">as added Dec. 10, 2009, D.C. Law 18-88, § 205, 56 DCR 7413</annotation>
        </annoGroup>
        <annoGroup>
          <heading>Emergency Legislation</heading>
          <annotation>For temporary (90 day) addition, see § 205 of Omnibus Public Safety and Justice Congressional Review Emergency Amendment Act of 2009 (D.C. Act 18-227, October 21, 2009,  56 DCR 8668).</annotation>
        </annoGroup>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section from-code="true">
      <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" path="|7|25|VIII"/>
      <num codify:value="7-2508.07">807</num>
      <heading>Penalties; mandatory release condition.</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>Any knowing violation by a gun offender of this subchapter or of rules or regulations established pursuant to this subchapter, including knowingly failing to register, verify, or update information in the manner and within the time periods provided for in this subchapter, shall be a misdemeanor punishable by a fine of not more than $1,000, imprisonment of not more than 12 months, or both.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>Compliance with the requirements of this subchapter, including any rules or regulations adopted by the Chief pursuant to this subchapter, shall be a mandatory condition after the expiration of any time being served on probation, parole, supervised release, or conditional release for any gun offender convicted in the District of Columbia.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annoGroup>
          <heading>History</heading>
          <annotation doc="D.C. Law 1-85">Sept. 24, 1976, D.C. Law 1-85, title VIII, § 807</annotation>
          <annotation doc="D.C. Law 18-88">as added Dec. 10, 2009, D.C. Law 18-88, § 205, 56 DCR 7413</annotation>
        </annoGroup>
        <annoGroup>
          <heading>Section References</heading>
          <annotation>This section is referenced in § <cite path="§7-2502.03">7-2502.03</cite>, § <cite path="§7-2507.06">7-2507.06</cite>, and § <cite path="§7-2508.02">7-2508.02</cite>.</annotation>
        </annoGroup>
        <annoGroup>
          <heading>Temporary Legislation</heading>
          <annotation>For temporary (225 days) addition of <cite doc="D.C. Law 1-85">D.C. Law 1-85</cite>, §§ 9<cite path="§01-910">01-910</cite>, concerning licenses to carry a pistol, see § 2(e) of the License to Carry a Pistol Temporary Amendment Act of 2014 (<cite doc="D.C. Law 20-169">D.C. Law 20-169</cite>, May 5, 2015, 61 DCR 11814).</annotation>
        </annoGroup>
        <annoGroup>
          <heading>Emergency Legislation</heading>
          <annotation>For temporary (90 day) addition, see § 205 of Omnibus Public Safety and Justice Congressional Review Emergency Amendment Act of 2009 (D.C. Act 18-227, October 21, 2009,  56 DCR 8668).</annotation>
          <annotation>For temporary (90 days) addition of <cite doc="D.C. Law 1-85">D.C. Law 1-85</cite>, §§ 901 to 910, concerning licenses to carry a pistol, see § 2(e) of the License to Carry a Pistol Emergency Amendment Act of 2014 (D.C. Act 20-447, Oct. 7, 2014, 61 DCR 10765, 20 STAT 4175).</annotation>
          <annotation>For temporary (90 days) addition of provisions concerning the applicability of new section 910 of the Firearms Control Regulations Act of 1975, see § 4(b) and (c) of the License to Carry a Pistol Emergency Amendment Act of 2014 (D.C. Act 20-447, Oct. 7, 2014, 61 DCR 10765, 20 STAT 4175).</annotation>
          <annotation>For temporary (90 days) repeal of emergency D.C. Act 20-447, § 4, the act’s applicability clause, see § 2 of the License to Carry a Pistol Clarification Emergency Amendment Act of 2014 (D.C. Act 20-448, Oct. 7, 2014,  61 DCR 10777, 20 STAT 4187).</annotation>
          <annotation>For temporary (90 days) addition of <cite doc="D.C. Law 1-85">D.C. Law 1-85</cite>, §§ 901 to 910, concerning licenses to carry a pistol, see § 2(f) of the License to Carry a Pistol Second Emergency Amendment Act of 2014 (D.C. Act 20-564, Jan. 6, 2015, 62 DCR 866, 21 STAT 527).</annotation>
          <annotation>For temporary (90 days) repeal of emergency D.C. Act 20-447, see § 4(b) of the License to Carry a Pistol Second Emergency Amendment Act of 2014 (D.C. Act 20-564, Jan. 6, 2015,  62 DCR 866, 21 STAT 527).</annotation>
          <annotation>For temporary (90 days) repeal of temporary D.C. Act 20-169, see § 4(c) of the License to Carry a Pistol Second Emergency Amendment Act of 2014 (D.C. Act 20-564, Jan. 6, 2015,  62 DCR 866, 21 STAT 527).</annotation>
          <annotation>For temporary (90 days) provision concerning the rules issued under the authority of D.C. Act 20-447, see § 5 of the License to Carry a Pistol Second Emergency Amendment Act of 2014 (D.C. Act 20-564, Jan. 6, 2015, 62 DCR 866, 21 STAT 527).</annotation>
        </annoGroup>
      </annotations>
    </section>
  </container>
  <section from-code="true">
    <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" path="|7|25|IV"/>
    <num codify:value="7-2504.10">410</num>
    <heading>District as federal firearms licensee.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>(a)</num>
      <text>Whenever there is no active federal firearms licensee in the District of Columbia, the Mayor may seek from federal authorities a license for the District to act as a federal firearms licensee solely for the benefit of any District resident eligible and seeking to obtain a lawful handgun.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(b)</num>
      <text>The Mayor shall delegate the authority under subsection (a) of this section to a subordinate agency.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(c)</num>
      <text>The District shall act under the license obtained pursuant to subsection (a) of this section only until such time as there is an active federal firearms licensee in the District of Columbia.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(d)</num>
      <text>The District may charge a fee to recover the cost of acting as a federal firearms licensee pursuant to subsection (a) of this section by charging $125 or its actual costs, whichever is less, for each handgun.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(e)</num>
      <text>For the purposes of this section, the term “active federal firearms licensee” means a person or business that has applied for and received a federal firearms license pursuant to 18 U.S.C. § 923 for the purpose of interstate transfer of handguns, and is operating commercially in the District of Columbia.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>History</heading>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 1-85">Sept. 24, 1976, D.C. Law 1-85, § 410</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 19-170">as added Sept. 29, 2012, D.C. Law 19-170, § 2(l), 59 DCR 5691</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Emergency Legislation</heading>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 day) addition of section, see § 2(l) of Firearms Emergency Amendment Act of 2012 (D.C. Act 19-352, May 11, 2012,  59 DCR 5116).</annotation>
        <annotation>For temporary addition of section, see § 2(l) of the Firearms Second Congressional Review Emergency Amendment Act of 2012 (D.C. Act 19-510, October 26, 2012,  59 DCR 12808).</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section from-code="true">
    <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" path="|7|25|IX"/>
    <num codify:value="7-2509.01">901</num>
    <heading>Definitions.</heading>
    <text>For the purposes of this subchapter, the term:</text>
    <para>
      <num>(1)</num>
      <text>“Child” means a person under 18 years of age.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(2)</num>
      <text>“Concealed pistol” means a loaded or unloaded pistol carried on or about a person entirely hidden from view of the public, or carried on or about a person in a vehicle in such a way as it is entirely hidden from view of the public.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(3)</num>
      <text>“Law enforcement officer” means a sworn member of the Metropolitan Police Department or of any other law enforcement agency operating and authorized to make arrests in the District of Columbia, and includes an MPD reserve officer, a special police officer appointed pursuant to § <cite path="§5-129.02">5-129.02</cite>, and a campus and a university special police officer appointed pursuant to the College and University Campus Security Amendment Act of 1995, effective October 18, 1995 (<cite doc="D.C. Law 11-63">D.C. Law 11-63</cite>; 6A DCMR § 1200et seq.).</text>
      <text>
        <em>et seq.</em>
      </text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(4)</num>
      <text>“License” means a license to carry a concealed pistol issued pursuant to §  22-4506.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(5)</num>
      <text>“Licensee” means a person who has been issued a license pursuant to §  22-4506.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(6)</num>
      <text>“MPD” means the Metropolitan Police Department.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(7)</num>
      <text>“Section 6 of the Pistols and Other Dangerous Weapons Act” means §  22-4506.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>History</heading>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 1-85">Sept. 24, 1976, D.C. Law 1-85, §  901</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 20-279">as added June 16, 2015, D.C. Law 20-279, § 2(f), 62 DCR 1944</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Emergency Legislation</heading>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 days) addition of this subchapter, see § 2(f) of the License to Carry a Pistol Congressional Review Emergency Amendment Act of 2015 (D.C. Act 21-74, June 4, 2015,  62 DCR 8242, 21 DCSTAT 1451).</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section from-code="true">
    <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" path="|7|25|IX"/>
    <num codify:value="7-2509.02">902</num>
    <heading>Application requirements.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>(a)</num>
      <text>A person who submits an application pursuant to § <cite path="§22-4506">22-4506</cite> shall certify and demonstrate to the satisfaction of the Chief that he or she:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Is at least 21 years of age;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Meets all of the requirements for a person registering a firearm pursuant to this unit, and has obtained a registration certificate for the pistol that the person is applying to carry concealed;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <para>
          <num>(A)</num>
          <text>Does not currently suffer from a mental illness or condition that creates a substantial risk that he or she is a danger to himself or herself or others; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(B)</num>
          <text>If he or she has suffered in the previous 5 years from a mental illness or condition that created a substantial risk that he or she was a danger to himself or herself or others, no longer suffers from a mental illness or condition that creates a substantial risk that he or she is a danger to himself or herself or others;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Has completed a firearms training course or combination of courses, conducted by an instructor (or instructors) certified by the Chief, which includes at least 16 hours of training, and covers the following:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(A)</num>
          <text>Firearm safety;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(B)</num>
          <text>Firearm nomenclature;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(C)</num>
          <text>Basic principles of marksmanship;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(D)</num>
          <text>Care, cleaning, maintenance, loading, unloading, and storage of pistols;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(E)</num>
          <text>Situational awareness, conflict management, and use of deadly force;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(F)</num>
          <text>Selection of pistols and ammunition for defensive purposes; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(G)</num>
          <text>All applicable District and federal firearms laws, including the requirements of this unit, Chapter 45 of Title 22 [§ <cite path="§22-4501">22-4501</cite> et seq.], and District law pertaining to self-defense;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Has completed at least 2 hours of range training, conducted by an instructor certified by the Chief, including shooting a qualification course of 50 rounds of ammunition from a maximum distance of 15 yards (45 feet); and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Has complied with any procedures the Chief may establish by rule.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(b)</num>
      <text>An applicant shall satisfy the requirements of subsection (a)(4) and (a)(5) of this section with a certification from a firearms instructor that the applicant:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Demonstrated satisfactory completion of the requirements of subsection (a)(4) and (a)(5) of this section; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Possesses the proper knowledge, skills, and attitude to carry a concealed pistol.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(c)</num>
      <text>An applicant may be exempt from some or all of the requirements of subsection (a)(4) and (a)(5) of this section if the applicant has submitted evidence that he or she has received firearms training in the United States military or has otherwise completed firearms training conducted by a firearms instructor that, as determined by the Chief, is equal to or greater than that required under subsection (a)(4) and (a)(5) of this section.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(d)</num>
      <text>An applicant for a license may satisfy any component of the requirements of subsection (a)(4) and (a)(5) of this section by demonstrating to the satisfaction of the Chief that the applicant has met that particular component as part of a successful application to carry a concealed pistol issued by the lawful authorities of any state or subdivision of the United States.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(e)</num>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>An applicant shall sign an oath or affirmation attesting to the truth of all the information required by § <cite path="§22-4506">22-4506</cite> and this section.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Any declaration, certificate, verification, or statement made for purposes of an application for a license to carry a concealed pistol pursuant to this unit shall be made under penalty of perjury pursuant to § <cite path="§22-2402">22-2402</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(f)</num>
      <text>An applicant is required to appear for an in-person interview at the MPD headquarters for purposes including verification of the applicant’s identity and verification of the information submitted as part of the application process for a license.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(g)</num>
      <text>Any person whose application has been denied may, within 15 days after the date of the notice of denial, appeal to the Concealed Pistol Licensing Review Board established pursuant to §  7-2509.08.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>History</heading>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 1-85">Sept. 24, 1976, D.C. Law 1-85, § 902</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 20-279">as added June 16, 2015, D.C. Law 20-279, § 2(f), 62 DCR 1944</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section from-code="true">
    <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" path="|7|25|IX"/>
    <num codify:value="7-2509.03">903</num>
    <heading>Expiration and renewal of licenses.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>(a)</num>
      <text>A license shall expire no later than 2 years after the date of issuance unless revoked by the Chief or renewed pursuant to this subchapter.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(b)</num>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A license shall be eligible for renewal if:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(A)</num>
          <text>The licensee continues to meet the requirements of § <cite path="§22-4506">22-4506</cite> and §  7-2509.02, except that:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>With regard to §  7-2509.02(a)(4), only 4 hours of such training shall be required for renewal; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>With regard to §  7-2509.02(a)(5), the licensee shall provide proof of 2 hours of range practice within the previous 12 months; and</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(B)</num>
          <text>The licensee follows any procedures the Chief may establish by rule.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Timely renewal shall be the responsibility of the licensee, pursuant to any procedures the Chief may establish by rule.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(c)</num>
      <text>Any person whose renewal application has been denied may, within 15 days after the date of the notice of denial, appeal to the Concealed Pistol Licensing Review Board established pursuant to §  7-2509.08.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>History</heading>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 1-85">Sept. 24, 1976, D.C. Law 1-85, § 903</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 20-279">as added June 16, 2015, D.C. Law 20-279, § 2(f), 62 DCR 1944</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section from-code="true">
    <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" path="|7|25|IX"/>
    <num codify:value="7-2509.04">904</num>
    <heading>Duties of licensees.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>(a)</num>
      <text>A licensee shall comply with all limits and conditions of the license.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(b)</num>
      <text>A licensee shall notify the Chief in writing:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Immediately upon discovery of the loss, theft, or destruction of the license and include the circumstances of the loss, theft, or destruction, if known; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Within 30 days after a change in the licensee’s name or address as it appears on the license.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(c)</num>
      <text>A licensee shall have on or about his or her person each time the pistol is carried in the District:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The license; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The registration certificate for the pistol being carried, issued pursuant to this unit.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(d)</num>
      <text>If a law enforcement officer initiates an investigative stop of a licensee carrying a concealed pistol pursuant to § <cite path="§22-4506">22-4506</cite>, the licensee, and any other licensee carrying a concealed pistol pursuant to § <cite path="§22-4506">22-4506</cite> who is with the stopped licensee at the time of the investigative stop, shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Disclose to the officer that he or she is carrying a concealed pistol;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Present the license and registration certificate;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Identify the location of the concealed pistol; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Comply with all lawful orders and directions from the officer, including allowing a pat down of his or her person and permitting the law enforcement officer to take possession of the pistol for so long as is necessary for the safety of the officer or the public.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(e)</num>
      <text>The duties set forth in this section are in addition to any other requirements imposed by this unit or applicable law.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(f)</num>
      <text>In addition to any other penalty provided by law, a person who violates this section shall be subject to revocation of his or her license.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>History</heading>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 1-85">Sept. 24, 1976, D.C. Law 1-85, § 904</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 20-279">as added June 16, 2015, D.C. Law 20-279, § 2(f), 62 DCR 1944</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section from-code="true">
    <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" path="|7|25|IX"/>
    <num codify:value="7-2509.05">905</num>
    <heading>Revocation and suspension of licenses.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>(a)</num>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The Chief may limit or revoke a license upon a finding that the licensee no longer meets the requirements of § <cite path="§22-4506">22-4506</cite> and this subchapter, or as a penalty as specified in this unit.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The United States Attorney for the District of Columbia, the Attorney General for the District of Columbia, or any person may apply to the MPD at any time for limitation or revocation of a license.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Any person having knowledge that a licensee no longer meets the requirements of this unit or the requirements of § <cite path="§22-4506">22-4506</cite> may so notify the Chief or any other law enforcement officer who may take such action as may be appropriate.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Before a limitation or revocation taking effect, the Chief shall serve a notice of intent to limit or revoke the license. The limitation or revocation shall take effect unless the licensee requests an appeal to the Concealed Pistol Licensing Review Board established pursuant to §  7-2509.08 no later than 15 days after the date of the notice of intent.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(b)</num>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The Chief may summarily suspend or limit, without a hearing, a license, when the Chief has determined that the conduct of a licensee presents an imminent danger to the health and safety of a person or the public.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>At the time of the summary suspension or limitation of a license, the Chief shall provide the licensee with written notice stating the action that is being taken, the basis for the action, and the right of the licensee to request a hearing.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>A licensee shall have the right to request a hearing within 72 hours after service of notice of the summary suspension or limitation of the license. The Concealed Pistol Licensing Review Board shall hold a hearing within 72 hours after receipt of a timely request, and shall issue a written decision within 72 hours after the hearing.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>History</heading>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 1-85">Sept. 24, 1976, D.C. Law 1-85, § 905</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 20-279">as added June 16, 2015, D.C. Law 20-279, § 2(f), 62 DCR 1944</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section from-code="true">
    <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" path="|7|25|IX"/>
    <num codify:value="7-2509.06">906</num>
    <heading>Carrying a pistol while impaired.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>(a)</num>
      <text>A licensee shall not carry a pistol while he or she is consuming alcohol.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(b)</num>
      <text>A licensee shall not carry a pistol while impaired.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(c)</num>
      <text>Upon establishing reasonable suspicion that a licensee has been consuming drugs or alcohol, a licensee’s failure to submit to one or more field sobriety, breathalyzer, or urine tests, administered to determine whether the licensee is impaired while carrying a pistol, shall be grounds for summary suspension of the license pursuant to §  7-2509.05(b).</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(d)</num>
      <text>In addition to any other penalty provided by law, any person who violates this section shall be subject to revocation of his or her license.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(e)</num>
      <text>For the purposes of this section, the term “impaired” means a licensee has consumed alcohol or other drug or drugs and that it has affected the licensee’s behavior in a way that can be perceived or noticed.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>History</heading>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 1-85">Sept. 24, 1976, D.C. Law 1-85, § 906</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 20-279">as added June 16, 2015, D.C. Law 20-279, § 2(f), 62 DCR 1944</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section from-code="true">
    <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" path="|7|25|IX"/>
    <num codify:value="7-2509.07">907</num>
    <heading>Prohibitions on carrying licensed pistols.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>(a)</num>
      <text>No person holding a license shall carry a pistol in the following locations or under the following circumstances:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A building or office occupied by the District of Columbia, its agencies, or instrumentalities;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The building and grounds, including any adjacent parking lot, of an childcare facility, preschool, public or private elementary or secondary school; or a public or private college or university;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>A hospital, or an office where medical or mental health services are the primary services provided;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>A penal institution, secure juvenile residential facility, or halfway house;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>A polling place while voting is occurring;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>A public transportation vehicle, including the Metrorail transit system and its stations;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>Any premises, or portion thereof, where alcohol is served, or sold and consumed on the premises, pursuant to a license issued under Title 25; provided, that this prohibition shall not apply to premises operating under a temporary license issued pursuant to § <cite path="§25-115">25-115</cite>, a C/R, D/R, C/H, D/H or caterer license issued pursuant to § <cite path="§25-113">25-113</cite>, or premises with small-sample tasting permits issued pursuant to § <cite path="§25-118">25-118</cite>, unless otherwise prohibited pursuant to subsection (b)(3) of this section;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(8)</num>
        <text>A stadium or arena;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(9)</num>
        <text>A gathering or special event open to the public; provided, that no licensee shall be criminally prosecuted unless:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(A)</num>
          <text>The organizer or the District has provided notice prohibiting the carrying of pistols in advance of the gathering or special event and by posted signage at the gathering or special event; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(B)</num>
          <text>The licensee has been ordered by a law enforcement officer to leave the area of the gathering or special event and the licensee has not complied with the order;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(10)</num>
        <text>The public memorials on the National Mall and along the Tidal Basin, and any area where firearms are prohibited under federal law or by a federal agency or entity, including U.S. Capitol buildings and grounds;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(11)</num>
        <text>The area around the White House between Constitution Avenue, N.W., and H Street, N.W., and between 15th Street, N.W., and 17th Street, N.W.;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(12)</num>
        <text>The U.S. Naval Observatory and its grounds, and from the perimeter of its fence to the curb of Massachusetts Avenue, N.W., from 34th Street, N.W., south on Massachusetts Avenue, N.W., to Observatory Circle, N.W.;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(13)</num>
        <para>
          <num>(A)</num>
          <text>When a dignitary or high-ranking official of the United States or a state, local, or foreign government is moving under the protection of the MPD, the U.S. Secret Service, the U.S. Capitol Police, or other law enforcement agency assisting or working in concert with MPD, within an area designated by the Chief, the Chief of the U.S. Secret Service, or the Chief of the U.S. Capitol Police, or a designee of any of the foregoing, that does not include any point at a distance greater than 1,000 feet from the moving dignitary or high-ranking official; provided, that no licensee shall be criminally prosecuted unless:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>The law enforcement agency provides notice of the designated area by the presence of signs, law enforcement vehicles or officers acting as a perimeter, or other means to make the designated area of protection obvious;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>The District or federal government has provided notice prohibiting the carrying of pistols along a designated route or in a designated area in advance of the event, if possible, and by posted signage along a route or in a designated area; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(iii)</num>
            <text>The licensee has been ordered by a law enforcement officer to leave the designated area and the licensee has not complied with the order.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(B)</num>
          <text>For the purposes of this paragraph, the term “moving” shall include any planned or unplanned stops, including temporary stops, in locations open to the public.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(14)</num>
        <text>When demonstration in a public place is occurring, within an area designated by the Chief or his or her designee, or other law enforcement agency, that does not include any point at a distance greater than 1,000 feet from the demonstration; provided, that no licensee shall be criminally prosecuted unless:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(A)</num>
          <text>The law enforcement agency provides notice of the designated area by the presence of signs, law enforcement vehicles or officers acting as a perimeter, or other means to make the designated area of the demonstration obvious;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(B)</num>
          <text>The District or federal government has provided notice prohibiting the carrying of pistols along or within a demonstration route or designated area in advance of the event, if possible, and by posted signage along a demonstration route or designated area; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(C)</num>
          <text>The licensee has been ordered by a law enforcement officer to leave the designated area and the licensee has not complied with the order; or</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(15)</num>
        <text>Any prohibited location or circumstance that the Chief determines by rule; provided, that for spontaneous circumstances, no criminal penalty shall apply unless the licensee has notice of the prohibition and has failed to comply.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(b)</num>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The carrying of a concealed pistol on private residential property shall be presumed to be prohibited unless otherwise authorized by the property owner or person in control of the premises and communicated personally to the licensee in advance of entry onto the residential property.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The carrying of a concealed pistol in a church, synagogue, mosque, or other place where people regularly assemble for religious worship shall be presumed to be prohibited unless the property is posted with conspicuous signage allowing the carrying of a concealed pistol, or the owner or authorized agent communicates such allowance personally to the licensee in advance of entry onto the property; provided, that such places may not authorize the carrying of a concealed pistol where services are conducted in locations listed in subsection (a) of this section.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The carrying of a concealed pistol on private property that is not a residence shall be presumed to be permitted unless the property is posted with conspicuous signage prohibiting the carrying of a concealed pistol, or the owner or authorized agent communicates such prohibition personally to the licensee.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(c)</num>
      <text>Whenever a licensee carries a concealed pistol and approaches any prohibited location, or is subject to any prohibited circumstance, under subsection (a) or (b) of this section, the licensee shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>If the licensee is in a vehicle or if a vehicle is readily available, immediately secure the pistol in the manner prescribed in § <cite path="§22-4504.02">22-4504.02</cite>(b); or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>If the licensee does not have a vehicle available, immediately leave the prohibited location or circumstance.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(d)</num>
      <text>A licensee shall not be in violation of this section:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>While he or she is traveling along a public street, road, or highway, including an adjacent public sidewalk that touches the perimeter of any of the premises where the carrying of a concealed pistol is prohibited under subsection (a) or subsection (b) of this section if the concealed pistol is carried on his or her person in accordance with this unit, or is being transported by the licensee in accordance with § <cite path="§22-4504.02">22-4504.02</cite>; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>While driving a vehicle into and immediately parking at any location listed in subsection (a)(2) of this section for the purpose of picking up or dropping off a student or a child; provided, that the licensee shall secure the concealed pistol in accordance with § <cite path="§22-4504.02">22-4504.02</cite>(b), before leaving the parked vehicle.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(e)</num>
      <text>A licensee shall not carry a pistol openly or otherwise in a manner that is not concealed.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(f)</num>
      <text>In addition to any other penalty provided by law, any person who violates this section shall be subject to revocation of his or her license.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(g)</num>
      <text>For the purposes of this section, the term:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>“Demonstration” means one or more persons demonstrating, picketing, speechmaking, marching, holding a vigil, or engaging in any other similar conduct that involves the communication or expression of views or grievances and that has the effect, intent, or propensity to attract a crowd or onlookers. The term “demonstration” does not include the casual use of property by visitors or tourists that does not have the effect, intent, or propensity to attract a crowd or onlookers.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>“Public place” means a place to which the general public has access and a right to occupy for business, entertainment, or other lawful purpose. The term “public place” is not limited to a place devoted solely to the uses of the public, and includes:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(A)</num>
          <text>The front or immediate area or parking lot of a store, restaurant, tavern, shopping center, or other place of business;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(B)</num>
          <text>A public building, including its grounds and curtilage;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(C)</num>
          <text>A public parking lot;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(D)</num>
          <text>A public street, sidewalk, or right-of-way;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(E)</num>
          <text>A public park; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(F)</num>
          <text>Other public grounds.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>“Public transportation vehicle” means any publicly owned or operated commercial vehicle, including any DC Circulator bus, DC Streetcar, MetroAccess vehicle, Metrobus, or Metrorail train.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>“Residence” means a building wholly or partly used or intended to be used for living and sleeping by human occupants, together with any fences, walls, sheds, garages, or other accessory buildings appurtenant to the building, and the area of land surrounding the building and actually or by legal construction forming one enclosure in which such a building is located, but does not include adjacent common areas or commercial property contained in any part of the building.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>History</heading>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 1-85">Sept. 24, 1976, D.C. Law 1-85, § 907</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 20-279">as added June 16, 2015, D.C. Law 20-279, § 2(f), 62 DCR 1944</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Temporary Legislation</heading>
        <annotation>For temporary (225 days) amendment of this section, see § 5 of the Fiscal Year 2016 Budget Support Clarification Temporary Amendment Act of 2015 (<cite doc="D.C. Law 21-76">D.C. Law 21-76</cite>, Feb. 27, 2016,  63 DCR 264).</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Emergency Legislation</heading>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 days) amendment of section, see § 4 of the Fiscal Year 2016 Second Budget Support Clarification Emergency Amendment Act of 2015 (D.C. Act 21-202, Nov. 23, 2015,  62 DCR 15276).</annotation>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 days) amendment of this section, see § 4 of the Fiscal Year 2016 Budget Support Clarification Congressional Review Emergency Amendment Act of 2016 (D.C. Act 21-307, Feb. 18, 2016,  63 DCR 2182).</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section from-code="true">
    <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" path="|7|25|IX"/>
    <num codify:value="7-2509.08">908</num>
    <heading>Concealed Pistol Licensing Review Board.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>(a)</num>
      <text>There is established a Concealed Pistol Licensing Review Board (“Board”) for the purpose of hearing appeals from:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>A denial of an application or renewal application for a license to carry a concealed pistol in the District pursuant to this unit;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>A summary suspension or limitation of a license to carry a concealed pistol; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>A limitation or revocation of a license to carry a concealed pistol.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(b)</num>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The Board shall consist of 7 members as follows:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(A)</num>
          <text>The United States Attorney (“USAO”) for the District of Columbia or his or her designee; provided, that if the USAO declines to provide a representative, the Mayor shall appoint a person who is a former employee of the USAO;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(B)</num>
          <text>The Attorney General for the District of Columbia or his or her designee;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(C)</num>
          <text>A mental health professional employed by the Department of Behavioral Health, appointed by the Mayor;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(D)</num>
          <text>A former sworn officer of a law enforcement agency other than the MPD, appointed by the Mayor;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(E)</num>
          <text>Three public members appointed by the Mayor, as follows:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>One mental health professional; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(ii)</num>
            <text>Two District residents with experience in the operation, care, and handling of firearms.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The appointment of members designated by subsection (b)(1)(D) and (b)(1)(E) of this section shall be made in accordance with the following provisions:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(A)</num>
          <text>Each member shall be appointed for a term of 4 years, and shall continue to serve during that time as long as the member remains eligible for the appointment;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(B)</num>
          <text>A member may be reappointed;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(C)</num>
          <text>A Board member whose term has expired may continue to serve as a member until a replacement member has been appointed;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(D)</num>
          <text>A person appointed to fill a vacancy occurring before the expiration of a term shall serve for the remainder of the term or until a successor has been appointed; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(E)</num>
          <text>A member may be removed by the appointing authority only for incompetence, neglect of duty, or misconduct.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The Mayor shall select a chairperson.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>Members shall serve without compensation, but shall be compensated for actual and necessary expenses incurred in the performance of their official duties.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(c)</num>
      <text>Four members of the Board shall constitute a quorum, except that 2 members shall be a quorum when hearing panels of 3 members are assigned by the Board to conduct a hearing and make a final decision required by this section. Each hearing panel shall contain at least one member designated by subsection (b)(1)(A), (B), or (D) of this section.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(d)</num>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Within 30 days after June 16, 2015, the Mayor, by rule, shall establish hearing procedures for a contested case review of any appeal, including the manner and time of appeals, and procedures for the Board to assign panels of 3 Board members to conduct such hearings and issue final decisions, pursuant to subsection (c) of this section.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The rules shall include that the burden of production of evidence, and the burden of persuasion, at a hearing before the Board shall be upon the applicant or licensee that is challenging a denial of an application or renewal application or limitation or revocation of a license.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(e)</num>
      <text>The meetings and hearings conducted by the Board shall be confidential and not open to the public.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(f)</num>
      <text>Any person, including the Chief, aggrieved by a final action of the Board may file an appeal in accordance with subchapter I of Chapter 5 of Title 2 [§ <cite path="§2-501">2-501</cite> et seq.].</text>
    </para>
    <annotations>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>History</heading>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 1-85">Sept. 24, 1976, D.C. Law 1-85, § 908</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 20-279">as added June 16, 2015, D.C. Law 20-279, § 2(f), 62 DCR 1944</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section from-code="true">
    <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" path="|7|25|IX"/>
    <num codify:value="7-2509.09">909</num>
    <heading>Freedom of information exception; report.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>(a)</num>
      <text>Any record regarding a person who has applied for, received, or had revoked a license shall not be made available as a public record under § <cite path="§2-532">2-532</cite>; provided, that aggregate data, excluding any personal identifying information, may be used for the purposes of the public report in subsection (b) of this section.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(b)</num>
      <text>Every 2 years, the MPD shall make public a report that includes the following information:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The total number of valid licenses; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>For the most recent 2-year period:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(A)</num>
          <text>The number of applications for a license received;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(B)</num>
          <text>The number of licenses issued;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(C)</num>
          <text>The number of licenses renewed, suspended, revoked, or denied;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(D)</num>
          <text>The number of licensees convicted of a crime involving a pistol, classified by type of crime;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(E)</num>
          <text>The number of pistols for which a license was issued that were reported lost or stolen; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(F)</num>
          <text>The number of pistols for which a license was issued that were found or recovered as stolen that were unreported by a licensee as lost or stolen.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>History</heading>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 1-85">Sept. 24, 1976, D.C. Law 1-85, § 909</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 20-279">as added June 16, 2015, D.C. Law 20-279, § 2(f), 62 DCR 1944</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section from-code="true">
    <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" path="|7|25|IX"/>
    <num codify:value="7-2509.10">910</num>
    <heading>Penalties.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>(a)</num>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Except as otherwise provided in this subchapter, a person convicted of a violation of a provision of this subchapter, or rules or regulations issued under the authority of this subchapter, shall be fined not more than the amount set forth in § <cite path="§22-3571.01">22-3571.01</cite>, or imprisoned for not more than 180 days.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Civil fines, penalties, and fees may be imposed as alternative sanctions for any infraction of the provisions of this subchapter, or any rules or regulations issued under the authority of this subchapter.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(b)</num>
      <text>All prosecutions for violations of this subchapter shall be brought in the name of the District of Columbia and prosecuted by the Office of the Attorney General for the District of Columbia.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>History</heading>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 1-85">Sept. 24, 1976, D.C. Law 1-85, § 910</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 20-279">as added June 16, 2015, D.C. Law 20-279, § 2(f), 62 DCR 1944</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section from-code="true">
    <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" path="|7|25|IX"/>
    <num codify:value="7-2509.11">911</num>
    <heading>Rules.</heading>
    <text>The Chief of the MPD, pursuant to subchapter I of Chapter 5 of Title 2 [§ <cite path="§2-501">2-501</cite> et seq.], shall issue rules to implement the provisions of <cite doc="D.C. Law 20-279">D.C. Law 20-279</cite>, including rules:</text>
    <para>
      <num>(1)</num>
      <text>To establish criteria for determining when an applicant has, pursuant to section 6 of the Pistols and Other Dangerous Weapons Act [§ <cite path="§22-4506">22-4506</cite>]:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(A)</num>
        <text>Demonstrated a good reason to fear injury to his or her person, which shall at a minimum require a showing of a special need for self-protection distinguishable from the general community as supported by evidence of specific threats or previous attacks that demonstrate a special danger to the applicant’s life;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(B)</num>
        <text>Demonstrated any other proper reason for carrying a concealed pistol, which shall at a minimum include types of employment that require the handling of cash or other valuable objects that may be transported upon the applicant’s person; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(C)</num>
        <text>Demonstrated the applicant’s suitability to carry a concealed pistol, which shall at a minimum include evidence that the applicant meets the requirements of § <cite path="§7-2509.02">7-2509.02</cite>;</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(2)</num>
      <text>To establish the type and amount of ammunition that may be carried concealed by a licensee;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(3)</num>
      <text>To establish the methods by which a pistol may be carried, including any standards for safe holstering;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(4)</num>
      <text>To establish all application forms, investigation procedures, background checks, and fees necessary to process an application for a license to carry a concealed pistol;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(5)</num>
      <text>To specify any procedures or requirements specific to non-residents who apply to carry a concealed pistol pursuant to § <cite path="§22-4506">22-4506</cite>, with regard to the registration requirements in this unit;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(6)</num>
      <text>To specify requirements for signage on any private premises where the owner or person in control of the premises prohibits the carrying of a concealed pistol pursuant to § <cite path="§7-2509.07">7-2509.07</cite>(b); and</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(7)</num>
      <text>To establish procedures for the renewal of licenses.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>History</heading>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 1-85">Sept. 24, 1976, D.C. Law 1-85, § 911</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 20-279">as added June 16, 2015, D.C. Law 20-279, § 2(f), 62 DCR 1944</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Editor's Notes</heading>
        <annotation><cite doc="D.C. Law 20-279">D.C. Law 20-279</cite>, referred to in the introductory language of this section, enacted § <cite path="§7-2502.11a">7-2502.11a</cite> and this subchapter, amended §§ <cite path="§7-2502.01">7-2502.01</cite>(b)(4), <cite path="§7-2502.02">7-2502.02</cite>(a)(4), <cite path="§7-2502.03">7-2502.03</cite>(a)(4), <cite path="§22-4504">22-4504</cite>(a), and <cite path="§22-4506">22-4506</cite>, and repealed §  22-2511.</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
    </annotations>
  </section>
</document>
