<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<document xmlns:codify="http://code.dccouncil.us/schemas/codify" id="Pub. L. 75-1-ch144">
  <heading/>
  <meta>
    <effective>1937-04-27</effective>
    <cites>
      <law congress="75" session="1" chapter="144"/>
    </cites>
  </meta>
  <section from-code="true">
    <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" path="|7|8"/>
    <num codify:value="7-801">1</num>
    <heading>Prophylactic solution to be administered.</heading>
    <text>The Mayor may, upon the advice of the Commissioner of Public Health and pursuant to subchapter I of Chapter 5 of Title 2, issue rules to prevent and monitor the occurrence of ophthalmia in newborns. Unless the Mayor provides otherwise, each physician or nurse-midwife who delivers or otherwise assumes the initial care of a newborn shall immediately upon that delivery or assumption of care administer to each eye of the newborn a 1% solution of silver nitrate, an ophthalmic ointment containing either 1% tetracycline or 0.5% erythromycin, or another prophylactic approved by the Mayor.</text>
    <annotations>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>History</heading>
        <annotation>Apr. 27, 1937, 50 Stat. 120, ch. 144, § 1</annotation>
        <annotation>Aug. 1, 1950, 64 Stat. 393, ch. 513, § 1</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 6-83">Feb. 21, 1986, D.C. Law 6-83, § 4(a), 32 DCR 7276</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Prior Codifications</heading>
        <annotation>1981 Ed., § 6-301.</annotation>
        <annotation>1973 Ed., § 6-201.</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Editor's Notes</heading>
        <annotation>Office of Director of Public Health abolished: See Historical and Statutory Notes following § <cite path="§7-101">7-101</cite>.</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section from-code="true">
    <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" path="|7|8"/>
    <num codify:value="7-802">2</num>
    <heading>Report of eye inflammation; treatment.</heading>
    <text>Whenever a physician or nurse-midwife discovers that a newborn in his or her care has inflammation of the eye(s) with suppuration, he or she shall report these symptoms to the Commissioner of Public Health within 6 hours of their discovery. Upon receipt of such communication the Commissioner of Public Health, unless he finds such report to be incorrect, shall issue an order directing the parents of such child (or other person charged with its care) either to: (1) place such child in the care of a registered physician; or (2) submit immediately satisfactory proof of inability to pay for such medical service. If the Director of the Department of Human Services finds that the parents or such other person are unable to pay for such medical treatment, he shall order the parents (or such other person) to place the child in a hospital to be designated by the Department of Human Services and at the expense of said Department.</text>
    <annotations>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>History</heading>
        <annotation>Apr. 27, 1937, 50 Stat. 120, ch. 144, § 2</annotation>
        <annotation>Aug. 1, 1950, 64 Stat. 393, ch. 513, § 1</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 6-83">Feb. 21, 1986, D.C. Law 6-83, § 4(b), 32 DCR 7276</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Prior Codifications</heading>
        <annotation>1981 Ed., § 6-302.</annotation>
        <annotation>1973 Ed., § 6-202.</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Editor's Notes</heading>
        <text>Office of Director of Public Health abolished: See Historical and Statutory Notes following § <cite path="§7-101">7-101</cite>.</text>
        <text>Health Department abolished: See Historical and Statutory Notes following § <cite path="§7-180">7-180</cite>.</text>
      </annoGroup>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section from-code="true">
    <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" path="|7|8"/>
    <num codify:value="7-803">3</num>
    <heading>Treatment by other than registered physician.</heading>
    <text>No person other than a registered physician shall treat any case of inflammation of the eyes, attended by a discharge therefrom, of a newborn child for any period longer than may be necessary to obtain the services of a registered physician.</text>
    <annotations>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>History</heading>
        <annotation>Apr. 27, 1937, 50 Stat. 120, ch. 144, § 3</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Prior Codifications</heading>
        <annotation>1981 Ed., § 6-303.</annotation>
        <annotation>1973 Ed., § 6-203.</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section from-code="true">
    <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" path="|7|8"/>
    <num codify:value="7-804">4</num>
    <heading>Penalty.</heading>
    <text>Any person who willfully violates this subchapter or any rule, regulation, or order issued pursuant to this subchapter shall be guilty of a misdemeanor and, upon conviction, subject to a fine not exceeding $1,000. Prosecution shall be in the Superior Court of the District of Columbia by information signed by the Corporation Counsel.</text>
    <annotations>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>History</heading>
        <annotation>Apr. 27, 1937, 50 Stat. 120, ch. 144, § 4</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 6-83">Feb. 21, 1986, D.C. Law 6-83, § 4(c), 32 DCR 7276</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Prior Codifications</heading>
        <annotation>1981 Ed., § 6-304.</annotation>
        <annotation>1973 Ed., § 6-204.</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
    </annotations>
  </section>
</document>
