<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<document xmlns:codify="http://code.dccouncil.us/schemas/codify" id="D.C. Law 4-108">
  <num type="law">4-108</num>
  <heading type="short">District of Columbia Administration of Oaths, Public Assistance Technical Clarification, and Police Service and Fire Service Schedule Approval Act of 1982</heading>
  <meta>
    <effective>1982-05-19</effective>
    <cites>
      <law lawId="108" period="4" url="./docs/4-108.pdf"/>
      <register page="1413" vol="29"/>
    </cites>
    <history>
      <narrative>Law 4-108, the “District of Columbia Administration of Oaths, Public Assistance Technical Clarification, and Police Service and Fire Service Schedule Approval Act of 1982,” was introduced in Council and assigned Bill No. 4-397, which was referred to the Committee of the Whole. The Bill was adopted on first and second readings on February 23, 1982 and March 9, 1982, respectively. Signed by the Mayor on March 26, 1982, it was assigned Act No. 4-169 and transmitted to both Houses of Congress for its review.</narrative>
    </history>
  </meta>
  <section from-code="true">
    <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" before="§1-301.23" path="|1|3|I|B"/>
    <num codify:value="1-301.22">2</num>
    <heading>Administration of oaths.</heading>
    <text>The Mayor of the District of Columbia, the Chairman of the Council of the District of Columbia, and the members of the Council of the District of Columbia may administer oaths as part of their official responsibilities. No fee shall be collected for the administration of such oaths, and the power to administer such oaths shall not be utilized for personal purposes.</text>
    <annotations>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>History</heading>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 4-108">May 19, 1982, D.C. Law 4-108, § 2, 29 DCR 1413</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Cross References</heading>
        <annotation>Council’s authority, power to investigate, issue subpoenas, and administer oaths, see § <cite path="§1-204.13">1-204.13</cite>.</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Prior Codifications</heading>
        <annotation>1981 Ed., § 1-338.1.</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
    </annotations>
  </section>
</document>
