<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<document xmlns:codify="http://code.dccouncil.us/schemas/codify" id="D.C. Law 4-87">
  <num type="law">4-87</num>
  <meta>
    <effective>1982-03-16</effective>
    <cites>
      <law lawId="87" period="4" url="./docs/4-87.pdf"/>
      <register page="433" vol="29"/>
    </cites>
    <history>
      <narrative>Law 4-87 was introduced in Council and assigned Bill No. 4-181, which was referred to the Committee of the Whole. The Bill was adopted on first and second readings on November 24, 1981 and December 8, 1981, respectively. Approved without the signature of the Mayor on January 19, 1981, it was assigned Act No. 4-141 and transmitted to both Houses of Congress for its review.</narrative>
    </history>
  </meta>
  <section from-code="true">
    <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" path="|1|10|V"/>
    <num codify:value="1-1041.01">2</num>
    <heading>Establishment of ward task forces on Advisory Neighborhood Commissions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>(a)</num>
      <text>Each member of the Council of the District of Columbia (“Council”) elected from a ward shall appoint a broadly-based ward task force on Advisory Neighborhood Commissions (“ward task force”) for his or her ward.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(b)</num>
      <text>In appointing the members of a ward task force, each Councilmember shall give full consideration to assuring fair representation for all racial and ethnic minorities, women, and geographical areas in his or her ward.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(c)</num>
      <text>Each member of a ward task force shall be a registered voter and resident of the ward for which his or her ward task force is appointed.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(d)</num>
      <text>Each member of the Council elected at-large and the Chairman of the Council may appoint a person to each ward task force.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(e)</num>
      <text>Ward task force members shall serve until the ward task force files its final report with the Council unless the Council, by resolution, extends the term of the ward task force.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(f)</num>
      <text>Each ward task force member shall serve without compensation.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>History</heading>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 4-87">Mar. 16, 1982, D.C. Law 4-87, § 2, 29 DCR 433</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 4-199">Mar. 10, 1983, D.C. Law 4-199, § 5, 30 DCR 119</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Cross References</heading>
        <annotation>Single-member districts, establishment and boundaries, subsequent adjustment of boundaries, see § <cite path="§1-309.03">1-309.03</cite>.</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Section References</heading>
        <annotation>This section is referenced in § <cite path="§1-309.03">1-309.03</cite>.</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Prior Codifications</heading>
        <annotation>1981 Ed., § 1-1331.</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section from-code="true">
    <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" path="|1|10|V"/>
    <num codify:value="1-1041.02">3</num>
    <heading>Report of ward task forces.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>(a)</num>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Each ward task force shall submit a report to the Council not later than 90 days after approval by the Mayor (or in the event of veto by the Mayor, action by the Council to override the veto) of legislation that reapportions the boundaries of the election wards pursuant to § <cite path="§1-1011.01">1-1011.01</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The Mayor and the District of Columbia Board of Elections and Ethics (“Board”) shall provide each ward task force with technical and analytical services necessary for decennial redistricting, including, but not limited to, statistical and demographic analysis of official census data and production of computerized election district maps.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The Mayor and the Board shall make available to the public, at cost, copies of the census data base and any maps to be used for redistricting in hard copy or machine readable form.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(b)</num>
      <text>The report submitted by a ward task force shall contain:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>Alternative recommendations for the adjustment of the boundaries of Advisory Neighborhood Commission area and single-member districts for that ward; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Other recommendations with respect to the operation of advisory neighborhood commissions.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(c)</num>
      <text>In developing its report, each ward task force shall comply with the requirements of this section and the requirements of § <cite path="§1-309.03">1-309.03</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(d)</num>
      <text>The total District population and the population of defined sub-units of the District population as determined by the federal decennial census, or any official adjustment to the federal decennial census, shall be the exclusive permissible population data for apportionment of single-member districts.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(e)</num>
      <text>No redistricting plan or proposed amendment to a redistricting plan shall result in district populations with a deviation range greater than 10% or a relative deviation greater than plus-or-minus 5%, unless the deviation results from the limitations of census geography or from the promotion of a rational public policy, including, but not limited to, respect for the political geography of the District, the natural geography of the District, neighborhood cohesiveness, or the development of compact and contiguous districts.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(f)</num>
      <text>No redistricting plan or proposed amendment to a redistricting plan shall be considered if the plan or amendment has the purpose and effect of diluting the voting strength of minority citizens.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>History</heading>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 4-87">Mar. 16, 1982, D.C. Law 4-87, § 3, 29 DCR 433</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 4-199">Mar. 10, 1983, D.C. Law 4-199, § 5, 30 DCR 119</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 8-240">Mar. 8, 1991, D.C. Law 8-240, § 4, 38 DCR 337</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Prior Codifications</heading>
        <annotation>1981 Ed., § 1-1332.</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section from-code="true">
    <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" path="|1|10|V"/>
    <num codify:value="1-1041.03">4</num>
    <heading>Adoption of election ward boundaries effective January 1, 2012.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>(a)</num>
      <text>Notwithstanding § <cite path="§1-1011.01">1-1011.01</cite>(h), and notwithstanding any other provision, the Council adopts the following election ward boundaries to be effective January 1, 2012, and to be used in all elections held after February 1, 2012, in the District of Columbia:</text>
      <para>
        <heading>WARD I</heading>
        <text>Starting at the intersection of a line projected from Rock Creek to Piney Branch Parkway N.W.; thence in an easterly direction along said Piney Branch Parkway, N.W., to Sixteenth Street, N.W.; thence south along said Sixteenth Street, N.W., to Spring Road, N.W.; thence in an easterly direction along said Spring Road, N.W., to New Hampshire Avenue, N.W.; thence in a northeasterly direction along said New Hampshire Avenue, N.W., to Rock Creek Church Road, N.W.; thence in an easterly direction along said Rock Creek Church Road, N.W., to Park Place, N.W.; thence south along said Park Place, N.W., to Michigan Avenue, N.W.; thence in an easterly direction along said Michigan Avenue, N.W., to First Street, N.W.; thence south along said First Street, N.W., to Bryant Street, N.W.; thence in a westerly direction along said Bryant Street, N.W., to Second Street, N.W.; thence south along said Second Street, N.W., to Rhode Island Avenue, N.W.; thence in a westerly direction along said Rhode Island Avenue, N.W., to Florida Avenue, N.W.; thence in a westerly direction along said Florida Avenue, N.W., to T Street, N.W.; thence in a westerly direction along said T Street, N.W., to Wiltberger Street, N.W.; thence in a southerly direction along said Wiltberger Street, N.W., to S Street, N.W.; thence west along said S Street, N.W., to Fourteenth Street, N.W.; thence north along said Fourteenth Street, N.W., to U Street, N.W.; thence west along said U Street, N.W., to Florida Avenue, N.W.; thence in a southwesterly direction along said Florida Avenue, N.W., to Connecticut Avenue, N.W.; thence in a northwesterly direction along said Connecticut Avenue, N.W., to the center line of Rock Creek; thence in a northeasterly direction along said Rock Creek to the intersection of a line projected from the end of Piney Branch Parkway; thence along said projected line to Piney Branch Parkway, N.W.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <heading>WARD II</heading>
        <text>Starting at the intersection of the center line of Connecticut Avenue, N.W., and the center line of Rock Creek; thence southeasterly along said Connecticut Avenue, N.W., to Florida Avenue, N.W.; thence in an easterly direction along said Florida Avenue, N.W., to U Street, N.W.; thence east along said U Street, N.W., to Fourteenth Street, N.W.; thence south along said Fourteenth Street, N.W., to S Street, N.W.; thence east along said S Street, N.W., to Eleventh Street, N.W.; thence south along said Eleventh Street, N.W., to P Street, N.W.; thence east along said P Street, N.W., to Ninth Street, N.W.; thence south along Ninth Street, N.W., to N street, N.W.; thence east along N Street, N.W., to the alley running along the eastern side of the Washington Convention Center; thence south along said alley to M Street, N.W.; thence east along said M Street, N.W., to Seventh Street, N.W.; thence south along Seventh Street, N.W., to Massachusetts Avenue, N.W.; thence along said Massachusetts Avenue, N.W., to the eastern boundary of Interstate 395; thence south along the said eastern boundary of Interstate 395 to the point where it crosses beneath Constitution Avenue, N.W.; thence east along said Constitution Avenue, N.W., to its intersection with a line extending north from the center line of South Capitol Street through the center of the Capitol building; thence south along said line to Independence Avenue, S.W.; thence west along said Independence Avenue, S.W., to Fourteenth Street, S.W.; thence south along said Fourteenth Street, S.W., to a center line projection of the Washington Channel; thence in a southerly direction along the center line projection of Washington Channel to a center line projection of the Anacostia River; thence southwesterly along the center line of said Anacostia River and the projection of that center line to the Commonwealth of Virginia-District of Columbia boundary line at the Commonwealth of Virginia shore of the Potomac River; thence in a northwesterly direction along said Commonwealth of Virginia-District of Columbia boundary line to its intersection with a line extending the eastern boundary of Glover Archbold Park south to the Commonwealth of Virginia shore of the Potomac River; thence in a northerly direction from said boundary line to the southern boundary of the eastern leg of Glover Archbold Park; thence in an easterly direction along the southern boundary of the eastern leg of Glover Archbold Park to Whitehaven Parkway, N.W.; thence east along Whitehaven Parkway, N.W., to Thirty-Fifth Street, N.W.; thence in a northerly direction along said Thirty-Fifth Street, N.W., to Wisconsin Avenue, N.W.; thence in a southeasterly direction along said Wisconsin Avenue, N.W., to Whitehaven Street, N.W.; thence in an easterly direction along said Whitehaven Street, N.W., to the northwest boundary of Dumbarton Oaks Park; thence in an easterly direction along said northwest boundary of Dumbarton Oaks Park to Whitehaven Street, N.W.; thence in an easterly direction along said Whitehaven Street, N.W., to Massachusetts Avenue, N.W.; thence in a southeasterly direction along said Massachusetts Avenue, N.W., to the center line of Rock Creek; thence in a northeasterly direction along said center line of Rock Creek to the point of beginning at its intersection with Connecticut Avenue, N.W.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <heading>WARD III</heading>
        <text>Starting at the intersection of the State of Maryland-District of Columbia boundary line and the center line of Broad Branch Road, N.W.; thence in a southerly direction along said Broad Branch Road to Twenty-Seventh Street, N.W.; thence in a northerly direction along said Twenty-Seventh Street, N.W., to Military Road, N.W.; thence in an easterly direction along said Military Road, N.W., to the center line of Rock Creek; thence in a southerly direction along Rock Creek to its intersection with the center line of Massachusetts Avenue, N.W.; thence in a northwesterly direction along said Massachusetts Avenue, N.W., to Whitehaven Street, N.W.; thence west along said Whitehaven Street, N.W., to the northwestern boundary of Dumbarton Oaks Park; thence in a westerly direction along said northwestern boundary of said Dumbarton Oaks Park to Whitehaven Street, N.W.; thence in a westerly direction along said Whitehaven Street, N.W., to Wisconsin Avenue, N.W.; thence in a northwesterly direction along said Wisconsin Avenue, N.W., to Thirty-Fifth Street, N.W.; thence south along said Thirty-Fifth Street, N.W., to Whitehaven Parkway, N.W.; thence west along said Whitehaven Parkway, N.W., to the southern boundary of the eastern leg of Glover Archbold Park; thence in a westerly direction along said southern boundary of the eastern leg of Glover Archbold Park to a point where it intersects with the eastern boundary of Glover Archbold Park; thence in a southerly direction along the eastern boundary of Glover Archbold Park, extending said boundary along a line south to the Commonwealth of Virginia shore of the Potomac River; thence in a northwesterly direction along said Commonwealth of Virginia-District of Columbia boundary line where it follows the Commonwealth of Virginia shore of the Potomac River to the western corner of the District of Columbia; thence in a northeasterly direction along the State of Maryland-District of Columbia boundary line to the point of beginning at its intersection with Broad Branch Road, N.W.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <heading>WARD IV</heading>
        <text>Starting at the intersection of the State of Maryland-District of Columbia boundary line and the center line of Broad Branch Road, N.W.; thence in a southerly direction along said Broad Branch Road to Twenty-Seventh Street, N.W.; thence in a northerly direction along said Twenty-Seventh Street, N.W., to Military Road, N.W.; thence in an easterly direction along said Military Road, N.W., to the center line of Rock Creek; thence along said Rock Creek to the intersection of a line projected from the end of Piney Branch Parkway; thence along said projected line to Piney Branch Parkway N.W.; thence in an easterly direction along said Piney Branch Parkway, N.W., to Sixteenth Street, N.W.; thence south along said Sixteenth Street, N.W., to Spring Road, N.W.; thence in an easterly direction along said Spring Road, N.W., to New Hampshire Avenue, N.W.; thence in a northeasterly direction along said New Hampshire Avenue, N.W., to Rock Creek Church Road, N.W.; thence in a northeasterly direction along said Rock Creek Church Road, N.W., to North Capitol Street, N.W.; thence in a northerly direction along said North Capitol Street to Riggs Road, N.E.; thence in a northeasterly direction along said Riggs Road, N.E., to South Dakota Avenue, N.E.; thence in a southeasterly direction along said South Dakota Avenue, N.E., to Kennedy Street, N.E.; thence in an easterly direction along said Kennedy Street, N.E., to the intersection of its center line with the State of Maryland-District of Columbia boundary line; thence in a northwesterly direction along said boundary line to the northern corner of the District of Columbia; thence in a southwesterly direction along said State of Maryland-District of Columbia boundary line to the point of beginning at its intersection with the center line of Broad Branch Road, N.W.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <heading>WARD V</heading>
        <text>Starting at the intersection of First Street, N.W., and Michigan Avenue, N.W.; thence south along said First Street, N.W., to Bryant Street, N.W.; thence in a westerly direction along said Bryant Street, N.W., to Second Street, N.W.; thence south on said Second Street, N.W., to Rhode Island Avenue, N.W.; thence in a westerly direction along said Rhode Island Avenue, N.W., to Florida Avenue, N.W.; thence in a northwesterly direction along said Florida Avenue, N.W., to New Jersey Avenue, N.W.; thence in a southerly direction along said New Jersey Avenue, N.W., to N Street, N.W.; thence east along said N Street, N.W., to Kirby Street, N.W.; thence south along said Kirby Street, N.W., to New York Avenue, N.W.; thence in an easterly direction along said New York Avenue, N.W., to New York Avenue, N.E., to Florida Avenue, N.E.; thence in an easterly direction along said Florida Avenue, N.E., to Benning Road, N.E.; thence in an easterly direction along said Benning Road, N.E., to the center line of the Anacostia River; thence in a northerly direction along the Anacostia River to the intersection of its center line with the State of Maryland-District of Columbia boundary line; thence in a northwesterly direction along said boundary line to Kennedy Street, N.E.; thence in a westerly direction along said Kennedy Street, N.E., to South Dakota Avenue, N.E.; thence in a northwesterly direction along said South Dakota Avenue, N.E., to Riggs Road, N.E.; thence in a westerly direction along Riggs Road, N.E., to North Capitol Street; thence in a southerly direction along said North Capitol Street to Rock Creek Church Road, N.W.; thence in a southwesterly direction along said Rock Creek Church Road, N.W., to Park Place, N.W.; thence south along said Park Place, N.W., to Michigan Avenue, N.W.; thence in an easterly direction along said Michigan Avenue, N.W., to the point of beginning at its intersection with First Street, N.W.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <heading>WARD VI</heading>
        <text>Starting at the intersection of North Capitol Street and New York Avenue, N.W.; thence southwesterly along New York Avenue, N.W., to Kirby Street, N.W.; thence north along said Kirby Street, N.W., to N Street, N.W.; thence west along said N Street, N.W., to New Jersey Avenue. N.W.; thence northwesterly along said New Jersey Avenue, N.W., to Florida Avenue, N.W.; thence in a northwesterly direction along said Florida Avenue, N.W., to T Street, N.W.; thence in a westerly direction along said T Street, N.W., to Wiltberger Street, N.W.; thence in a southerly direction along said Wiltberger Street, N.W., to S Street, N.W.; thence west along said S Street, N.W., to Eleventh Street, N.W.; thence south along said Eleventh Street, N.W., to P Street, N.W.; thence east said P Street, N.W., to Ninth Street, N.W.; thence in a south along said Ninth Street, N.W., to N Street, N.W.; thence east along said N street, N.W., to the alley running along the eastern side of the Washington Convention Center; thence south along said alley to M Street, N.W.; thence east along said M Street, N.W., to Seventh Street, N.W.; thence south along Seventh Street, N.W., to Massachusetts Avenue, N.W.; to the eastern boundary of Interstate 395; thence south along the said eastern boundary of Interstate 395 to the point where it crosses beneath Constitution Avenue, N.W.; thence east along said Constitution Avenue, N.W., to its intersection with a line extending north from the center line of South Capitol Street through the center of the Capitol building; thence south along said line to Independence Avenue, S.W.; thence west along said Independence Avenue, S.W., to Fourteenth Street, S.W.; thence south along said Fourteenth Street, S.W., to a center line projection of the Washington Channel; thence in a southerly direction along the center line projection of Washington Channel to a center line projection of the Anacostia River; thence in a northeasterly direction along said center line of the Anacostia River to a line extending from the northern property line of the eastern portion of Congressional Cemetery; thence in a westerly direction along said boundary of the Congressional Cemetery to its intersection with Nineteenth Street, S.E.; thence north along said Nineteenth Street, S.E., to East Capitol Street; thence east along the northern portion of East Capitol Street to Twenty-Second Street N.E.; thence in a northerly direction along said Twenty-Second Street N.E., to C Street N.E.; thence west along said C Street N.E., to Nineteenth Street N.E.; thence north along said Nineteenth Street, N.E., to Benning Road, N.E.; thence in a westerly direction along said Benning Road, N.E., to Florida Avenue, N.E.; thence in a northwesterly direction along Florida Avenue, N.E., to New York Avenue, N.E., and west along New York Avenue, N.E., to the point of beginning at its intersection with North Capitol Street.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <heading>WARD VII</heading>
        <text>Starting at the intersection of the State of Maryland-District of Columbia boundary line and the center line of the Anacostia River; thence in a southerly direction along the center line of said Anacostia River to Benning Road, N.E.; thence in a northwesterly direction along said Benning Road to Nineteenth Street, N.E; thence in a southerly direction along said Nineteenth Street, N.E., to C Street N.E.; thence east along said C Street N.E., to Twenty-Second Street N.E.; thence south along Twenty-Second Street N.E., to the northern portion of East Capitol Street; thence west along said East Capitol Street to Nineteenth Street S.E.; thence south along said Nineteenth Street S.E., to its intersection with the property line of Congressional Cemetery; thence in an easterly direction along said property line to its easternmost point and continuing east on the same bearing to the centerline of the Anacostia River; thence in a southwesterly direction along said Anacostia River to its intersection with Pennsylvania Avenue S.E.; thence along a line connecting to the intersection of Nicholson Street, S.E., and Anacostia Drive S.E.; thence south along said Nicholson Street S.E., to Minnesota Avenue, S.E; thence northerly along said Minnesota Avenue, S.E., to Twenty-Fifth Street, S.E.; thence south along said Twenty-Fifth Street, S.E., to Naylor Road, S.E.; thence in a southeasterly direction along said Naylor Road, S.E., to the State of Maryland-District of Columbia boundary line; thence in a northeasterly direction along said State of Maryland-District of Columbia boundary line to the eastern corner of the District of Columbia; thence in a northwesterly direction along the State of Maryland-District of Columbia boundary line to the point of beginning at its intersection with the center line of the Anacostia River.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <heading>WARD VIII</heading>
        <text>Starting at the intersection of the Commonwealth of Virginia-District of Columbia boundary line on the Commonwealth of Virginia shore of the Potomac River with the projection of the center line of the Anacostia River; thence in a northerly direction along the Anacostia River to Pennsylvania Avenue, S.E.; thence along a line connecting to the intersection of Nicholson Street, S.E., and Anacostia Drive, S.E.; thence south along said Nicholson Street, S.E., to Minnesota Avenue, S.E.; thence in a northerly direction along said Minnesota Avenue, S.E., to Twenty-Fifth Street, S.E.; thence south along said Twenty-Fifth Street, S.E., to Naylor Road, S.E.; thence in a southeasterly direction along said Naylor Road, S.E., to the State of Maryland-District of Columbia boundary line; thence in a southwesterly direction along said State of Maryland-District of Columbia boundary line to the southern corner of the District of Columbia on the Commonwealth of Virginia shore of the Potomac River; thence along the Commonwealth of Virginia-District of Columbia boundary line to the point of beginning at its intersection with the projection of the center line of the Anacostia River.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(b)</num>
      <text>Except where otherwise indicated, the boundary line is the center of the street.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>History</heading>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 4-87">Mar. 16, 1982, D.C. Law 4-87, § 4, 29 DCR 433</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 9-26">Aug. 17, 1991, D.C. Law 9-26, § 2, 38 DCR 4198</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 9-65">Mar. 11, 1992, D.C. Law 9-65, § 2, 39 DCR 8</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 14-27">Oct. 2, 2001, D.C. Law 14-27, § 2, 48 DCR 6380</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 19-38">Nov. 16, 2011, D.C. Law 19-38, § 2, 58 DCR 5823</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 19-171">Sept. 26, 2012, D.C. Law 19-171, § 147, 59 DCR 6190</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Section References</heading>
        <annotation>This section is referenced in § <cite path="§7-1671.06">7-1671.06</cite>, § <cite path="§25-340.01">25-340.01</cite>, § <cite path="§25-342">25-342</cite>, § <cite path="§25-343">25-343</cite>, § <cite path="§25-345">25-345</cite>, § <cite path="§25-346">25-346</cite>, and § <cite path="§25-374">25-374</cite>.</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Prior Codifications</heading>
        <annotation>1981 Ed., § 1-1333.</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Effect of Amendments</heading>
        <annotation><cite doc="D.C. Law 14-27">D.C. Law 14-27</cite> rewrote the section.</annotation>
        <annotation>The 2012 amendment by <cite doc="D.C. Law 19-171">D.C. Law 19-171</cite> added “Notwithstanding § <cite path="§1-1011.01">1-1011.01</cite>(h), and notwithstanding any other provision” in the introductory language of (a); substituted “to N Street, N.W.; thence east along said N Street, N.W., to Kirby Street, N.W.; thence south along said Kirby Street, N.W., to New York Avenue, N.W.; thence in an easterly direction along said New York Avenue, N.W.” for “to New York Avenue, N.W.; thence in an easterly direction along said New York Avenue, N.W.” in the boundary description for Ward V in (a); and substituted “thence along a line connecting to the intersection of Nicholson Street, S.E., and Anacostia Drive, S.E.; thence south along said Nicholson Street, S.E., to Minnesota Avenue, S.E.; thence in a northerly direction along said Minnesota Avenue, S.E.” for “thence in an easterly direction along said Pennsylvania Avenue, S.E.” in the boundary description for Ward VIII in (a).</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Temporary Amendment of Section</heading>
        <annotation>Section 2 of <cite doc="D.C. Law 19-92">D.C. Law 19-92</cite>, in subsec. (a), substituted “Notwithstanding section 2(h) of the Boundaries Act of 1975, effective December 16, 1975 (<cite doc="D.C. Law 1-38">D.C. Law 1-38</cite>; D.C. Official Code § <cite path="§1-1011.01">1-1011.01</cite>(h)), and notwithstanding any other provision, the Council” for “The Council”,; in the boundaries for Ward 5 in subsec. (a), substituted “to N Street, N.W.; thence east along said N Street, N.W., to Kirby Street, N.W.; thence south along said Kirby Street, N.W., to New York Avenue, N.W.; thence in an easterly direction along said New York Avenue, N.W.,” for “to New York Avenue, N.W.; thence in an easterly direction along said New York Avenue, N.W.,”; in the boundaries for Ward 8 in subsec. (a), substituted “thence along a line connecting to the intersection of Nicholson Street, S.E., and Anacostia Drive, S.E.; thence south along said Nicholson Street, S.E., to Minnesota Avenue, S.E.; thence in a northerly direction along said Minnesota Avenue, S.E.,” for “thence in an easterly direction along said Pennsylvania Avenue, S.E.,”; and added subsec. (c) to read as follows: “(c) The election ward boundaries set forth in subsection (a) of this section that become effective January 1, 2012, shall apply for the purpose of determining the ward residence of a person signing a nominating petition for the April 3, 2012 primary election during the period from November 14, 2011 through December 31, 2011.”.</annotation>
        <annotation>Section 4(b) of <cite doc="D.C. Law 19-92">D.C. Law 19-92</cite> provided that the act shall expire after 225 days of its having taken effect.</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Emergency Legislation</heading>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 day) amendment of section, see §§ 2, 4 of Ward Redistricting Emergency Amendment Act of 2011 (D.C. Act 19-218, November 4, 2011,  58 DCR 9464).</annotation>
        <annotation>For temporary (90 day) amendment of section, see § 2 of Ward Redistricting Congressional Review Emergency Amendment Act of 2012 (D.C. Act 19-311, February 21, 2012,  59 DCR 1699).</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section from-code="true">
    <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" path="|1|10|V"/>
    <num codify:value="1-1041.04">6</num>
    <heading>Residency requirement.</heading>
    <text>No official elected from any ward or from any single-member district shall be required to forfeit his or her office solely by reason of a change in boundaries which places the residence of such official outside the ward or single-member district from which he or she was elected. Such official shall be permitted to complete his or her term of office, but in future elections he or she may be a candidate only in the ward or single-member district in which he or she resides.</text>
    <annotations>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>History</heading>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 4-87">Mar. 16, 1982, D.C. Law 4-87, § 6, 29 DCR 433</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Prior Codifications</heading>
        <annotation>1981 Ed., § 1-1334.</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
    </annotations>
  </section>
</document>
