<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<document xmlns:codify="http://code.dccouncil.us/schemas/codify" id="D.C. Law 2-103">
  <num type="law">2-103</num>
  <heading type="short">Home Purchase Assistance Fund Act of 1978</heading>
  <meta>
    <effective>1978-09-12</effective>
    <cites>
      <law lawId="103" period="2" url="./docs/2-103.pdf"/>
      <register page="1977" vol="25"/>
    </cites>
    <history>
      <narrative>Law 2-103, the “Home Purchase Assistance Fund Act of 1978,” was introduced in Council and assigned Bill No. 2-316, which was referred to the Committee on Housing and Urban Development. The Bill was adopted on first and second readings on June 13, 1978, and June 27, 1978, respectively. Signed by the Mayor on July 1, 1978, it was assigned Act No. 2-214 and transmitted to both Houses of Congress for its review.</narrative>
    </history>
  </meta>
  <section from-code="true">
    <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" path="|42|26|I"/>
    <num codify:value="42-2601">2</num>
    <heading>Establishment; purpose; unexpended balance.</heading>
    <text>There is hereby established in the District of Columbia and there is authorized, and accounted for in the General Fund as a separate revenue source allocable to provide financial assistance to low and moderate income persons, and District of Columbia Government employees participating in the District of Columbia Employer-Assisted Housing Program, and families seeking to purchase homes in the District of Columbia, for the purposes of enabling them to purchase decent, safe, and sanitary homes in the District of Columbia. Any unexpended balance at the end of the year shall be reserved as a restricted fund balance and used to provide authorization to expend for subsequent years subject to the direction of the Mayor.</text>
    <annotations>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>History</heading>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 2-103">Sept. 12, 1978, D.C. Law 2-103, § 2, 25 DCR 1977</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 3-70">June 14, 1980, D.C. Law 3-70, § 7(1), 27 DCR 1776</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 4-44">Oct. 24, 1981, D.C. Law 4-44, § 2(b), 28 DCR 4265</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 6-151">Sept. 23, 1986, D.C. Law 6-151, § 2(a), 33 DCR 4783</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 9-118">June 11, 1992, D.C. Law 9-118, § 8(a), 39 DCR 3189</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 12-60">Mar. 20, 1998, D.C. Law 12-60, § 1101, 44 DCR 7378</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 12-259">Apr. 20, 1999, D.C. Law 12-259, § 2(a), 46 DCR 1316</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 13-96">May 9, 2000, D.C. Law 13-96, § 9(a), 47 DCR 1081</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Prior Codifications</heading>
        <annotation>1981 Ed., § 45-2201.</annotation>
        <annotation>1973 Ed., § 45-1801.</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Effect of Amendments</heading>
        <annotation><cite doc="D.C. Law 13-96">D.C. Law 13-96</cite> inserted “the District of Columbia Government employees participating in the District of Columbia Employer-Assisted Housing Program” following “low and moderate income persons.”</annotation>
        <annotation>Section 11 of <cite doc="D.C. Law 13-96">D.C. Law 13-96</cite> provided: “This act shall apply as of October 1, 1997.”</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Emergency Legislation</heading>
        <annotation>For temporary (90-day) amendment of section, see § 9(a) of the Government Employer-Assisted Housing Emergency Amendment Act of 1999 (D.C. Act 13-188, December 1, 1999,  46 DCR 10407).</annotation>
        <annotation>For temporary (90-day) amendment of section, see § 9(a) of the Government Employer-Assisted Housing Legislative Review Emergency Amendment Act of 1999 (D.C. Act 13-258, February 9, 2000,  47 DCR 1124).</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Repeal of Law</heading>
        <text>Repeal of Law 9-118</text>
        <text>Section 1101 of <cite doc="D.C. Law 12-60">D.C. Law 12-60</cite> repealed the District of Columbia Employer-Assisted Housing Act of 1992, <cite doc="D.C. Law 9-118">D.C. Law 9-118</cite>.</text>
      </annoGroup>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section from-code="true">
    <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" path="|42|26|I"/>
    <num codify:value="42-2602">3</num>
    <heading>Deposits to credit of Fund.</heading>
    <text>There shall be deposited to the credit of the Fund such amounts as may be appropriated pursuant to this subchapter; grants and gifts from public and private sources to the Fund or to the District of Columbia for the purposes of the Fund; repayments of principal and any interest on loans provided from the Fund; proceeds realized from the liquidation of any security interests held by the District of Columbia under the terms of any assistance provided from the Fund; interest earned from the deposit or investment of monies of the Fund; repayments of principal and any interest on loans provided under the District of Columbia Government Employer-Assisted Housing Program; and all other revenues, receipts and fees of whatever nature derived from the operation of the Fund.</text>
    <annotations>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>History</heading>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 2-103">Sept. 12, 1978, D.C. Law 2-103, § 3, 25 DCR 1977</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 9-118">June 11, 1992, D.C. Law 9-118, § 8(b), 39 DCR 3189</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 12-60">Mar. 20, 1998, D.C. Law 12-60, § 1101, 44 DCR 7378</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 13-96">May 9, 2000, D.C. Law 13-96, § 9(b), 47 DCR 1081</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Prior Codifications</heading>
        <annotation>1981 Ed., § 45-2202.</annotation>
        <annotation>1973 Ed., § 45-1802.</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Effect of Amendments</heading>
        <annotation><cite doc="D.C. Law 13-96">D.C. Law 13-96</cite> inserted “repayments of principal and any interest on loans provided under the District of Columbia Government Employer-Assisted Housing Program;” following “interest earned from the deposit or investment of monies of the Fund;”.</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Emergency Legislation</heading>
        <annotation>For temporary (90-day) amendment of section, see § 9(b) of the Government Employer-Assisted Housing Emergency Amendment Act of 1999 (D.C. Act 13-188, December 1, 1999,  46 DCR 10407).</annotation>
        <annotation>For temporary (90-day) amendment of section, see § 9(b) of the Government Employer-Assisted Housing Legislative Review Emergency Amendment Act of 1999 (D.C. Act 13-258, February 9, 2000,  47 DCR 1124).</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Repeal of Law</heading>
        <text>Repeal of Law 9-118</text>
        <text>Section 1101 of <cite doc="D.C. Law 12-60">D.C. Law 12-60</cite> repealed the District of Columbia Employer-Assisted Housing Act of 1992, <cite doc="D.C. Law 9-118">D.C. Law 9-118</cite>.</text>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Editor's Notes</heading>
        <text>Because of the enactment of subchapter II of this chapter by <cite doc="D.C. Law 12-266">D.C. Law 12-266</cite>, “subchapter” has been substituted for “chapter”.</text>
        <text>Section 11 of <cite doc="D.C. Law 13-96">D.C. Law 13-96</cite> provided: “This act shall apply as of October 1, 1997.”</text>
      </annoGroup>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section from-code="true">
    <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" path="|42|26|I"/>
    <num codify:value="42-2603">4</num>
    <heading>Availability; use prescribed by Mayor.</heading>
    <text>The Fund shall be available without fiscal year limitation for the purpose of providing financial assistance for down payments or interim financing to recipients for the purpose of purchasing or securing housing, including single family homes, condominium units, or occupancy rights to cooperative housing in the District of Columbia as their principal place of residence and of providing financial assistance to District of Columbia government employees eligible under the District of Columbia Employer-Assisted Housing Program to purchase a home in the District of Columbia. Under terms and conditions prescribed by the Mayor of the District of Columbia (“Mayor”), the Fund shall be used for making loans and providing other forms of financial assistance. The assistance provided pursuant to the Fund may be used in conjunction with other available home assistance programs.</text>
    <annotations>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>History</heading>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 2-103">Sept. 12, 1978, D.C. Law 2-103, § 4, 25 DCR 1977</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 4-44">Oct. 24, 1981, D.C. Law 4-44, § 2(c), 28 DCR 4265</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 9-118">June 11, 1992, D.C. Law 9-118, § 8(c), 39 DCR 3189</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 12-60">Mar. 20, 1998, D.C. Law 12-60, § 1101, 44 DCR 7378</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 13-96">May 9, 2000, D.C. Law 13-96, § 9(c), 47 DCR 1081</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Prior Codifications</heading>
        <annotation>1981 Ed., § 45-2203.</annotation>
        <annotation>1973 Ed., § 45-1803.</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Effect of Amendments</heading>
        <annotation><cite doc="D.C. Law 13-96">D.C. Law 13-96</cite> rewrote the first sentence which formerly provided: “The Fund shall be available without fiscal year limitation for the purpose of providing financial assistance for down payments or interim financing to recipients for the purpose of purchasing or securing housing, including single family homes, condominium units, or occupancy rights to cooperative housing in the District of Columbia as their principal place of residence and of providing financial assistance to District of Columbia government employees eligible under the District of Columbia Employer-Assisted Housing Program to purchase a home in the District of Columbia.”</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Emergency Legislation</heading>
        <annotation>For temporary (90-day) amendment of section, see § 9(c) of the Government Employer-Assisted Housing Emergency Amendment Act of 1999 (D.C. Act 13-188, December 1, 1999,  46 DCR 10407).</annotation>
        <annotation>For temporary (90-day) amendment of section, see § 9(c) of the Government Employer-Assisted Housing Legislative Review Emergency Amendment Act of 1999 (D.C. Act 13-258, February 9, 2000,  47 DCR 1124).</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Repeal of Law</heading>
        <text>Repeal of Law 9-118</text>
        <text>Section 1101 of <cite doc="D.C. Law 12-60">D.C. Law 12-60</cite> repealed the District of Columbia Employer-Assisted Housing Act of 1992, <cite doc="D.C. Law 9-118">D.C. Law 9-118</cite>.</text>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Editor's Notes</heading>
        <annotation>Section 11 of <cite doc="D.C. Law 13-96">D.C. Law 13-96</cite> provided: “This act shall apply as of October 1, 1997.”</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section from-code="true">
    <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" path="|42|26|I"/>
    <num codify:value="42-2604">5</num>
    <heading>Promulgation of rules and regulations by Mayor; review by Council; contents of loan agreements.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>(a)</num>
      <text>The Mayor is authorized to promulgate rules and regulations to govern the operation of the Fund, including but not limited to, rules and regulations establishing standards for determining the eligibility and selection of applicants; procedures for applying for assistance and for notifying applicants (including the development of appropriate forms); and criteria for determining the terms and conditions under which loans or other forms of financial assistance may be made from the Fund which, among things, shall reflect the ability of the recipient to pay and may provide for the deferred payment or forgiveness of loans. The rules and regulations issued by the Mayor for the purpose of implementing the provisions of this subchapter shall be submitted by the Mayor to the Council of the District of Columbia for a 45 calendar day review period, excluding days of Council recess. No such rules or regulations shall take effect until the end of the 45 calendar day period beginning on the day such rules or regulations are transmitted by the Mayor to the Chairman of the Council, and then only if during such period, the Council does not adopt a resolution disapproving such rules and regulations in whole or in part.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(b)</num>
      <text>Any loan agreement entered into pursuant to such rules and regulations shall provide that:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>All applicants for and recipients of financial assistance from the Funds shall be tenant organizations (as defined in § <cite path="§42-3401.03">42-3401.03</cite>(18) or a first time homebuyer seeking to purchase housing in the District of Columbia as a primary residence including, but not limited to, single family homes, condominium units, or occupancy rights to cooperative housing. For the purposes of this section, the term “first time homebuyer” means a real property purchaser who had no ownership interest in his or her principal residence at any time during the 3 year period ending on the date of his or her application for assistance, but including an applicant who has divorced or separated during the 3 year period where a formal settlement has been made under which the applicant does not receive an ownership interest in a primary residence which had been jointly owned, and who has no other current ownership interest in residential real property.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(1A)</num>
        <text>Priority in the allocation of assistance under the Fund shall be given to residents of the District of Columbia and District of Columbia residents who are low income, elderly, displaced applicants, or residents with disabilities.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>If the home purchased ceases to be the primary residence of the recipient of financial assistance from the Fund, the payments to such Fund by the recipient shall be accelerated on terms and conditions prescribed by the Mayor; provided, that such obligation shall not be inconsistent with the applicable law or regulations of any federal home purchase assistance program made available to the recipient.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Repealed.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <annotations>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>History</heading>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 2-103">Sept. 12, 1978, D.C. Law 2-103, § 5, 25 DCR 1977</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 4-44">Oct. 24, 1981, D.C. Law 4-44, § 2(d), 28 DCR 4265</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 6-151">Sept. 23, 1986, D.C. Law 6-151, § 2(b), 33 DCR 4783</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 12-259">Apr. 20, 1999, D.C. Law 12-259, § 2(b), 46 DCR 1316</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 16-305">Apr. 24, 2007, D.C. Law 16-305, § 61, 53 DCR 6198</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Cross References</heading>
        <annotation>Lower income homeownership households, qualifications, see § <cite path="§47-3502">47-3502</cite>.</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Section References</heading>
        <annotation>This section is referenced in § <cite path="§47-3502">47-3502</cite>.</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Prior Codifications</heading>
        <annotation>1981 Ed., § 45-2204.</annotation>
        <annotation>1973 Ed., § 45-1804.</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Effect of Amendments</heading>
        <annotation><cite doc="D.C. Law 16-305">D.C. Law 16-305</cite>, in subsec. (b)(1A), substituted “displaced applicants, or residents with disabilities” for “handicapped, disabled, or displaced applicants”.</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Resolutions</heading>
        <annotation>Resolution 16-651, the “Home Purchase Assistance Program Approval Resolution of 2006”, was approved effective May 29, 2006.</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Editor's Notes</heading>
        <text>Because of the enactment of subchapter II of this chapter by <cite doc="D.C. Law 12-266">D.C. Law 12-266</cite>, “subchapter” has been substituted for “chapter” in the second sentence of (a).</text>
        <text>Home Purchase Assistance Program Loan Repayment Resolution of 1998: Pursuant to Resolution 12-(PR12-890), effective October 7, 1998, the Council approved the amendment of Chapter 25 of the Home Purchase Assistance Program Regulations to authorize the use of loan repayment funds to pay reasonable administrative costs associated with making loans.</text>
      </annoGroup>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section from-code="true">
    <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" path="|42|26|I"/>
    <num codify:value="42-2605">6</num>
    <heading>Annual audit; report to Congress and Council; appropriations.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>(a)</num>
      <text>An annual audit of the operations of the Fund shall be conducted by the Office of the Inspector General of the District of Columbia.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(b)</num>
      <text>Not later than 6 months after the end of each fiscal year, the Mayor shall submit to the Congress of the United States and to the Council of the District of Columbia a report of the financial condition of the Fund and the results of the operations for such fiscal year.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(c)</num>
      <text>The Mayor shall include in the budget estimates of the District of Columbia for each fiscal year, and there is authorized to be appropriated annually, such amounts out of the revenues of the District of Columbia as may be required for the Fund.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>History</heading>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 2-103">Sept. 12, 1978, D.C. Law 2-103, § 6, 25 DCR 1977</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 4-44">Oct. 24, 1981, D.C. Law 4-44, § 2(e), 28 DCR 4265</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Prior Codifications</heading>
        <annotation>1981 Ed., § 45-2205.</annotation>
        <annotation>1973 Ed., § 45-1805.</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Mayor's Orders</heading>
        <annotation>Office of Internal Audits and Inspections abolished: The District of Columbia Office of Internal Audits and Inspections was replaced by Mayor’s Order 79-7, dated January 2, 1979, and Mayor’s Order 79-224, dated September 24, 1979, which Orders established the Office of the Inspection General of the District of Columbia.</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
    </annotations>
  </section>
</document>
