<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<document xmlns:codify="http://code.dccouncil.us/schemas/codify" id="D.C. Law 2-40" flag="true">
  <num type="law">2-40</num>
  <meta>
    <effective>1978-02-22</effective>
    <cites>
      <law lawId="40" period="2" url="./docs/2-40.pdf"/>
      <register page="3344" vol="24"/>
    </cites>
    <history>
      <narrative>Law 2-40 was introduced in Council and assigned Bill No. 2-121, which was referred to the Committee on Transportation and Environmental Affairs. The Bill was adopted on first and second readings on July 26, 1977 and September 13, 1977, respectively. Signed by the Mayor on October 25, 1977, it was assigned Act No. 2-92 and transmitted to both Houses of Congress for its review.</narrative>
    </history>
  </meta>
  <section from-code="true">
    <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" path="|35|2|I"/>
    <num codify:value="35-216">2</num>
    <heading>Failure to pay established fare or to present valid transfer; entry by rear exit door prohibited.</heading>
    <text>No person shall either knowingly board a public or private passenger vehicle for hire, including vehicles owned and/or operated by the Washington Metropolitan Area Transit Authority, which is transporting passengers within the corporate limits of the District of Columbia; or knowingly board a rail transit car owned and/or operated by the Washington Metropolitan Area Transit Authority which is transporting passengers within the corporate limits of the District of Columbia; or knowingly enter or leave the paid area of a real transit station owned and/or operated by the Washington Metropolitan Area Transit Authority which is located within the corporate limits of the District of Columbia without paying the established fare or presenting a valid transfer for transportation on such public passenger vehicle or rail transit car. No person shall board a public or private passenger vehicle for hire, including vehicles owned and/or operated by the Washington Metropolitan Area Transit Authority, through the rear exit door, unless so directed by an employee or agent of the carrier.</text>
    <annotations>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>History</heading>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 2-40">Feb. 22, 1978, D.C. Law 2-40, § 2, 24 DCR 3344</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Section References</heading>
        <annotation>This section is referenced in § <cite path="§35-252">35-252</cite> and § <cite path="§35-253">35-253</cite>.</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Prior Codifications</heading>
        <annotation>1981 Ed., § 44-224.</annotation>
        <annotation>1973 Ed., § 44-216.1.</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
    </annotations>
  </section>
</document>
