<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<document xmlns:codify="http://code.dccouncil.us/schemas/codify" id="Pub. L. 66-2-ch39">
  <heading/>
  <meta>
    <effective>1920-01-15</effective>
    <cites>
      <law congress="66" session="2" chapter="39"/>
    </cites>
  </meta>
  <section from-code="true">
    <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" before="§38-2001.15" path="|38|20|I"/>
    <num codify:value="38-2001.01">1</num>
    <heading>Annuity — Salary deductions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>(a)</num>
      <text>There shall be deducted and withheld from the annual salary of every teacher in the public schools of the District of Columbia an amount computed to the nearest tenth of a dollar that will be sufficient, with interest thereon at 4 per centum per annum, compounded annually, to purchase, under the provisions of this subchapter, an annuity equal to 1% of his average annual salary received during the 10 years immediately preceding retirement, for each year of his whole term of service rendered after June 30, 1926, payable monthly throughout life, for every such teacher who shall be retired, as herein provided.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(b)</num>
      <text>The deductions herein provided for shall be based on such annuity table or tables as the Council of the District of Columbia shall direct; provided, however, that said deductions shall in no case exceed 8% of his annual salary; and provided further, that when the annual salary exceeds $2,000 the deductions and benefits shall be made as on an annual salary of $2,000.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(c)</num>
      <text>The Council of the District of Columbia shall cause to be filed with the Board of Education on September 10th of each year a certificate showing the amount of deduction to be made from the salary of each teacher during the year, said deduction to be made in equal amounts, one to be deducted for each school month. A similar certificate shall be filed not later than the 15th day of each calendar month to cover cases of new entrants. No deduction shall be made from less than an entire month’s salary.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>History</heading>
        <annotation>Jan. 15, 1920, 41 Stat. 387, ch. 39, § 1</annotation>
        <annotation>June 11, 1926, 44 Stat. 727, ch. 556, § 1</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Section References</heading>
        <annotation>This section is referenced in § <cite path="§1-621.03">1-621.03</cite> and § <cite path="§1-622.04">1-622.04</cite>.</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Prior Codifications</heading>
        <annotation>1981 Ed., § 31-1201.</annotation>
        <annotation>1973 Ed., § 31-701.</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Change in Government</heading>
        <annotation>This section originated at a time when local government powers were delegated to a Board of Commissioners of the District of Columbia (see Acts Relating to the Establishment of the District of Columbia and its Various Forms of Governmental Organization in Volume 1). Section 402(237) of Reorganization Plan No. 3 of 1967 (see Reorganization Plans in Volume 1) transferred all of the functions of the Board of Commissioners under this section to the District of Columbia Council, subject to the right of the Commissioner as provided in § 406 of the Plan. The District of Columbia Self-Government and Governmental Reorganization Act, 87 Stat. 818, § 711 ( D.C. Code, § <cite path="§1-207.11">1-207.11</cite>), abolished the District of Columbia Council and the Office of Commissioner of the District of Columbia. These branches of government were replaced by the Council of the District of Columbia and the Office of Mayor of the District of Columbia, respectively. Accordingly, and also pursuant to § 714(a) of such Act ( D.C. Code, § <cite path="§1-207.14">1-207.14</cite>(a)), appropriate changes in terminology were made in this section.</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section from-code="true">
    <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" before="§38-2001.15" path="|38|20|I"/>
    <num codify:value="38-2001.02">2</num>
    <heading>Annuity — Deposit in United States Treasury.</heading>
    <text>The amount so deducted and withheld from the annual salary of every teacher shall be deposited in the Treasury of the United States and shall be credited, together with interest at 4% per annum, compounded annually, to an individual account of the teacher from whose salary the deduction is made, which account shall be kept by the Auditor of the District of Columbia. The fund thus created shall be held and invested by the Treasurer of the United States until paid out as hereinafter provided, and the income derived from such investments shall constitute a part of said fund for the purpose of carrying out the provisions of this subchapter.</text>
    <annotations>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>History</heading>
        <annotation>Jan. 15, 1920, 41 Stat. 387, ch. 39, § 2</annotation>
        <annotation>June 11, 1926, 44 Stat. 727, ch. 556, § 1</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Section References</heading>
        <annotation>This section is referenced in § <cite path="§38-2021.02">38-2021.02</cite>.</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Prior Codifications</heading>
        <annotation>1981 Ed., § 31-1202.</annotation>
        <annotation>1973 Ed., § 31-702.</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Editor's Notes</heading>
        <annotation>Office of Auditor abolished: The Office of the Auditor of the District of Columbia was abolished and the functions thereof transferred to the Board of Commissioners of the District of Columbia by Reorganization Plan No. 5 of 1952. Reorganization Order No. 3 of the Board of Commissioners, dated August 28, 1952, and effective September 2, 1952, established, under the direction and control of the Board of Commissioners, a Department of General Administration headed by a Director. The Order transferred to the Director of General Administration all of the functions of the Office of Auditor. Reorganization Order No. 19 established the Internal Audit Office headed by an Internal Audit Officer in the Department of General Administration. The function of certifying as to the accuracy of the yearly financial statement of the Armory Board was transferred to the Internal Audit Office. The executive functions of the Board of Commissioners were transferred to the Commissioner of the District of Columbia by § 401 of Reorganization Plan No. 3 of 1967. Reorganization Order Nos. 3 and 19 were revoked by Organization Order No. 3 of the Commissioner of the District of Columbia, dated December 13, 1967. Organization Order No. 3 established within the newly created Department of General Administration an Internal Audit Office and prescribed the functions thereof. These functions were subsequently transferred to the Director of the Department of Finance and Revenue by Commissioner’s Order No. 69-96, dated March 7, 1969. Part IVB of Organization Order No. 3 and that portion of paragraph 4 of Commissioner’s Order No. 69-96 pertaining to a transfer of audit functions to the Department of Finance and Revenue were revoked by Organization Order No. 33, dated July 14, 1972. The latter Order established an Office of Municipal Audit and Inspection and prescribed the functions thereof. Organization Order No. 50, dated December 31, 1974, established the Office of Budget and Management Systems, and transferred to that office the functions of the Municipal Audit Office. The Office of Budget and Management Systems was replaced by Mayor’s Order 79-5, dated January 2, 1977, which Order established the Office of Budget and Revenue Development.</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section from-code="true">
    <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" before="§38-2001.15" path="|38|20|I"/>
    <num codify:value="38-2001.03">3</num>
    <heading>Retirement age; continuous employment requirements.</heading>
    <text>Any teacher who shall have reached the age of 62 may be retired by the Board of Education on its own motion, or shall be retired if application is made by the teacher. Any teacher who shall have reached the age of 70 shall be retired unless, in the judgment of two thirds of the Board of Education, such teacher should be longer retained for the good of the service; provided, that no sum shall be paid to any teacher upon his retirement under the provisions of this section unless he shall have been continuously employed as a teacher in the public schools of the District of Columbia from the time of his attainment of the age of 52 years.</text>
    <annotations>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>History</heading>
        <annotation>Jan. 15, 1920, 41 Stat. 388, ch. 39, § 3</annotation>
        <annotation>June 11, 1926, 44 Stat. 728, ch. 556, § 1</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Section References</heading>
        <annotation>This section is referenced in § <cite path="§38-2001.05">38-2001.05</cite> and § <cite path="§38-2001.09">38-2001.09</cite>.</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Prior Codifications</heading>
        <annotation>1981 Ed., § 31-1203.</annotation>
        <annotation>1973 Ed., § 31-703.</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section from-code="true">
    <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" before="§38-2001.15" path="|38|20|I"/>
    <num codify:value="38-2001.04">4</num>
    <heading>Disability retirement; requirements.</heading>
    <text>Any teacher who shall have reached the age of 45, and who shall have been continuously employed in the public schools of the District of Columbia for not less than 10 years immediately prior to his retirement, or who shall have been continuously employed for not less than 15 years prior to his retirement and who by reason of accident or illness not due to vicious habits has acquired a physical or mental disability and is incapable of satisfactorily performing the duties of his position, may be retired by the Board of Education under the provisions hereinafter stated; provided, that absence of any teacher on authorized leave of absence without pay for a period not in excess of 2 years shall not constitute a break in continuous employment; provided further, that no teacher shall be retired by the Board of Education under the provisions of this section until said teacher shall have been examined under the direction of the health officer of the District of Columbia, and as a result of said examination, in his judgment, or in the judgment of two-thirds of the members of the Board of Education shall have been found to be physically or mentally incapacitated for efficient service.</text>
    <annotations>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>History</heading>
        <annotation>Jan. 15, 1920, 41 Stat. 388, ch. 39, § 4</annotation>
        <annotation>June 11, 1926, 44 Stat. 728, ch. 556, § 1</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 16-305">Apr. 24, 2007, D.C. Law 16-305, § 55, 53 DCR 6198</annotation>
        <annotation doc="D.C. Law 17-353">Mar. 25, 2009, D.C. Law 17-353, § 172(c), 56 DCR 1117</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Section References</heading>
        <annotation>This section is referenced in § <cite path="§38-2001.05">38-2001.05</cite>, § <cite path="§38-2001.06">38-2001.06</cite>, and § <cite path="§38-2001.09">38-2001.09</cite>.</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Prior Codifications</heading>
        <annotation>1981 Ed., § 31-1204.</annotation>
        <annotation>1973 Ed., § 31-704.</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Effect of Amendments</heading>
        <annotation><cite doc="D.C. Law 16-305">D.C. Law 16-305</cite> substituted “has acquired a physical or mental disability and is” for “has become physically or mentally disabled and”.</annotation>
        <annotation><cite doc="D.C. Law 17-353">D.C. Law 17-353</cite> validated a previously made technical correction.</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section from-code="true">
    <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" before="§38-2001.15" path="|38|20|I"/>
    <num codify:value="38-2001.05">5</num>
    <heading>Annuity allowance.</heading>
    <text>Every teacher who shall be retired under the provisions of § <cite path="§38-2001.03">38-2001.03</cite> or § <cite path="§38-2001.04">38-2001.04</cite> shall receive during the remainder of his life a combined annuity composed of:</text>
    <para>
      <num>(1)</num>
      <text>An annuity equal to 1% of his average annual salary received during the 10 years immediately preceding retirement for each year of his whole term of service after June 30, 1926;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(2)</num>
      <text>A sum equal to 1% of his average annual salary received during the 10 years immediately preceding retirement for each year of his whole term of service prior to July 1, 1926, but not to exceed 40 years; and</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(3)</num>
      <text>An additional sum of $15 for each year of said service, but in neither case to exceed 40 years, such annuity to be fixed at the nearest multiple of 12 cents and to be payable monthly and to cease and determine at his death.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>History</heading>
        <annotation>Jan. 15, 1920, 41 Stat. 388, ch. 39, § 5</annotation>
        <annotation>June 11, 1926, 44 Stat. 728, ch. 556, § 1</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Section References</heading>
        <annotation>This section is referenced in § <cite path="§38-2001.06">38-2001.06</cite> and § <cite path="§38-2001.07">38-2001.07</cite>.</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Prior Codifications</heading>
        <annotation>1981 Ed., § 31-1205.</annotation>
        <annotation>1973 Ed., § 31-705.</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section from-code="true">
    <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" before="§38-2001.15" path="|38|20|I"/>
    <num codify:value="38-2001.06">6</num>
    <heading>Minimum-service credit in cases of disability retirement.</heading>
    <text>In calculating, as provided in § <cite path="§38-2001.05">38-2001.05</cite>, the 3rd part of the annuity of a teacher retired under the provisions of § <cite path="§38-2001.04">38-2001.04</cite>, a minimum credit of 20 years shall be used in determining the sum allowable to a teacher with less than 20 years of service.</text>
    <annotations>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>History</heading>
        <annotation>Jan. 15, 1920, 41 Stat. 388, ch. 39, § 6</annotation>
        <annotation>June 11, 1926, 44 Stat. 728, ch. 556, § 1</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Prior Codifications</heading>
        <annotation>1981 Ed., § 31-1206.</annotation>
        <annotation>1973 Ed., § 31-706.</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section from-code="true">
    <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" before="§38-2001.15" path="|38|20|I"/>
    <num codify:value="38-2001.07">7</num>
    <heading>Appropriations for annuity; reserves; interest.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>(a)</num>
      <text>The second and third parts of the annuity provided for by § <cite path="§38-2001.05">38-2001.05</cite> shall be paid by appropriations from the same fund as the current expenses of the District of Columbia were paid on June 11, 1926, or may thereafter be paid.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(b)</num>
      <text>The reserves created as the result of such annual appropriations shall be held by the Treasurer of the United States separate from the fund created by the contributions of the teachers, and the fund shall be credited with interest at 4% per annum, compounded annually. The fund thus created shall be held and invested by the Treasurer of the United States until paid out as hereinafter provided, and the income derived from such investments shall constitute a part of said fund for the purpose of carrying out the provisions of this subchapter.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>History</heading>
        <annotation>Jan. 15, 1920, 41 Stat. 388, ch. 39, § 7</annotation>
        <annotation>June 11, 1926, 44 Stat. 728, ch. 556, § 1</annotation>
        <annotation doc="Pub. L. 96-122">Nov. 17, 1979, 93 Stat. 866, Pub. L. 96-122, § 146(c)(1)</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Section References</heading>
        <annotation>This section is referenced in § <cite path="§38-2021.02">38-2021.02</cite>.</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Prior Codifications</heading>
        <annotation>1981 Ed., § 31-1207.</annotation>
        <annotation>1973 Ed., § 31-707.</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section from-code="true">
    <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" before="§38-2001.15" path="|38|20|I"/>
    <num codify:value="38-2001.08">8</num>
    <heading>Credit for service outside District.</heading>
    <text>In computing length of service of retiring teachers credit may be given, year for year, but not to exceed 10 years, for public school service or its equivalent outside the District of Columbia; provided, that no credit for service outside of the public schools of the District of Columbia shall be given to any teacher entering the said public schools after June 30, 1926, until he shall have deposited to the credit of the teachers’ retirement fund of the District of Columbia a sum equal to the contributions that would have been required of the teacher if such service had been rendered in the public schools of the District of Columbia, with interest thereon at 4% per annum, compounded annually, said contributions to be based on the average annual salary of the class to which the teacher is appointed; provided further, that when the average annual salary of the class exceeds $2,000 the contributions shall be based on a salary of $2,000; provided further, that if the teacher so elects he may deposit the required sum in the fund in any number of monthly installments not exceeding 100, with interest at 4% per annum, compounded annually; and provided further, that the provisions of this subchapter shall not apply to any teacher who receives an annuity from any state or municipality other than the District of Columbia, nor to allow any teacher more than one year’s credit for all services rendered in any one fiscal year.</text>
    <annotations>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>History</heading>
        <annotation>Jan. 15, 1920, 41 Stat. 388, ch. 39, § 8</annotation>
        <annotation>June 11, 1926, 44 Stat. 729, ch. 556, § 1</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Prior Codifications</heading>
        <annotation>1981 Ed., § 31-1208.</annotation>
        <annotation>1973 Ed., § 31-708.</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section from-code="true">
    <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" before="§38-2001.15" path="|38|20|I"/>
    <num codify:value="38-2001.09">9</num>
    <heading>Refund on leaving service; reinstatement.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>(a)</num>
      <text>Upon separation of any teacher from the service of the public schools of the District of Columbia, except for retirement under § <cite path="§38-2001.03">38-2001.03</cite> or § <cite path="§38-2001.04">38-2001.04</cite>, he shall receive the amount of his deductions, together with the interest then credited thereon.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(b)</num>
      <text>No teacher who shall withdraw the amount of his deductions under this section shall, after reinstatement, be entitled to credit for previous service unless he shall deposit in the fund the amount so withdrawn by him; provided, that the amount required to be so deposited may be paid by the teacher, if he so elects, in any number of monthly installments, not exceeding 100, with interest at 4% compounded annually, but no credit for previous service shall be given in any case of retirement where the teacher has been separated from teaching service in any public school system for more than 5 years.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>History</heading>
        <annotation>Jan. 15, 1920, 41 Stat. 388, ch. 39, § 9</annotation>
        <annotation>June 11, 1926, 44 Stat. 729, ch. 556, § 1</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Prior Codifications</heading>
        <annotation>1981 Ed., § 31-1209.</annotation>
        <annotation>1973 Ed., § 31-709.</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section from-code="true">
    <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" before="§38-2001.15" path="|38|20|I"/>
    <num codify:value="38-2001.10">10</num>
    <heading>Death of teacher — Designation of beneficiary.</heading>
    <text>Every teacher from whose salary retirement deductions are made in accordance with this subchapter shall be required to designate in writing a beneficiary or beneficiaries to whom the amount of his deductions, together with interest then credited thereon, shall be payable in the event of the death of such teacher.</text>
    <annotations>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>History</heading>
        <annotation>Jan. 15, 1920, 41 Stat. 389, ch. 39, § 10</annotation>
        <annotation>June 11, 1926, 44 Stat. 729, ch. 556, § 1</annotation>
        <annotation>Apr. 5, 1939, 53 Stat. 571, ch. 42, § 1</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Prior Codifications</heading>
        <annotation>1981 Ed., § 31-1210.</annotation>
        <annotation>1973 Ed., § 31-710.</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section from-code="true">
    <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" before="§38-2001.15" path="|38|20|I"/>
    <num codify:value="38-2001.11">11</num>
    <heading>Consent to deductions.</heading>
    <text>Every teacher who shall continue in the service of the public schools of the District of Columbia after January 15, 1920, as well as every person who on and after January 15, 1920, may be appointed to a position as teacher in the public schools of the District of Columbia, shall be deemed to consent and agree to the deductions made and provided for in this subchapter; and the salary, pay, or compensation, which may be paid monthly or at any other time, shall be full and complete discharge and acquittance of all claims and demands whatsoever for all services rendered by such teacher during the period covered by such payment, except his claim for the benefits to which he may be entitled under the provisions of this subchapter, notwithstanding the provisions of said Public Act No. 254, approved June 20, 1906, and of any other law, rule or regulation affecting the salary, pay, or compensation of the teachers employed in the service of the public schools of the District of Columbia.</text>
    <annotations>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>History</heading>
        <annotation>Jan. 15, 1920, 41 Stat. 389, ch. 39, § 11</annotation>
        <annotation>June 11, 1926, 44 Stat. 730, ch. 556, § 1</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Prior Codifications</heading>
        <annotation>1981 Ed., § 31-1212.</annotation>
        <annotation>1973 Ed., § 31-712.</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>References in Text</heading>
        <annotation>“Public Act No. 254, approved June 20, 1906,” referred to near the end of the section, refers to the Act of June 20, 1906, 34 Stat. 316, ch. 3446.</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section from-code="true">
    <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" before="§38-2001.15" path="|38|20|I"/>
    <num codify:value="38-2001.12">12</num>
    <heading>Discharge of teachers.</heading>
    <text>Nothing in this subchapter shall be construed to prevent the discharge of any teacher at any time in the discretion of the Board of Education of the District of Columbia under the provisions of law.</text>
    <annotations>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>History</heading>
        <annotation>Jan. 15, 1920, 41 Stat. 389, ch. 39, § 12</annotation>
        <annotation>June 11, 1926, 44 Stat. 730, ch. 556, § 1</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Prior Codifications</heading>
        <annotation>1981 Ed., § 31-1213.</annotation>
        <annotation>1973 Ed., § 31-713.</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section from-code="true">
    <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" before="§38-2001.15" path="|38|20|I"/>
    <num codify:value="38-2001.13">13</num>
    <heading>Definitions.</heading>
    <text>The term “teacher,” under this subchapter, shall include all teachers permanently employed by the Board of Education in the public day schools of the District of Columbia, including other educational employees whose salaries are established in the Act approved June 20, 1906, and acts amendatory thereof, except the employees of the Recreation Board and the Department of School Attendance and Work Permits; the term “annual salary” shall be construed to mean the total annual income received during the fiscal year for services rendered in the public day schools of the District of Columbia, including basic salary, longevity allowance, session room allowance, and increase of compensation (bonus); and whenever the pronoun “his” occurs in this subchapter it shall be construed to mean both male and female teachers.</text>
    <annotations>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>History</heading>
        <annotation>Jan. 15, 1920, 41 Stat. 389, ch. 39, § 13</annotation>
        <annotation>June 11, 1926, 44 Stat. 730, ch. 556, § 1</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Prior Codifications</heading>
        <annotation>1981 Ed., § 31-1214.</annotation>
        <annotation>1973 Ed., § 31-714.</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>References in Text</heading>
        <annotation>The “Act approved June 20, 1906,” referred to near the beginning of the section, refers to the Act of June 20, 1906, 34 Stat. 316, ch. 3446.</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section from-code="true">
    <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" before="§38-2001.15" path="|38|20|I"/>
    <num codify:value="38-2001.14">14</num>
    <heading>Records to be kept by Mayor.</heading>
    <text>The Mayor of the District of Columbia shall prepare and keep all needful tables, records, and accounts required for carrying out the provisions of this subchapter. The records to be kept shall include data showing the mortality experience of the teachers in the service of the public schools of the District of Columbia and the rate of withdrawal from such service, and any other information pertaining to such service that may be of value and may serve as a guide for future valuations and adjustments of the plan for the retirement of teachers.</text>
    <annotations>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>History</heading>
        <annotation>Jan. 15, 1920, 41 Stat. 389, ch. 39, § 14</annotation>
        <annotation>June 11, 1926, 44 Stat. 730, ch. 556, § 1</annotation>
        <annotation doc="Pub. L. 96-122">Nov. 17, 1979, 93 Stat. 866, Pub. L. 96-122, § 146(c)(2)</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Prior Codifications</heading>
        <annotation>1981 Ed., § 31-1215.</annotation>
        <annotation>1973 Ed., § 31-715.</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Change in Government</heading>
        <annotation>This section originated at a time when local government powers were delegated to a Board of Commissioners of the District of Columbia (see Acts Relating to the Establishment of the District of Columbia and its Various Forms of Governmental Organization in Volume 1). Section 401 of Reorganization Plan No. 3 of 1967 (see Reorganization Plans in Volume 1) transferred all of the functions of the Board of Commissioners under this section to a single Commissioner. The District of Columbia Self-Government and Governmental Reorganization Act, 87 Stat. 818, § 711 ( D.C. Code, § <cite path="§1-207.11">1-207.11</cite>), abolished the District of Columbia Council and the Office of Commissioner of the District of Columbia. These branches of government were replaced by the Council of the District of Columbia and the Office of Mayor of the District of Columbia, respectively. Accordingly, and also pursuant to § 714(a) of such Act ( D.C. Code, § <cite path="§1-207.14">1-207.14</cite>(a)), appropriate changes in terminology were made in this section.</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section from-code="true">
    <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" path="|38|20|I"/>
    <num codify:value="38-2001.16">16</num>
    <heading>Rules and regulations.</heading>
    <text>The Mayor of the District of Columbia is hereby authorized to perform, or cause to be performed, any or all acts and the Council of the District of Columbia is hereby authorized to make such rules and regulations as may be necessary and proper for the purpose of carrying the provisions of this subchapter into full force and effect.</text>
    <annotations>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>History</heading>
        <annotation>Jan. 15, 1920, 41 Stat. 390, ch. 39, § 16</annotation>
        <annotation>June 11, 1926, 44 Stat. 731, ch. 556, § 1</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Cross References</heading>
        <annotation>Rules and regulations, authority of Council to adopt, see § <cite path="§1-303.03">1-303.03</cite>.</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Prior Codifications</heading>
        <annotation>1981 Ed., § 31-1216.</annotation>
        <annotation>1973 Ed., § 31-717.</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Change in Government</heading>
        <annotation>This section originated at a time when local government powers were delegated to a Board of Commissioners of the District of Columbia (see Acts Relating to the Establishment of the District of Columbia and its Various Forms of Governmental Organization in Volume 1). Section 402(238) of Reorganization Plan No. 3 of 1967 (see Reorganization Plans in Volume 1) transferred all of the functions of the Board of Commissioners under this section to the District of Columbia Council, subject to the right of the Commissioner as provided in § 406 of the Plan. The District of Columbia Self-Government and Governmental Reorganization Act, 87 Stat. 818, § 711 ( D.C. Code, § <cite path="§1-207.11">1-207.11</cite>), abolished the District of Columbia Council and the Office of Commissioner of the District of Columbia. These branches of government were replaced by the Council of the District of Columbia and the Office of Mayor of the District of Columbia, respectively. Accordingly, and also pursuant to § 714(a) of such Act ( D.C. Code, § <cite path="§1-207.14">1-207.14</cite>(a)), appropriate changes in terminology were made in this section.</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section from-code="true">
    <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" path="|38|20|I"/>
    <num codify:value="38-2001.17">17</num>
    <heading>Funds not subject to assignment, execution or levy.</heading>
    <text>None of the money mentioned in this subchapter shall be assignable, either in law or equity, or be subject to execution or levy by attachment, garnishment, or other legal process.</text>
    <annotations>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>History</heading>
        <annotation>Jan. 15, 1920, 41 Stat. 390, ch. 39, § 17</annotation>
        <annotation>June 11, 1926, 44 Stat. 731, ch. 556, § 1</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Prior Codifications</heading>
        <annotation>1981 Ed., § 31-1217.</annotation>
        <annotation>1973 Ed., § 31-718.</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section from-code="true">
    <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" path="|38|20|I"/>
    <num codify:value="38-2001.18">18</num>
    <heading>Application of subchapter — Annuities from other governments.</heading>
    <text>The provisions of this subchapter shall not apply to any teacher who receives an annuity from any state or municipality other than the District of Columbia.</text>
    <annotations>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>History</heading>
        <annotation>Jan. 15, 1920, 41 Stat. 390, ch. 39, § 18</annotation>
        <annotation>June 11, 1926, 44 Stat. 731, ch. 556, § 1</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Prior Codifications</heading>
        <annotation>1981 Ed., § 31-1218.</annotation>
        <annotation>1973 Ed., § 31-719.</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section from-code="true">
    <codify:insert doc="D.C. Code" path="|38|20|I"/>
    <num codify:value="38-2001.19">19</num>
    <heading>Application of subchapter — Annuities under prior act.</heading>
    <text>The provisions of this subchapter shall apply to: (1) all teachers who were on the rolls of the public schools of the District of Columbia for the month of June, 1926, if otherwise eligible; and (2) all teachers who, on June 30, 1926, were receiving an annuity under the provisions of this subchapter, the annuity to be paid each such teacher after June 30, 1926, to be computed in the manner provided herein; provided, that nothing in this subchapter shall be construed to require a reduction in the amount of the annuity being paid to any teacher on July 1, 1926.</text>
    <annotations>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>History</heading>
        <annotation>Jan. 15, 1920, 41 Stat. 389, ch. 39, § 19</annotation>
        <annotation>June 11, 1926, 44 Stat. 731, ch. 556, § 1</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Cross References</heading>
        <annotation>Federal City College, assumption of the District of Columbia Teachers College, retirement benefits of educational employees, election, see § <cite path="§38-1103">38-1103</cite>.</annotation>
        <annotation>Schoolteachers, retirees, reemployment as substitute teachers, see § <cite path="§38-1910">38-1910</cite>.</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
      <annoGroup>
        <heading>Prior Codifications</heading>
        <annotation>1981 Ed., § 31-1219.</annotation>
        <annotation>1973 Ed., § 31-720.</annotation>
      </annoGroup>
    </annotations>
  </section>
</document>
